<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop on Hecke Algebras and Lie Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>16000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>16000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports US-based participants, primarily graduate students and postdoctoral researchers, in the "Workshop on Hecke Algebras and Lie Theory," held May 12-15, 2016 at the University of Ottawa. The workshop brings together experts in algebraic combinatorics and Lie theory with the goal of fostering the international collaboration between researchers in several areas connected to representation theory and algebraic combinatorics, including Lie superalgebras, extended affine Lie algebras, and Hecke algebras. In addition to talks by experts in the field, the workshop includes a mini-course accessible to non-experts, including junior researchers, that covers recent progress in double affine Hecke algebras and related areas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hecke algebras of finite and affine Weyl groups arise naturally as convolution algebras associated to finite and locally compact groups, and they play a prominent role in the representation theory of finite groups of Lie type and of reductive p-adic groups. In the early 1990's a class of algebras, known as double affine Hecke algebras, was introduced in connection with affine quantum Knizhnik-Zamolodchikov equations. Since then, profound connections have been discovered between double affine Hecke algebras and a broad spectrum of areas in mathematics, including combinatorics, algebraic geometry, number theory, representation theory, harmonic analysis, knot theory, special functions, many body problems, and conformal field theory. Recent results hint at a new and promising connection between double affine Hecke algebras and Lie superalgebras and open the door to many intriguing possibilities that will be explored at the workshop. The website for the workshop is https://www.fields.utoronto.ca/programs/scientific/15-16/Hecke/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1623501</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Siddhartha</FirstName>
<LastName>Sahi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Siddhartha Sahi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sahi@math.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484457973</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000116540</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hadi</FirstName>
<LastName>Salmasian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hadi Salmasian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hsalmasi@uottawa.ca</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6135625399</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000714156</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2nd Floor East Wing]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey]]></Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088548019</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 Frelinghuysen Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7970</Code>
<Text>Combinatorics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main outcome of the project was the organization of a workshop and a conference, which fostered the collaboration of researchers in a broad spectrum of areas of mathematics that interact with Lie theory. In addition to regular talks, the scheduled activities included extended time slots for discussions between participants. There was also ample opportunity for graduate students and postdoctoral fellows to present their work in the form of 30 minute talks and a poster session.<br /><br />The major activity was a four-day <em>Workshop on Hecke Algebras and Lie Theory</em>, held at the University of Ottawa during May 12-15, 2016. This brought together nearly 50 local and international participants at all levels, from prominent established researchers, to aspiring and enthusiastic graduate students and postdoctoral fellows. The workshop lectures included 3 mini-courses aimed primarily at junior participants, as well as several advanced research talks.<br /><br />A small surplus from the offered NSF grant, in combination with additional funds from other sources, was then used to organize a follow-up conference on<em> Lie Theory and its Interactions with Geometry and Combinatorics</em> at the University of Ottawa on November 11-12, 2017. This conference attracted more than 15 local and international participants, who were again a mix of senior researchers, postdoctoral fellows, and graduate students. <br /><br />The organized activities have led to extended collaborations between the organizers and several of the participants, which have so far resulted in 3 accepted papers and 2 preprints.</p> <!-- p { margin-bottom: 0.25cm; direction: ltr; line-height: 120%; text-align: left; } --><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/04/2018<br>      Modified by: Hadi&nbsp;Salmasian</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1623501/1623501_10414473_1524259590983_mathfieldworkshops2016--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1623501/1623501_10414473_1524259590983_mathfieldworkshops2016--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Photo of Participants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1623501/1623501_10414473_1524259590983_mathfieldworkshops2016--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Photo of Participants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conference Picture</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mehrak Hazaveh</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hadi&nbsp;Salmasian</div> <div class="imageTitle">Photo of Participants</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main outcome of the project was the organization of a workshop and a conference, which fostered the collaboration of researchers in a broad spectrum of areas of mathematics that interact with Lie theory. In addition to regular talks, the scheduled activities included extended time slots for discussions between participants. There was also ample opportunity for graduate students and postdoctoral fellows to present their work in the form of 30 minute talks and a poster session.  The major activity was a four-day Workshop on Hecke Algebras and Lie Theory, held at the University of Ottawa during May 12-15, 2016. This brought together nearly 50 local and international participants at all levels, from prominent established researchers, to aspiring and enthusiastic graduate students and postdoctoral fellows. The workshop lectures included 3 mini-courses aimed primarily at junior participants, as well as several advanced research talks.  A small surplus from the offered NSF grant, in combination with additional funds from other sources, was then used to organize a follow-up conference on Lie Theory and its Interactions with Geometry and Combinatorics at the University of Ottawa on November 11-12, 2017. This conference attracted more than 15 local and international participants, who were again a mix of senior researchers, postdoctoral fellows, and graduate students.   The organized activities have led to extended collaborations between the organizers and several of the participants, which have so far resulted in 3 accepted papers and 2 preprints.        Last Modified: 05/04/2018       Submitted by: Hadi Salmasian]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
