<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  The PIPELINE Network</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>73740.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>73740</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Turley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PIPELINE Network project will significantly enhance physics education by developing and evaluating methods to incorporate workforce-relevant skills and activities in the student experience. The majority of physics graduates at all degree levels will become scientists and innovators working in the private sector, yet very little of the knowledge they gain while earning their degree specifically prepares them for these roles (for example, few physics programs emphasize real-world applications of scientific concepts, communication skills, or basic business concepts, all of which are important to successful private sector careers). Adding workforce-relevant learning to the discipline will attract a larger and more diverse student body to major in physics, and by extension improve the quality of the future STEM workforce. The PIPELINE project will bring together efforts of six institutions to create and document new approaches to teaching innovation and entrepreneurship in physics which can be shared with the broader community. The project will also advance our understanding of how these practices affect student and faculty attitudes towards innovation and entrepreneurship in physics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of the PIPELINE network are to build students' workforce confidence, improve physics faculty attitudes toward private sector careers, foster better integration of academic and industrial sectors, promote innovation in the physics discipline, and build a framework for wider adoption of physics innovation and entrepreneurship practices. The project will accomplish these by implementing physics innovation and entrepreneurship (PIE) approaches at member institutions during each year of the project, revising approaches between iterations, and finally documenting and disseminating curriculum. Most importantly, PIPELINE will develop surveys and interview protocols which will investigate the link between PIE experiences and student and faculty attitudes about innovation and entrepreneurship, and which can be used by other departments for gauging, monitoring, and improving institutional change around PIE. These research findings and tools will provide insights and utility that go beyond the immediate partner institutions, and live on beyond the duration of the project. PIPELINE will generate a core network of experienced PIE practitioners, a readily accessible body of tested PIE curricula deliberately varied in scope to fit unique needs and challenges of future adopters, and robust insight into the obstacles to PIE implementation and how future adopters might address them.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1624887</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Kotlarchyk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Kotlarchyk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mnksps@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5854756115</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000497549</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
<LastName>Barton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Linda S Barton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lsbsps@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5854757525</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000504863</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne Elyse</FirstName>
<LastName>Leak</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne Elyse E Leak</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aleak@highpoint.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3368419846</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000614289</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Zwickl</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin Zwickl</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bmzsps@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5854754512</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000651920</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rochester Institute of Tech</Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5854757987</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 LOMB MEMORIAL DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002223642</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ROCHESTER INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (INC)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002223642</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rochester Institute of Tech]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Lomb Memorial Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~73740</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   p { margin-bottom: 0.1in; line-height: 120% }   --> <p>The PIPELINE project consists of six universities all working to perform, document and disseminate Physics Innovation and Entrepreneurship (PIE) implenmentations within the physics undergraduate curriculum.    Each university has taken different but interrelated approaches, with the goal of disseminating a broad spectrum of documented and tested PIE implementations to physics programs nationwide.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>At RIT, we worked on several approaches to incorporating Physics Innovation and Entrepreneurship (PIE).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We have developed separate &ldquo;tracks&rdquo; so as to allow physics majors to obtain a basic BS degree in physics with a focus area that is appropriate for their career and professional goals.    In addition to the traditional physics degree, which is preparatory for graduate school in physics, we have put together tracks in each of Applied Physics, Computational Physics, Biophysics, Optics and Photonics, Education, and Entrepreneurship.     These options position students for immediate integration into the workforce, blending the tradional breadth of a physics degree with some specific coursework in their area of interest.    The Entrepreneurship track incorporates business courses in basic accounting, entrepreneurship, and choices of courses in management, business law, or marketing.    While this track is the one with obvious focus on entrepreneurship, the other tracks also allow students the flexibility and creativity to tailor their physics training in preparation for industrial R&amp;D.      The Tracks proposal is in the  committee approval process at this time, and is expected to be  fully implemented by academic 2020.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In recent years, many engineering entrepreneurship programs use &ldquo;PopUp&rdquo; courses to deliver short, fun, non-credit bearing introductions to various topics.   At RIT, we have adopted this model and offered pop-up courses on a variety of topics.      Some were hands-on skill development in electronics, machine shop, Linux familiarity, etc.   Some were career training with subjects like resume writing, elevator pitches, and mock interviews.   The curricular materials for several pop-ups are on the PIPELINE webpage.   Pop-up classes were discussed at an invited talk at the 2018 Beyond the First Year Laboratories &ndash; Advanced Lab Physics Association conference, as well as in an APS webinar.     The Pop-Up model allows innovative faculty to test out new ideas in a low pressure, short-time-frame environment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Physics education research work surveyed both student and faculty attitudes about careers, innovation, and entrepreneurship.     These surveys have polled 178 students from twelve colleges and universities as well as 40 faculty from seven instututions.     These results have been disseminated in the Physics Education Research conference proceedings as well as at AAPT conferences.    Summative data has been shared with the PIPELINE network members.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/12/2019<br>      Modified by: Linda&nbsp;S&nbsp;Barton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The PIPELINE project consists of six universities all working to perform, document and disseminate Physics Innovation and Entrepreneurship (PIE) implenmentations within the physics undergraduate curriculum.    Each university has taken different but interrelated approaches, with the goal of disseminating a broad spectrum of documented and tested PIE implementations to physics programs nationwide.     At RIT, we worked on several approaches to incorporating Physics Innovation and Entrepreneurship (PIE).     We have developed separate "tracks" so as to allow physics majors to obtain a basic BS degree in physics with a focus area that is appropriate for their career and professional goals.    In addition to the traditional physics degree, which is preparatory for graduate school in physics, we have put together tracks in each of Applied Physics, Computational Physics, Biophysics, Optics and Photonics, Education, and Entrepreneurship.     These options position students for immediate integration into the workforce, blending the tradional breadth of a physics degree with some specific coursework in their area of interest.    The Entrepreneurship track incorporates business courses in basic accounting, entrepreneurship, and choices of courses in management, business law, or marketing.    While this track is the one with obvious focus on entrepreneurship, the other tracks also allow students the flexibility and creativity to tailor their physics training in preparation for industrial R&amp;D.      The Tracks proposal is in the  committee approval process at this time, and is expected to be  fully implemented by academic 2020.     In recent years, many engineering entrepreneurship programs use "PopUp" courses to deliver short, fun, non-credit bearing introductions to various topics.   At RIT, we have adopted this model and offered pop-up courses on a variety of topics.      Some were hands-on skill development in electronics, machine shop, Linux familiarity, etc.   Some were career training with subjects like resume writing, elevator pitches, and mock interviews.   The curricular materials for several pop-ups are on the PIPELINE webpage.   Pop-up classes were discussed at an invited talk at the 2018 Beyond the First Year Laboratories &ndash; Advanced Lab Physics Association conference, as well as in an APS webinar.     The Pop-Up model allows innovative faculty to test out new ideas in a low pressure, short-time-frame environment.     Physics education research work surveyed both student and faculty attitudes about careers, innovation, and entrepreneurship.     These surveys have polled 178 students from twelve colleges and universities as well as 40 faculty from seven instututions.     These results have been disseminated in the Physics Education Research conference proceedings as well as at AAPT conferences.    Summative data has been shared with the PIPELINE network members.             Last Modified: 12/12/2019       Submitted by: Linda S Barton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
