<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Planning for a Great Basin Ecological Observatory: from NevCAN to the Spring Valley Field Station</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24993.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24993</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter McCartney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmccartn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928470</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will support strategic planning for the Spring Valley Field Station, located in the Great Basin of North America.  Long-term changes in forest ecosystems are difficult to predict and detect, and field stations allow for multi-year investigations that are otherwise very difficult to perform. While this project will utilize existing long-term infrastructure associated with the Nevada Climate-eco-hydrological Assessment Network (NevCAN), it will support new biological research and education on Great Basin species, from sagebrush to the iconic bristlecone pine. The station will therefore contribute to ecological studies in a semi-arid region that is considered at risk of widespread mortality linked to warmer droughts. The main objective of this project is to develop a long-term vision for the station, together with a realistic management strategy during its first five years.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Three NevCAN sites, from the sagebrush steppe on the valley floor to the bristlecone pine stands at the subalpine tree-line, will be part of the Spring Valley Field Station to capture ecological patterns and processes over a 2000-m elevation gradient. The station will fill a growing demand for long-term information on Great Basin population dynamics, ecosystem processes, threats to biodiversity from invasive species, and overall resilience to future climatic changes, especially in connection with forward-looking resource management, conservation, and restoration. A one-week workshop to be held at the end of August near the proposed station will bring together university faculty and stakeholders from inside and outside of Nevada to draft the master planning document, including a facility needs, details of data management, and fee structure. The Great Basin is characterized by both an upper and a lower tree-line, hence the Spring Valley Field Station will be ideally suited to investigate the linkages between climate and ecosystem dynamics in space and time, including the expansion, retreat, or persistence of trailing and leading ecotonal edges.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1624832</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Franco</FirstName>
<LastName>Biondi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Franco Biondi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>franco.biondi@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7757846921</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485992</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Sponsored Projects / MS 325]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>146515460</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEVADA SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067808063</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno]]></Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1664 N. Virginia St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1104</Code>
<Text>FIELD STATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~24993</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project supported strategic planning for the Spring Valley Field Station, located in the Great Basin of North America. The station would be able to utilize the long-term monitoring tools of the Nevada Climate-eco-hydrological Assessment Network (NevCAN), while also supporting new biological research and education on Great Basin species, from sagebrush to the iconic bristlecone pine. The main objective of this project was to develop a long-term vision for the station, together with a realistic management strategy during its first five years.</p> <p>A one-week workshop was held in 2016 near the proposed station to bring together university faculty and stakeholders from inside and outside of Nevada to draft the master planning document. About 30 people participated in the workshop, with about 1/3 of them from UNR, 1/3 from the rest of Nevada, and 1/3 from outside the state.</p> <p>A website was created in relation to the 2016 workshop, and can be found here: http://naes.unr.edu/springvalleyworkshop/. The website includes a description of the project, short biographies for the speakers (a group photo is provided in this report), powerpoint presentations, and other information related to the project.  A news article was also produced about the workshop and the project (https://www.unr.edu/nevada-today/news/2016/field-station-workshop).</p> <p>A graduate student participated in the workshop with the assigned task of taking notes and helping with general organization and<br />logistics. The student was then able to interact with local stakeholders, invited speakers, and researchers, thereby expanding his exposure to the interaction between science and society.</p> <p>The proposed Spring Valley Field Station will fill a growing demand for long-term information on Great Basin population dynamics, ecosystem processes, threats to biodiversity from invasive species, and overall resilience to future climatic changes. Once the field station is established, rural communities as well as urban dwellers will be able to learn more about changes happening in a semi-arid region that is considered at risk of widespread species mortality linked to warmer droughts.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/06/2017<br>      Modified by: Franco&nbsp;Biondi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501894081541_GroupPhoto--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501894081541_GroupPhoto--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Group photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501894081541_GroupPhoto--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Group photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Participants in the week-long planning workshop for the field station.</div> <div class="imageCredit">DendroLab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Franco&nbsp;Biondi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Group photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501894370504_GBNP_GreaterArea_Map--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501894370504_GBNP_GreaterArea_Map--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Area map"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501894370504_GBNP_GreaterArea_Map--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Area map"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map of the area where the field station is going to be located, near the Nevada-Utah boundary. The workshop was located in Snake Valley, on the east side of Great Basin National Park. The field station sites are located in Spring Valley, on the west side of Great Basin National Park.</div> <div class="imageCredit">DendroLab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Franco&nbsp;Biondi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Area map</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501894683200_OBFSpicture--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501894683200_OBFSpicture--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Landscape view"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501894683200_OBFSpicture--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Landscape view"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">View from the summit of Mt. Washington, looking at a treeline population of bristlecone pine on bright limestone rocks. A thunderstorm cloud hovers in the sky, while Great Basin valleys and ranges stretch into the horizon.</div> <div class="imageCredit">DendroLab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Franco&nbsp;Biondi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Landscape view</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501895005543_SpringValley--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501895005543_SpringValley--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Spring Valley"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501895005543_SpringValley--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Spring Valley"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Panoramic view of Spring Valley, where the field station would be located. It is a typical example of Great Basin sagebrush ecosystem, which has also been the focus of water rights disputes because of a planned groundwater diversion to Las Vegas.</div> <div class="imageCredit">DendroLab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Franco&nbsp;Biondi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Spring Valley</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501895352527_ViewFromMtWashington--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501895352527_ViewFromMtWashington--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Field station ecosystems"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501895352527_ViewFromMtWashington--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Field station ecosystems"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The proposed field station covers an elevation gradient of 2000 m (about 6500 feet). Here you can see how the valley ecosystems (sagebrush, irrigated fields carved into a rare rocky mountain juniper population) transition into pinyon-juniper woodlands and then into montane mixed conifer forests.</div> <div class="imageCredit">DendroLab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Franco&nbsp;Biondi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Field station ecosystems</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501895589681_Ziaco_SpringValley--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501895589681_Ziaco_SpringValley--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pronghorn antelope in Spring Valley"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1624832/1624832_10437128_1501895589681_Ziaco_SpringValley--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Pronghorn antelope in Spring Valley"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Pronghorn antelope, the ?American Antelope?, can be easily spotted in Spring Valley. The fastest land mammal in North America, it exemplifies the biodiversity that could be studied and enjoyed by field station users.</div> <div class="imageCredit">DendroLab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Franco&nbsp;Biondi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Pronghorn antelope in Spring Valley</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project supported strategic planning for the Spring Valley Field Station, located in the Great Basin of North America. The station would be able to utilize the long-term monitoring tools of the Nevada Climate-eco-hydrological Assessment Network (NevCAN), while also supporting new biological research and education on Great Basin species, from sagebrush to the iconic bristlecone pine. The main objective of this project was to develop a long-term vision for the station, together with a realistic management strategy during its first five years.  A one-week workshop was held in 2016 near the proposed station to bring together university faculty and stakeholders from inside and outside of Nevada to draft the master planning document. About 30 people participated in the workshop, with about 1/3 of them from UNR, 1/3 from the rest of Nevada, and 1/3 from outside the state.  A website was created in relation to the 2016 workshop, and can be found here: http://naes.unr.edu/springvalleyworkshop/. The website includes a description of the project, short biographies for the speakers (a group photo is provided in this report), powerpoint presentations, and other information related to the project.  A news article was also produced about the workshop and the project (https://www.unr.edu/nevada-today/news/2016/field-station-workshop).  A graduate student participated in the workshop with the assigned task of taking notes and helping with general organization and logistics. The student was then able to interact with local stakeholders, invited speakers, and researchers, thereby expanding his exposure to the interaction between science and society.  The proposed Spring Valley Field Station will fill a growing demand for long-term information on Great Basin population dynamics, ecosystem processes, threats to biodiversity from invasive species, and overall resilience to future climatic changes. Once the field station is established, rural communities as well as urban dwellers will be able to learn more about changes happening in a semi-arid region that is considered at risk of widespread species mortality linked to warmer droughts.       Last Modified: 08/06/2017       Submitted by: Franco Biondi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
