<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FSML Planning for the Future of the Holt Research Forest</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24993.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24993</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter McCartney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmccartn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928470</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>University of Maine is awarded a planning grant to enable the development of a 10year plan to update and formulate new research, educational, and public outreach programs at Holt Research Forest (HRF) in southern Maine. Recent changes of project leadership and supporting foundation creates an ideal opportunity to build on past successes and create a plan to ensure the legacy and sustainability of HRF as a field station. This plan is needed in part because a whole new set of environmental challenges, not foreseen in 1982, have emerged. The plan will develop strategies to stimulate research and teaching on the value of healthy managed forest ecosystems, climate change adaptation, and forest dynamics at the urban/rural interface. A strategic plan will establish the steps needed for establishing an enhanced infrastructure, a refined data management plan with increased access to the valuable long-term data, broader dissemination of research results, and developing greater communication between HRF and similar field stations. A key outcome of the planning grant and resulting strategic plan would be expanded opportunities for teaching, training, and learning that engage graduate students, postdocs, undergraduate students, K-12 teachers and youth, and adult learners. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Holt Research Forest (HRF) a field station located in southern mid-coastal Maine and has a 35-year history of multidisciplinary ecological research. The site features a red oak white pine forest ecosystem, an important and relatively understudied forest type, estuarine frontage with salt marshes and tidal flats, and the largest fresh water pond on the island. The unique coastal setting of HRF within the nationally recognized Kennebec Estuary with 30,000acres of conservation lands within a 15 mile radius provides a wide spectrum of possibilities for expansion of research. This planning project seeks to articulate the growth potential for research, educational, and public outreach programming. The process will involve a wide diversity of stakeholders and potential beneficiaries. Other universities and colleges, scientists, natural resource professionals, local schools, conservation organizations, state agencies, woodlot owners, and the general public will all be engaged to improve the outcomes. This will be accomplished through three workshops and a conference; soliciting an external evaluation from experts in the field; networking with peers at similar stations; and synthesizing the findings into a10-year strategic plan that will guide future endeavors.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1624065</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Malcolm</FirstName>
<LastName>Hunter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Malcolm L Hunter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mhunter@maine.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2075812865</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000087527</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
<LastName>Leahy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jessica Leahy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jessica_leahy@umit.maine.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2075812834</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000473371</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Weiskittel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron Weiskittel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aaron.weiskittel@maine.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2075811484</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513454</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
<LastName>Witham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jack Witham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jwitham@maine.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2074439438</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000713644</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maine</Name>
<CityName>ORONO</CityName>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2075811484</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5717 Corbett Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>186875787</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MAINE SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071750426</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maine]]></Name>
<CityName>Orono</CityName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<ZipCode>044695755</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5755 Nutting Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1104</Code>
<Text>FIELD STATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~24993</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of the award was the development of a strategic plan to guide improved research, educational, and outreach programs and the continued success of Holt Research Forest (HRF) for the next ten years. An updated mission was developed: To utilize and collect quality long-term, multitaxon data to generate critical synthesis science that will inform and teach forest, wildlife, and watershed scientists, managers, landowners, students, and the public. The HRF vision is to provide research, education, and guidance to ecologically and economically maintain and manage oak-pine forest ecosystems.</p> <p>HRF hosted and conducted meetings and had numerous discussions with potential collaborators, researchers, and numerous other individuals to collect ideas and information. This included a full day research workshop of presentations designed to highlight the ecological importance of the Kennebec Estuary, the many acres of conserved land, the 35+ research history of HRF, and stimulate interest in research at HRF and in the region. The outcomes of these interactions highlighted the importance of our long-term data sets.</p> <p>A Board of Visitors, consisting of Mark Ashton, Yale School of Forestry and Env. Studies; Brian Kloeppel, Western Carolina University; Bill Schuster, Black Rock Forest Consortium; Jennifer Seavey, UNH/Shoals Marine Laboratory; and Hilary Swain, Archbold Biological Station, were hosted for three days. The visit included meetings with the local Steering Committee, tours of facilities and study area of Holt Research Forest, a one-day research workshop, and meetings with Principal Investigators. They produced a report that became the basis for the strategic plan.</p> <p>Discussions with the Board of Visitors made us re-envision the importance of outreach, good communication, and being recognized by a greater segment of the population. This created a shift in focus within the research team to better promote Holt Research Forest and outcomes of our studies. The <a href="https://holtforest.org/">HRF</a> website has been improved, <a href="https://holtforest.org/new-videos/">two videos</a> were produced and posted, and HRF has gained more visibility by greater presence on the <a href="https://crsf.umaine.edu/">Center for Research on Sustainable Forests</a> website. Additional projects are underway to further supplement this need.</p> <p>The promise of the outcomes of this process stimulated increased funding for a data management planning and implementation. As a result, a significant portion of the HRF database has been processed and posted on the <a href="https://www.uvm.edu/femc/products/collections/">Forest Ecology Monitoring Cooperative</a> website.</p> <p>The HRF Strategic Plan identified 5 directions with goals and initiatives for each. The directions are Excellence in Research, Education, Outreach, and Administration, and Facility Development.</p> <p>We strongly believe that the Holt Research Forest strategic plan will lead to enhanced infrastructure, sustainable data management implementation, more utilization of research site, and broader dissemination of research data and results. The Holt Research Forest stakeholders, from researchers and students using the long-term data, to K-12 youth developing connections with natural and managed forests, to natural resource professionals implementing the findings in locations around New England, will continue to benefit from our efforts; which in turn will ensure the continued longevity of this unique field station.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/17/2019<br>      Modified by: Aaron&nbsp;Weiskittel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624065/1624065_10437124_1570049086451_PFL.workshop--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624065/1624065_10437124_1570049086451_PFL.workshop--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Attendees at Research Workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624065/1624065_10437124_1570049086451_PFL.workshop--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Attendees at Research Workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Holt Research Forest workshop at Patten Free Library</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jack Witham</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jack&nbsp;Witham</div> <div class="imageTitle">Attendees at Research Workshop</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624065/1624065_10437124_1570049544724_backriver--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624065/1624065_10437124_1570049544724_backriver--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Holt Research Forest along the Back River"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624065/1624065_10437124_1570049544724_backriver--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Holt Research Forest along the Back River"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">HRF at the Back River, nearing high tide</div> <div class="imageCredit">David Sanderlands</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jack&nbsp;Witham</div> <div class="imageTitle">Holt Research Forest along the Back River</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624065/1624065_10437124_1570463878221_BOV--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624065/1624065_10437124_1570463878221_BOV--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Board of Visitors at the Back River"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624065/1624065_10437124_1570463878221_BOV--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Board of Visitors at the Back River"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Board of visitors and local committee at the Back River</div> <div class="imageCredit">Clarke Cooper</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jack&nbsp;Witham</div> <div class="imageTitle">Board of Visitors at the Back River</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of the award was the development of a strategic plan to guide improved research, educational, and outreach programs and the continued success of Holt Research Forest (HRF) for the next ten years. An updated mission was developed: To utilize and collect quality long-term, multitaxon data to generate critical synthesis science that will inform and teach forest, wildlife, and watershed scientists, managers, landowners, students, and the public. The HRF vision is to provide research, education, and guidance to ecologically and economically maintain and manage oak-pine forest ecosystems.  HRF hosted and conducted meetings and had numerous discussions with potential collaborators, researchers, and numerous other individuals to collect ideas and information. This included a full day research workshop of presentations designed to highlight the ecological importance of the Kennebec Estuary, the many acres of conserved land, the 35+ research history of HRF, and stimulate interest in research at HRF and in the region. The outcomes of these interactions highlighted the importance of our long-term data sets.  A Board of Visitors, consisting of Mark Ashton, Yale School of Forestry and Env. Studies; Brian Kloeppel, Western Carolina University; Bill Schuster, Black Rock Forest Consortium; Jennifer Seavey, UNH/Shoals Marine Laboratory; and Hilary Swain, Archbold Biological Station, were hosted for three days. The visit included meetings with the local Steering Committee, tours of facilities and study area of Holt Research Forest, a one-day research workshop, and meetings with Principal Investigators. They produced a report that became the basis for the strategic plan.  Discussions with the Board of Visitors made us re-envision the importance of outreach, good communication, and being recognized by a greater segment of the population. This created a shift in focus within the research team to better promote Holt Research Forest and outcomes of our studies. The HRF website has been improved, two videos were produced and posted, and HRF has gained more visibility by greater presence on the Center for Research on Sustainable Forests website. Additional projects are underway to further supplement this need.  The promise of the outcomes of this process stimulated increased funding for a data management planning and implementation. As a result, a significant portion of the HRF database has been processed and posted on the Forest Ecology Monitoring Cooperative website.  The HRF Strategic Plan identified 5 directions with goals and initiatives for each. The directions are Excellence in Research, Education, Outreach, and Administration, and Facility Development.  We strongly believe that the Holt Research Forest strategic plan will lead to enhanced infrastructure, sustainable data management implementation, more utilization of research site, and broader dissemination of research data and results. The Holt Research Forest stakeholders, from researchers and students using the long-term data, to K-12 youth developing connections with natural and managed forests, to natural resource professionals implementing the findings in locations around New England, will continue to benefit from our efforts; which in turn will ensure the continued longevity of this unique field station.       Last Modified: 10/17/2019       Submitted by: Aaron Weiskittel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
