<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>AGS-PRF: Antecedent Remote and Local Synoptic Environments Most Conducive to North American Polar/Subtropical Jet Superpositions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>86000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>172000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nicholas Anderson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nanderso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924715</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The jet stream is a well-known atmospheric phenomena, but the public is generally unaware that there are two main jet streams in each hemisphere, the polar jet stream and the subtropical jet stream.  These jets are typically separated by a significant distance, but in certain circumstances can end up in the same geographic location, known as a jet stream superposition.  These superposition occurrences can be tied to very high-impact weather events, so learning more about their causes and characteristics is important for improving weather forecasts.  The researcher funded under this award will use 35 years of atmospheric data to identify, classify, and analyze an estimated 700 superposition events over North America.  The main societal impact will be the development and testing of an operational forecast product that would provide a first alert to high-impact weather events in the 8-10 day forecast range.  The early career researcher also plans to continue his education and outreach activities by mentoring an undergraduate student and communicating scientific results to the public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researcher plans to study the topic of jet superposition events, wherein the polar jet and the subtropical jet meet in a vertical superposition of initially distinct jet streams.  The NCEP CFSR dataset will be used to identify superposition events over North America and then various analyses will be run to answer the following research questions:  1) What is the nature of the large-scale interactions between polar cyclonic and tropical anticyclonic PV anomalies throughout the production of a jet superposition and does the polar or tropical component consistently dominate those interactions?  2) What are the antecedent remote and local synoptic environments that are most conducive to the production of a superposition for each type of PV anomaly interaction and what influence does a superposition have on the downstream midlatitude flow pattern?  3) What environmental discriminators exist between jet superposition events and "null cases", or instances in which the PJ and STJ closely approach one another but do not superpose, for each type of PV anomaly interaction?</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1624316</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Winters</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew C Winters</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>3037355775</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000688547</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Winters                 Andrew         C</Name>
<CityName>Albany</CityName>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University at Albany, SUNY]]></Name>
<CityName>Albany</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>Postdoctoral Fellowships</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL &amp; DYNAMIC METEOROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE &amp; LARGE-SCALE DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~86000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~86000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span>Intellectual Merit</span></strong></p> <p>The Northern Hemisphere is typically characterized by two rapidly moving currents of air, or jet streams, that are situated 10-12 km above the Earth's surface. The polar jet (PJ) stream is located around 50<span><sup>o</sup></span>N and sits atop a strong, tropospheric-deep temperature contrast known as the polar front. The subtropical jet (SJ) stream is located equatorward of the PJ around 30<span><sup>o</sup></span>N and sits atop a comparatively modest temperature contrast in the middle and upper-troposphere. While the PJ and SJ often remain separated from one another, they can occasionally merge to form a polar-subtropical jet superposition. Jet superpositions are characterized by strong upper-tropospheric wind speeds that can often exceed 100 m/s, as well as the development of an intense horizontal temperature contrast in the vicinity of the jet. Jet superpositions can also contribute to the production of high-impact weather events, including strong low-pressure systems, floods, blizzards, and severe weather outbreaks. Consequently, this project was centered on providing an improved understanding the processes that contribute to the development of jet superpositions over North America.</p> <p>This study identified a total of 326 jet superposition events using the NCEP Climate Forecast System Reanalysis (CFSR) dataset during November-March 1979-2010. These events were then classified into event types based on the location at which the PJ and SJ became superposed. Polar dominant events are those events in which the PJ superposed with the SJ near the climatological latitude of the SJ, while subtropical dominant events are those in which the SJ superposed with the PJ near the climatological latitude of the PJ. While polar dominant events are most frequent along the U.S./Mexico border and Gulf Coast, subtropical dominant events are most frequent along either the east or west coasts of North America. This latter observation motivated splitting subtropical dominant events into an eastern and western category for further analysis. Overall, North American jet superposition events are most frequent during the early part of the cold season (November-December) and become less frequent during January-March.&nbsp;</p> <p>The development of each jet superposition event type is summarized within the conceptual models attached to this summary. Polar dominant events result from an amplification of the upper-tropospheric flow pattern over the eastern North Pacific that leads to an equatorward displacement of the PJ towards the position of the SJ. The development of a jet superposition in this case is predominantly driven by strong subsidence on the northwestern flank of the jet, which acts to strengthen the horizontal temperature contrast beneath the jet and accelerate jet wind speeds. Farther downstream of the superposition, polar dominant events feature the concurrent development of a strong surface low-pressure system and a corridor of enhanced moisture transport into the southern U.S. that may be conducive to heavy precipitation. Both subtropical dominant event types are preceded by precipitation on the equatorward side of the jet and the development of a surface low-pressure system. The extensive precipitation to the south of the developing jet superposition acts to amplify the upper-tropospheric flow pattern and displace the SJ northward into closer proximity with the PJ. Once the two jets are in close proximity, descending motion on the northwestern flank of the developing jet superposition strengthens the horizontal temperature contrast beneath the jet, similar to polar dominant events, and acts to accelerate jet wind speeds.</p> <p>Numerical simulations of a subtropical dominant event suggest that the cumulative influence of precipitation processes on the structure of the upper-tropospheric flow pattern is a discriminating factor as to whether the PJ and SJ superpose or remain separate. Such a result has important implications for the predictability of jet superpositions, given that forecasts of precipitation processes are a considerable source of uncertainty in forecast models. The analysis also reveals that a considerable fraction of vertical motion in the vicinity of jet superpositions is driven by upper-level disturbances on the poleward flank of the PJ, whereas the encroachment of the SJ into close proximity with the PJ primarily provides a favorable thermodynamic environment with enhanced moisture and reduced resistance to vertical motion.&nbsp;</p> <p><span><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></span></p> <p>The results from this project have a tangible impact on society by fostering improved situational awareness among forecasters and researchers of a type of meteorological environment conducive to high-impact weather events. This project also contributed to the training of 4 undergraduate students at the University at Albany, SUNY and the University of Colorado Boulder, as well as 1 graduate student at the University at Albany, SUNY. This project supported a review article coauthored by the PI summarizing 100 years of research on extratropical cyclones, which will serve as a guide for future research conducted by synoptic-dynamic meteorologists. Last, this fellowship contributed to the professional development of the PI, an early-career scientist, and the development of his research program.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/26/2020<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;C&nbsp;Winters</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1624316/1624316_10494170_1603729879597_NSF_OutcomesFig--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1624316/1624316_10494170_1603729879597_NSF_OutcomesFig--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Conceptual Models of Jet Superpositions"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1624316/1624316_10494170_1603729879597_NSF_OutcomesFig--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Conceptual Models of Jet Superpositions"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conceptual models illustrating the development of each jet superposition event type. Figure adapted from Winters et al. (2020; their Fig. 14), which is copyrighted by the American Meteorological Society.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Winters, A. C., D. Keyser, L. F. Bosart, and J. E. Martin, 2020: Composite synoptic-scale environments conducive to North American polar-subtropical jet superposition events. Mon. Wea. Rev., 148, doi: 10.1175/MWR-D-19-0353.1.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andrew&nbsp;C&nbsp;Winters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Conceptual Models of Jet Superpositions</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  The Northern Hemisphere is typically characterized by two rapidly moving currents of air, or jet streams, that are situated 10-12 km above the Earth's surface. The polar jet (PJ) stream is located around 50oN and sits atop a strong, tropospheric-deep temperature contrast known as the polar front. The subtropical jet (SJ) stream is located equatorward of the PJ around 30oN and sits atop a comparatively modest temperature contrast in the middle and upper-troposphere. While the PJ and SJ often remain separated from one another, they can occasionally merge to form a polar-subtropical jet superposition. Jet superpositions are characterized by strong upper-tropospheric wind speeds that can often exceed 100 m/s, as well as the development of an intense horizontal temperature contrast in the vicinity of the jet. Jet superpositions can also contribute to the production of high-impact weather events, including strong low-pressure systems, floods, blizzards, and severe weather outbreaks. Consequently, this project was centered on providing an improved understanding the processes that contribute to the development of jet superpositions over North America.  This study identified a total of 326 jet superposition events using the NCEP Climate Forecast System Reanalysis (CFSR) dataset during November-March 1979-2010. These events were then classified into event types based on the location at which the PJ and SJ became superposed. Polar dominant events are those events in which the PJ superposed with the SJ near the climatological latitude of the SJ, while subtropical dominant events are those in which the SJ superposed with the PJ near the climatological latitude of the PJ. While polar dominant events are most frequent along the U.S./Mexico border and Gulf Coast, subtropical dominant events are most frequent along either the east or west coasts of North America. This latter observation motivated splitting subtropical dominant events into an eastern and western category for further analysis. Overall, North American jet superposition events are most frequent during the early part of the cold season (November-December) and become less frequent during January-March.   The development of each jet superposition event type is summarized within the conceptual models attached to this summary. Polar dominant events result from an amplification of the upper-tropospheric flow pattern over the eastern North Pacific that leads to an equatorward displacement of the PJ towards the position of the SJ. The development of a jet superposition in this case is predominantly driven by strong subsidence on the northwestern flank of the jet, which acts to strengthen the horizontal temperature contrast beneath the jet and accelerate jet wind speeds. Farther downstream of the superposition, polar dominant events feature the concurrent development of a strong surface low-pressure system and a corridor of enhanced moisture transport into the southern U.S. that may be conducive to heavy precipitation. Both subtropical dominant event types are preceded by precipitation on the equatorward side of the jet and the development of a surface low-pressure system. The extensive precipitation to the south of the developing jet superposition acts to amplify the upper-tropospheric flow pattern and displace the SJ northward into closer proximity with the PJ. Once the two jets are in close proximity, descending motion on the northwestern flank of the developing jet superposition strengthens the horizontal temperature contrast beneath the jet, similar to polar dominant events, and acts to accelerate jet wind speeds.  Numerical simulations of a subtropical dominant event suggest that the cumulative influence of precipitation processes on the structure of the upper-tropospheric flow pattern is a discriminating factor as to whether the PJ and SJ superpose or remain separate. Such a result has important implications for the predictability of jet superpositions, given that forecasts of precipitation processes are a considerable source of uncertainty in forecast models. The analysis also reveals that a considerable fraction of vertical motion in the vicinity of jet superpositions is driven by upper-level disturbances on the poleward flank of the PJ, whereas the encroachment of the SJ into close proximity with the PJ primarily provides a favorable thermodynamic environment with enhanced moisture and reduced resistance to vertical motion.   Broader Impacts:  The results from this project have a tangible impact on society by fostering improved situational awareness among forecasters and researchers of a type of meteorological environment conducive to high-impact weather events. This project also contributed to the training of 4 undergraduate students at the University at Albany, SUNY and the University of Colorado Boulder, as well as 1 graduate student at the University at Albany, SUNY. This project supported a review article coauthored by the PI summarizing 100 years of research on extratropical cyclones, which will serve as a guide for future research conducted by synoptic-dynamic meteorologists. Last, this fellowship contributed to the professional development of the PI, an early-career scientist, and the development of his research program.          Last Modified: 10/26/2020       Submitted by: Andrew C Winters]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
