<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Easy-to-Use Software for Automation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Automation can make repetitive or boring physical tasks ? like moving boxes onto a conveyor belt-a trivial component of life; however, small businesses and consumers that want to use automation in their workspace and/or home face insurmountable challenges to enter a highly technical field. Typically, external companies called robotic integrators are employed for designing and implementing such systems. While the hardware used in this process is getting cheaper and cheaper, the physical labor of highly trained technical engineers needed to build and program these systems is not. This I-Corps team is developing easy-to-use software that will allow nontechnical users to design and implement their own automated systems that are customized to their own needs without having to hire costly robotic integrators. The new, proposed technology is lowering the barrier to entry for small business owners and home consumers through a web-based software platform where users can build their own programs for automation through a nontechnical, intuitive user interface. This initial prototype leverages a way of thinking about automation in terms of action and sensing primitives that derives from a university robotics research lab. The proposed technology has the potential to dramatically transform the population of people to whom automation, and its well-documented benefits, is available. The approach taken in this technology could bring simple, moving machines into many more environments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Expanding the use cases of industrial automation to smaller batch sizes and narrower profit margins is a key challenge toward realizing the vision of the Internet of Things. This challenge is due in large part to the high cost of technical expertise required for the integration of available, cost-effective sensors, actuators, and algorithms. However, relatively inexpensive software can be developed to help users adapt existing technology to their environment. The proposed technology utilizes two key technical areas. One area is the computational architecture of the product and the development of a scalable code architecture and support for a larger number of so-called sensing and action primitives. Another area is in human factors where the ability of an untrained user to move from a contextualized use-case to specific logic design is key. Here, a relatively complex process must be distilled to essential steps that an untrained user can relate to a familiar process in a particular environment. Participation in the Innovation Corps will allow the team to identify and research the appropriate market in which to develop and launch a first product. In particular, the team will explore which customer base ? ranging from at-home hobbyists to small-to-medium sized industrial companies-is a good fit, in terms of feasible application of the technology as well as market demand and pricing, for the proposed technology. The team's participation will influence parallel development of technology and inform a business plan that will allow for commercialization of the technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1624112</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
<LastName>LaViers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amy E LaViers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amy@theradlab.xyz</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8655489232</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000652815</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S. Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>AE Machines empowers manufacturers and hobbyists to program and reprogram simple automated systems without relying on the help of engineers. The company was founded as a result of the co-founders&rsquo;, one of whom is a university faculty member and robotics researcher, work with a small business to implement a simple automated system.&nbsp; The system AE has built is predicated on a simple, key technological approach: <strong><em>we work from a top-down movement abstraction and build the necessary low-level architecture needed to realize the high-level function.</em></strong> This is accomplished through an interdisciplinary team approach combining computer science, robotics expertise, and movement-based abstractions to build a web-based, easy-to-use platform.</p> <p>This I-Corps award trained the founding team of AE Machines in lean start up methodology and funded extensive customer interviews in the maker/hobbyist and industrial/manufacturing areas. &nbsp;Additionally, the award funded travel to meetings with and presentations for potential investors.&nbsp; The objective of these activities was to determine a product-market fit and commercialize research in robotic automation.</p> <p>Two customer bases, and related pain points were identified through customer interviews: 1) hobbyists and educators who want to work with cheap, easily available hardware, such as Arduino microcontrollers but lack technical acumen, e.g., coding skills, to get started and 2) small manufacturers, and the system integrators who serve them, who need flexible automation solutions to serve their small-batch processes. To the former, the current demo tool developed by the start up is a meaningful tool; thus, much of the customer interviews conducted were with this first group of stakeholders. To the latter, site visits to factories and system integrators facilitated needed understanding to propose how to scale the demo tool to industrial settings, which is the target market for the start up company.</p> <p>In customer interviews with hobbyists, conducted in Maker Spaces and at Maker Faires, the team identified key issues with the site's usability, which was being tested in a parallel NSF SBIR Phase I award. &nbsp;In customer interviews with industrial stakeholders, conducted mainly in the Central Illinois (and surrounding states) region or by phone, the team learned about how most small manufacturers outsource the integration of automation cells to specialized engineering and fabrication companies, known as "system integrators" or original equipment manufacturers (OEMs). &nbsp;&nbsp;In meetings with private investors, the team learned which key progress indicators (KPIs) are of most interest to investors. In particular, letters of intent (LOIs) can show traction for the commercialization approach even when funding for a prototype is not available. Toward the end of the grant period, the team began focusing on these types of interaction to gain LOIs and will continue them after the award period.</p> <p>Through these activities, the team identified tangible improvements to a demo prototype, the AE Design Tool, which is live at <a href="http://www.aemachines.com">www.aemachines.com</a> and <a href="http://www.aemachines.io">www.aemachines.io</a>, potential industrial customers and investors (to support a company in that space), as well as a partner and user base in the educational/hobbyist domain with a start up called MakeCrate, which creates educational kits centered around Arduino microcontrollers. The development of the prototype occurred through a separate grant, but the customer discovery supported by this grant was critical in guiding that development.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> &nbsp;The intellectual merit of the project was in understanding the technical challenges faced by hobbyists and small manufacturers in the framework of value propositions the company could make to customers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader/Commercial Impact:</strong>&nbsp; The commercialization efforts initiated in the project aim to translate an initial hobbyist prototype to an industrially viable prototype that can attract private venture funding to launch a successful software company in the space of automation.&nbsp; Flexible automation cells are particularly needed in small-batch processes, which change week-to-week or day-to-day, that can be powered by our software.&nbsp; In this context, our tool has the potential to allow workers currently on the factory floor to be able to manage and automate factory lines with skills they already have, creating &ldquo;middle-skilled&rdquo; jobs needed in an advanced manufacturing economy.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/26/2017<br>      Modified by: Amy&nbsp;E&nbsp;Laviers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ AE Machines empowers manufacturers and hobbyists to program and reprogram simple automated systems without relying on the help of engineers. The company was founded as a result of the co-founders?, one of whom is a university faculty member and robotics researcher, work with a small business to implement a simple automated system.  The system AE has built is predicated on a simple, key technological approach: we work from a top-down movement abstraction and build the necessary low-level architecture needed to realize the high-level function. This is accomplished through an interdisciplinary team approach combining computer science, robotics expertise, and movement-based abstractions to build a web-based, easy-to-use platform.  This I-Corps award trained the founding team of AE Machines in lean start up methodology and funded extensive customer interviews in the maker/hobbyist and industrial/manufacturing areas.  Additionally, the award funded travel to meetings with and presentations for potential investors.  The objective of these activities was to determine a product-market fit and commercialize research in robotic automation.  Two customer bases, and related pain points were identified through customer interviews: 1) hobbyists and educators who want to work with cheap, easily available hardware, such as Arduino microcontrollers but lack technical acumen, e.g., coding skills, to get started and 2) small manufacturers, and the system integrators who serve them, who need flexible automation solutions to serve their small-batch processes. To the former, the current demo tool developed by the start up is a meaningful tool; thus, much of the customer interviews conducted were with this first group of stakeholders. To the latter, site visits to factories and system integrators facilitated needed understanding to propose how to scale the demo tool to industrial settings, which is the target market for the start up company.  In customer interviews with hobbyists, conducted in Maker Spaces and at Maker Faires, the team identified key issues with the site's usability, which was being tested in a parallel NSF SBIR Phase I award.  In customer interviews with industrial stakeholders, conducted mainly in the Central Illinois (and surrounding states) region or by phone, the team learned about how most small manufacturers outsource the integration of automation cells to specialized engineering and fabrication companies, known as "system integrators" or original equipment manufacturers (OEMs).   In meetings with private investors, the team learned which key progress indicators (KPIs) are of most interest to investors. In particular, letters of intent (LOIs) can show traction for the commercialization approach even when funding for a prototype is not available. Toward the end of the grant period, the team began focusing on these types of interaction to gain LOIs and will continue them after the award period.  Through these activities, the team identified tangible improvements to a demo prototype, the AE Design Tool, which is live at www.aemachines.com and www.aemachines.io, potential industrial customers and investors (to support a company in that space), as well as a partner and user base in the educational/hobbyist domain with a start up called MakeCrate, which creates educational kits centered around Arduino microcontrollers. The development of the prototype occurred through a separate grant, but the customer discovery supported by this grant was critical in guiding that development.     Intellectual Merit:  The intellectual merit of the project was in understanding the technical challenges faced by hobbyists and small manufacturers in the framework of value propositions the company could make to customers.     Broader/Commercial Impact:  The commercialization efforts initiated in the project aim to translate an initial hobbyist prototype to an industrially viable prototype that can attract private venture funding to launch a successful software company in the space of automation.  Flexible automation cells are particularly needed in small-batch processes, which change week-to-week or day-to-day, that can be powered by our software.  In this context, our tool has the potential to allow workers currently on the factory floor to be able to manage and automate factory lines with skills they already have, creating "middle-skilled" jobs needed in an advanced manufacturing economy.          Last Modified: 09/26/2017       Submitted by: Amy E Laviers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
