<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Metalloradical Catalysis for Selective Radical Reactions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/06/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Dawes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rdawes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927486</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project funded by the Chemical Catalysis program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Peter Zhang of the University of South Florida applies the concept of metalloradical catalysis for the development of new catalytic systems based on cobalt(II) complexes of porphyrins to control the reactivity and selectivity of radical reactions. Since metalloradical catalysis can generate radical intermediates catalytically without the need for stoichiometric initiators such as the commonly employed organotin reagents, the method will have a positive environmental impact. In comparison with the typical need for rare and expensive second- and third-row metal ions to catalyze two-electron ionic reactions, one-electron radical reactions can be carried out effectively with catalysts based on earth-abundant and inexpensive first-row transition metal ions such as cobalt. As such, the development of metalloradical catalysis addresses the increasing need for sustainable catalysts. The proposed project by Professor Zhang integrates research and educational activities. In addition to scientific training for graduate and postdoctoral students, laboratory experiences for high school students and teachers, as well as undergraduate students, are provided.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These new catalytic radical processes, which are both mechanistically distinctive and operationally attractive, serve as valuable synthetic tools for constructing organic compounds, such as biologically important natural products and pharmaceutically interesting small molecules. On the basis of the fundamental understanding of the catalytic mechanisms of Co(II)-based radical cyclopropanation and aziridination reactions, new catalytic processes that involve a cascade sequence of radical reactions are in development to allow for the efficient construction of carbocycles and heterocycles beyond three-membered cyclopropanes and aziridines. Through the design and synthesis of chiral porphyrins possessing potential hydrogen bonding capability and with tunable electronic, steric, and chiral environments as the supporting ligands, this project aims to achieve several specific types of Co(II)-catalyzed radical cascade processes. The success of this project may prompt the identification of new metalloradical catalyst systems based on different combinations of open-shell metal ions and chiral ligands that can catalyze a broad range of stereoselective radical reactions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1624216</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>peter.zhang@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175521483</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000224638</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673860</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2609 Beacon Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8398</Code>
<Text>Hydrocarbon Conversion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~420000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Organic reactions are bond breaking and bond forming processes. Between two fundamental pathways, ionic reactions via heterolysis have been extensively utilized for organic synthesis while radical reactions via homolysis have are much less explored for construction of organic molecules. However, radical chemistry has attracted growing research interest over the last few decades and radical reactions have now been well recognized as potentially powerful tools for organic synthesis. In fact, their synthetic applications have already been demonstrated in many fields, including in the synthesis of complex natural products. In comparison with ionic reactions, radical reactions have a number of inherent synthetic advantages. For example, they typically proceed at fast reaction rates under mild and neutral conditions in a broad spectrum of solvents and show significantly high functional group tolerance. Furthermore, radical processes have the capability to perform in a cascade fashion, allowing for the rapid construction of complex molecular structures with multiple stereogenic centers. In order to further harness the vast potential of radical reactions for organic synthesis, there are needs for the development of new approaches for the effective control of their reactivity as well as stereoselectivity, especially enantioselectivity, a challenging issue that is intrinsically associated with the "free" nature of radical chemistry.</p> <p>This research has been&nbsp;<em></em>centered on the identification of new approaches to take full advantage of 1e radical chemistry for development of new synthetic methods. Results from recent studies have led to the establishment of metalloradical catalysis (MRC) as a fundamentally new approach for controlling stereoselectivity of both C- and N-centered radical reactions. Co(II) complexes of porphyrins ([Co(Por)]), a class of stable metalloradicals, have been shown to enable the activation of diazo reagents and organic azides to&nbsp;cleanly generate&nbsp;&alpha;-Co(III)-alkyl radicals and&nbsp;&alpha;-Co(III)-aminyl radicals, respectively, with N<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>as the only byproduct in a controlled and catalytic manner. The initially formed C- and N-centered radicals, which remain bonded covalently with [Co(Por)] units, can undergo common radical reactions such as radical addition and radical abstraction, but with effective control of reactivity and stereoselectivity by the environment of the porphyrin ligand. In addition to the radical nature of [Co(Por)], the low bond dissociation energy of Co-C/Co-N bonds plays a key role for the successful turnover of the Co(II)-based catalytic radical processes. Through the support of porphyrin ligands with tunable electronic, steric, and chiral environments, this general concept of Co(II)-based metalloradical catalysis is applied for the development of various radical processes for stereoselective synthesis of organic molecules.</p> <p>In this project funded by the Chemical Catalysis program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Peter Zhang at Boston College applies the concept of metalloradical catalysis for the development of new catalytic systems based on cobalt(II) complexes of porphyrins to control the reactivity and selectivity of radical reactions. Since metalloradical catalysis can generate radical intermediates catalytically without the need for stoichiometric initiators such as the commonly employed organotin reagents, the method will have a positive environmental impact. In comparison with the typical need for rare and expensive second- and third-row metal ions to catalyze two-electron ionic reactions, one-electron radical reactions can be carried out effectively with catalysts based on earth-abundant and inexpensive first-row transition metal ions such as cobalt. As such, the development of metalloradical catalysis addresses the increasing need for sustainable catalysts. The project by Professor Zhang integrates research and educational activities. In addition to scientific training for graduate and postdoctoral students, laboratory experiences for high school students and teachers, as well as undergraduate students, are provided.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2019<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Organic reactions are bond breaking and bond forming processes. Between two fundamental pathways, ionic reactions via heterolysis have been extensively utilized for organic synthesis while radical reactions via homolysis have are much less explored for construction of organic molecules. However, radical chemistry has attracted growing research interest over the last few decades and radical reactions have now been well recognized as potentially powerful tools for organic synthesis. In fact, their synthetic applications have already been demonstrated in many fields, including in the synthesis of complex natural products. In comparison with ionic reactions, radical reactions have a number of inherent synthetic advantages. For example, they typically proceed at fast reaction rates under mild and neutral conditions in a broad spectrum of solvents and show significantly high functional group tolerance. Furthermore, radical processes have the capability to perform in a cascade fashion, allowing for the rapid construction of complex molecular structures with multiple stereogenic centers. In order to further harness the vast potential of radical reactions for organic synthesis, there are needs for the development of new approaches for the effective control of their reactivity as well as stereoselectivity, especially enantioselectivity, a challenging issue that is intrinsically associated with the "free" nature of radical chemistry.  This research has been centered on the identification of new approaches to take full advantage of 1e radical chemistry for development of new synthetic methods. Results from recent studies have led to the establishment of metalloradical catalysis (MRC) as a fundamentally new approach for controlling stereoselectivity of both C- and N-centered radical reactions. Co(II) complexes of porphyrins ([Co(Por)]), a class of stable metalloradicals, have been shown to enable the activation of diazo reagents and organic azides to cleanly generate &alpha;-Co(III)-alkyl radicals and &alpha;-Co(III)-aminyl radicals, respectively, with N2 as the only byproduct in a controlled and catalytic manner. The initially formed C- and N-centered radicals, which remain bonded covalently with [Co(Por)] units, can undergo common radical reactions such as radical addition and radical abstraction, but with effective control of reactivity and stereoselectivity by the environment of the porphyrin ligand. In addition to the radical nature of [Co(Por)], the low bond dissociation energy of Co-C/Co-N bonds plays a key role for the successful turnover of the Co(II)-based catalytic radical processes. Through the support of porphyrin ligands with tunable electronic, steric, and chiral environments, this general concept of Co(II)-based metalloradical catalysis is applied for the development of various radical processes for stereoselective synthesis of organic molecules.  In this project funded by the Chemical Catalysis program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Peter Zhang at Boston College applies the concept of metalloradical catalysis for the development of new catalytic systems based on cobalt(II) complexes of porphyrins to control the reactivity and selectivity of radical reactions. Since metalloradical catalysis can generate radical intermediates catalytically without the need for stoichiometric initiators such as the commonly employed organotin reagents, the method will have a positive environmental impact. In comparison with the typical need for rare and expensive second- and third-row metal ions to catalyze two-electron ionic reactions, one-electron radical reactions can be carried out effectively with catalysts based on earth-abundant and inexpensive first-row transition metal ions such as cobalt. As such, the development of metalloradical catalysis addresses the increasing need for sustainable catalysts. The project by Professor Zhang integrates research and educational activities. In addition to scientific training for graduate and postdoctoral students, laboratory experiences for high school students and teachers, as well as undergraduate students, are provided.       Last Modified: 08/31/2019       Submitted by: Peter Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
