<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Development of a Separator for Capture Reactions (SECAR) Phase 2</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allena K. Opper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aopper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928958</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>It is well known that nuclei are made from protons and neutrons.  One of the open questions in nuclear science, as identified by the Nuclear Science Advisory Committee, is: what is the origin of the elements?  To produce nuclei having more than a few neutrons and protons requires a sequence of nuclear reactions that take place in stars.  To produce nuclei heavier than iron requires a highly energetic environment, such as a supernova explosion or a neutron star merger.  The equipment to be built here, the Separated Capture Reaction (SECAR) spectrometer, will enable physicists at the National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory (NSCL) to measure rare nuclear reactions that are necessary to understand the origin of the elements.  Phase 2 of the SECAR spectrometer, planned here, will become a world-leading facility for this purpose.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SECAR Phase 2 opens a wide range of science opportunities. It enables measurements of the entire range of important reactions in X-ray bursts, the most common thermonuclear explosions observed in our Galaxy. X-ray bursts occur on the surface of mass-accreting neutron stars. With the SECAR Phase 2 data, burst observations can be used to probe the properties of neutron stars and X-ray binary systems. In addition, predictions can be made of the elements created that form the crust of the neutron star and may also, in part, be ejected into space. SECAR Phase 2 will also enable predictions of the element signatures of astrophysical Nova explosions, especially unusually energetic events that may be observed with new telescopes in the near future. This will help to identify the signatures of these events in observational data, and in the composition of meteoritic grains found on earth. SECAR Phase 2 data will also help understand the production of radioactive elements in supernovae, the signatures of the most massive stars ever that existed in the early universe, the contribution of supernova neutrino winds to the origin of the elements, and help prove, or disprove, the existence of Thorne-Zytkov objects, hypothetical stellar objects that contain a neutron star as their core.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1624942</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Manoel</FirstName>
<LastName>Couder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Manoel Couder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcouder@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746317432</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000642724</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hendrik</FirstName>
<LastName>Schatz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hendrik Schatz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schatz@nscl.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173336397</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000292624</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael S Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>msmith@mail.phy.ornl.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8655765037</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000330611</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488244538</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[640 South Shaw Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~1500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project established the second stage of the SECAR Recoil Separator instrument at the National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory and the Facility for Rare Isotope Beams at Michigan State University. SECAR will enable to restage and study in the laboratory the nuclear reactions that power stellar explosions in the cosmos. Data obtained with SECAR will be used to predict which elements and isotopes stellar explosions such as x-ray bursts, gamma-ray bursts, novae, or supernovae create. This will answer questions about the origin of the elements and, through comparison with observed elements, about the nature of these explosions. For example, with data from SECAR one will be able to predict the amount radioactive isotopes created in a supernova explosion. These isotopes may be searched for by present and future space based gamma-ray observatories, and may also leave traces on earth should a stellar explosion occur in close proximity to the solar system.</p> <p>The second stage established in this project dramatically increases the sensitivity to enable measurement of many very slow astrophysical reactions for the first time. This is accomplished through a custom-built Wien filter, a device that combines a magnetic field with a strong electric field created by a potential difference of up to 600,000 Volts. With this second stage, SECAR will be able to detect reactions that occur down to a level of 1 in 100 quadrillions.</p> <p>SECAR is being installed at Michigan State University, and students play a critical role in the project. The SECAR project offered unique hands on training and education in the technology and operation of an ion optical transport device that is directly applicable to nuclear accelerators and spectrometers more broadly. As such SECAR contributes to highly specialized workforce development in an area that is important for the broader economy, energy, and security. The impact was further broadened by an ion optics school for students from multiple US educational institutions that used hands on cooperative group work with SECAR ion optics as a novel teaching tool.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2021<br>      Modified by: Hendrik&nbsp;Schatz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project established the second stage of the SECAR Recoil Separator instrument at the National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory and the Facility for Rare Isotope Beams at Michigan State University. SECAR will enable to restage and study in the laboratory the nuclear reactions that power stellar explosions in the cosmos. Data obtained with SECAR will be used to predict which elements and isotopes stellar explosions such as x-ray bursts, gamma-ray bursts, novae, or supernovae create. This will answer questions about the origin of the elements and, through comparison with observed elements, about the nature of these explosions. For example, with data from SECAR one will be able to predict the amount radioactive isotopes created in a supernova explosion. These isotopes may be searched for by present and future space based gamma-ray observatories, and may also leave traces on earth should a stellar explosion occur in close proximity to the solar system.  The second stage established in this project dramatically increases the sensitivity to enable measurement of many very slow astrophysical reactions for the first time. This is accomplished through a custom-built Wien filter, a device that combines a magnetic field with a strong electric field created by a potential difference of up to 600,000 Volts. With this second stage, SECAR will be able to detect reactions that occur down to a level of 1 in 100 quadrillions.  SECAR is being installed at Michigan State University, and students play a critical role in the project. The SECAR project offered unique hands on training and education in the technology and operation of an ion optical transport device that is directly applicable to nuclear accelerators and spectrometers more broadly. As such SECAR contributes to highly specialized workforce development in an area that is important for the broader economy, energy, and security. The impact was further broadened by an ion optics school for students from multiple US educational institutions that used hands on cooperative group work with SECAR ion optics as a novel teaching tool.          Last Modified: 08/05/2021       Submitted by: Hendrik Schatz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
