<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Screened Lab Addition to Enhance New Ecological Research at Clemson's Baruch Institute</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>171473.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>171473</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter McCartney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmccartn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928470</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Coastal landscapes experience a variety of environmental stresses caused by changes in land&amp;#8232;use, climate, storm frequency and intensity, and saltwater intrusion. Research at the Clemson University &amp;#8232;Baruch Institute of Coastal Ecology and Forest Science (BICEFS) focuses on understanding how three major components of the landscape - water, vegetation, and wildlife - are affected by and respond to man-made and natural disturbances. Research at BICEFS spans from the heart of cities to the wildest places in the landscape in an effort to understand how these components&amp;#8232;are interconnected. In the last three years, BICEFS has doubled the size of its faculty from five to ten, adding new research lines in wildlife biology, landscape ecology, and ecosystem service economics. This project responds to that growth by adding a 1110-square-foot screened lab to an existing lab building to provide new, flexible workspace to support new research initiatives, field lab activities, and training. The institute's location in coastal South Carolina enables outside activities year-round and therefore the design provides energy efficiency and simplicity for cleaning, maintenance, and project specific set up. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Like many field stations, BICEFS operates its labs and major equipment on a shared basis. Lab space is designated to various activities or analyses that support major research lines, rather than to individual investigators. As the faculty has expanded in the last two years, common space has been repurposed for more specialized uses and upgraded or new instrumentation has been added as part of start-up or state-funded initiatives. As a result, the lab is limited by available workspace for staging experiments, sample processing, instrument maintenance, etc. Various space studies have provided recommendations for lab space on a per scientist basis that is sufficient to support a vibrant research program and the development of graduate&amp;#8232;and undergraduate research. To bring capacity up to  these recommendations, a 1110-ft2 screened workspace will be constructed on the side and end of the existing laboratory building. The construction is a simple design, with a concrete slab, screened walls, and a metal roof. Basic electrical and plumbing hookups are included, as well as shelving, cabinets, and portable furniture. A walk-in cooler will be installed at one end of the space to store plant, soil, and animal samples. The flexible, all-season design facilitates research by faculty and students and, in part, that of collaborators from 39 other institutions that use the property.  The design also facilitates lab-type classroom activities and workshops. The Institute's web site is www.clemson.edu/baruch.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1624705</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Skip</FirstName>
<LastName>Van Bloem</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Skip J Van Bloem</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>skipvb@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8435641013</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000662858</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clemson University</Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296345701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLEMSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clemson University -- Baruch Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Georgetown</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>294401903</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[130 Heriot]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1104</Code>
<Text>FIELD STATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~171473</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Since 2013, the Baruch Institute of Coastal Ecology and Forest Science (Clemson University) has doubled the size of its faculty.&nbsp;&nbsp;We added new research lines in wetlands, waterfowl, other wildlife ecology and conservation, landscape ecology, and ecosystem service economics.&nbsp;&nbsp;In the process, we have outgrown current lab facilities, particularly ?dirty? workspace.&nbsp;&nbsp;This project funded the construction of a 1,110-ft<sup>2</sup>screened addition to our existing lab building to provide new, flexible workspace to support our current and new research initiatives.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our location in coastal South Carolina allows us to work outside year-round and therefore the design provides energy efficiency and simplicity for sample processing, cleaning, maintenance, and project logistics.</p> <p>The construction of this project was completed in August 2018 according to plan and budget. Using screened outdoor space is energy efficient because we use natural lighting and climate control, and use less building materials than enclosed additions. This helps add to our LEED certified campus and continues to set the example for sustainable development.</p> <p>Additional flexible dirty lab space is particularly critical for our research program.&nbsp;For example, our wildlife biologists focus on the biology and conservation of important species in coastal Carolina ecosystems, such as migratory waterfowl, alligators, and other wetland plants and animals. These species are important components of coastal Carolina ecosystems. This additional space has already been extremely useful for the sorting, processing, prepping, and storing of field samples, particularly those that are messy (e.g., muddy, dirty, wet) and often malodorous (e.g., spoiled alligator and waterfowl eggs, tissues from animals in various stages of decomposition, wildlife stomach contents).&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The additional space has already been used for a Forested Wetland Ecology graduate course, a Longleaf Pine Restoration and Management course for landowners and resource managers, a workshop on developing new coastal environmental monitoring networks. The space will be used to support three graduate courses that are offered this spring: Biogeochemistry, Forest Dynamics, and Forested Wetland Management.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/15/2019<br>      Modified by: Skip&nbsp;J&nbsp;Van Bloem</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624705/1624705_10460653_1550265255020_20190104_125310--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624705/1624705_10460653_1550265255020_20190104_125310--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Front View"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624705/1624705_10460653_1550265255020_20190104_125310--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Front View"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Front View of the new porch at the Clemson Baruch Institute</div> <div class="imageCredit">Skip Van Bloem</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Skip&nbsp;J&nbsp;Van Bloem</div> <div class="imageTitle">Front View</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624705/1624705_10460653_1550265466727_20181030_134124--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624705/1624705_10460653_1550265466727_20181030_134124--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Space in Use"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1624705/1624705_10460653_1550265466727_20181030_134124--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Space in Use"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students and staff using the new space to sort wetlands plants collected from the Savannah River.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Skip Van Bloem</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Skip&nbsp;J&nbsp;Van Bloem</div> <div class="imageTitle">Space in Use</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Since 2013, the Baruch Institute of Coastal Ecology and Forest Science (Clemson University) has doubled the size of its faculty.  We added new research lines in wetlands, waterfowl, other wildlife ecology and conservation, landscape ecology, and ecosystem service economics.  In the process, we have outgrown current lab facilities, particularly ?dirty? workspace.  This project funded the construction of a 1,110-ft2screened addition to our existing lab building to provide new, flexible workspace to support our current and new research initiatives.  Our location in coastal South Carolina allows us to work outside year-round and therefore the design provides energy efficiency and simplicity for sample processing, cleaning, maintenance, and project logistics.  The construction of this project was completed in August 2018 according to plan and budget. Using screened outdoor space is energy efficient because we use natural lighting and climate control, and use less building materials than enclosed additions. This helps add to our LEED certified campus and continues to set the example for sustainable development.  Additional flexible dirty lab space is particularly critical for our research program. For example, our wildlife biologists focus on the biology and conservation of important species in coastal Carolina ecosystems, such as migratory waterfowl, alligators, and other wetland plants and animals. These species are important components of coastal Carolina ecosystems. This additional space has already been extremely useful for the sorting, processing, prepping, and storing of field samples, particularly those that are messy (e.g., muddy, dirty, wet) and often malodorous (e.g., spoiled alligator and waterfowl eggs, tissues from animals in various stages of decomposition, wildlife stomach contents).    The additional space has already been used for a Forested Wetland Ecology graduate course, a Longleaf Pine Restoration and Management course for landowners and resource managers, a workshop on developing new coastal environmental monitoring networks. The space will be used to support three graduate courses that are offered this spring: Biogeochemistry, Forest Dynamics, and Forested Wetland Management.          Last Modified: 02/15/2019       Submitted by: Skip J Van Bloem]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
