<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Crime Risk and Police Notification</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>81110.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>81110</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reggie Sheehan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsheehan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925389</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will examine three questions: (1) Is the risk of non-lethal criminal victimization among persons and households in the US significantly influenced by neighborhood immigrant concentration? (2) Is the likelihood of police notification among crime victims significantly influenced by neighborhood immigrant concentration? and (3) Do the effects of neighborhood immigrant concentration on victimization risk and police notification differ by individual race and ethnicity, and across counties that exhibit variability in immigration history, minority political incorporation, and the nature of policing?  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These questions will be addressed by linking data on victimization and police notification from more than 600,000 household and 1 million person interviews from the 2007-2014 restricted-use NCVS to data from the American Community Survey and other sources. This project will advance understanding by: (1) offering the first nationwide analysis of the influence of neighborhood immigrant concentration on reporting crime to the police; (2) reevaluating the impact of neighborhood immigrant concentration on crime with data that include incidents both reported and unreported to the police; and (3) considering multiple measures of neighborhood immigrant concentration (the percentage foreign born, neighborhood spatial clustering or isolation of the foreign born, and foreign born concentration for Latinos and Asians).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1625698</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Baumer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric Baumer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>epb5167@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148652527</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000522510</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[U.S. Census Bureau]]></Name>
<CityName>Suitland</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207462574</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4600 Silver Hill Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LSS-Law And Social Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~81110</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview</strong></p> <p>The collaborative project<strong>&nbsp;</strong>integrates data from area-identified National Crime Victimization Survey (NCVS) and other external data sources to examine three questions: (1) Is the risk of non-lethal criminal victimization among persons and households in the US significantly influenced by neighborhood (i.e., census tract) immigrant concentration? (2) Is the likelihood of police notification among crime victims significantly influenced by neighborhood immigrant concentration? (3) Do observed effects of neighborhood immigrant concentration on victimization risk and police notification differ across counties that vary significantly on immigration history (traditional vs. new immigrant destinations) and other attributes (economic and political conditions)?</p> <p>These questions are addressed by linking data on victimization and police notification from the 1996-2014 restricted-use, area-identified, NCVS to data on demographic, socioeconomic, and political attributes of census tracts and counties drawn from the American Community Survey and other sources. To date, the collaborative project has yielded four peer-reviewed journal publications, among other results (see image).</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>The project has provided important new insights into the nature and meaning of community differences in levels of immigration and crime that previous data analyses has not been able to identify. Previously, a substantial body of research has documented lower rates of crime in communities with higher immigrant concentrations, but this research has relied almost exclusively on police-based data or data on homicides, and thus a high percentage of crime that is non-lethal and not known to the police has been left out of the investigation.</p> <p>The project significantly advances understanding of neighborhood patterns of immigration and crime by: (1) offering the first nationwide analysis of the influence of neighborhood immigrant concentration on the reporting of crime to the police; (2) reevaluating the impact of neighborhood immigrant concentration on crime with data that include incidents both reported and unreported to the police; and (3) examining several theoretically informed conditional impacts of neighborhood immigrant concentration on both victimization and reporting, including whether observed effects are moderated by individual race and ethnicity and theoretically relevant county conditions.</p> <p>Important findings of the project include: (1) Neighborhood immigration concentration is negatively associated with victimization risk even including crimes not reported to the police.&nbsp; For whites, blacks, and Latinos, we find a consistent protective role of neighborhood immigrant concentration on violence risk that is not weakened by low education, low income, being unemployed, or being subject to labor market competition, which suggests that even those who are economically more vulnerable enjoy the crime-reducing benefit of immigration.&nbsp; (2) Crimes are less likely to be reported to the police by victims of high-immigrant-centration neighborhoods located in new immigrant counties.&nbsp; In traditional immigrant counties, crime reporting rates are not significantly influenced by the level of immigrant concentration in neighborhoods. &nbsp;(3) States have different approaches to immigration.&nbsp; We find that the total number of state-level immigration policies has risen significantly since the mid-2000s, and state-level immigration policies vary substantially in their underlying principles (e.g., a goal of integrating immigrants vs. a goal of identifying immigrants and enforcing immigration law).&nbsp; In addition, we find that the states' legislative efforts are better explained by their historical experience with immigration than by their location close to or far away from national borders.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>The results of the project help inform public discourse and social policy regarding the incorporation of the immigrant population into local communities. Our finding that even those who are vulnerable to competition in labor markets enjoy the crime-reduction benefit of immigrant concentration is an important finding that should encourage local communities to evaluate their attitude towards immigration and create a more immigrant-friendly environment to facilitate the adaptation of immigrants into the receiving communities.&nbsp; Our study on crime reporting, in addition, indicates that residents of high-concentration immigrant neighborhoods have lower rates of crime reporting than do residents of other neighborhoods.&nbsp; This relationship is shown to be dependent on several conditions: how high is the level of neighborhood immigrant concentration, and how long is the history of the counties in receiving immigrants.&nbsp; These findings provide a better understanding of the victims' needs in immigrant neighborhoods that will be useful in making decisions on victim service planning to better serve local communities.</p> <p>Further, the project team has emphasized the integration of research into several educational activities, including the development of new undergraduate and graduate courses on core themes of the project (immigration, victimology, and the mobilization of law) and the integration of students from underrepresented groups and ethnic minorities into research and professional development. &nbsp;</p> <p>The project also has contributed to enhancing the social science infrastructure and capacity to study immigration and crime by integrating data from a wide variety of sources including the National Crime Victimization Survey (NCVS), the American Community Survey, the Decennial Census, and the National Conference of State Legislatures (NCSL).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/04/2019<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;Baumer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1625698/1625698_10441851_1570881908363_Image--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1625698/1625698_10441851_1570881908363_Image--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Baumer and Xie_Award 1625730 Outcomes Image"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1625698/1625698_10441851_1570881908363_Image--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Baumer and Xie_Award 1625730 Outcomes Image"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The collaborative award to Baumer and Xie (award 1625730) supported four published articles in peer-reviewed scientific journals.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Baumer and Xie_Award 1625730</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eric&nbsp;Baumer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Baumer and Xie_Award 1625730 Outcomes Image</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview  The collaborative project integrates data from area-identified National Crime Victimization Survey (NCVS) and other external data sources to examine three questions: (1) Is the risk of non-lethal criminal victimization among persons and households in the US significantly influenced by neighborhood (i.e., census tract) immigrant concentration? (2) Is the likelihood of police notification among crime victims significantly influenced by neighborhood immigrant concentration? (3) Do observed effects of neighborhood immigrant concentration on victimization risk and police notification differ across counties that vary significantly on immigration history (traditional vs. new immigrant destinations) and other attributes (economic and political conditions)?  These questions are addressed by linking data on victimization and police notification from the 1996-2014 restricted-use, area-identified, NCVS to data on demographic, socioeconomic, and political attributes of census tracts and counties drawn from the American Community Survey and other sources. To date, the collaborative project has yielded four peer-reviewed journal publications, among other results (see image).  Intellectual Merit  The project has provided important new insights into the nature and meaning of community differences in levels of immigration and crime that previous data analyses has not been able to identify. Previously, a substantial body of research has documented lower rates of crime in communities with higher immigrant concentrations, but this research has relied almost exclusively on police-based data or data on homicides, and thus a high percentage of crime that is non-lethal and not known to the police has been left out of the investigation.  The project significantly advances understanding of neighborhood patterns of immigration and crime by: (1) offering the first nationwide analysis of the influence of neighborhood immigrant concentration on the reporting of crime to the police; (2) reevaluating the impact of neighborhood immigrant concentration on crime with data that include incidents both reported and unreported to the police; and (3) examining several theoretically informed conditional impacts of neighborhood immigrant concentration on both victimization and reporting, including whether observed effects are moderated by individual race and ethnicity and theoretically relevant county conditions.  Important findings of the project include: (1) Neighborhood immigration concentration is negatively associated with victimization risk even including crimes not reported to the police.  For whites, blacks, and Latinos, we find a consistent protective role of neighborhood immigrant concentration on violence risk that is not weakened by low education, low income, being unemployed, or being subject to labor market competition, which suggests that even those who are economically more vulnerable enjoy the crime-reducing benefit of immigration.  (2) Crimes are less likely to be reported to the police by victims of high-immigrant-centration neighborhoods located in new immigrant counties.  In traditional immigrant counties, crime reporting rates are not significantly influenced by the level of immigrant concentration in neighborhoods.  (3) States have different approaches to immigration.  We find that the total number of state-level immigration policies has risen significantly since the mid-2000s, and state-level immigration policies vary substantially in their underlying principles (e.g., a goal of integrating immigrants vs. a goal of identifying immigrants and enforcing immigration law).  In addition, we find that the states' legislative efforts are better explained by their historical experience with immigration than by their location close to or far away from national borders.  Broader Impacts  The results of the project help inform public discourse and social policy regarding the incorporation of the immigrant population into local communities. Our finding that even those who are vulnerable to competition in labor markets enjoy the crime-reduction benefit of immigrant concentration is an important finding that should encourage local communities to evaluate their attitude towards immigration and create a more immigrant-friendly environment to facilitate the adaptation of immigrants into the receiving communities.  Our study on crime reporting, in addition, indicates that residents of high-concentration immigrant neighborhoods have lower rates of crime reporting than do residents of other neighborhoods.  This relationship is shown to be dependent on several conditions: how high is the level of neighborhood immigrant concentration, and how long is the history of the counties in receiving immigrants.  These findings provide a better understanding of the victims' needs in immigrant neighborhoods that will be useful in making decisions on victim service planning to better serve local communities.  Further, the project team has emphasized the integration of research into several educational activities, including the development of new undergraduate and graduate courses on core themes of the project (immigration, victimology, and the mobilization of law) and the integration of students from underrepresented groups and ethnic minorities into research and professional development.    The project also has contributed to enhancing the social science infrastructure and capacity to study immigration and crime by integrating data from a wide variety of sources including the National Crime Victimization Survey (NCVS), the American Community Survey, the Decennial Census, and the National Conference of State Legislatures (NCSL).       Last Modified: 12/04/2019       Submitted by: Eric Baumer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
