<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Engineering Stable Glass Films Using Molecular Design and Surface-Mediated Equilibration</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Schlueter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jschluet@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927766</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION: Nanoscopic thin films of small molecule amorphous organic materials are widely used in applications that range from protective coatings to organic photovoltaics and resist materials in nanoimprint lithography. These films are frequently manufactured through use of physical vapor deposition (PVD) onto a substrate held below the materials' glass transition temperature, Tg. Tg signifies the temperature where a system is unable to equilibrate on laboratory or computational time scales. Since glassy systems are out of equilibrium, the precise method of their fabrication, including substrate temperature, its properties, and rate of deposition can profoundly affect the materials properties and function in these applications. This project employs a combination of molecular synthesis, high-throughput characterization, and molecular simulation to design and characterize a library of synthetic glass-forming materials as a function of deposition variables. Addressing fundamental questions of the formation of highly stable glasses during PVD will have a transformative effect on the community's ability to engineer the properties of amorphous organic thin films and open the door to new applications of stable glasses for various industries. In addition to the project's impact on our fundamental understanding of stable glass formation and industrial applications, this project will impact the education of junior scientists from the undergraduate level through the PhD level. Undergraduate education is integrated into all aspects of the project. The starting material for the synthesis of glass formers is prepared as part of an undergraduate organic chemistry laboratory course. Advanced undergraduates and graduate students participate in the synthesis of the glass-formers as well as the characterization of PVD films using various experimental and computational techniques.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION: When held at a constant temperature a glass very slowly evolves towards a more stable, higher density state. This process, called physical aging, can take millions of years to reach equilibrium and only result in modest improvement in properties. Recent breakthrough studies have shown that PVD onto a substrate held just below Tg leads to a glass with properties that appear to be that of a glass that has aged hundreds or even thousands of years. It is hypothesized that this is a result of the enhanced mobility at the free surface of the film during deposition. Through PVD, each deposited molecule experiences this enhanced mobility upon condensation, allowing it to find a low energy state. As such, this process is referred to as surface mediated equilibration (SME). The remarkable kinetic stability of SME-generated glasses opens the door for their use in a number of new applications, but several fundamental challenges hinder their adoption. Most notably, a systematic understanding of the role of the chemical structure and intermolecular interactions, the interactions of the organic molecule with the substrate, and the effect of film thickness remain poorly understood. The synthesis capabilities previously developed by the PIs allows one to dial in particular structural motifs and intermolecular interactions. High-throughput characterization methods will enable rapid determination of a materials' kinetic stability as well as the relationship between stability and enhanced surface dynamics. Finally, molecular-level insights will be provided through coarse-grained simulations of the molecules synthesized and characterized experimentally. Specifically, the primary goals of this project are to i) determine the influence of chemical structure on surface mobility and SME glass stability; ii) determine the effect of film thickness on stability; and iii) determine the role of substrate interactions on altering materials' packing and ability to form a stable glass. Addressing these questions will have a transformative effect on the community's ability to engineer the properties of amorphous organic thin films and open the door to new applications of stable glasses.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1628407</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Walsh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick J Walsh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pwalsh@sas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2155732875</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000440471</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Riggleman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert A Riggleman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rrig@seas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158987293</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574073</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zahra</FirstName>
<LastName>Fakhraai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zahra Fakhraai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fakhraai@sas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2157468436</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000588610</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3451 Walnut St, 5th Flr Franklin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Trustees of the University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046323</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Department of Chemistry]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8292</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8400</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~1200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Glasses are out of equilibrium materials. They are typically produced by quenching a supercooled liquid to a temperature where it can no longer maintain its equilibrium properties and is kinetically arrested. The pathway by which a glass is produced can define the specific state of the glass and its physical properties. In this project, we produced highly stable glasses through physical vapor deposition (PVD). In this process, the enhanced mobility of the liquid at its surface is used to trap glasses at low energy states that are not accessible through liquid-quenching. As such, uniquely stable, high-density glasses can be produced with interesting physical properties.</p> <p>While the enhanced mobility at the surface allows for surface-mediated equilibration, the structure of the liquid at the surface can also affect the structure of the resulting glass. For example, in computer simulations we have demonstrated how an organic molecule with a fluorinated tail can produce networked structures due to the trapping of the tails in fluorine-rich domains. This provides a unique opportunity to study structure-property relationships in vapor-deposited glasses and engineer glasses with desired properties.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit. </strong>In this project, we combined chemical design, high-throughput experiments, and coarse-grained computer simulations to understand structure-property relationships in stable vapor-deposited glasses. Specifically, we investigated:</p> <ul> <li>The role of inter-molecular interactions in glass properties by introducing fluorinated tails of various lengths in the structure and thermodynamic stability of molecules. We demonstrated that increasing interactions could lead to a slow-down of enhanced mobility, resulting in networked structures that are thermally less stable. </li> <li>The role of substrate temperature and deposition rate in the orientation of molecules, templated by the free surface, as well as layering structures that make stable glasses optically birefringent. </li> <li>The effect of intra-molecular degrees of freedom in the structural entropy of the liquid and its ability to equilibrate rapidly at the free surface. We demonstrated that increasing rotational degrees of freedom leads to increased stability and reduced birefringence. </li> <li>The effect of film thickness and substrate interactions on the stability of PVD glasses. In particular, we demonstrated that exceptionally dense glasses can be produced in the thickness range of 30-50 nm, with packings that correspond to a uniquely high-density liquid state that has not been previously observed. </li> </ul> <p>To achieve these goals we developed new synthesis that enables modular design of homologous series of molecules, designed and custom built an ultra-high vacuum chamber with high-throughput temperature-gradient stage and in-situ characterization capabilities, and developed new modeling tools to predict properties of vapor-deposited glasses.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts. </strong>Understanding structure-property relationships in molecular glasses is helpful in designing new materials for various applications. For example, it has been known that thin molecular glass films used for photoresist or thin film electronics are prone to dewetting if their thickness is below 30 nm. Our studies highlight that in the proper range of substrate deposition and rates, these films can be made into stable layers that can resist dewetting. A fundamental understanding of such properties can have impact in various fields such as coatings, organic electronics, and lithography. &nbsp;Our studies also elucidate fundamental properties of glasses by producing super-cooled liquid states at low temperatures, were it was previously impossible to access.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We have started a new database for molecular glass materials, which includes the measured properties of glass molecules synthesized for this project. We aim to broaden this database by adding data obtained in other research groups. All of this data is made available online, which facilitates big-data analysis of the structure-property relationships obtained in this project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Graduate and undergraduate education was an integrated part of this study. The starting material for the synthesis of all of our molecules, tri halide benzene, is synthesized in an undergraduate organic lab, by undergraduate students. This material is then collected, purified, and used for synthesizing organic molecules. Both graduate and undergraduate students were involved in all aspects of the project, including synthesis, method development, simulations, and characterization.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Zahra&nbsp;Fakhraai</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Glasses are out of equilibrium materials. They are typically produced by quenching a supercooled liquid to a temperature where it can no longer maintain its equilibrium properties and is kinetically arrested. The pathway by which a glass is produced can define the specific state of the glass and its physical properties. In this project, we produced highly stable glasses through physical vapor deposition (PVD). In this process, the enhanced mobility of the liquid at its surface is used to trap glasses at low energy states that are not accessible through liquid-quenching. As such, uniquely stable, high-density glasses can be produced with interesting physical properties.  While the enhanced mobility at the surface allows for surface-mediated equilibration, the structure of the liquid at the surface can also affect the structure of the resulting glass. For example, in computer simulations we have demonstrated how an organic molecule with a fluorinated tail can produce networked structures due to the trapping of the tails in fluorine-rich domains. This provides a unique opportunity to study structure-property relationships in vapor-deposited glasses and engineer glasses with desired properties.  Intellectual Merit. In this project, we combined chemical design, high-throughput experiments, and coarse-grained computer simulations to understand structure-property relationships in stable vapor-deposited glasses. Specifically, we investigated:  The role of inter-molecular interactions in glass properties by introducing fluorinated tails of various lengths in the structure and thermodynamic stability of molecules. We demonstrated that increasing interactions could lead to a slow-down of enhanced mobility, resulting in networked structures that are thermally less stable.  The role of substrate temperature and deposition rate in the orientation of molecules, templated by the free surface, as well as layering structures that make stable glasses optically birefringent.  The effect of intra-molecular degrees of freedom in the structural entropy of the liquid and its ability to equilibrate rapidly at the free surface. We demonstrated that increasing rotational degrees of freedom leads to increased stability and reduced birefringence.  The effect of film thickness and substrate interactions on the stability of PVD glasses. In particular, we demonstrated that exceptionally dense glasses can be produced in the thickness range of 30-50 nm, with packings that correspond to a uniquely high-density liquid state that has not been previously observed.    To achieve these goals we developed new synthesis that enables modular design of homologous series of molecules, designed and custom built an ultra-high vacuum chamber with high-throughput temperature-gradient stage and in-situ characterization capabilities, and developed new modeling tools to predict properties of vapor-deposited glasses.     Broader Impacts. Understanding structure-property relationships in molecular glasses is helpful in designing new materials for various applications. For example, it has been known that thin molecular glass films used for photoresist or thin film electronics are prone to dewetting if their thickness is below 30 nm. Our studies highlight that in the proper range of substrate deposition and rates, these films can be made into stable layers that can resist dewetting. A fundamental understanding of such properties can have impact in various fields such as coatings, organic electronics, and lithography.  Our studies also elucidate fundamental properties of glasses by producing super-cooled liquid states at low temperatures, were it was previously impossible to access.     We have started a new database for molecular glass materials, which includes the measured properties of glass molecules synthesized for this project. We aim to broaden this database by adding data obtained in other research groups. All of this data is made available online, which facilitates big-data analysis of the structure-property relationships obtained in this project.     Graduate and undergraduate education was an integrated part of this study. The starting material for the synthesis of all of our molecules, tri halide benzene, is synthesized in an undergraduate organic lab, by undergraduate students. This material is then collected, purified, and used for synthesizing organic molecules. Both graduate and undergraduate students were involved in all aspects of the project, including synthesis, method development, simulations, and characterization.          Last Modified: 08/30/2020       Submitted by: Zahra Fakhraai]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
