<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CI-P: Collaborative Project: Massively-Parallel Analog Co-Processors for Simulating Complex Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yuanyuan Yang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>yyang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928067</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Digital supercomputers have become exponentially faster in recent years, but these general-purpose machines still leave much to be desired in terms of computational speed for mathematically rigorous simulations of various physics-based systems. Moreover, digital computer performance is beginning to saturate due to fundamental limitations in transistor scaling and switching speed. However, the analog performance of transistors continues to improve, and frequency ranges exceeding 400 GHz are now available for applications such as millimeter wave wireless communications, imaging, and radar. Hence there is a lot of interest in high-speed analog co-processors that can rapidly perform certain specialized simulations by taking advantage of modern nanoscale integrated circuit technology. The overall goal of the project is to discover the theory, design the circuits, and verify the operation of scalable analog computation units with multi-GHz bandwidths that can be seamlessly integrated into modern digital computation architectures, thus enabling novel hybrid (analog/digital) computing paradigms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This "planning" research is designed to obtain the foundational knowledge, derive the requirements and specifications, and determine the teaming needs for an eventual full project to the CRI program that will enable the CISE community to more easily explore this "beyond Moore" computing paradigm. In particular, it will provide shared resources for developing and using radio frequency (RF) analog accelerators for various scientific computing applications. This CI-P planning activities will explore several mathematical models that can be efficiently mapped to massively-parallel integrated analog accelerators. The mathematical models may include simplified versions of difficult scientific computing problems (e.g., the shallow-water version of the Navier-Stokes equations) and important problems in engineering (e.g., Maxwell's equations of electromagnetism). The planning stage will include a one-day "Ideas Workshop" to facilitate informal discussions between CISE researchers belonging to several universities who are either experienced in analog and hybrid computing, or have significant interest in the topic. The project includes significant educational and outreach activities, including outreach activities at local high schools in the Cleveland-Akron area, summer workshops at the lead-PI's laboratory at the University of Akron, and mentorship/research experiences at Case Western Reserve University.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1629790</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Soumyajit</FirstName>
<LastName>Mandal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Soumyajit Mandal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>soumyajit@ece.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523920912</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000673670</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
<CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[10900 Euclid Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077758407</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CASE WESTERN RESERVE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>077758407</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Case Western Reserve University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cleveland</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Nord Hall, Suite 615]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>CCRI-CISE Cmnty Rsrch Infrstrc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>COMPUTING RES INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~49997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary goals of this project were i) to enable the regional  academic community to take advantage of hybrid analog-digital computing,  and ii) to create educational infrastructure that enables both  undergraduate and graduate students to design and program such systems.  The proposed hybrid computers should be i) scalable and seamlessly  integrated into modern digital computer architectures (e.g., within  existing high-performance computing [HPC] clusters), and ii) provide at  least 10-100&times; improvement in throughput per Watt over the  state-of-the-art (field-programmable gate arrays [FPGAs], graphics  processing units [GPUs], etc.) for specific applications. Thus, they are  expected to serve as an unique resource for interdisciplinary academic  research (e.g., in computer science, engineering, physics, chemistry,  and other fields) that requires i) solving systems of partial  differential equations (PDEs) and optimization problems, ii) machine  learning using deep neural networks, iii) computing mathematical  transforms (e.g., Fourier transforms, discrete cosines, wavelets), or  iv) performing stochastic simulations.</p> <p>Over the last two years,  the project has pursued these goals by catalyzing the development of i)  new educational infrastructure (custom chips, course assignments, and  lecture material) that enables instructors to pursue an experiential  learning approach while teaching students about analog integrated  circuit (IC) design; and ii) new algorithms, hardware, and embedded  software for massively-parallel analog computing.</p> <p>Project  outcomes related to the first topic (educational infrastructure) are  summarized in Figures 1-2,&nbsp; while those related to the second topic (new  research on analog computing) are summarized in Figures 3-5.  Specifically, Figure 1 shows the institutional curriculum plan for  teaching analog IC design, and how a new course focused on experiential  learning fits into the existing curriculum. The figure also shows the  high-level block diagram for a custom IC that contains common analog  building-blocks that students simulate and test during the course.  Figure 2 shows the die photograph and test board for this instructional  IC, which has been successfully fabricated and tested.</p> <p>Figure 3  summarizes one of the major computing topics that was pursued during the  project, namely low-complexity approximations to the discrete Fourier  transform (DFT), which is used in a wide variety of applications  including beamforming for wireless communications. In particular, PI  Mandal&rsquo;s group at Case Western Reserve University (CWRU) has studied  analog current-mode approximate DFT (ADFT) processors that are accurate  enough to be used without additional post-fabrication calibration, as  shown in the figure. Figures 4-5 summarize another major computing topic  that was pursued, namely programmable application-specific analog  integrated circuits (ASICs) for solving partial differential equations  (PDEs). Initial efforts by the CWRU team, in collaboration with PI  Madanayake&rsquo;s team at the University of Akron (UA) and later Florida  International University (FIU), have focused on analog ASICs to solve  Maxwell&rsquo;s equations of electromagnetism. Figures 4 and 5 summarize the  design and performance of analog chips for solving Maxwell's equations  that operate either in continuous time (Figure 4) or discrete time  (Figure 5).</p> <p>Finally, Figure 6 summarizes community engagement and outreach activities related to the project. The first major activity was a &ldquo;<em>NE-Ohio Regional Workshop on Community Infrastructure for Analog Circuit Design</em>&rdquo; that was co-organized by PIs Mandal and Madanayak eto  obtain feedback from the local analog circuit design community on  community infrastructure requirements. The workshop was held on the CWRU  campus in Cleveland, OH on August 18, 2017 with participation from  local universities, research institutes, and industry. The second major  activity was a two-hour tutorial on &ldquo;<em>Emerging Topics in Analog&ndash;Hybrid All&ndash;Programmable Embedded Computing</em>&rdquo; at the Embedded Systems Conference (ESC) in Minneapolis, MN (<a href="https://escminn.com">https://escminn.com</a>) on November 1, 2018. The tutorial, which was part of &ldquo;<em>Track D: Advanced Technologies</em>&rdquo;  at ESC, covered various aspects of analog and mixed analog-digital  (i.e., hybrid) computing using programmable ASICs. It was co-organized  by PIs Mandal and Madanayake along with Prof. Mingoo Seok of Columbia  University.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/15/2018<br>      Modified by: Soumyajit&nbsp;Mandal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544895583948_Fig_1_curriculum_plan_chip_architecture--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544895583948_Fig_1_curriculum_plan_chip_architecture--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Instructional curriculum plan and chip architecture"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544895583948_Fig_1_curriculum_plan_chip_architecture--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Instructional curriculum plan and chip architecture"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Proposed three-course sequence for graduate students interested in mixed-signal integrated circuit (IC) design, with the new course in the middle. (b) High-level block diagram of the custom IC to be used in lab sessions for the new course.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Soumyajit Mandal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Soumyajit&nbsp;Mandal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Instructional curriculum plan and chip architecture</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544895745314_Fig_2_class_chip_die_photo_test_board--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544895745314_Fig_2_class_chip_die_photo_test_board--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Die photograph and test board for the instructional chip"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544895745314_Fig_2_class_chip_die_photo_test_board--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Die photograph and test board for the instructional chip"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Test board for the educational chip, including bias generator array (0-1.8 V), RF inputs/outputs, digital input buffers, jumper/SMA test point array, and ECG micro-connector.  (b) Die photograph of the chip, which was fabricated in the UMC 180 nm CMOS process.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Soumyajit Mandal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Soumyajit&nbsp;Mandal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Die photograph and test board for the instructional chip</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544895974566_Fig_3_analog_DFT--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544895974566_Fig_3_analog_DFT--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Analog approximate-DFT chip architecture, simulation, and layout"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544895974566_Fig_3_analog_DFT--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Analog approximate-DFT chip architecture, simulation, and layout"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) A multi-output dynamic current mirror (DCM) for high-accuracy analog ADFT computations. (b) Simulated output beam patterns (at 130 MHz) from a DCM-based 8-point analog ADFT chip. (c) Layout of the chip (area 3.94 ? 1.77 mm) in 180 nm CMOS, which consumes ~50 mW for a -3 dB bandwidth of 170 MHz.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Soumyajit Mandal</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Soumyajit&nbsp;Mandal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Analog approximate-DFT chip architecture, simulation, and layout</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544896428323_Fig_4_analog_maxwell_nilan--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544896428323_Fig_4_analog_maxwell_nilan--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Layout, die photograph, and test board of analog Maxwell's equations solver chip"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544896428323_Fig_4_analog_maxwell_nilan--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Layout, die photograph, and test board of analog Maxwell's equations solver chip"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Complete layout and (b) the die photograph of the 180 nm CMOS wave equation solver chip, which measures 2 x 2 mm in size. (b) Printed circuit board (PCB) used to test the chip.</div> <div class="imageCredit">NIlan Udayanga</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Soumyajit&nbsp;Mandal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Layout, die photograph, and test board of analog Maxwell's equations solver chip</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544896914269_Fig_5_sc_maxwell_sim--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544896914269_Fig_5_sc_maxwell_sim--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Architecture, chip design, simulation results, and layout of switched-capacitor Maxwell's equations solver"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544896914269_Fig_5_sc_maxwell_sim--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Architecture, chip design, simulation results, and layout of switched-capacitor Maxwell's equations solver"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Architecture of the integrated analog co-processors. (b) A single stage for a switched-capacitor (SC) 1-D wave equation solver. (c) Layout of the SC solver chip (2.88 x 2.65 mm), which contains 16 stages in 180 nm CMOS. (d-e) Simulation of the solver for (d) radiation and (e) hard boundaries.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Soumyajit Mandal</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Soumyajit&nbsp;Mandal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Architecture, chip design, simulation results, and layout of switched-capacitor Maxwell's equations solver</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544897317432_Fig_6_broader_impact--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544897317432_Fig_6_broader_impact--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Community outreach activities"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1629790/1629790_10448216_1544897317432_Fig_6_broader_impact--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Community outreach activities"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Workshop on community infrastructure for analog circuits organized by the PIs at CWRU. (b) PI Madayanake discussing analog PDE solvers at a tutorial on ?Emerging Topics in Analog?Hybrid All?Programmable Embedded Computing? organized by the PIs at the Embedded Systems Conference (ESC).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Soumyajit Mandal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Soumyajit&nbsp;Mandal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Community outreach activities</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goals of this project were i) to enable the regional  academic community to take advantage of hybrid analog-digital computing,  and ii) to create educational infrastructure that enables both  undergraduate and graduate students to design and program such systems.  The proposed hybrid computers should be i) scalable and seamlessly  integrated into modern digital computer architectures (e.g., within  existing high-performance computing [HPC] clusters), and ii) provide at  least 10-100&times; improvement in throughput per Watt over the  state-of-the-art (field-programmable gate arrays [FPGAs], graphics  processing units [GPUs], etc.) for specific applications. Thus, they are  expected to serve as an unique resource for interdisciplinary academic  research (e.g., in computer science, engineering, physics, chemistry,  and other fields) that requires i) solving systems of partial  differential equations (PDEs) and optimization problems, ii) machine  learning using deep neural networks, iii) computing mathematical  transforms (e.g., Fourier transforms, discrete cosines, wavelets), or  iv) performing stochastic simulations.  Over the last two years,  the project has pursued these goals by catalyzing the development of i)  new educational infrastructure (custom chips, course assignments, and  lecture material) that enables instructors to pursue an experiential  learning approach while teaching students about analog integrated  circuit (IC) design; and ii) new algorithms, hardware, and embedded  software for massively-parallel analog computing.  Project  outcomes related to the first topic (educational infrastructure) are  summarized in Figures 1-2,  while those related to the second topic (new  research on analog computing) are summarized in Figures 3-5.  Specifically, Figure 1 shows the institutional curriculum plan for  teaching analog IC design, and how a new course focused on experiential  learning fits into the existing curriculum. The figure also shows the  high-level block diagram for a custom IC that contains common analog  building-blocks that students simulate and test during the course.  Figure 2 shows the die photograph and test board for this instructional  IC, which has been successfully fabricated and tested.  Figure 3  summarizes one of the major computing topics that was pursued during the  project, namely low-complexity approximations to the discrete Fourier  transform (DFT), which is used in a wide variety of applications  including beamforming for wireless communications. In particular, PI  Mandal?s group at Case Western Reserve University (CWRU) has studied  analog current-mode approximate DFT (ADFT) processors that are accurate  enough to be used without additional post-fabrication calibration, as  shown in the figure. Figures 4-5 summarize another major computing topic  that was pursued, namely programmable application-specific analog  integrated circuits (ASICs) for solving partial differential equations  (PDEs). Initial efforts by the CWRU team, in collaboration with PI  Madanayake?s team at the University of Akron (UA) and later Florida  International University (FIU), have focused on analog ASICs to solve  Maxwell?s equations of electromagnetism. Figures 4 and 5 summarize the  design and performance of analog chips for solving Maxwell's equations  that operate either in continuous time (Figure 4) or discrete time  (Figure 5).  Finally, Figure 6 summarizes community engagement and outreach activities related to the project. The first major activity was a "NE-Ohio Regional Workshop on Community Infrastructure for Analog Circuit Design" that was co-organized by PIs Mandal and Madanayak eto  obtain feedback from the local analog circuit design community on  community infrastructure requirements. The workshop was held on the CWRU  campus in Cleveland, OH on August 18, 2017 with participation from  local universities, research institutes, and industry. The second major  activity was a two-hour tutorial on "Emerging Topics in Analog&ndash;Hybrid All&ndash;Programmable Embedded Computing" at the Embedded Systems Conference (ESC) in Minneapolis, MN (https://escminn.com) on November 1, 2018. The tutorial, which was part of "Track D: Advanced Technologies"  at ESC, covered various aspects of analog and mixed analog-digital  (i.e., hybrid) computing using programmable ASICs. It was co-organized  by PIs Mandal and Madanayake along with Prof. Mingoo Seok of Columbia  University.       Last Modified: 12/15/2018       Submitted by: Soumyajit Mandal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
