<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CI-P: Collaborative: Planning for a Community-Driven Open Research Infrastructure to Support Secure Computing Research involving Intel SGX</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marilyn McClure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmcclure@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Historically,when designing the security of a system, operating systems have been considered a part of the trusted computing base (TCB).&lt;br/&gt;However, with the recent shift to cloud computing, there is a pressing need to exclude the OS from the TCB. The Intel Software Guard Extensions (SGX) is a promising new technology that has a great potential to solve this problem. However, its infrastructure, tools, and development ecosystems are developed in a closed manner.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is to initiate a community effort in developing an open research infrastructure and support for Intel SGX. In particular, the work will initiate a long-term plan to develop, enhance, and maintain an open source project, OpenSGX, focusing on developing a system emulator, SGX-enabled applications, libraries, kernel drivers, etc., to support its ecosystem. Being an open source research infrastructure, all of the code and documentation will be publicly shared and maintained.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1629851</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Taesoo</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Taesoo Kim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>taesoo@gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048944819</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000678400</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Tech Research Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>CCRI-CISE Cmnty Rsrch Infrstrc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>COMPUTING RES INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This funded project so far has generated 11 peer-reviewed<br />publications, and 6 research prototypes (the corresponding source<br />code has been released in the github.com).<br /><br />More specifically, the publication includes:<br /><br />[1] "A Case for Protecting Computer Games With SGX". Erick Bauman, and<br />Zhiqiang Lin. In Proceedings of the 1st Workshop on System Software<br />for Trusted Execution, Trento, Italy. December 2016<br /><br />[2] "SGX-Log: Securing System Logs With SGX". Vishal Karande, Erick<br />Buaman, Zhiqiang Lin, and Latifur Khan. In Proceedings of the 12th ACM<br />Asia Conference on Computer and Communications Security, Abu<br />Dhabi. April 2017. [Source code at<br />https://github.com/utds3lab/sgx-log]<br /><br />[3] "Securing Data Analytics on SGX With Randomization". Swarup<br />Chandra, Vishal Karande, Zhiqiang Lin, Latifur Khan, Murat<br />Kantarcioglu, and Bhavani Thuraisingham. To appear In Proceedings of<br />the 22nd European Symposium on Research in Computer Security, Oslo,<br />Norway. September, 2017<br /><br />[4] "Thwarting Controlled Side Channel Attacks via Enclave Verifiable<br />Page Faults". Yangchun Fu, Erick Bauman, Raul Quinonez, and Zhiqiang<br />Lin. To appear In Proceedings of the 20th International Symposium on<br />Research in Attacks, Intrusions and Defenses, Atlanta,<br />Georgia. September 2017 [Source code at<br />https://github.com/utds3lab/sgx-lapd]<br /><br />[5] "A Practical Encrypted Data Analytic Framework With Trusted<br />Processors". Fahad Shaon, Murat Kantarcioglu, Zhiqiang Lin, and<br />Latifur Khan. To appear In Proceedings of the 24th ACM Conference on<br />Computer and Communications Security, Dallas, Texas. November<br />2017. [Source code to be released]<br /><br />[6] Inferring Fine-grained Control Flow Inside SGX Enclaves with Branch Shadowing.<br />Sangho Lee, Ming-Wei Shih, Prasun Gera, Taesoo Kim, Hyesoon Kim, and Marcus Peinado.<br />In Proceedings of the 26th USENIX Security Symposium (Security 2017),<br />Vancouver, Canada, August 2017. <br /><br />[7] Hacking in Darkness: Return-oriented Programming against Secure Enclaves.<br />Jaehyuk Lee, Jinsoo Jang, Yeongjin Jang, Nohyun Kwak, Yeseul Choi, Changho Choi, Taesoo Kim, Marcus Peinado, and Brent B. Kang.<br />In Proceedings of the 26th USENIX Security Symposium (Security 2017),<br />Vancouver, Canada, August 2017. <br /><br />[8] Enhancing Security and Privacy of Tor's Ecosystem by using Trusted Execution Environments.<br />Seongmin Kim, Juhyeng Han, Jaehyeong Ha, Taesoo Kim, and Dongsu Han.<br />In Proceedings of the 14th USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI 2017),<br />Boston, MA, March 2017. <br />https://github.com/KAIST-INA/SGX-Tor<br /><br />[9] SGX-Shield: Enabling Address Space Layout Randomization for SGX Programs.<br />Jaebaek Seo, Byoungyoung Lee, Sungmin Kim, Ming-Wei Shih, Insik Shin, Dongsu Han, and Taesoo Kim.<br />In Proceedings of the 2017 Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS 2017),<br />San Diego, CA, February 2017. <br />https://github.com/jaebaek/SGX-Shield<br /><br />[10] T-SGX: Eradicating Controlled-Channel Attacks Against Enclave Programs.<br />Ming-Wei Shih, Sangho Lee, Taesoo Kim, and Marcus Peinado.<br />In Proceedings of the 2017 Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS 2017),<br />San Diego, CA, February 2017. <br />https://github.com/sslab-gatech/t-sgx</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/21/2017<br>      Modified by: Taesoo&nbsp;Kim</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This funded project so far has generated 11 peer-reviewed publications, and 6 research prototypes (the corresponding source code has been released in the github.com).  More specifically, the publication includes:  [1] "A Case for Protecting Computer Games With SGX". Erick Bauman, and Zhiqiang Lin. In Proceedings of the 1st Workshop on System Software for Trusted Execution, Trento, Italy. December 2016  [2] "SGX-Log: Securing System Logs With SGX". Vishal Karande, Erick Buaman, Zhiqiang Lin, and Latifur Khan. In Proceedings of the 12th ACM Asia Conference on Computer and Communications Security, Abu Dhabi. April 2017. [Source code at https://github.com/utds3lab/sgx-log]  [3] "Securing Data Analytics on SGX With Randomization". Swarup Chandra, Vishal Karande, Zhiqiang Lin, Latifur Khan, Murat Kantarcioglu, and Bhavani Thuraisingham. To appear In Proceedings of the 22nd European Symposium on Research in Computer Security, Oslo, Norway. September, 2017  [4] "Thwarting Controlled Side Channel Attacks via Enclave Verifiable Page Faults". Yangchun Fu, Erick Bauman, Raul Quinonez, and Zhiqiang Lin. To appear In Proceedings of the 20th International Symposium on Research in Attacks, Intrusions and Defenses, Atlanta, Georgia. September 2017 [Source code at https://github.com/utds3lab/sgx-lapd]  [5] "A Practical Encrypted Data Analytic Framework With Trusted Processors". Fahad Shaon, Murat Kantarcioglu, Zhiqiang Lin, and Latifur Khan. To appear In Proceedings of the 24th ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security, Dallas, Texas. November 2017. [Source code to be released]  [6] Inferring Fine-grained Control Flow Inside SGX Enclaves with Branch Shadowing. Sangho Lee, Ming-Wei Shih, Prasun Gera, Taesoo Kim, Hyesoon Kim, and Marcus Peinado. In Proceedings of the 26th USENIX Security Symposium (Security 2017), Vancouver, Canada, August 2017.   [7] Hacking in Darkness: Return-oriented Programming against Secure Enclaves. Jaehyuk Lee, Jinsoo Jang, Yeongjin Jang, Nohyun Kwak, Yeseul Choi, Changho Choi, Taesoo Kim, Marcus Peinado, and Brent B. Kang. In Proceedings of the 26th USENIX Security Symposium (Security 2017), Vancouver, Canada, August 2017.   [8] Enhancing Security and Privacy of Tor's Ecosystem by using Trusted Execution Environments. Seongmin Kim, Juhyeng Han, Jaehyeong Ha, Taesoo Kim, and Dongsu Han. In Proceedings of the 14th USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI 2017), Boston, MA, March 2017.  https://github.com/KAIST-INA/SGX-Tor  [9] SGX-Shield: Enabling Address Space Layout Randomization for SGX Programs. Jaebaek Seo, Byoungyoung Lee, Sungmin Kim, Ming-Wei Shih, Insik Shin, Dongsu Han, and Taesoo Kim. In Proceedings of the 2017 Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS 2017), San Diego, CA, February 2017.  https://github.com/jaebaek/SGX-Shield  [10] T-SGX: Eradicating Controlled-Channel Attacks Against Enclave Programs. Ming-Wei Shih, Sangho Lee, Taesoo Kim, and Marcus Peinado. In Proceedings of the 2017 Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS 2017), San Diego, CA, February 2017.  https://github.com/sslab-gatech/t-sgx       Last Modified: 08/21/2017       Submitted by: Taesoo Kim]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
