<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DMREF: Collaborative Research: Designing Optimal Nanoparticle Shapes and Ligand Parameters for Polymer-Grafted Nanoparticle Membranes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1271974.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1271974</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccabe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924826</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project investigates a new class of polymer-grafted membranes that have the potential to improve gas separation characteristics for a wide range of applications in the environmental, energy, and chemical manufacturing areas.  The polymer-grafted membranes consist of a matrix of inorganic nanoparticles with grafted polymer ligands that show improved separation characteristics compared to commonly used organic membranes.  The project will use a combination of theoretical analysis, synthesis, and experimental evaluation to optimize both the nanoparticle shape and the polymer properties, while providing basic understanding of the mechanism by which the grafted structures improve separation efficiency.  The project will also provide educational and outreach components including research opportunities for undergraduate students from Florida A&amp;M University (a historically black college or university). &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;While a key class of organic membranes is made of glassy polymers, they suffer from the fact that their permeability (i.e., product flux) and selectivity (i.e., purity of the desired species) are inversely correlated. Preliminary work using assemblies of inorganic nanoparticles (NPs) chemically grafted with polymer chains show that these materials offer unexpected advantages in this context. Based on simulations it is postulated that the self-assembly of the polymer grafted-NPs into ordered arrays creates "interstitial spaces" which can only be filled by stretching some of the grafted chains ("entropic frustration"). Placing solute molecules relieves this frustration and yields the improved separation ability. The study is predicated on the hypothesis that non-spherical nanoparticles may offer a separation advantage due to packing into meta-crystals that are stabilized by vacancies (of order 10%). Non-spherical NP-grafted polymers will be studied by (1) developing novel theoretical design tools to find the NP shapes and grafting parameters that optimize the permeability and selectivity of relevant gas mixtures; and (2) synthesizing polymer grafted non-spherical NPs, assembling them into membranes and characterizing their multi-scale structure and dynamics using a suite of tools including advanced scattering techniques (x-ray, neutron) coupled with theory. This should allow for the validation of the design results and help close the prediction-synthesis-characterization loop. This validated design software will be made freely available to the research community. In addition to the educational collaboration with Florida A&amp;M University, the investigators will also recruit underrepresented students (both women and minorities) with the dual goals of placing Columbia University students into local industry and attracting industrial participants into higher degree and/or refresher programs at Columbia.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1629502</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sanat</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sanat K Kumar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sk2794@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128542193</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000101049</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Simon  J. L.</FirstName>
<LastName>Billinge</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Simon  J. L. Billinge</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sb2896@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128542918</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000207342</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 W 120th Street, 801 Mudd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8292</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8400</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~1271974</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our proposal's emphasis was on designing new classes of polymer membranes with vastly improved separation performance and mechanical resilience. Our research work has the ultimate goal of&nbsp;<em>a priori&nbsp;</em>designing superior membrane constructs which could significantly impact a variety of sustainability applications.</p> <p><em>Intellectual Merit:&nbsp;</em>In a predictive prong, we developed a&nbsp;high-throughput machine learning (ML) method for discovering new polymer membranes for gas separation.&nbsp;After training a ML algorithm on CO<sub>2</sub>/CH<sub>4</sub>&nbsp;separation data for ~700 pure polymers, we used it to&nbsp;screen a library of 11,000 known polymers and predicted the enhanced separations performances of many previously untested materials. Experimental validation of two such lead compounds from this data-rich approach closed the polymer structure-to-separations efficacy &ldquo;design loop.&rdquo;&nbsp;</p> <p>Our ultimate goal is to use these novel tools of data science to design new classes of membrane constructs comprising polymer grafted NPs (GNPs). Our work was motivated to find optimal hybrid constructs of plastics and inorganic nanoparticles, which have been proposed as a unique platform with vastly improved separations performance. We have found that previous work in this area is hampered by the immiscibility between the NPs and the polymers. Covalently linking polymer grafts to the surfaces of inorganic NPs naturally prevents NP agglomeration. Surprisingly, these GNP membranes display up to 100 times greater gas flux relative to their neat polymer analogs. GNP membranes also exhibit substantially improved mechanical properties. We additionally showed that adding free chains to GNPs mediates these packing effects in pure GNPs. Short added chains reduce the permeability of all gases, while long chain additives preferentially hinder large solute motion to yield extraordinary selectivities.&nbsp;These unexpected results, combined with other independent experimental and simulation results, clearly show that&nbsp;GNPs are heterogenous transport media, with large gases localized in the interstices of the particle packing while smaller gases are homogeneously transported through the polymer.&nbsp;Manipulating the morphologies of these soft colloids is thus a new, generic means of dramatically improving membrane performance.</p> <p><em>Broader Impacts:</em>&nbsp;Over the years we have recruited both high school students and undergraduates into our laboratory research. Over the last five years we have hosted between 3-5 undergraduate students and a similar number of MS students each year in our laboratories &ndash; about 50% of these are women and URM students. In the summer we mentor 1-3 high school students in addition to these more senior students. These junior students have published papers with us, allowing us to test the viability of new ideas in addition to being trained in the scientific method. This is a particularly good pipeline effort; for example, the most recent high school student, Reha Mathur is now a frosh at Princeton. In a different vein, during the pandemic&nbsp;the PI has organized three separate 2-3 hour long webinars (on Membranes, Nanocomposites and Polymers for Sustainability) under the auspices of the Division of Polymer Physics, American Physical Society &ndash; nearly 1000 people signed up for these webinars. At Columbia, he organized a workshop focused on &ldquo;Machine Learning in Materials Science&rdquo; which drew nearly 500 participants (Dec &rsquo;20).&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/27/2021<br>      Modified by: Sanat&nbsp;K&nbsp;Kumar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our proposal's emphasis was on designing new classes of polymer membranes with vastly improved separation performance and mechanical resilience. Our research work has the ultimate goal of a priori designing superior membrane constructs which could significantly impact a variety of sustainability applications.  Intellectual Merit: In a predictive prong, we developed a high-throughput machine learning (ML) method for discovering new polymer membranes for gas separation. After training a ML algorithm on CO2/CH4 separation data for ~700 pure polymers, we used it to screen a library of 11,000 known polymers and predicted the enhanced separations performances of many previously untested materials. Experimental validation of two such lead compounds from this data-rich approach closed the polymer structure-to-separations efficacy "design loop."   Our ultimate goal is to use these novel tools of data science to design new classes of membrane constructs comprising polymer grafted NPs (GNPs). Our work was motivated to find optimal hybrid constructs of plastics and inorganic nanoparticles, which have been proposed as a unique platform with vastly improved separations performance. We have found that previous work in this area is hampered by the immiscibility between the NPs and the polymers. Covalently linking polymer grafts to the surfaces of inorganic NPs naturally prevents NP agglomeration. Surprisingly, these GNP membranes display up to 100 times greater gas flux relative to their neat polymer analogs. GNP membranes also exhibit substantially improved mechanical properties. We additionally showed that adding free chains to GNPs mediates these packing effects in pure GNPs. Short added chains reduce the permeability of all gases, while long chain additives preferentially hinder large solute motion to yield extraordinary selectivities. These unexpected results, combined with other independent experimental and simulation results, clearly show that GNPs are heterogenous transport media, with large gases localized in the interstices of the particle packing while smaller gases are homogeneously transported through the polymer. Manipulating the morphologies of these soft colloids is thus a new, generic means of dramatically improving membrane performance.  Broader Impacts: Over the years we have recruited both high school students and undergraduates into our laboratory research. Over the last five years we have hosted between 3-5 undergraduate students and a similar number of MS students each year in our laboratories &ndash; about 50% of these are women and URM students. In the summer we mentor 1-3 high school students in addition to these more senior students. These junior students have published papers with us, allowing us to test the viability of new ideas in addition to being trained in the scientific method. This is a particularly good pipeline effort; for example, the most recent high school student, Reha Mathur is now a frosh at Princeton. In a different vein, during the pandemic the PI has organized three separate 2-3 hour long webinars (on Membranes, Nanocomposites and Polymers for Sustainability) under the auspices of the Division of Polymer Physics, American Physical Society &ndash; nearly 1000 people signed up for these webinars. At Columbia, he organized a workshop focused on "Machine Learning in Materials Science" which drew nearly 500 participants (Dec ’20).                 Last Modified: 01/27/2021       Submitted by: Sanat K Kumar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
