<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>33rd International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML 2016)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Weng-keen Wong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) is considered to be the premier conference in Machine Learning, both from an educational and scientific standpoint. ICML encompasses topics on all facets of Machine Learning, and solicits papers on problem areas, research topics, learning paradigms, and approaches to evaluation. It is a key forum for exchange of ideas in the Machine Learning community, and features scientific poster sessions, educational tutorials, forward-looking workshops, and invited talks.   This project offers awards to students to help defray their travel costs, promoting a broader societal reach for the conference.  Promoting education and participation in cutting edge data science is central to the mission of the NSF, and this project and its awards speak directly to that mission.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ICML 2016 will be held in New York City. We have estimated itemized costs based on previous ICML conferences.  Students funded via this project will be selected by a peer review process based on their financial needs, alignment of research areas, and participation in the conference.  These awards will offer the opportunity to network with experts in the area and gain valuable insights into the cutting edge of Machine Learning research. This will positively impact the depth and breadth of their research as well as quality of their dissertations.  Long-term career benefits should also result, as ICML has a number of industrial sponsors who set up booths and discuss Machine Learning-oriented job opportunities within their own companies.  The ICML 2016 scholarship program follows the successful scholarship programs from the last several years. The requested funds will be used exclusively to help defray the travel and registration costs of students attending the conference. These student scholarships are very important for encouraging student participation in this premier conference and for shaping the future of the field as a whole.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1630365</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Cunningham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John P Cunningham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jpc2181@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128512132</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000704396</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100275927</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1255 Amsterdam Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 12.0px Helvetica} p.p2 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 12.0px Helvetica; min-height: 14.0px} --> <!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 12.0px Helvetica} p.p2 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 12.0px Helvetica; min-height: 14.0px} --> <p class="p1">The International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) is held annually and is considered to be the premier conference in Machine Learning. ICML encompasses topics on all facets of Machine Learning, and solicits papers on problem areas, research topics, learning paradigms, and approaches to evaluation. It is a key forum for exchange of ideas in the Machine Learning community, and features poster sessions, tutorials, workshops and invited talks. The ICML conference and its venue are accessible to participants with disabilities.</p> <p class="p1">Attendance at ICML represents a unique opportunity for students pursuing Machine Learning research. The poster sessions at the conference are designed to give valuable feedback to students from internationally leading researchers in Machine Learning and to integrate students into the broader research community. Our primary goal is to facilitate the integration of graduate students into the research community by providing them with a forum to talk to leading scientists in the field about their Ph.D. research and how it is situated within the broader scope of efforts of the field.</p> <p class="p1">This award funded support scholarships for students from US institutions to help defray their travel and registration costs, thereby broadening access to ICML and helping promote the training and professional development of student scientists. ICML 2016, the 33rd annual ICML, was held in New York City. The students funded via this grant were selected by a peer review process based on their financial needs and alignment of research areas.&nbsp;</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/14/2017<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;P&nbsp;Cunningham</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) is held annually and is considered to be the premier conference in Machine Learning. ICML encompasses topics on all facets of Machine Learning, and solicits papers on problem areas, research topics, learning paradigms, and approaches to evaluation. It is a key forum for exchange of ideas in the Machine Learning community, and features poster sessions, tutorials, workshops and invited talks. The ICML conference and its venue are accessible to participants with disabilities. Attendance at ICML represents a unique opportunity for students pursuing Machine Learning research. The poster sessions at the conference are designed to give valuable feedback to students from internationally leading researchers in Machine Learning and to integrate students into the broader research community. Our primary goal is to facilitate the integration of graduate students into the research community by providing them with a forum to talk to leading scientists in the field about their Ph.D. research and how it is situated within the broader scope of efforts of the field. This award funded support scholarships for students from US institutions to help defray their travel and registration costs, thereby broadening access to ICML and helping promote the training and professional development of student scientists. ICML 2016, the 33rd annual ICML, was held in New York City. The students funded via this grant were selected by a peer review process based on their financial needs and alignment of research areas.            Last Modified: 06/14/2017       Submitted by: John P Cunningham]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
