<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Indo-US Workshop on "Cell Factories" to be held in Mumbai, India</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15910.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15910</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Devaki Bhaya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award, funded jointly the Biological Sciences Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences and the Engineering Division of Chemical, Biological, Environmental, and Transport Systems Division, will bring together leading scientists and bioengineers from the US and India to develop an optimize cellular systems for the productions of industrially relevant chemicals and products using approaches derived from theoretical principles of biology and engineering. One of the anticipated outcomes will be the development of parallel strategic partnerships for research collaborations and student and postdoctoral exchange opportunities.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will be held March 18-20, 2016 at the India Institute of Technology in Mumbai, India. Approximately 30 senior researchers with expertise in the fields of systems and synthetic biology from the US and India will be in attendance in addition to researchers from select Asian countries.  The outcomes of this workshop is to develop strategic collaborative and educational opportunities in addition to creating an infrastructure that will be necessary to realize the overarching goals of this workshop.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1630180</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jay</FirstName>
<LastName>Keasling</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jay D Keasling</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jdkeasling@lbl.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5104952620</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000404654</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UC Berkeley at the Joint BioEnergy Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Emeryville</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>946082404</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5885 Hollis Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~15910</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">The 2016 Indo-US workshop, which was primarily funded by the IUSSFT, brought together a very prominent and diverse group of scientists from US and India on the topic of metabolic cellular and tissue engineering. The plenary session spanned two days of talks in key topic in this field. The talks were very well received and generated extensive discussion in the Q and A sessions as well as the subsequent poster sessions. As the attendees were primarily students, postdocs and early career scientists, this resulted in a very robust networking opportunity for them. Key outcome of the workshop:&nbsp;<br /> 1. Funds to invite and host a diverse and prominent speakers from the US and from India to the workshop</p> <p class="Default">2. Extensive communication of the state-of-art science and research in the field of metabolic and cellular engineering from academia, US and Indian National labs and industry</p> <p class="Default">3. Well attended and productive poster session.</p> <p class="Default">4. Networking opportunities for students and post docs</p> <p class="Default">5. Collaborations between laboratories in India and India-US</p> <p class="Default">6. Plans for a future follow up workshop to be held in the US</p> <p class="Default">Additional NSF funds had been obtained for the workshop, but the funds arrived too late for use in the workshop itself. As such a no cost extension was approved for the funds to be used for productive follow-up activities to the Indo US workshop, such as but not limited to travel for researchers to attend conferences, or for training. Key outcomes from these follow up activities include:</p> <p class="Default">1.Funds for participation of an early career scientist and two students in WCBP 2017 in Asilomar, CA</p> <p class="Default">2. Opportunity for three students to visit JBEI to see the world-class facilities and to learn about the ongoing research in Dr. Aindrila Mukhopadhyay&rsquo;s lab.</p> <p class="Default">3. Funds for one student to attend the 13<sup>th</sup> DOE JGI User Meeting, including two workshops on KBase: Genome Analysis and Community Analysis.</p> <p class="Default">4. Training for one student on instruments such as the HPLC, Lyophilizer, LCMS and the corresponding data analysis software.</p> <p class="Default">5. Addiontional Networking opportunities for students and post docs.</p> <p class="Default">6. Opportunity to build on collaborations between laboratories initiated at the 2016 conference.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/25/2018<br>      Modified by: Jay&nbsp;D&nbsp;Keasling</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The 2016 Indo-US workshop, which was primarily funded by the IUSSFT, brought together a very prominent and diverse group of scientists from US and India on the topic of metabolic cellular and tissue engineering. The plenary session spanned two days of talks in key topic in this field. The talks were very well received and generated extensive discussion in the Q and A sessions as well as the subsequent poster sessions. As the attendees were primarily students, postdocs and early career scientists, this resulted in a very robust networking opportunity for them. Key outcome of the workshop:   1. Funds to invite and host a diverse and prominent speakers from the US and from India to the workshop 2. Extensive communication of the state-of-art science and research in the field of metabolic and cellular engineering from academia, US and Indian National labs and industry 3. Well attended and productive poster session. 4. Networking opportunities for students and post docs 5. Collaborations between laboratories in India and India-US 6. Plans for a future follow up workshop to be held in the US Additional NSF funds had been obtained for the workshop, but the funds arrived too late for use in the workshop itself. As such a no cost extension was approved for the funds to be used for productive follow-up activities to the Indo US workshop, such as but not limited to travel for researchers to attend conferences, or for training. Key outcomes from these follow up activities include: 1.Funds for participation of an early career scientist and two students in WCBP 2017 in Asilomar, CA 2. Opportunity for three students to visit JBEI to see the world-class facilities and to learn about the ongoing research in Dr. Aindrila Mukhopadhyay?s lab. 3. Funds for one student to attend the 13th DOE JGI User Meeting, including two workshops on KBase: Genome Analysis and Community Analysis. 4. Training for one student on instruments such as the HPLC, Lyophilizer, LCMS and the corresponding data analysis software. 5. Addiontional Networking opportunities for students and post docs. 6. Opportunity to build on collaborations between laboratories initiated at the 2016 conference.          Last Modified: 04/25/2018       Submitted by: Jay D Keasling]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
