<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Sociocultural Consequences of Legal Innovation: An Anthropological Analysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Legislative support for physician aid-in-dying (PAD) in the United States has risen steadily in recent years. Five states currently authorize physicians to prescribe a lethal dose of medication to a mentally competent, terminally ill, adult patient for the purpose of ending the patient's life, provided that certain preconditions are met. With ongoing legislative activities in many other states, these laws are expected to spread nationally. While such laws remain contentious, regardless of one's moral position on PAD, this shifting legislative climate raises questions of broad public significance about how the legalization of PAD affects death, dying, and end-of-life care in the US. Much of the social scientific research on PAD in the U.S. has focused on the social and political factors that give rise to legalization. Less is known about how jurisdictions accommodate PAD as a new end-of-life practice and incorporate it into existing medical and bureaucratic institutions responsible for managing death. Dr. Mara Buchbinder, a medical anthropologist at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, will investigate the implementation and cultural impact of a recently enacted PAD law. The project will yield descriptive information that can be used to improve clinical practices and end-of-life communication in the U.S. The findings will also enhance democratic process in states considering PAD laws by contributing a more comprehensive understanding of the societal effects of PAD laws. Teaching and mentoring activities will extend the broader impacts of this project, most directly, through the training of a social science graduate student. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project focuses on Vermont's "Patient Choice and Control at End of Life" Act (Act 39), enacted in May 2013. The 2-year ethnographic study will address the following overarching research questions: How do ordinary people understand, access, experience, and contest the right to PAD once it has been granted?  How do healthcare providers and policy stakeholders accommodate or resist PAD as a new end-of-life practice? How does PAD affect the cultural landscape of care for the dying in the US? Due to the recent enactment of Act 39, and Vermont's small size and the geographic proximity of key institutions, Vermont offers an unparalleled setting for documenting emergent responses to the law across multiple sites (e.g. legal/medical, lay people/experts, urban/rural). Data collection will include: 1) semi-structured interviews with patients, survivors of people who have used Act 39, healthcare providers and administrators, activists, and legislators, and 2) participant observation in settings in which PAD is likely to be discussed (e.g. continuing education events for healthcare providers, community advocacy events). Qualitative data analysis will yield valuable information about the broad sociocultural consequences of legalizing PAD,including unintended consequences,that will be relevant to US policymakers, clinicians, patients, and families. It will also contribute to emerging social science theory on the relation between law, ethics, and social change.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1630010</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mara</FirstName>
<LastName>Buchbinder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mara Buchbinder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mara_buchbinder@med.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9198436881</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000699355</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>608195277</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName>Chapel Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[104 Airport Dr Ste 2200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>Cultural Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>STS-Sci, Tech &amp; Society</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, TECH &amp; SOCIETY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Dr. Mara Buchbinder, a medical anthropologist at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, studied the implementation and cultural impact of Vermont's 2013 medical aid-in-dying law in the period directly after the law passed. Legislative support for medical aid-in-dying (also known as assisted suicide) in the United States has risen steadily in recent years. Nine jurisdictions currently authorize physicians to prescribe a lethal dose of medication to a mentally competent, terminally ill, adult patient, provided that certain preconditions are met. With ongoing legislative activities in many additional states, these laws are expected to spread nationally. While such laws remain contentious, regardless of one's moral position on assisted death, this shifting legislative climate raises questions of broad public significance about how the legalization of aid-in-dying affects death, dying, and end-of-life care.</p> <p>The major goal of this project was to describe experiences with aid-in-dying from the perspectives of terminally ill people and their caregivers, health care providers, and policy stakeholders using semi-structured, qualitative interviews and ethnographic fieldwork. Including data collected during a preliminary research phase prior to this award, the project resulted in 144 interviews with physicians (n=29), nurses, chaplains, and social workers (n=22), terminally ill patients (n=9), lay caregivers (n=34), activists, legislators, and other policy stakeholders (n=37), and additional Vermont residents (n=13). Ninety-seven of these interviews were conducted with NSF funding. Research materials also include ethnographic fieldnotes recorded during four professional medical conferences, a court hearing regarding a lawsuit that challenged the law, and several community-based educational and advocacy events. Project data were collected during 2016-2017, and data analysis was completed from 2017-2019.</p> <p>Access to aid-in-dying was much more difficult than lay people anticipated, due to barriers that included: 1) finding a supportive physician, 2) paying for the medication, 3) obtaining social support to complete the bureaucratic protocol, 4) accessing information about the law, and 5) navigating legislative safeguards, particularly the requirement that medication be self-administered. These structural constraints resulted in the stratification of access to aid-in-dying, with patients from more socioeconomically privileged backgrounds having better access. Those patients who successfully navigated access to aid-in-dying were faced with different challenges regarding choosing the right time and circumstances for dying. These patients relied heavily on social support from family and friends to choreograph their deaths in personally meaningful ways.</p> <p>&nbsp;Most health care providers in the study were not either starkly "for" or "against" aid-in-dying. Instead, many harbored nuanced and ambivalent feelings that evolved over time through direct experiences with patients. Of the 51 health care providers interviewed, 37 had direct clinical experiences with Vermont?s aid-in-dying law, including 12 physicians who had participated as prescribing physicians. Health care providers engaged with the practice through 1) clinical communication and counseling, 2) navigating the bureaucratic protocol, 3) prescribing medication, 4) planning for death, and 5) professional education. The extent to which providers felt burdened by these clinical duties was a function of the institutional resources and professional support available to them. Health care providers ascribed a range of moral meanings to assisting death, and the moral significance of aid-in-dying for the physician?s professional role varied considerably, even among those who agreed to participate. Overall, the research demonstrated critical gaps between passing the law and implementing it. Health care providers and policy stakeholders were surprised to learn that important details of how aid-in-dying operates were unspecified in the legislative text, and that they were left to interpret and resolve certain ambiguities in the practice.</p> <p>&nbsp;Findings from this study contribute to anthropological scholarship in four primary areas: 1) biopolitics, 2) anthropologies of dependency and care, 3) bioethics and the law, and 4) clinical communication and disclosure. They also contribute to interdisciplinary work in bioethics and public health, particularly by bringing attention to justice as a neglected topic in studies of aid-in-dying. The research resulted in 8 peer-reviewed journal articles and a book manuscript currently in progress. The project also contributed to the training of several graduate, undergraduate, and medical students in methods of qualitative analysis and academic writing.</p> <p>The study has generated practical, previously unknown information about the practice of aid-in-dying in one US jurisdiction. This information will be valuable to newly legalizing jurisdictions or those that will legalize in the future. A subset of the interview transcripts was deposited in a publicly accessible data repository. Key study findings were incorporated into a report by the National Academies of Science, Engineering, and Medicine that offered a set of national guidelines on aid-in-dying. Results were also presented to the Vermont Department of Health, and at national and international conferences on assisted death attended by key clinical and policy stakeholders. Finally, the book manuscript in progress is being written in a clear and jargon-free manner, without assuming specialist knowledge, and will be pitched to academic presses that have successfully marketed academic books to general audiences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/15/2019<br>      Modified by: Mara&nbsp;Buchbinder</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Dr. Mara Buchbinder, a medical anthropologist at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, studied the implementation and cultural impact of Vermont's 2013 medical aid-in-dying law in the period directly after the law passed. Legislative support for medical aid-in-dying (also known as assisted suicide) in the United States has risen steadily in recent years. Nine jurisdictions currently authorize physicians to prescribe a lethal dose of medication to a mentally competent, terminally ill, adult patient, provided that certain preconditions are met. With ongoing legislative activities in many additional states, these laws are expected to spread nationally. While such laws remain contentious, regardless of one's moral position on assisted death, this shifting legislative climate raises questions of broad public significance about how the legalization of aid-in-dying affects death, dying, and end-of-life care.  The major goal of this project was to describe experiences with aid-in-dying from the perspectives of terminally ill people and their caregivers, health care providers, and policy stakeholders using semi-structured, qualitative interviews and ethnographic fieldwork. Including data collected during a preliminary research phase prior to this award, the project resulted in 144 interviews with physicians (n=29), nurses, chaplains, and social workers (n=22), terminally ill patients (n=9), lay caregivers (n=34), activists, legislators, and other policy stakeholders (n=37), and additional Vermont residents (n=13). Ninety-seven of these interviews were conducted with NSF funding. Research materials also include ethnographic fieldnotes recorded during four professional medical conferences, a court hearing regarding a lawsuit that challenged the law, and several community-based educational and advocacy events. Project data were collected during 2016-2017, and data analysis was completed from 2017-2019.  Access to aid-in-dying was much more difficult than lay people anticipated, due to barriers that included: 1) finding a supportive physician, 2) paying for the medication, 3) obtaining social support to complete the bureaucratic protocol, 4) accessing information about the law, and 5) navigating legislative safeguards, particularly the requirement that medication be self-administered. These structural constraints resulted in the stratification of access to aid-in-dying, with patients from more socioeconomically privileged backgrounds having better access. Those patients who successfully navigated access to aid-in-dying were faced with different challenges regarding choosing the right time and circumstances for dying. These patients relied heavily on social support from family and friends to choreograph their deaths in personally meaningful ways.   Most health care providers in the study were not either starkly "for" or "against" aid-in-dying. Instead, many harbored nuanced and ambivalent feelings that evolved over time through direct experiences with patients. Of the 51 health care providers interviewed, 37 had direct clinical experiences with Vermont?s aid-in-dying law, including 12 physicians who had participated as prescribing physicians. Health care providers engaged with the practice through 1) clinical communication and counseling, 2) navigating the bureaucratic protocol, 3) prescribing medication, 4) planning for death, and 5) professional education. The extent to which providers felt burdened by these clinical duties was a function of the institutional resources and professional support available to them. Health care providers ascribed a range of moral meanings to assisting death, and the moral significance of aid-in-dying for the physician?s professional role varied considerably, even among those who agreed to participate. Overall, the research demonstrated critical gaps between passing the law and implementing it. Health care providers and policy stakeholders were surprised to learn that important details of how aid-in-dying operates were unspecified in the legislative text, and that they were left to interpret and resolve certain ambiguities in the practice.   Findings from this study contribute to anthropological scholarship in four primary areas: 1) biopolitics, 2) anthropologies of dependency and care, 3) bioethics and the law, and 4) clinical communication and disclosure. They also contribute to interdisciplinary work in bioethics and public health, particularly by bringing attention to justice as a neglected topic in studies of aid-in-dying. The research resulted in 8 peer-reviewed journal articles and a book manuscript currently in progress. The project also contributed to the training of several graduate, undergraduate, and medical students in methods of qualitative analysis and academic writing.  The study has generated practical, previously unknown information about the practice of aid-in-dying in one US jurisdiction. This information will be valuable to newly legalizing jurisdictions or those that will legalize in the future. A subset of the interview transcripts was deposited in a publicly accessible data repository. Key study findings were incorporated into a report by the National Academies of Science, Engineering, and Medicine that offered a set of national guidelines on aid-in-dying. Results were also presented to the Vermont Department of Health, and at national and international conferences on assisted death attended by key clinical and policy stakeholders. Finally, the book manuscript in progress is being written in a clear and jargon-free manner, without assuming specialist knowledge, and will be pitched to academic presses that have successfully marketed academic books to general audiences.                   Last Modified: 05/15/2019       Submitted by: Mara Buchbinder]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
