<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CONFERENCE:  Post-transcriptional Gene Regulation in Plants to be held July 14-15, 2016 at the Austin Convention Center in Austin, TX</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Cone</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kccone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924967</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide support for a Conference on Post-transcriptional Gene Regulation in Plants to be held July 14-15, 2016 at the Austin Convention Center in Austin, Texas. The format of the meeting, which includes oral presentations and poster sessions, will provide a highly interactive environment to facilitate the sharing of latest research developments in this exciting field of plant biology. The program will also include career-building opportunities for young and early-career scientists, thus contributing to development of a new generation of plant scientists. The timing of this meeting--immediately after, and at the same site as, the American Society of Plant Biologists' Plant Biology 2016 Conference--is intended to make attendance convenient and affordable.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Post-transcriptional regulation of gene expression is crucial to many fundamental plant processes, and recent discoveries have highlighted many new regulatory mechanisms impacting pre-mRNA processing, RNA modification, and RNA stability. This conference will provide opportunities for scientists to exchange ideas concerning these new models of gene regulation and their impacts on plant growth and development, including responses to various abiotic and biotic stresses. Discussions will also include novel experimental and computational methods that permit collection and integrative analyses of high throughput data. The conference will have broad impact on scientific career development by promoting participation of women and members of underrepresented groups and by providing early-career researchers with structured opportunities to network and form collaborations with experts in the field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1631903</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Browning</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen S Browning</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kbrowning@cm.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124714562</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000375771</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A meeting on &ldquo;Post-transcriptional Gene Regulation in Plants&rdquo; (PGRP-2016) was held July 14-15<sup>th</sup> 2016 at the Austin Convention Center, Austin, Texas, as a satellite to Plant Biology 2016 (July 9-13) run by the American Society of Plant Biologists (ASPB). This was the 10th meeting (meetings started in 1997) on plant regulation of gene expression at the post-transcriptional level. The paradoxical discoveries that led to the understanding of RNA-mediated gene silencing were first discussed at the first of these meetings in Riverside, CA and Switzerland in the late 1990s. The field of RNA-based gene regulation continues to grow at a rapid pace, due to the importance of diverse post-transcriptional control mechanisms. New unexpected paradigms of gene regulation are emerging from these studies. Novel experimental and computational tools are being developed to address the extent of this regulation globally and its impact on plant growth, development and responses to diverse stresses.&nbsp;</p> <p>PGRP-2016 considered all aspects of post-transcriptional regulation of gene expression ranging from RNA biogenesis, structure and function, turnover, and targeting, as well as mechanistic studies of translation and protein stability. This event brought together a diverse group of researchers from different disciplines (e.g., biology, biochemistry, computer sciences, statistics) that investigate various aspects of gene regulation at the post-transcriptional level.&nbsp;</p> <p>The objectives of PGRP-2016 were 1) to bring researchers at all levels (undergraduates, MS/PhD students, postdocs, early career and senior researchers) from diverse fields to present and discuss new developments and cutting-edge tools related to all aspects of post-transcriptional regulation, 2) to provide an opportunity to new and established researchers in this field to develop collaborations across disciplines, 3) to facilitate networking and career-building opportunities for the younger researchers, and 4) to enhance participation of women and under-represented minorities by coupling PGRP-2016 with Plant Biology 2016. &nbsp;</p> <p class="details">The meeting had a diverse group of 82 participants from various institutions representing 14 countries.&nbsp; A goal of the meeting was achieved in having approximately one half graduate and post-doctoral students, the other half being principal investigators.&nbsp; Participants from industry were also present.&nbsp; Awards were given for the best talks by graduate and post-doctoral students.&nbsp; A meeting report was published in Plant, Cell &amp; Environment (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27859406">Meeting report: processing, translation, decay - three ways to keep RNA sizzling.</a> (2016) von Arnim AG, Hellmann HA. <span class="jrnl" title="Plant, cell &amp; environment">Plant Cell Environ</span>. 39:2624-2628. doi: 10.1111/pce.12819. Epub 2016 Nov 11.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/17/2017<br>      Modified by: Karen&nbsp;S&nbsp;Browning</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1631903/1631903_10417688_1494364270430_program_cover--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1631903/1631903_10417688_1494364270430_program_cover--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PGRP 2016 Cover"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1631903/1631903_10417688_1494364270430_program_cover--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PGRP 2016 Cover"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Program for the 2016 Post-transcriptional Gene Regulation in Plants meeting held July 14-16 in Austin, Texas.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Karen Browning</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karen&nbsp;S&nbsp;Browning</div> <div class="imageTitle">PGRP 2016 Cover</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A meeting on "Post-transcriptional Gene Regulation in Plants" (PGRP-2016) was held July 14-15th 2016 at the Austin Convention Center, Austin, Texas, as a satellite to Plant Biology 2016 (July 9-13) run by the American Society of Plant Biologists (ASPB). This was the 10th meeting (meetings started in 1997) on plant regulation of gene expression at the post-transcriptional level. The paradoxical discoveries that led to the understanding of RNA-mediated gene silencing were first discussed at the first of these meetings in Riverside, CA and Switzerland in the late 1990s. The field of RNA-based gene regulation continues to grow at a rapid pace, due to the importance of diverse post-transcriptional control mechanisms. New unexpected paradigms of gene regulation are emerging from these studies. Novel experimental and computational tools are being developed to address the extent of this regulation globally and its impact on plant growth, development and responses to diverse stresses.   PGRP-2016 considered all aspects of post-transcriptional regulation of gene expression ranging from RNA biogenesis, structure and function, turnover, and targeting, as well as mechanistic studies of translation and protein stability. This event brought together a diverse group of researchers from different disciplines (e.g., biology, biochemistry, computer sciences, statistics) that investigate various aspects of gene regulation at the post-transcriptional level.   The objectives of PGRP-2016 were 1) to bring researchers at all levels (undergraduates, MS/PhD students, postdocs, early career and senior researchers) from diverse fields to present and discuss new developments and cutting-edge tools related to all aspects of post-transcriptional regulation, 2) to provide an opportunity to new and established researchers in this field to develop collaborations across disciplines, 3) to facilitate networking and career-building opportunities for the younger researchers, and 4) to enhance participation of women and under-represented minorities by coupling PGRP-2016 with Plant Biology 2016.   The meeting had a diverse group of 82 participants from various institutions representing 14 countries.  A goal of the meeting was achieved in having approximately one half graduate and post-doctoral students, the other half being principal investigators.  Participants from industry were also present.  Awards were given for the best talks by graduate and post-doctoral students.  A meeting report was published in Plant, Cell &amp; Environment (Meeting report: processing, translation, decay - three ways to keep RNA sizzling. (2016) von Arnim AG, Hellmann HA. Plant Cell Environ. 39:2624-2628. doi: 10.1111/pce.12819. Epub 2016 Nov 11.       Last Modified: 05/17/2017       Submitted by: Karen S Browning]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
