<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Conference on Computational Mathematics and Inverse Problems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24700.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24700</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The main goal of the International Conference on Computational Mathematics and Inverse Problems is to bring together an international collection of established specialists as well as junior researchers in the area of computational mathematics and inverse problems. This type of scientific gathering and interaction can have long-lasting impact on junior researchers and graduate students. A significant broader impact will be to bring young researchers into the field, and establish new connections between disparate groups. The conference will also build a bridge between computational mathematics and inverse problems. The exchange of ideas will be beneficial to researchers in both areas. In addition, there will be a significant attendance of graduate students. The conference is a great opportunity for them to access the cutting-edge research, find interesting research topics, learn from world leading researchers, and build the network/collaboration for future academic careers. Geographically, Michigan Technological University is a little isolated from major cities. The conference will provide a boost to the research activities and give the department more visibility in the mathematical sciences community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;On the basis of current research trends and the wide spectrum of applications, the conference focuses on the following topics: iterative methods for large sparse eigenvalue problems with applications in big data sciences, finite element methods for eigenvalue problems, computational electromagnetic, direct techniques in inverse scattering theory, full wave inversion. The conference will feature plenary talks given by international experts on the aforementioned topics, invited talks from junior researchers, and contributed talks mainly from graduate students. The topics of the conference involve rapidly developments at the frontiers on today's research in computational mathematics and inverse problems. On one hand, the demand of computational methods in inverse problems is ever increasing. On the other hand, the computational mathematicians can find interesting new problems in inverse problems. Applicability of the conference topics extends to many real world applications including big data sciences, high performance computing, medical imaging, non-destructive testing, underground imaging and exploration.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1632364</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jiguang</FirstName>
<LastName>Sun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jiguang Sun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jiguangs@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064873172</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000238002</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan Technological University</Name>
<CityName>Houghton</CityName>
<ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9064871885</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 Townsend Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065453268</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN TECHNOLOGICAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065453268</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan Technological University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houghton</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 Townsend Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~24700</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The International Conference on Numerical Analysis and Inverse Problems was held Aug.15-19, 2016 at Michigan Technological University, Houghton MI. The conference brought leading researchers to discuss the recent developments on numerical analysis, scientific computing, and inverse problems. The topics of the conference included numerical methods for eigenvalue problems, finite element methods for Maxwell's equation, computational inverse problems, inverse scattering problems, etc.&nbsp;</p> <p>The conference gathered together a diverse group of people. The speakers included international experts from United States, Brazil, Canada, China, France, Finland, Germany, Italy, Greece, Spain, &nbsp;and UK. There were 45 speakers from 11 countries, 31 universities or research institutions. Half of the speakers are junior faculty and graduate students. Five of the speakers and one of the organizing committee are women.&nbsp;In addition, there were approximately 20 student participants.&nbsp;</p> <p>The conferece was an important scientific gathering, brought young researchers into the field, and established connections between disparate groups. The conference also built a bridge between the computational mathematics and inverse problems. The exchange of ideas was beneficial to participants in both areas. The conference was a great opportunity for graduate students to access the cutting-edge research, find interesting research topics, learn from world leading researchers, and build the network/collaboration for their future academic careers. The conference provided a boost to the research activities and gave the Mathematical Department a lot of visibility in the mathematical sciences community. A special issue of contributed papers from conference participants is in press in&nbsp;Computers &amp; Mathematics with Applications.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2017<br>      Modified by: Jiguang&nbsp;Sun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632364/1632364_10443005_1504210400539_DSC_0022--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632364/1632364_10443005_1504210400539_DSC_0022--rgov-800width.jpg" title="GroupPhoto"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632364/1632364_10443005_1504210400539_DSC_0022--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="GroupPhoto"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conference Group Photo</div> <div class="imageCredit">N/A</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jiguang&nbsp;Sun</div> <div class="imageTitle">GroupPhoto</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The International Conference on Numerical Analysis and Inverse Problems was held Aug.15-19, 2016 at Michigan Technological University, Houghton MI. The conference brought leading researchers to discuss the recent developments on numerical analysis, scientific computing, and inverse problems. The topics of the conference included numerical methods for eigenvalue problems, finite element methods for Maxwell's equation, computational inverse problems, inverse scattering problems, etc.   The conference gathered together a diverse group of people. The speakers included international experts from United States, Brazil, Canada, China, France, Finland, Germany, Italy, Greece, Spain,  and UK. There were 45 speakers from 11 countries, 31 universities or research institutions. Half of the speakers are junior faculty and graduate students. Five of the speakers and one of the organizing committee are women. In addition, there were approximately 20 student participants.   The conferece was an important scientific gathering, brought young researchers into the field, and established connections between disparate groups. The conference also built a bridge between the computational mathematics and inverse problems. The exchange of ideas was beneficial to participants in both areas. The conference was a great opportunity for graduate students to access the cutting-edge research, find interesting research topics, learn from world leading researchers, and build the network/collaboration for their future academic careers. The conference provided a boost to the research activities and gave the Mathematical Department a lot of visibility in the mathematical sciences community. A special issue of contributed papers from conference participants is in press in Computers &amp; Mathematics with Applications.        Last Modified: 08/31/2017       Submitted by: Jiguang Sun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
