<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop:   Toward Sustainable Groundwater in Agriculture - An International Conference Linking Science with Policy - Burlingame, California, June 28-30, 2016</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49980.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49980</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karl Rockne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>krockne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925356</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1632540 &lt;br/&gt;Harter&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Groundwater is the lifeline for many rural and agricultural regions and their associated cultures and populations around the globe and a cornerstone of global food production. Groundwater constitutes one-third of the worlds drinking water supplies, often the soul source of drinking water in rural areas; more than one-third of the world's irrigation water supply. In many regions, groundwater is the insurance against surface water shortages due to drought. Drought; overuse; groundwater salinity; nonpoint source pollution from agricultural activities (including animal farming, ranching, and forestry activities); and groundwater quality and quantity conflicts at the urban-rural interface have reached global dimensions and threaten the health and livelihood of this planet. This conference will serve as a state-wide, national, and global forum for scientists, agricultural representatives, NGOs, consultants, and policy and decision makers to discover and discuss solutions to managing, sharing, assessing, and protecting groundwater resources within agricultural landscapes. The meeting will be held at the Hyatt Regency Hotel in Burlingame, California, conveniently located within a few miles of the San Francisco International Airport June 28-30, 2016.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;California is among the global leaders in agricultural production, with nearly 10 million acres of irrigated agricultural lands, providing over 400 different commodities worth $50 billion, and consuming well over 32 million acre-feet of water annually for irrigation. California is also the leader in U.S. milk production, responsible for over 20% of U.S. dairy output. While California's agriculture is unique in many ways, it shares many aspects of its nexus with groundwater with other irrigated and non-irrigated agricultural regions in the United States and around the world. Many intensively farmed regions are overlying unconsolidated sedimentary aquifer systems similar to those in California. Irrigated agricultural lands are common in semi-arid and arid climates. While irrigated lands represent merely one-fifth of the global agricultural lands, provide for 40% of overall agricultural production worldwide, underscoring the importance of irrigated agriculture to global food security. This conference is comprehensive in its organization and will be broken into several separate but related areas; 1) Groundwater Management, Governance, Policy, and Regulation, Agricultural Water Use, Conjunctive/Integrated Management, 2) Socio-Economic Aspects of Agricultural Groundwater, Climate, Energy, and Agricultural Groundwater, 3) Agricultural Groundwater Quality and Contamination, Regulation, 4) Groundwater at the Agriculture-Urban Interface, 5) Groundwater Linkages to Groundwater-dependent Ecosystems, and, 6) Forecasting and Modeling. The meeting will follow a format where each of the three conference days is divided into four meeting periods: early morning, late morning, early afternoon, late afternoon. Each period will be approximately 100 minutes in length, featuring 3-4 speakers per session. The early morning period on each of the three conference days will be reserved for a plenary session on a key conference theme, featuring 3-4 keynote speakers and allowing for participation and discussion among the entire audience. The remaining periods will feature four parallel sessions to accommodate for a wide range of themes and participant interests. The final panel will provide a lively and critical ad hoc review of topics discussed at the conference and reflect on next steps and future challenges in moving toward global sustainability of groundwater in agricultural regions. With respect to outreach, the Water Education Foundation and other conference partners (UC Water, PPIC) will be interfacing with social media (Twitter, Facebook, etc) before and during the conference.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1632540</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Harter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Harter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>thharter@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5304001784</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485489</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/17/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956168628</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Shields Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~49980</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This three-day international conference brought together scientists, policy analysts, decision makers, and agricultural and environmental stakeholder groups from around the world to share awareness of and discuss the challenges and potential solutions to agricultural groundwater resource assessment, management, and groundwater quality protection and regulation, including agricultural technology and training solutions.</p> <p>California is among the global leaders in agricultural production. While California&rsquo;s agriculture is unique in many ways, it shares many aspects of its nexus with groundwater with other irrigated and non-irrigated agricultural regions in the United States and around the world. Many of these intensively farmed regions are overlying unconsolidated sedimentary aquifer systems similar to those in California.&nbsp; Irrigated agricultural lands are common in semi-arid and arid climates. While irrigated lands represent merely one-fifth of the global agricultural lands, provide for 40% of overall agricultural production worldwide, underscoring the importance of irrigated agriculture to global food security.</p> <p>As recent estimates show, irrigated agriculture is by far the largest global groundwater use &ndash; over 85% of all global groundwater extraction is for irrigation. In California and the U.S., groundwater extraction for irrigation is estimated at 73% and 69% of all groundwater use. Groundwater constitutes more than one-third of the global water supply (not including water for powerplant cooling) &ndash; more than 40% of the global irrigation water use, more than one-third of domestic water supplies, and nearly one-third of water supplies in manufacturing. Estimated global groundwater use is on the order of 1,500 km<sup>3</sup>&nbsp;of the approximately 4,300 km<sup>3</sup>&nbsp;total global water use.</p> <p>The intensity of agricultural production in California and similar regions worldwide has not been without environmental costs:&nbsp; groundwater overpumping &ndash; the long-term (multi-decadal) withdrawal of groundwater resources in excess of long-term groundwater recharge &ndash; has led to a falling groundwater table, which is further exacerbated by droughts with even higher rates of groundwater extractions. Declining groundwater resources, including during the current California drought, are at a record-breaking pace, and have a wide range of economic costs: wells fall dry, well maintenance costs increase, pumping costs rise, water production decreases, irrigation wells and domestic wells fail prematurely necessitating well replacement, land subsidence causes large scale damage to canals and other infrastructure, seawater intrusion threatens public water supplies, and significant strains are put on groundwater-dependent ecosystems and surface water flows.</p> <p>The conference supported by this project provided a unique interdisciplinary platform to bring together researchers in hydrogeology, hydrology, geography, engineering, and agricultural sciences with decision- and policy-makers, agricultural industry representatives, regulatory agency personnel, and environmental stakeholders.&nbsp; Participants share a common interest in groundwater at the nexus with agriculture.&nbsp; These opportunities have helped better define this emerging field, which is critical to global food security and the future of many agricultural regions. Presentations are archived online (<a href="http://ag-groundwater.org/">http://ag-groundwater.org</a>) and about two-thirds of the presentations are available as <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCS-mQDuWhJEw7as2XEVhK3A">videos online</a> providing excellent education resources.&nbsp; The conference also has provided opportunities for networking. For example, the Groundwater Solutions Initiative for Policy and Practice (<a href="http://www.iwmi.cgiar.org/issues/groundwater/gripp/">GRIPP</a>) was represented through Karen Villholth held a special meeting at the conference to engage interested participants further on issues related to sustainable groundwater in agriculture.</p> <p>The format of the conference allowed for an intensive exchange of information between participating groups. Non-academic participants reported that they were inspired by the many ideas shared, by finding partners in other states or countries facing similar challenges and by seeing solutions presented that have been successfully employed elsewhere.&nbsp; Some reported that they are planning to adopt assessment, monitoring, or management solutions presented at the conference in their region. The wide range of participants forced presenters to communicate clearly and effectively to an interdisciplinary and not exclusively scientific audience.&nbsp; The high quality of the presentations was reviewed enthusiastically by participants, which contributed positively to the sharing of ideas across institutional and academic barriers.</p> <p>The conversation around sustainable groundwater in agriculture, which has been initiated and stirred by this conference, is a critical conversation piece to ensure future global food security.&nbsp; Yet, there are few focused meetings that specifically address groundwater (as opposed to surface water) issues in the context of agriculture, across the wide range of aspects reflected in the conference session themes. The dialogue that this conference afforded to participants provides important impetus to take the conversation back to individual localities, states, or countries. Through the reflection of the many topical facets, participants are provided a more conscious framework within which to address conflicts and questions about properly understanding and managing groundwater in agriculture.&nbsp; Without this dialogue and information exchange, the local and often siloed institutional and academic perspectives remain isolated and uninformed &ndash; therefore without proper policy decisions &ndash; to address the globally extensive threat to groundwater resources in agricultural regions.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/25/2017<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Harter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This three-day international conference brought together scientists, policy analysts, decision makers, and agricultural and environmental stakeholder groups from around the world to share awareness of and discuss the challenges and potential solutions to agricultural groundwater resource assessment, management, and groundwater quality protection and regulation, including agricultural technology and training solutions.  California is among the global leaders in agricultural production. While California?s agriculture is unique in many ways, it shares many aspects of its nexus with groundwater with other irrigated and non-irrigated agricultural regions in the United States and around the world. Many of these intensively farmed regions are overlying unconsolidated sedimentary aquifer systems similar to those in California.  Irrigated agricultural lands are common in semi-arid and arid climates. While irrigated lands represent merely one-fifth of the global agricultural lands, provide for 40% of overall agricultural production worldwide, underscoring the importance of irrigated agriculture to global food security.  As recent estimates show, irrigated agriculture is by far the largest global groundwater use &ndash; over 85% of all global groundwater extraction is for irrigation. In California and the U.S., groundwater extraction for irrigation is estimated at 73% and 69% of all groundwater use. Groundwater constitutes more than one-third of the global water supply (not including water for powerplant cooling) &ndash; more than 40% of the global irrigation water use, more than one-third of domestic water supplies, and nearly one-third of water supplies in manufacturing. Estimated global groundwater use is on the order of 1,500 km3 of the approximately 4,300 km3 total global water use.  The intensity of agricultural production in California and similar regions worldwide has not been without environmental costs:  groundwater overpumping &ndash; the long-term (multi-decadal) withdrawal of groundwater resources in excess of long-term groundwater recharge &ndash; has led to a falling groundwater table, which is further exacerbated by droughts with even higher rates of groundwater extractions. Declining groundwater resources, including during the current California drought, are at a record-breaking pace, and have a wide range of economic costs: wells fall dry, well maintenance costs increase, pumping costs rise, water production decreases, irrigation wells and domestic wells fail prematurely necessitating well replacement, land subsidence causes large scale damage to canals and other infrastructure, seawater intrusion threatens public water supplies, and significant strains are put on groundwater-dependent ecosystems and surface water flows.  The conference supported by this project provided a unique interdisciplinary platform to bring together researchers in hydrogeology, hydrology, geography, engineering, and agricultural sciences with decision- and policy-makers, agricultural industry representatives, regulatory agency personnel, and environmental stakeholders.  Participants share a common interest in groundwater at the nexus with agriculture.  These opportunities have helped better define this emerging field, which is critical to global food security and the future of many agricultural regions. Presentations are archived online (http://ag-groundwater.org) and about two-thirds of the presentations are available as videos online providing excellent education resources.  The conference also has provided opportunities for networking. For example, the Groundwater Solutions Initiative for Policy and Practice (GRIPP) was represented through Karen Villholth held a special meeting at the conference to engage interested participants further on issues related to sustainable groundwater in agriculture.  The format of the conference allowed for an intensive exchange of information between participating groups. Non-academic participants reported that they were inspired by the many ideas shared, by finding partners in other states or countries facing similar challenges and by seeing solutions presented that have been successfully employed elsewhere.  Some reported that they are planning to adopt assessment, monitoring, or management solutions presented at the conference in their region. The wide range of participants forced presenters to communicate clearly and effectively to an interdisciplinary and not exclusively scientific audience.  The high quality of the presentations was reviewed enthusiastically by participants, which contributed positively to the sharing of ideas across institutional and academic barriers.  The conversation around sustainable groundwater in agriculture, which has been initiated and stirred by this conference, is a critical conversation piece to ensure future global food security.  Yet, there are few focused meetings that specifically address groundwater (as opposed to surface water) issues in the context of agriculture, across the wide range of aspects reflected in the conference session themes. The dialogue that this conference afforded to participants provides important impetus to take the conversation back to individual localities, states, or countries. Through the reflection of the many topical facets, participants are provided a more conscious framework within which to address conflicts and questions about properly understanding and managing groundwater in agriculture.  Without this dialogue and information exchange, the local and often siloed institutional and academic perspectives remain isolated and uninformed &ndash; therefore without proper policy decisions &ndash; to address the globally extensive threat to groundwater resources in agricultural regions.             Last Modified: 08/25/2017       Submitted by: Thomas Harter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
