<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Multifrequency Coordination in Dyads and Teams</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/14/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30842.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30842</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Betty Tuller</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>btuller@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927238</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>People coordinate their actions with one another in many different contexts and in many different ways:  Drivers in traffic manage to merge without accident; people walking on crowded streets usually avoid mishap; musicians coordinate a variety of nested rhythms produced by band members. These examples highlight the human capacity to coordinate behavior and exchange information at different rates to accomplish an overall goal, a phenomenon called interperson, multifrequency coordination. The researchers will study interperson, multifrequency coordination by applying the physics of coupled, oscillator systems to the perceptual, cognitive, and social information inherent in this type of coordination. Pairs of participants (dyads) will coordinate their movements while listening to different metronome frequencies through headphones.  Both performance pattern and pattern stability will be measured under different experimental conditions in order to test fundamental predictions of the mathematical model.  Experimental manipulations specifically designed to increase or decrease coupling between dyads' movements will be tested in the context of perceptual (e.g., visual), cognitive (e.g., counting), and social (e.g., partner familiarity) coupling mechanisms.  Field studies are also planned to discover how people coordinate in naturalistic situations.  This sequence of studies is designed to advance basic research on multifrequency coordination in dyads and to extend that research to spontaneous coordination in larger teams.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One important aspect of this project is the extension of experimentally induced multifrequency coordination in the laboratory to real-world settings in which spontaneous multifrequency coordination occurs across teams of individuals.  The project also has a significant outreach component, including a visit to a nationally organized competitive youth summer camp, where investigators will collect data on spontaneous interperson, multifreqency coordination and teach campers about coordination science and STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1632812</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamie</FirstName>
<LastName>Gorman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jamie C Gorman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jamie.gorman@gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6025762700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000597190</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/01/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Tech Research Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320415</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[505 10th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7252</Code>
<Text>Perception, Action &amp; Cognition</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7252</Code>
<Text>Perception, Action and Cognition</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7956</Code>
<Text>SBE Interdisciplinary Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~30842</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; mso-pagination: none; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span><span style="font-size: small;">Nearly every aspect of our lives includes the need to interact and coordinate with other people. There are relatively simple and well-understood forms of coordination, such as mirroring or mimicry, in which the coordinated movements are identical in tempo or frequency. However less is known about more complicated forms of interperson coordination. <span style="color: black; mso-themecolor: text1;">This research was designed to understand how people coordinate with each other when each person acts at a different tempo or frequency. This is called multifrequency coordination, and its complexity is measured by frequency ratios across people. We studied <span style="mso-bidi-font-weight: bold;">multifrequency coordination both </span>in the lab, where patterns were induced and highly controlled, and in a real-world task, where coordination was spontaneous and freely changing. <span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp;</span></span></span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; mso-pagination: none; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span style="color: black;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; mso-pagination: none; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span style="color: black;"><span style="font-size: small;">We tested the math behind multifrequency coordination using a model from mathematical number theory that applies to many physical, chemical, and biological phenomena. That same math has been applied previously to performance within a single person, but this project was the first to investigate it in coordination across individuals.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>What makes interperson coordination so interesting is that communication can no longer occur across hard physical or physiological connections.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>Instead, information must be shared through "softer&rdquo; channels, where people are coupled across perceptual, cognitive, and social relations.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>We tested those informational<em> </em>coupling mechanisms in dyads and small groups and found overall support for the math model that we were testing.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>We were able to make predictions about which patterns would be easiest for people to perform as well as quantify the strength of informational coupling needed to maintain interperson coordination. The <strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal;">intellectual merit</strong> of this research is the finding that common mathematical principles can be used to describe the physical, chemical, biological, psychological, and social world.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>That means that discoveries made in one scientific field can help us to understand phenomena in another scientific field.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; mso-pagination: none; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span style="color: black;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; mso-pagination: none; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="color: black;">This collaborative research required coordination across two universities and data collection in the real-world.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>We conducted conference calls and in-person visits to ensure that the experimental protocols would be compatible and to maintain consistency in mathematical modeling and data analysis. <span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp;</span>We implemented </span><span>a hierarchical training program that included four graduate and twelve undergraduate research assistants across both universities.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>All research assistants were engaged in research and presentation of findings at a level that was appropriate for their level of education. Graduate students gained training as mentors by helping to supervise undergraduate students.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="color: black;">Throughout the project, we worked to enhance </span><span>educational opportunities for underrepresented groups and to encourage diversity.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>That includes the underrepresentation of women in STEM fields. Five female undergraduate students were paid as </span><span style="color: black;">Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) recipients. One of those students even took three graduate-level courses in mathematical modeling and stayed on after graduation to complete a paper that she will publish in a scientific journal. </span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt;"><strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal;"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></strong></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span><span>An important part of any research program is sharing the results of the research with other scientists and with the broader community.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>We traveled to international, national, and regional conferences and engaged in discussion panels, workshops, and invited talks to present our results to fellow scientists.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>We published papers about this research in scientific journals. <span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp;</span></span><span>Perhaps the most exciting <strong style="mso-bidi-font-weight: normal;">broader impact</strong> of our research was the scientific outreach with a nationally-organized competitive youth summer camp, where we collected real-world data and taught campers about coordination science and STEM fields.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>We included graduate and undergraduate students in more local scientific outreach as well.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>We conducted a three-part series on "Math in our Behavior:<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>Fractions, Fractions Everywhere" for accelerated math students at a local elementary school; designed a Day of Science for 100 elementary school children in an after-school program; invited students from a Title I school to the lab for hands-on research experience; and showcased our research in a university-wide Night of the Open Door that was open to the broader community.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/21/2017<br>      Modified by: Jamie&nbsp;C&nbsp;Gorman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064415883_MathModel--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064415883_MathModel--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mathematical Modeling"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064415883_MathModel--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mathematical Modeling"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Math in our Behavior. Math can be used to make predictions about social coordination: performance of these ratios improves as additional information is shared. Predictions hold across different (perceptual, social, and cognitive) channels of communication.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Generated by PI</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jamie&nbsp;C&nbsp;Gorman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mathematical Modeling</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064521325_LabTask2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064521325_LabTask2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Laboratory Task"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064521325_LabTask2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Laboratory Task"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Lab Task. Conditions are highly controlled in the research laboratory: We ask participants to tap different rhythms and "help them along" with pacing signals delivered through headphones. Electronic data collection ensures clean data for analysis.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Generated by PI</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jamie&nbsp;C&nbsp;Gorman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Laboratory Task</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064627755_Results--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064627755_Results--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Results"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064627755_Results--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Results"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Results. We supported the predictions from our mathematical model. The intellectual merit of this research is the finding that common mathematical principles can be used to describe the physical, chemical, biological, psychological, and social world.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Generated by PI</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jamie&nbsp;C&nbsp;Gorman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Results</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064706468_Results2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064706468_Results2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Results"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064706468_Results2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Results"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Results. In accordance with the mathematical model, the difficulty of any coordination ratio scales with the amount of informational coupling between people.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Created by PI</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jamie&nbsp;C&nbsp;Gorman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Results</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064798606_ScientificOutreach2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064798606_ScientificOutreach2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Scientific Outreach"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1632812/1632812_10237993_1498064798606_ScientificOutreach2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Scientific Outreach"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Scientific Community Outreach: We engaged these children from a Title I school in a day of STEM learning.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Geneated by PI</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jamie&nbsp;C&nbsp;Gorman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Scientific Outreach</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Nearly every aspect of our lives includes the need to interact and coordinate with other people. There are relatively simple and well-understood forms of coordination, such as mirroring or mimicry, in which the coordinated movements are identical in tempo or frequency. However less is known about more complicated forms of interperson coordination. This research was designed to understand how people coordinate with each other when each person acts at a different tempo or frequency. This is called multifrequency coordination, and its complexity is measured by frequency ratios across people. We studied multifrequency coordination both in the lab, where patterns were induced and highly controlled, and in a real-world task, where coordination was spontaneous and freely changing.           We tested the math behind multifrequency coordination using a model from mathematical number theory that applies to many physical, chemical, and biological phenomena. That same math has been applied previously to performance within a single person, but this project was the first to investigate it in coordination across individuals.  What makes interperson coordination so interesting is that communication can no longer occur across hard physical or physiological connections.  Instead, information must be shared through "softer" channels, where people are coupled across perceptual, cognitive, and social relations.  We tested those informational coupling mechanisms in dyads and small groups and found overall support for the math model that we were testing.  We were able to make predictions about which patterns would be easiest for people to perform as well as quantify the strength of informational coupling needed to maintain interperson coordination. The intellectual merit of this research is the finding that common mathematical principles can be used to describe the physical, chemical, biological, psychological, and social world.  That means that discoveries made in one scientific field can help us to understand phenomena in another scientific field.         This collaborative research required coordination across two universities and data collection in the real-world.  We conducted conference calls and in-person visits to ensure that the experimental protocols would be compatible and to maintain consistency in mathematical modeling and data analysis.  We implemented a hierarchical training program that included four graduate and twelve undergraduate research assistants across both universities.  All research assistants were engaged in research and presentation of findings at a level that was appropriate for their level of education. Graduate students gained training as mentors by helping to supervise undergraduate students.  Throughout the project, we worked to enhance educational opportunities for underrepresented groups and to encourage diversity.  That includes the underrepresentation of women in STEM fields. Five female undergraduate students were paid as Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) recipients. One of those students even took three graduate-level courses in mathematical modeling and stayed on after graduation to complete a paper that she will publish in a scientific journal.         An important part of any research program is sharing the results of the research with other scientists and with the broader community.  We traveled to international, national, and regional conferences and engaged in discussion panels, workshops, and invited talks to present our results to fellow scientists.  We published papers about this research in scientific journals.  Perhaps the most exciting broader impact of our research was the scientific outreach with a nationally-organized competitive youth summer camp, where we collected real-world data and taught campers about coordination science and STEM fields.  We included graduate and undergraduate students in more local scientific outreach as well.  We conducted a three-part series on "Math in our Behavior:  Fractions, Fractions Everywhere" for accelerated math students at a local elementary school; designed a Day of Science for 100 elementary school children in an after-school program; invited students from a Title I school to the lab for hands-on research experience; and showcased our research in a university-wide Night of the Open Door that was open to the broader community.       Last Modified: 06/21/2017       Submitted by: Jamie C Gorman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
