<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Long-Term Human-Environmental Interaction In a Lowland Tropic Setting</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>127188.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>127188</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The aim of this interdisciplinary study, conducted by researchers at the University of New Mexico (UNM) and Pennsylvania State University (PSU), is to study human-climate-environmental dynamics among the earliest inhabitants of the American tropics. The work is designed to investigate the hypothesis that major behavioral changes in subsistence economies and technology were partially mediated by demographic transitions, climate variability, and anthropogenic environmental change on multiple timescales. The study of human adaptive capacity in the face of rapid environmental change has become more urgent given predictions of future warming and rapid population growth globally. This study is centrally relevant to this societal challenge. It will promote teaching, training, and learning, providing opportunities for collecting original data for graduate and undergraduate student projects at the University of New Mexico, Pennsylvania State University, and other institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team will conduct a range of archaeological, bioarchaeological, and geochemical analyses on artifacts, skeletal materials (human and non-human), and plant remains from two rockshelter sites in the Maya Mountains of southern Belize with demonstrated occupations ranging between 13,000 and 3,500 years ago. Researchers will also develop a parallel paleoclimate record from nearby cave deposits with incremental geochemical analyses of stalagmites known to span this interval. During this time, humans successfully adapted to tropical habitats, responded to important changes in climate and ecosystem organization, coalesced into the first sedentary communities, and developed agriculture. Precision accelerator mass spectrometry radiocarbon dating of animal and human bone along with stable isotope measurements will be conducted at the PSU Accelerator Mass Spectrometry Facility and UNM Center for Stable isotopes. At PSU, variation in internal bone structure in the lower and upper limbs will be measured using 3D microCT scans to provide insights into human mobility and adaptation to changing lifeways through time. At UNM, and in collaboration with climate science collaborators, the team will develop a high-resolution paleoclimate record from cave stalagmites in the region that will be anchored precisely in time with uranium series dates. The climate backdrop will be used to interpret both cultural and biological change.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1632144</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Kennett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas J Kennett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kennett@anth.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8149542445</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000109494</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Ryan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy M Ryan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tmr21@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148651531</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000359270</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brendan</FirstName>
<LastName>Culleton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brendan J Culleton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bjc23@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148655342</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000668096</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>Archaeology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~127188</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Maize is a cultigen of global economic importance, but when it first became a staple grain in the Americas, was unknown and contested. We obtained direct isotopic dietary evidence from 52 radiocarbon-dated human skeletons from two remarkably well-preserved rock-shelter contexts in the Maya Mountains of Belize spanning the past 10,000 years. Individuals dating before 4700 years ago show no clear evidence for the consumption of maize. Evidence for substantial maize consumption (~30% of total diet) appears in some individuals between 4700 and 4000 years ago. Isotopic evidence after 4000 years ago indicates that maize became a persistently used staple grain comparable in dietary significance to later maize agriculturalists in the region (&gt;70% of total diet). These data provide the earliest definitive evidence for maize as a staple grain in the Americas.</p> <p>&nbsp;The two archaeological sites investigated (Mayahak Cab Pek and Saki Tzul) are highly significant because they are the only archeological sites in the Americas with a relatively continuous diachronic sample of human skeletal material spanning the past 10,000 years. Therefore, the stable isotope analysis of these directly radiocarbon-dated individuals provides an unprecedented view of dietary changes during the transition from foraging to farming in the Americas. In the lowland neotropics, these data complement genetic and paleobotanical evidence for the domestication and spread of maize after 9000 years ago. Paleoecological records in the Maya region suggest that the initial introduction of maize, in its earliest form, occurred between 6500 and 5500 years ago, but maize had little dietary impact as a staple before 4700 years ago. Consumption increased after this time, and it became a persistent dietary staple by 4000 years ago. Comparable isotopic studies indicate the adoption of maize as a staple elsewhere in Mesoamerica by ~3000 years ago and in North America later than 2500 years ago. Ultimately, this transition contributed to the expansion and aggregation of populations, increases in social inequality, and major environmental transformations.</p> <p>&nbsp;We trained multiple students (graduate and undergraduate) in scientific methodologies in the process of doing this research. We also worked closely with Maya farmers and shared these results with them. In 2020 we invited indigenous leaders and community members from villages pin the region to consult on this research. We provided advance invitations and arranged transportation for forty-six people from five villages to attend the public consultation. We delivered a one-hour presentation detailing the fieldwork, laboratory work and results of this study, and an additional one hour was devoted to answering questions and clarifying the data and interpretations. Community members requested future public consultations to update them on additional research results, as well as copies of all study results in English with translations into Mopan and Q&rsquo;eqchi&rsquo; languages. After this meeting we translated a summary of our work into Mopan and Q&rsquo;eqchi&rsquo; and distributed it widely in these communities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/07/2021<br>      Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;J&nbsp;Kennett</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Maize is a cultigen of global economic importance, but when it first became a staple grain in the Americas, was unknown and contested. We obtained direct isotopic dietary evidence from 52 radiocarbon-dated human skeletons from two remarkably well-preserved rock-shelter contexts in the Maya Mountains of Belize spanning the past 10,000 years. Individuals dating before 4700 years ago show no clear evidence for the consumption of maize. Evidence for substantial maize consumption (~30% of total diet) appears in some individuals between 4700 and 4000 years ago. Isotopic evidence after 4000 years ago indicates that maize became a persistently used staple grain comparable in dietary significance to later maize agriculturalists in the region (&gt;70% of total diet). These data provide the earliest definitive evidence for maize as a staple grain in the Americas.   The two archaeological sites investigated (Mayahak Cab Pek and Saki Tzul) are highly significant because they are the only archeological sites in the Americas with a relatively continuous diachronic sample of human skeletal material spanning the past 10,000 years. Therefore, the stable isotope analysis of these directly radiocarbon-dated individuals provides an unprecedented view of dietary changes during the transition from foraging to farming in the Americas. In the lowland neotropics, these data complement genetic and paleobotanical evidence for the domestication and spread of maize after 9000 years ago. Paleoecological records in the Maya region suggest that the initial introduction of maize, in its earliest form, occurred between 6500 and 5500 years ago, but maize had little dietary impact as a staple before 4700 years ago. Consumption increased after this time, and it became a persistent dietary staple by 4000 years ago. Comparable isotopic studies indicate the adoption of maize as a staple elsewhere in Mesoamerica by ~3000 years ago and in North America later than 2500 years ago. Ultimately, this transition contributed to the expansion and aggregation of populations, increases in social inequality, and major environmental transformations.   We trained multiple students (graduate and undergraduate) in scientific methodologies in the process of doing this research. We also worked closely with Maya farmers and shared these results with them. In 2020 we invited indigenous leaders and community members from villages pin the region to consult on this research. We provided advance invitations and arranged transportation for forty-six people from five villages to attend the public consultation. We delivered a one-hour presentation detailing the fieldwork, laboratory work and results of this study, and an additional one hour was devoted to answering questions and clarifying the data and interpretations. Community members requested future public consultations to update them on additional research results, as well as copies of all study results in English with translations into Mopan and Q’eqchi’ languages. After this meeting we translated a summary of our work into Mopan and Q’eqchi’ and distributed it widely in these communities.          Last Modified: 01/07/2021       Submitted by: Douglas J Kennett]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
