<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Responsible Innovation with Genetically Modified American Chestnut Trees</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>291974.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>291974</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick Kronz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fkronz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>General Audience Summary &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This collaborative proposal focuses on the Genetically Modified American Chestnut tree (GMAC). Unlike other emerging biotechnologies, such as gene drives, the GMAC has already been subjected to multiple years of field testing; it is on the verge of entering the regulatory review process for full environmental release. Two research teams will engage with four core stakeholder groups: biotechnologists, indigenous communities, non-governmental organizations, and policy makers. The research team at North Carolina State University will engage in interviews and laboratory ethnographies with biotechnologists, and the team will conduct a workshop that will include significant interaction and dialogue among university researchers, non-governmental organizations, and associated scientists in the public and private sectors. It will also conduct a narrative policy framework analysis to reveal the ways in which non-governmental organizations and other political actors use narratives to govern the development and deployment of the GMAC. The stakeholder workshop will lay groundwork for a highly collaborative future effort to engage the public on an emerging technology; it will focus on the ways in which public audiences might be meaningfully engaged to decide if and how the GMAC should be released into shared environments. The research team at the collaborating institution, the State University of New York College of Environmental Science and Forestry's Center for Native Peoples and the Environment, will conduct linguistic analysis and host a workshop in Haudenosaunee territory to understand the ways in which the GMAC might intersect with the history and sovereignty of indigenous communities. The collaboration will create multiple engagements between university researchers and underrepresented communities often excluded from decision-making processes. Project personnel will produce research reports for stakeholders, presentations for interdisciplinary academic conferences, and at least eight manuscripts for publication in peer-reviewed journals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By focusing on a common set of themes across four core stakeholder groups, the proposed research aims to advance scholarship on expertise, anticipatory governance, responsible innovation, and environmental justice. Interviews of tree biotechnologists explore the anticipations, which is related to governance in the broadest sense, of innovative technologies and their regulatory environments. The collaboration with the State University of New York researchers will co-produce knowledge addressing a public that is often excluded, to incorporate perceptions of genetically modified trees and provide insight into relationships among responsible innovation, indigenous expertise, and environmental justice. The narrative policy framework analysis promises more nuanced understandings of the activities of non-governmental organizations beyond their positive and negative stances concerning genetically modified organisms. The stakeholder workshop confronts experts with social science research to test how their own perceptions change and to what degree they re-imagine their own roles in engaging with the public about genetically modified trees and other biotechnologies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1632670</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Delborne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason A Delborne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jadelbor@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9199802867</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000519434</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Binder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew R Binder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>arbinder@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195132430</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000606316</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Louie</FirstName>
<LastName>Rivers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Louie Rivers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lrivers@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195152444</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000660812</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276038008</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5221 Jordan Hall Addition]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>STS-Sci, Tech &amp; Society</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7567</Code>
<Text>SOC STUDIES OF SCI, ENG &amp; TECH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~291974</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Professor Jason Delborne led a team of faculty, postdoctoral researchers, and doctoral students to study the social and political issues surrounding the development of the genetically engineered (GE) American chestnut tree. This case study is significant because it represents the first genetically modified organism submitted for unrestricted environmental release into unmanaged environments in the United States. It is a biotechnology aimed at restoring a functionally extinct species, but it has also created controversy.</p> <p>Our team studied the scientists central to the development of the GE chesnut through interviews and interactions at workshops and meetings. We investigated the role of The American Chestnut Foundation and other environmental NGOs in promoting or challenging the GE tree. By partnering with the Center for Native Peoples and the Environment and the Haudenosaunee Environmental Task Force, we also explored Indigenous perspectives about American chestnut restoration and biotechnology. Specifically, we helped create opportunities for dialogue between Indigenous leaders and scientists working on the transgenic tree.</p> <p>Three PhD students were funded by this research, and all include their study of the GE chestnut in their disserations. Two postdoctoral researchers were also supported and participated in data collection and analysis, and the writing of scholarly manuscripts.</p> <p>This grant supported us in organizing a workshop at North Carolina State University in April 2018 for a diverse set of stakeholders that surround the GE chestnut case. This workshop created opportunities for mutual learning among participants and explored the ways in which broader public engagement might contribute to the governance of the GE chestnut and other emerging environmental biotechnologies. The workshop enabled the formulation of a conceptual framework to consider the many ways that public engagement could inform decision making during the stages of research and development, regulatory review, and deployment and management.</p> <p>Largely due to the expertise developed during this project, Dr. Delborne was invited to join the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (NASEM) expert committee on the Potential for Biotechnology to Address Forest Health, which published a consensus study report in 2019. Relatedly, Delborne was invited to join the International Union for Conservation of Nature's task force on Synthetic Biology and Biodiversity Conservation, which produced a report in 2019 and engaged with the IUCN leadership and member organizations to develop guidelines on how to understand the potential for biotechnology and synthetic biology to affect biodiversity across the globe.</p> <p>Our findings point to the complexities that surround the application of biotechnology tools and methods to a conservation goal. On the one hand, this case study disrupts the narratives of corporate-dominated biotechnology in agriculture that emerged from activist movements in the 1990s and 2000s. The GE chestnut is not patented, its primary boosters are academic scientists and nonprofit organizations, and the goal is the restoration of a functionally extinct species rather than profit. On ther other hand, concerns remain about whose interests and preferences take precedence in governing a technology that will not respect political boundaries, how best to anticipate the ecological impacts of a long-lived organism, and the degree to which the GE chestnut might pave the way for further expansions in biotech forestry.</p> <p>The results of our research do not dictate whether the GE chestnut tree is "good" or "bad," but rather point to ways in which the governance of emerging environmental biotechnologies might better engage communities, stakeholders, and publics in the service of pursuing responsible innovation and environmental justice.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/06/2021<br>      Modified by: Jason&nbsp;A&nbsp;Delborne</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1632670/1632670_10458328_1628279653906_20180425_124847(1)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1632670/1632670_10458328_1628279653906_20180425_124847(1)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="GE chestnut stakeholder workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1632670/1632670_10458328_1628279653906_20180425_124847(1)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="GE chestnut stakeholder workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">GE American chestnut stakeholder workshop at North Carolina State University, April 2018</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jason Delborne</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jason&nbsp;A&nbsp;Delborne</div> <div class="imageTitle">GE chestnut stakeholder workshop</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1632670/1632670_10458328_1628279394742_IMG_3422(2016_05_0402_31_10UTC)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1632670/1632670_10458328_1628279394742_IMG_3422(2016_05_0402_31_10UTC)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="American chestnut bur"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1632670/1632670_10458328_1628279394742_IMG_3422(2016_05_0402_31_10UTC)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="American chestnut bur"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">American chestnut bur</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jessica Cavin Barnes</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jason&nbsp;A&nbsp;Delborne</div> <div class="imageTitle">American chestnut bur</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1632670/1632670_10458328_1628279509300_IMG_3430(2016_05_0402_31_10UTC)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1632670/1632670_10458328_1628279509300_IMG_3430(2016_05_0402_31_10UTC)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Doctoral student by American chestnut"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1632670/1632670_10458328_1628279509300_IMG_3430(2016_05_0402_31_10UTC)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Doctoral student by American chestnut"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Visiting American chestnut restoration site</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jessica Cavin Barnes</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jason&nbsp;A&nbsp;Delborne</div> <div class="imageTitle">Doctoral student by American chestnut</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1632670/1632670_10458328_1628279272890_045--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1632670/1632670_10458328_1628279272890_045--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Prof Delborne and student"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1632670/1632670_10458328_1628279272890_045--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Prof Delborne and student"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Research team at laboratories where the GE chestnut was developed</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jason Delborne</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jason&nbsp;A&nbsp;Delborne</div> <div class="imageTitle">Prof Delborne and student</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Professor Jason Delborne led a team of faculty, postdoctoral researchers, and doctoral students to study the social and political issues surrounding the development of the genetically engineered (GE) American chestnut tree. This case study is significant because it represents the first genetically modified organism submitted for unrestricted environmental release into unmanaged environments in the United States. It is a biotechnology aimed at restoring a functionally extinct species, but it has also created controversy.  Our team studied the scientists central to the development of the GE chesnut through interviews and interactions at workshops and meetings. We investigated the role of The American Chestnut Foundation and other environmental NGOs in promoting or challenging the GE tree. By partnering with the Center for Native Peoples and the Environment and the Haudenosaunee Environmental Task Force, we also explored Indigenous perspectives about American chestnut restoration and biotechnology. Specifically, we helped create opportunities for dialogue between Indigenous leaders and scientists working on the transgenic tree.  Three PhD students were funded by this research, and all include their study of the GE chestnut in their disserations. Two postdoctoral researchers were also supported and participated in data collection and analysis, and the writing of scholarly manuscripts.  This grant supported us in organizing a workshop at North Carolina State University in April 2018 for a diverse set of stakeholders that surround the GE chestnut case. This workshop created opportunities for mutual learning among participants and explored the ways in which broader public engagement might contribute to the governance of the GE chestnut and other emerging environmental biotechnologies. The workshop enabled the formulation of a conceptual framework to consider the many ways that public engagement could inform decision making during the stages of research and development, regulatory review, and deployment and management.  Largely due to the expertise developed during this project, Dr. Delborne was invited to join the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (NASEM) expert committee on the Potential for Biotechnology to Address Forest Health, which published a consensus study report in 2019. Relatedly, Delborne was invited to join the International Union for Conservation of Nature's task force on Synthetic Biology and Biodiversity Conservation, which produced a report in 2019 and engaged with the IUCN leadership and member organizations to develop guidelines on how to understand the potential for biotechnology and synthetic biology to affect biodiversity across the globe.  Our findings point to the complexities that surround the application of biotechnology tools and methods to a conservation goal. On the one hand, this case study disrupts the narratives of corporate-dominated biotechnology in agriculture that emerged from activist movements in the 1990s and 2000s. The GE chestnut is not patented, its primary boosters are academic scientists and nonprofit organizations, and the goal is the restoration of a functionally extinct species rather than profit. On ther other hand, concerns remain about whose interests and preferences take precedence in governing a technology that will not respect political boundaries, how best to anticipate the ecological impacts of a long-lived organism, and the degree to which the GE chestnut might pave the way for further expansions in biotech forestry.  The results of our research do not dictate whether the GE chestnut tree is "good" or "bad," but rather point to ways in which the governance of emerging environmental biotechnologies might better engage communities, stakeholders, and publics in the service of pursuing responsible innovation and environmental justice.          Last Modified: 08/06/2021       Submitted by: Jason A Delborne]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
