<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The reticulation/activation nexus in organizations:  An agent-based model and empirical test using unique data</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>205060.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>205060</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skiesler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928643</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding the development of communication networks in organizational contexts is a fundamental research problem in the science of organizations.  An explosion of research in this area over the last 30 years has produced an understanding of how networks operate in equilibrium conditions based on dyadic features like balance, homophily, and exchange. Yet we still do not understand the effects of individual agency and contextual factors like organizational activity.  The purpose of this project is to develop and test a theory of network structuring and development based on the activities of human agents influencing one another within group contexts.  This project makes four contributions: (1) modeling network nodes as agents with their own motives and networking tendencies, (2) describing the influence of focused activities on network development, (3) accounting for the influence of organizational structures and work units on network development, and (4) explaining network dynamics as the product of a loop of structure and behavior which influences one another over time.  Understanding these phenomena will enable better design of a wide range of organizations, as well as better prediction and mitigation of organizational failure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theoretical context of this work is Network Reticulation Theory (NRT).  This theory draws-together elements of structuration theory and activity focus theory to explain how perceived network relationships are activated by triggers in an organizational system, for example how a deadline in a software engineering firm activates certain elements of an organizational network to produce a hackathon, potentially strengthening the constituent network relationships in the process.  We study this process using a unique dataset comprising ubiquitous observation of a software engineering shop, from which data about perceived relationships, observed communication, task activities, and member perceptions are recorded for 79 employees over a period of three years.  To evaluate the theory, we employ three complimentary methods: (1) A direct test on the empirical data using statistical relational event modeling; (2) a multi-agent social-network simulation that faithfully models NRT by capturing activation, reticulation, and enactment processes; and (3) a cognitive multi-agent social-network simulation that adds architecture for decision making at the network nodes.  The project also utilizes a novel method for identifying network connections from audio recordings that offers a useful supplement to sociometric badges.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1632707</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Corman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven R Corman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>steve.corman@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809653830</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000307729</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Bliss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel W Bliss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>d.w.bliss@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809653913</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000640375</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Visar</FirstName>
<LastName>Berisha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Visar Berisha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>visar@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809655479</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000672841</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>SoO-Science Of Organizations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~205060</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project addressed a key unresolved problem in the organizational science literature:&nbsp; In an organizational system, what are the relationships between activity, communication that can be observed, and communication perceived by members?i.e., answers to questions like ?how much did you communicate with person X this week at work??&nbsp; Previous research, commonly called the <em>accuracy studies</em> in social network research, found a weak relationship between perceived and observable communication; however, it was largely based on unusual settings and limited observation periods.&nbsp; It also assumed that perceived communication should be a straightforward reflection of observable communication, albeit with some error.&nbsp;</p> <p>In contrast, this project used a unique setting, a software development shop at a university that operated over 140 weeks and had 54 employees.&nbsp; Furthermore, employees wore individual digital voice recorders while at work.&nbsp; These were processed by an algorithm developed for this project to provide a comprehensive and objective record of observable communication over the life of the organization. &nbsp;Employees completed weekly perceived communication questionnaires too.&nbsp; The project also proceeded from the assumptions of Network Reticulation Theory (NRT), which says that we should expect perceived and observable communication to differ because of the effects of the organizational activity system.</p> <p>The project found correlations between perceived and observable communication similar to those in the accuracy studies overall.&nbsp; But, consistent with NRT assumptions, they varied substantially from week to week (see Figure), something we would not expect if perceptions we merely observations plus error.&nbsp; We also found a significant relationship between observable communication and productivity.&nbsp; Although it is a truism that these are related, it has rarely been tested in empirical research because of the difficulty of measuring observable communication.&nbsp; Finally, this study developed a cognitive agent-based model (ABM) that simulates the software shop?s communication and activity system based on NRT.&nbsp; It allows comparisons of its predictions of perceived and observable communication with the empirical data from our study.&nbsp; An initial run of this ABM indicates some significant correlations, and we expect these to improve with model refinement.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/31/2020<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;R&nbsp;Corman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1632707/1632707_10443827_1609463681730_dist--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1632707/1632707_10443827_1609463681730_dist--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Graph of correlation distribution"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1632707/1632707_10443827_1609463681730_dist--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Graph of correlation distribution"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Number of 121 correlations in 0.05 ranges</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Corman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;R&nbsp;Corman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Graph of correlation distribution</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project addressed a key unresolved problem in the organizational science literature:  In an organizational system, what are the relationships between activity, communication that can be observed, and communication perceived by members?i.e., answers to questions like ?how much did you communicate with person X this week at work??  Previous research, commonly called the accuracy studies in social network research, found a weak relationship between perceived and observable communication; however, it was largely based on unusual settings and limited observation periods.  It also assumed that perceived communication should be a straightforward reflection of observable communication, albeit with some error.   In contrast, this project used a unique setting, a software development shop at a university that operated over 140 weeks and had 54 employees.  Furthermore, employees wore individual digital voice recorders while at work.  These were processed by an algorithm developed for this project to provide a comprehensive and objective record of observable communication over the life of the organization.  Employees completed weekly perceived communication questionnaires too.  The project also proceeded from the assumptions of Network Reticulation Theory (NRT), which says that we should expect perceived and observable communication to differ because of the effects of the organizational activity system.  The project found correlations between perceived and observable communication similar to those in the accuracy studies overall.  But, consistent with NRT assumptions, they varied substantially from week to week (see Figure), something we would not expect if perceptions we merely observations plus error.  We also found a significant relationship between observable communication and productivity.  Although it is a truism that these are related, it has rarely been tested in empirical research because of the difficulty of measuring observable communication.  Finally, this study developed a cognitive agent-based model (ABM) that simulates the software shop?s communication and activity system based on NRT.  It allows comparisons of its predictions of perceived and observable communication with the empirical data from our study.  An initial run of this ABM indicates some significant correlations, and we expect these to improve with model refinement.       Last Modified: 12/31/2020       Submitted by: Steven R Corman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
