<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>BIGDATA: Collaborative Research: IA: F: Latent and Graphical Models for Complex Dependent Data in Education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>800671.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>800671</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Finbarr Sloane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fsloane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928465</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This is a comprehensive research proposal on the statistical modeling and analysis for educational assessment. This research addresses issues concerning fundamental statistical problems that arise in the analysis of Big Data in education. The research focus is on modeling and inference for large-scale data with complex dependence and structures (such as high-dimensional response and process data). These data arise from the introduction of new methods of testing student knowledge that rely on scenarios presented to the students and on simulation-based environments where student responses to a simulated environment are tested. This research is collaborative between Columbia University  and the Educational Testing Service.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The topics studied include latent graphical modeling for high-dimensional item response data, modeling and segmentation of process data via dictionary models, estimation of item-attribute relationship, dimension reduction, theoretical analysis and computational methods for the proposed models. The analysis combines techniques and concepts from mathematics and probability and applies them to nonlinear statistical models and data analysis. The proposed model combines latent variable and graphical approaches for high-dimensional data; for modeling process data, recent advances in modeling and segmenting techniques for natural language processing will be investigated. In the theoretical development,  several algebraic concepts to formulate model identifiability and perform combinatorial analysis on high-dimensional discrete spaces will be studied. In addition, optimization algorithms will be developed using recent advances in numerical methods.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1633360</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhiliang</FirstName>
<LastName>Ying</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhiliang Ying</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zying@stat.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128512151</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000152577</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jingchen</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jingchen Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jcliu@stat.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128512146</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000516295</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York, NY</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100275927</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1255 Amsterdam Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7261</Code>
<Text>Project &amp; Program Evaluation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8251</Code>
<Text>Math Sci Innovation Incubator</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~800671</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This research developes statistical modeling and learning methods for educational assessment. It addresses issues concerning fundamental statistical problems that arise in the analysis of Big Data in education. The research focus is on modeling and inference for large-scale data sets of complex dependence structures and data of non-standard structures such as high-dimensional responses and process responses. The speicific methodological contributions are</span></p> <p>1. Developed a fused latent graphical model for multivariate item respnose data.</p> <p>2. Developed a general estimation method for Q-matrix.</p> <p>3. Developed a testing procedure for Q-matrix.</p> <p>4. Developed several feature extraction methods for the process data that can be proved to contain substantially more information than the traditional responses&nbsp;empirically.</p> <p>5. A process-data-based partial scoring system is developed that is much more accurate than that of the traditional responses.</p> <p>We also made a great effort to desseminate our research to other researchers. The specific activities are</p> <p>1.&nbsp;<span>Built and distributed an R package (ProcData) to implement the process data feature extraction methods.</span></p> <p>2. Delivered a short course on processs data analysis open to public. There are over 500 registrations. The course materials are available at&nbsp;http://www.scientifichpc.com/processdata/workshop.html.&nbsp;</p> <p><span>The research funds were able to partially support the research of three postdoctoral researchers and several PhD students who have finished (or are close to finishing) their training. Several of them have become faculty members in mathematics, psychology, and educational psychology departments across the country.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/05/2021<br>      Modified by: Jingchen&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research developes statistical modeling and learning methods for educational assessment. It addresses issues concerning fundamental statistical problems that arise in the analysis of Big Data in education. The research focus is on modeling and inference for large-scale data sets of complex dependence structures and data of non-standard structures such as high-dimensional responses and process responses. The speicific methodological contributions are  1. Developed a fused latent graphical model for multivariate item respnose data.  2. Developed a general estimation method for Q-matrix.  3. Developed a testing procedure for Q-matrix.  4. Developed several feature extraction methods for the process data that can be proved to contain substantially more information than the traditional responses empirically.  5. A process-data-based partial scoring system is developed that is much more accurate than that of the traditional responses.  We also made a great effort to desseminate our research to other researchers. The specific activities are  1. Built and distributed an R package (ProcData) to implement the process data feature extraction methods.  2. Delivered a short course on processs data analysis open to public. There are over 500 registrations. The course materials are available at http://www.scientifichpc.com/processdata/workshop.html.   The research funds were able to partially support the research of three postdoctoral researchers and several PhD students who have finished (or are close to finishing) their training. Several of them have become faculty members in mathematics, psychology, and educational psychology departments across the country.       Last Modified: 03/05/2021       Submitted by: Jingchen Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
