<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Engineered Thermal Transition Zones for Enhanced Geotechnical Foundation Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>261169.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>261169</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Fragaszy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Working with an industry partner, this research will develop a new design configuration and installation methodology for heat exchange thermal piles which deviates from the current approach of internally modifying conventional structural piles.  This will be achieved by replacing the conventional system with a transition zone that is manufactured in-place between a conventional structural pile and the surrounding soil to significantly increase thermal performance of the pile system.  Proof-of-concept modeling has shown the potential for dramatic increases in the thermal performance of an energy pile that can make them a more feasible renewable and sustainable energy alternative for heating and cooling buildings, including single and multi-family residential buildings.  The study will use the new insight from the proof-of-concept modeling as the motivation for laboratory and field scale physical and numerical testing.  The broader impacts of being able to dramatically alter the performance and efficiency of thermal pile systems has significant implications on global heating and cooling needs in both developed and developing countries, and can contribute to reducing greenhouse gas emissions.  This research is very much aligned with the concept and philosophy of sustainable infrastructure, and encourages a systematic approach to evaluating alternative approaches across the key dimensions most likely to influence system performance including environmental, societal and economic impact, as well as technical factors. Projects based on this research will be developed for the Georgia Tech class "Sustainable Subsurface Infrastructure."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In order to better understand the various factors influencing thermal performance of energy piles and to optimize heat transfer characteristics, a series of tasks will build on the insights derived during the proof-of-concept studies.  The focus of this investigation is to not only to study the problem in a controlled lab environment, but also to develop practical methodologies for utilization of the results in designing and installing thermally optimized energy piles.  To achieve this, the project will first design, fabricate and utilize a laboratory scale apparatus to test model engineered transition zone piles with different soil conditions and different boundary conditions.  The tests will be used to validate additional numerical simulations that extend the findings of the original proof-of-concept numerical model studies to design prototype full scale field systems.  Working with an industry partner, a full-scale field system will be installed and monitored during a series of trials to assess both the initial response as well as the longer term performance of the system as heating and cooling cycles are applied to the system.  The installation method to be used in the field involves the strategic repurposing of existing equipment to allow a staged installation procedure of the new thermal pile configuration.  This has important implications for the adoption of the method in practice.  Upon completion of the full scale field testing, a design methodology that can be used for future installations in a variety of subsurface conditions with engineered thermal transition zones of different dimensions will be developed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1634493</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>J. David</FirstName>
<LastName>Frost</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>J. David Frost</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david.frost@ce.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048942280</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000292520</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1636</Code>
<Text>Geotechnical Engineering and M</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>037E</Code>
<Text>GEOTECHNICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>038E</Code>
<Text>FOUNDATION ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~261169</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span><span style="font-size: small;">Energy pile foundations have emerged as a desirable alternative variation of the traditional pile foundation system where a conventional structural pile is fitted with fluid-circulating tubes. The constant temperature characteristics of the ground, which typically remains at an approximately constant temperature below the upper few (~5 to 10) meters, are utilized by the pile foundation to exchange heat energy with the ground. Energy pile foundations can thus be used to extract heat from the ground for heating in the winter and re-injecting heat into the ground for cooling during the summer, in addition to providing structural foundation support. The depths at which the energy transfer takes place when using energy piles are substantially less than those required for traditional deep geothermal systems, which can reduce the installation costs significantly.</span></span></p> <p>In this study, results are presented from both a numerical model and a laboratory scale physical model to demonstrate the potential for improvement in thermal performance of shallow thermo-active foundations resulting from a novel concept termed the Engineered Transition Zone (ETZ). An ETZ provides a means to introduce a thermally optimized zone between the foundation and the surrounding geomaterials to reduce thermal resistance. It also allows decoupling of the structural portion of the foundation from the thermal portion, such that the length of each component can be selected individually to meet the specific structural and thermal needs. Additionally, it allows for various novel circulation pipe configurations to be used (for example, helical loops) to further enhance heat transfer due to increased pipe surface area available for heat transfer.<strong>&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="font-size: small;"><span>This study presents some of the public policy challenges related to the adoption of shallow thermo-active foundations. </span><span>A case study was performed looking at the application of the punctuated equilibrium theory and policy diffusion to gain insight into ground source heat pump (GSHP) related policies in the U.S. between 2000 and 2015, as well as GSHP adoption rates between 2002 and 2009. </span><span>Using t</span><span lang="NL">he Bass Diffusion Model (BDM) and longitudinal data analysis, it is shown that that </span><span>policies enacted at the federal level can act as a trigger and a signal for GSHP related policies to be enacted at the state level. </span><span>Policy diffusion can in turn create awareness through signaling and information, leading to more widespread market adoption. In this case, the increase in GSHP adoption rates is observed to be more gradual, most likely because of higher initial costs relative to more conventional HVAC systems, as well as other market failures such as information asymmetry and split incentives between owners and building tenants. The longitudinal data analysis appears to confirm that the accumulation of GSHP related policies has an impact on GSHP adoption. Additionally, it highlights some of the other factors that may have contributed to higher adoption of GSHPs, such as increasing energy prices. These findings suggest that <span>policy alternatives can be devised at the state and local levels to complement federal incentives, to help overcome market failures, and to encourage more widespread adoption of emerging energy efficient technologies such as shallow thermo-active foundations. </span>Significantly improving the thermal performance of shallow thermo-active foundations through the use of an ETZ can also act to accelerate the rate of adoption of shallow thermo-active foundations by enabling the use of these systems in subsurface conditions that would otherwise preclude their use, and also by potentially reducing the payback period associated with these installations through the use of fewer but much higher performing elements.</span></span></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em></em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/04/2019<br>      Modified by: J. David&nbsp;Frost</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Energy pile foundations have emerged as a desirable alternative variation of the traditional pile foundation system where a conventional structural pile is fitted with fluid-circulating tubes. The constant temperature characteristics of the ground, which typically remains at an approximately constant temperature below the upper few (~5 to 10) meters, are utilized by the pile foundation to exchange heat energy with the ground. Energy pile foundations can thus be used to extract heat from the ground for heating in the winter and re-injecting heat into the ground for cooling during the summer, in addition to providing structural foundation support. The depths at which the energy transfer takes place when using energy piles are substantially less than those required for traditional deep geothermal systems, which can reduce the installation costs significantly.  In this study, results are presented from both a numerical model and a laboratory scale physical model to demonstrate the potential for improvement in thermal performance of shallow thermo-active foundations resulting from a novel concept termed the Engineered Transition Zone (ETZ). An ETZ provides a means to introduce a thermally optimized zone between the foundation and the surrounding geomaterials to reduce thermal resistance. It also allows decoupling of the structural portion of the foundation from the thermal portion, such that the length of each component can be selected individually to meet the specific structural and thermal needs. Additionally, it allows for various novel circulation pipe configurations to be used (for example, helical loops) to further enhance heat transfer due to increased pipe surface area available for heat transfer.    This study presents some of the public policy challenges related to the adoption of shallow thermo-active foundations. A case study was performed looking at the application of the punctuated equilibrium theory and policy diffusion to gain insight into ground source heat pump (GSHP) related policies in the U.S. between 2000 and 2015, as well as GSHP adoption rates between 2002 and 2009. Using the Bass Diffusion Model (BDM) and longitudinal data analysis, it is shown that that policies enacted at the federal level can act as a trigger and a signal for GSHP related policies to be enacted at the state level. Policy diffusion can in turn create awareness through signaling and information, leading to more widespread market adoption. In this case, the increase in GSHP adoption rates is observed to be more gradual, most likely because of higher initial costs relative to more conventional HVAC systems, as well as other market failures such as information asymmetry and split incentives between owners and building tenants. The longitudinal data analysis appears to confirm that the accumulation of GSHP related policies has an impact on GSHP adoption. Additionally, it highlights some of the other factors that may have contributed to higher adoption of GSHPs, such as increasing energy prices. These findings suggest that policy alternatives can be devised at the state and local levels to complement federal incentives, to help overcome market failures, and to encourage more widespread adoption of emerging energy efficient technologies such as shallow thermo-active foundations. Significantly improving the thermal performance of shallow thermo-active foundations through the use of an ETZ can also act to accelerate the rate of adoption of shallow thermo-active foundations by enabling the use of these systems in subsurface conditions that would otherwise preclude their use, and also by potentially reducing the payback period associated with these installations through the use of fewer but much higher performing elements.             Last Modified: 04/04/2019       Submitted by: J. David Frost]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
