<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>High Dimensional Statistical Inference in Flexible Response Surface Models for Product Formulation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>270568.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>270568</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Georgia-Ann Klutke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gaklutke@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922443</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over the last few decades, multicomponent drugs have proved beneficial in the treatment of the most severe of diseases, e.g., anti-Cancer agents or antiviral agents. More generally, a multicomponent product formulation problem requires the determination of not only the component proportions and their amounts (or doses) but also the manufacturing process conditions that accompany the production of such formulation. With the introduction of new regulations by the Food and Drug Administration, pharmaceutical companies gained additional flexibility to make changes in their formulations and process operations. A key guideline in these regulations is that companies must specify a design space for their product/process for approval, i.e., a region of formulation and process operating conditions that guarantees quality. How to determine such design space poses several statistical inference challenges and is the goal of this research. This research also has important broader impacts in Biology. Experiments in animals vary the components and amounts of diets and measure surrogates of "fitness" and lifetime. These experiments have a similar structure as some of the experiments in drug development and they too require flexible models. Collaboration with researchers from the pharmaceutical sector and biologists in academia will consider these broader impacts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overall goal of this research is to contribute new statistical methodology for computing frequentist and bayesian regions for the location of optima of flexible, supervised learning models that will aid in defining a design for product formulation.  The research will study methods for finding confidence regions for optima of nonparametric models which are functions in a high-dimensional space without recourse to any distributional assumption. A very general Reproducible Kernel Hilbert Space construction will be adopted, which will find design spaces based on many different models used in practice. This research will also extend the theory of bootstrapping functions of parameters to the vector function case. The research includes an investigation of the data depth notion used to generate valid, unbiased, and small high dimensional confidence regions for the parameters, which in turn will be used to find the desired design region.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1634878</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Enrique</FirstName>
<LastName>Del Castillo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Enrique Del Castillo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>exd13@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148636408</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485085</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>006Y</Code>
<Text>OE Operations Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>071E</Code>
<Text>MFG ENTERPRISE OPERATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>072E</Code>
<Text>NETWORKS &amp; QUEUING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>073E</Code>
<Text>OPTIMIZATION &amp; DECISION MAKING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>077E</Code>
<Text>SIMULATION MODELS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>078E</Code>
<Text>ENTERPRISE DESIGN &amp; LOGISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~270568</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Engineers and scientists often conduct experiments to determine the best design of a process, the best formulation of a drug, or more generally, to model a response of interest as a function of variables that were manipulated during the experiment. Optimization experiments of this kind have been studied for a long time in Statistics under the name Response Surface Methods. Usually, the type of models fitted from experimental data are simple regression models that cannot take too many different shapes and that assume a particular type of errors, namely, Gaussian (Normal) errors.</p> <p>Today, with modern statistical analysis software, it is customary to visualize and smooth experimental data with a variety of other response models that are more flexible than regression models, in the sense that the types of shapes possible are more varied, and the assumptions behind the errors of the model are not necessarily Normal.</p> <p>A region estimate, or confidence region, provide a measure of how precisely one estimates the location of the optimum, and have applications in both engineering and science. &nbsp;For instance, a confidence region on optimum effectiveness of a drug as a function of its ingredients is often found from experiments where different chemical mixtures are tried. The region then provides alternative formulations that would not result in statistically different response values.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual merit</span></p> <p>The main intellectual merit of this research consisted in developing new algorithms for confidence region computation, in assessing their validity, and in implementing them in computer software of easy distribution, namely, as an R package. The methods utilized modern nonparametric statistical methods such as the bootstrapping (for functions) and the use of data depth computations to deal with the high dimensional parametric space of the models used.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader impacts</span></p> <p>&nbsp;A main application of methods for computing confidence regions on the location of response surface optima occurs in Biology. Experimental evolutionary Biologists conduct nutrition experiments in animals to estimate its fitness function. In collaboration with Prof. John Hunt, from Western Sydney University, Australia (formerly at U. Exeter in the UK) the methods in the present research were utilized to study the evolutionary fitness function in decorated crickets and in flour beetles, leading to two journal publications.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Main outcomes</span></p> <p>New methods (algorithms) were developed for computing and displaying confidence region estimates on the location of the global optimum of three different types of response surface models: Thin Plate Splines, Spatial Processes, and polynomial regression models of order 3. The methods do not rely on a Gaussian (normality) assumption, contrary to earlier methods which were also available only for less flexible response models. The performance (coverage) of the algorithms was demonstrated. &nbsp;Applications in nutrition experiments for Evolutionary Biology took place in collaboration with Prof. John Hunt, Western Sydney University, Australia.</p> <p>All algorithms developed in this project have been implemented as computer functions and incorporated in a package in the statistical software R. The package OptimaRegion, downloadable from the CRAN website, was written. Since first posted in 2017, it has been downloaded 15,339 times.</p> <p>Four journal papers have been submitted for journals as output of this research, with 3 either published or accepted, and one currently under review. &nbsp;Two of these journals pertain to the Statistical Community (Communications in Statistics and J. of Statistical Computation and Simulation) , and the other two (Evolution and the American Naturalist) pertain to Biology:</p> <ul> <li>Del      Castillo, E., Chen*, P., Meyer*, A., Hunt, J., and Rapkin, J., ``      Confidence regions for the location of Response Surface Optima: the R      package OptimaRegion", accepted in <em>Communications in Statistics,      Simulation and Computation</em>, (2020).</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Chen*,      P., and Del Castillo, ``On Inferences about the location of a Response      Surface Optima on a Latent Spatial Process", submitted to <em>J. of      Statistical Computation and Simulation</em>, (2020).</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Rapkin,      J., Archer, R., House, C.M., Skaluk, S.K., del Castillo, E., and Hunt, J.,      ``The geometry of nutritionally based life-history trade-offs: sex      differences in the effect of macronutrient intake on the trade-off between      immune function and reproductive effort in decorated crickets", <em>The      American Naturalist</em>, Vol. 191 (no. 4), pp. 452-474, (2018).</li> </ul> <ul> <li>House,      C., Tunstall, P, Rapkin, J., Janicot, M., Gage, M., del Castillo, E., and      Hunt, J., ``Multivariate stabilizing sexual selection and the evolution of      male and female genital morphology in the red&nbsp; flour      beetle",&nbsp; <em>Evolution</em>, 74(5), pp. 883-896, (2020).</li> </ul> <p>Mr. Peng Chen, a PhD. Student funded by this grant and advised by the PI, defended his dissertation on August 2020, which focused in the grant&rsquo;s research. He joined Axtria Inc. (NJ, USA), after graduation, where he is currently a Senior Associate.</p> <p>Secondary outcomes of this research are several conference talks at INFORMS and in various university department seminars over the course of this grant.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/22/2020<br>      Modified by: Enrique&nbsp;Del Castillo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1634878/1634878_10446059_1606023803154_FigureCrickets--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1634878/1634878_10446059_1606023803154_FigureCrickets--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Application in Biology"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1634878/1634878_10446059_1606023803154_FigureCrickets--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Application in Biology"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Confidence regions in decorated crickets</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. Hunt and E. del Castillo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Enrique&nbsp;Del Castillo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Application in Biology</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1634878/1634878_10446059_1606023069341_CR_5D_cubic--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1634878/1634878_10446059_1606023069341_CR_5D_cubic--rgov-800width.jpg" title="5-D Confidence region"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1634878/1634878_10446059_1606023069341_CR_5D_cubic--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="5-D Confidence region"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A 5-factor confidence region on the maximum of a cubic polynomial response surface, computed with the OptimaRegion R package.</div> <div class="imageCredit">E. del Castilloi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Enrique&nbsp;Del Castillo</div> <div class="imageTitle">5-D Confidence region</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1634878/1634878_10446059_1606022900426_Mixture_plot2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1634878/1634878_10446059_1606022900426_Mixture_plot2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2D Confidence region plot"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1634878/1634878_10446059_1606022900426_Mixture_plot2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2D Confidence region plot"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A confidence region on the maximum response of a 2-component mixture pharmaceutical experiment</div> <div class="imageCredit">E. del Castillo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Enrique&nbsp;Del Castillo</div> <div class="imageTitle">2D Confidence region plot</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Engineers and scientists often conduct experiments to determine the best design of a process, the best formulation of a drug, or more generally, to model a response of interest as a function of variables that were manipulated during the experiment. Optimization experiments of this kind have been studied for a long time in Statistics under the name Response Surface Methods. Usually, the type of models fitted from experimental data are simple regression models that cannot take too many different shapes and that assume a particular type of errors, namely, Gaussian (Normal) errors.  Today, with modern statistical analysis software, it is customary to visualize and smooth experimental data with a variety of other response models that are more flexible than regression models, in the sense that the types of shapes possible are more varied, and the assumptions behind the errors of the model are not necessarily Normal.  A region estimate, or confidence region, provide a measure of how precisely one estimates the location of the optimum, and have applications in both engineering and science.  For instance, a confidence region on optimum effectiveness of a drug as a function of its ingredients is often found from experiments where different chemical mixtures are tried. The region then provides alternative formulations that would not result in statistically different response values.  Intellectual merit  The main intellectual merit of this research consisted in developing new algorithms for confidence region computation, in assessing their validity, and in implementing them in computer software of easy distribution, namely, as an R package. The methods utilized modern nonparametric statistical methods such as the bootstrapping (for functions) and the use of data depth computations to deal with the high dimensional parametric space of the models used.  Broader impacts   A main application of methods for computing confidence regions on the location of response surface optima occurs in Biology. Experimental evolutionary Biologists conduct nutrition experiments in animals to estimate its fitness function. In collaboration with Prof. John Hunt, from Western Sydney University, Australia (formerly at U. Exeter in the UK) the methods in the present research were utilized to study the evolutionary fitness function in decorated crickets and in flour beetles, leading to two journal publications.  Main outcomes  New methods (algorithms) were developed for computing and displaying confidence region estimates on the location of the global optimum of three different types of response surface models: Thin Plate Splines, Spatial Processes, and polynomial regression models of order 3. The methods do not rely on a Gaussian (normality) assumption, contrary to earlier methods which were also available only for less flexible response models. The performance (coverage) of the algorithms was demonstrated.  Applications in nutrition experiments for Evolutionary Biology took place in collaboration with Prof. John Hunt, Western Sydney University, Australia.  All algorithms developed in this project have been implemented as computer functions and incorporated in a package in the statistical software R. The package OptimaRegion, downloadable from the CRAN website, was written. Since first posted in 2017, it has been downloaded 15,339 times.  Four journal papers have been submitted for journals as output of this research, with 3 either published or accepted, and one currently under review.  Two of these journals pertain to the Statistical Community (Communications in Statistics and J. of Statistical Computation and Simulation) , and the other two (Evolution and the American Naturalist) pertain to Biology:  Del      Castillo, E., Chen*, P., Meyer*, A., Hunt, J., and Rapkin, J., ``      Confidence regions for the location of Response Surface Optima: the R      package OptimaRegion", accepted in Communications in Statistics,      Simulation and Computation, (2020).   Chen*,      P., and Del Castillo, ``On Inferences about the location of a Response      Surface Optima on a Latent Spatial Process", submitted to J. of      Statistical Computation and Simulation, (2020).   Rapkin,      J., Archer, R., House, C.M., Skaluk, S.K., del Castillo, E., and Hunt, J.,      ``The geometry of nutritionally based life-history trade-offs: sex      differences in the effect of macronutrient intake on the trade-off between      immune function and reproductive effort in decorated crickets", The      American Naturalist, Vol. 191 (no. 4), pp. 452-474, (2018).   House,      C., Tunstall, P, Rapkin, J., Janicot, M., Gage, M., del Castillo, E., and      Hunt, J., ``Multivariate stabilizing sexual selection and the evolution of      male and female genital morphology in the red  flour      beetle",  Evolution, 74(5), pp. 883-896, (2020).   Mr. Peng Chen, a PhD. Student funded by this grant and advised by the PI, defended his dissertation on August 2020, which focused in the grant’s research. He joined Axtria Inc. (NJ, USA), after graduation, where he is currently a Senior Associate.  Secondary outcomes of this research are several conference talks at INFORMS and in various university department seminars over the course of this grant.          Last Modified: 11/22/2020       Submitted by: Enrique Del Castillo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
