<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GOALI/Collaborative Research: Autonomous Thermomechanical Fabrication of 3D Structures using Heat-Responsive Polymers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>174987.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>174987</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>khcooper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927017</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Autonomously fabricating macro-scale polymeric objects by subjecting a preform to a non-contact stimulus such as heat holds significant technological implications. For instance, it offers the ability to transform a preform (fabricated in simple, compact geometries) into target shapes on demand. It also offers the ability to simultaneously transform a large number of parts into target shapes by triggering them en masse using a globally applied stimulus. Hence, mass manufacturability emerges without an additional overhead.  This Grant Opportunity for Academic Liaison with Industry (GOALI) award supports fundamental research on the self-assembly of 3D structures based on designs embedded at the molecular level in heat-responsive polymers.  Research results can help spawn new technologies in applications such as biomedicine, where implants can be deployed into desired shapes and reshaped as-needed using an external stimulus.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first research objective is to establish the relationship between the spatiotemporal evolution of strain fields (leading to the creation of 3D helical structures) and controllable parameters (nematic director orientation and temperature). To achieve this objective, crosslinked, acrylate-based liquid crystalline polymers in twisted nematic configurations will be synthesized. Freely suspended polymer samples will be subjected to heat treatment with varying nematic director orientation (ranging from 0 to 45° with respect to the mid-plane of samples) and temperature (ranging from the glass transition temperature to close to the thermal decomposition temperature). The evolution of strain fields in these samples will be measured in situ using image analysis based characterization. The second research objective is to establish the effect of the displacement (preimposed on the sample) on the spatiotemporal evolution of torsional, bending strain fields (underpinning the creation of 3D prismatic and hierarchically supercoiled shapes). Various displacements (up to 20 percent of the length of the samples) will be imposed to samples. Spatiotemporal evolution of torsional, bending strain fields will be measured using imaging analysis based characterization.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1635966</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>M. Ravi</FirstName>
<LastName>Shankar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>M. Ravi Shankar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shankarr@engr.pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126249835</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000289078</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Makowski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>PhD</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael P Makowski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>makowski@ppg.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4124925219</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000718029</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1468</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1468</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING &amp; CONST MACH EQP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~174987</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcomes Report: National Science Foundation ENG/CMMMI ? Award #1635966</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>GOALI/Collaborative Research: Autonomous Thermomechanical Fabrication of 3D Structures using Heat-Responsive Polymers</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Performance Period: 09/01/2016 ? 08/31/2020</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Performing Organizations: University of Pittsburgh in collaboration with Carnegie Mellon University. GOALI partner: PPG Industries.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>PI: M. Ravi Shankar</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project studied actuation and self-assembly in polymeric structures that spontaneously build themselves into a target geometry and perform mechanical actuation. The material system undergoing this transformation is composed of rod-shaped molecules, whose orientation and alignment are tailored through its volume (Liquid Crystal Polymers: LCP). LCP samples that are characterized by a chiral (twisted) arrangement of the molecular arrangement through their thickness were subjected to confinement and stimulated using heat. Temperature disrupts the alignment of the molecules and this disordering from a hitherto crosslinked state leads to mechanical strain generation. Chiral molecular alignment, if triggered without constraints, results in a spiral geometry. However, the samples we consider are not free to adopt this shape. The competition between the geometry the sample seeks to adopt versus the confinement it is forced to endure results in an array of self-assembled geometries. The shape selection is hierarchical as a function of the thermal stimulus. Such self-assembly also enables new methods for creating active structures. Figure 1 illustrates the implications in a) spontaneous motility in response to an unmodulated thermal stimulus and b) self-directed kinematic manipulation, where a crank-rocker mechanism assembles and actuates.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This grant also supported the study of multi-stable structures fabricated from light responsive polymers. Geometries that were hierarchically buckled due to lateral constraints and intermediate rigid boundary conditions (line and point contacts) were considered. It was shown that light can be used to toggle between a multitude of mechanically stable states by modifying where the sample is irradiated. This enabled prototypical demonstration of light driven actuators that respond at millisecond timescales. This demonstration holds applications as oscillators and energy harvesting devices. To understand the latency of the actuation (i.e., how long it takes to trigger), the kinetics of the underlying molecular transformation were measured. Using in situ imaging and spectroscopy, the rate at which the molecular distortions occur was characterized. The effect of composition and processing on the reaction kinetics and resulting photoactuation provides a framework for discovering new materials that present robust responses.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Additionally, this effort supported research into distortions induced in metals-based manufacturing processes. Concepts on the interplay of internal stresses and boundary conditions to control structural implications have broad implications. This ancillary effort explored whether these concepts can be utilized to modulate and predict distortions resulting from laser-based powder metal sintering.</p> <p>Detailed captions for Attached Figures:</p> <p><strong>Figure 1: a) A confined LCP self-assembles a distinctive head and tail configuration and spontaneously traverses on a hotplate. The interaction between the self-assembled shapes and the surface constraint leads to progressive build-up of strain energy. Energy release in bursts drives the motility even with an unmodulated, static heat source. b) Self-assembly is used to create a prototypical crank-rocker mechanism that evolves as a function of temperature and then actuates in response to a thermal stimulus.</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/27/2020<br>      Modified by: M. Ravi&nbsp;Shankar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635966/1635966_10456464_1609079596005_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635966/1635966_10456464_1609079596005_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635966/1635966_10456464_1609079596005_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1: a) A confined LCP self-assembles a distinctive head and tail configuration and spontaneously traverses on a hotplate. b) Self-assembly is used to create a prototypical crank-rocker mechanism.</div> <div class="imageCredit">M. Ravi Shankar</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">M. Ravi&nbsp;Shankar</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report: National Science Foundation ENG/CMMMI ? Award #1635966     GOALI/Collaborative Research: Autonomous Thermomechanical Fabrication of 3D Structures using Heat-Responsive Polymers     Performance Period: 09/01/2016 ? 08/31/2020     Performing Organizations: University of Pittsburgh in collaboration with Carnegie Mellon University. GOALI partner: PPG Industries.     PI: M. Ravi Shankar     This project studied actuation and self-assembly in polymeric structures that spontaneously build themselves into a target geometry and perform mechanical actuation. The material system undergoing this transformation is composed of rod-shaped molecules, whose orientation and alignment are tailored through its volume (Liquid Crystal Polymers: LCP). LCP samples that are characterized by a chiral (twisted) arrangement of the molecular arrangement through their thickness were subjected to confinement and stimulated using heat. Temperature disrupts the alignment of the molecules and this disordering from a hitherto crosslinked state leads to mechanical strain generation. Chiral molecular alignment, if triggered without constraints, results in a spiral geometry. However, the samples we consider are not free to adopt this shape. The competition between the geometry the sample seeks to adopt versus the confinement it is forced to endure results in an array of self-assembled geometries. The shape selection is hierarchical as a function of the thermal stimulus. Such self-assembly also enables new methods for creating active structures. Figure 1 illustrates the implications in a) spontaneous motility in response to an unmodulated thermal stimulus and b) self-directed kinematic manipulation, where a crank-rocker mechanism assembles and actuates.     This grant also supported the study of multi-stable structures fabricated from light responsive polymers. Geometries that were hierarchically buckled due to lateral constraints and intermediate rigid boundary conditions (line and point contacts) were considered. It was shown that light can be used to toggle between a multitude of mechanically stable states by modifying where the sample is irradiated. This enabled prototypical demonstration of light driven actuators that respond at millisecond timescales. This demonstration holds applications as oscillators and energy harvesting devices. To understand the latency of the actuation (i.e., how long it takes to trigger), the kinetics of the underlying molecular transformation were measured. Using in situ imaging and spectroscopy, the rate at which the molecular distortions occur was characterized. The effect of composition and processing on the reaction kinetics and resulting photoactuation provides a framework for discovering new materials that present robust responses.     Additionally, this effort supported research into distortions induced in metals-based manufacturing processes. Concepts on the interplay of internal stresses and boundary conditions to control structural implications have broad implications. This ancillary effort explored whether these concepts can be utilized to modulate and predict distortions resulting from laser-based powder metal sintering.  Detailed captions for Attached Figures:  Figure 1: a) A confined LCP self-assembles a distinctive head and tail configuration and spontaneously traverses on a hotplate. The interaction between the self-assembled shapes and the surface constraint leads to progressive build-up of strain energy. Energy release in bursts drives the motility even with an unmodulated, static heat source. b) Self-assembly is used to create a prototypical crank-rocker mechanism that evolves as a function of temperature and then actuates in response to a thermal stimulus.          Last Modified: 12/27/2020       Submitted by: M. Ravi Shankar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
