<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Using Mixed Discrete-Continuum Representations to Characterize the Dynamics of Large Many-Body Dynamics Problems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399960.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399960</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Irina Dolinskaya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>idolinsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927078</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to understand how computer simulation can be used to predict the motion of large systems of bodies interacting with each other through friction and contact. Studying these so-called "many-body dynamics problems" has theoretical and practical relevance in several disciplines (physics, chemistry, astronomy, geomechanics), industries (pharmaceuticals, food processing, farming, manufacturing, construction, mining), and engineering applications (additive manufacturing, nanoparticle self-assembly, robotics, ground vehicle mobility). In terms of educational and outreach impact, initiatives undertaken as part of this project will (i) promote the discipline of Computational Science at middle and high-school levels via a "The Science Behind Video Gaming" short course and a residential summer program, respectively; (ii) update and expand curricula in two graduate courses on high performance computing and advanced computational dynamics; (iii) expand a biannual advanced computing forum that facilitates transfer of technology; and, (iv) provide training via a Master of Engineering distance learning program for practitioners who need to analyze, process, and solve problems using information generated by the growing use of data collection in engineering design and industrial operations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research effort will focus on investigating techniques that facilitate a discrete-continuum dual representation in the simulation of many-body dynamics problems. The fundamental question answered is how should one handle parts of a many-body dynamics problem using a continuum formalism so that the new mixed discrete-continuum representation manages to preserve the dynamics of the original problem? Also, how should a continuum representation be fine-grained into a discrete one, and conversely, what techniques should be used to coarse-grain a discrete representation into a continuous one? Mechanical engineering expertise (dynamics of many-body systems, solid mechanics, plasticity), applied math techniques (meshless methods for solving partial differential equations, optimization methods), and computer science components (machine learning, software engineering) will combine in a coordinated effort to solve the stated problem. In this context, the goal of this project is to (a) establish a systematic methodology for producing rheologies that, when embedded in a continuum mechanics model, produce a solution that is close to that of a large discrete many-body dynamics problem; and (b) use this methodology to understand whether there are rheologies that have a universal attribute; i.e., that are applicable to all, or a large spectrum of, many-body dynamics problems. In this context, a rheology is regarded as a methodology that ties at microscale the dynamics/flow of a continuum to the forces acting on it. The research plan is built around the idea of augmenting physical insights with a machine learning process that uses large amounts of data generated by fully-resolved, many-body dynamics solutions to produce rheology candidates.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1635004</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Radu</FirstName>
<LastName>Serban</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Radu Serban</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>serban@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000684489</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dan</FirstName>
<LastName>Negrut</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dan Negrut</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>negrut@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6088900914</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000390470</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>Dynamics, Control and System D</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>031E</Code>
<Text>MECHATRONICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>032E</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND ACTUATORS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>033E</Code>
<Text>Smart and responsive structures</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>035E</Code>
<Text>NOISE, ACOUSTICS, VIBRATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>040E</Code>
<Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>099E</Code>
<Text>High voltage switching &amp; conversion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1059</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSOR SYSTEMS FOR CIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7234</Code>
<Text>SENSORS NON-SOLICITATION RESEA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8024</Code>
<Text>Complex Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~399960</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The hypothesis investigated under NSF project CMMI-1635004 is that one can use a continuum representation to capture the dynamics of discrete, many-body systems made up of elements such as encountered in granular material.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: Over four years, the individuals engaged in the project have pursued two research thrusts: under the first one, we fully resolved the dynamics of many-body systems (tens to hundreds of millions of elements), and individually looked at the motion of each body in the system. Under the second one, we homogenized the motion of the many-body system and thus treated the system as a continuum endowed with appropriate constitutive laws. The research effort was successful in proving our hypothesis correct. In doing so, we established an approach that relies on conservation of mass and momentum laws associated with continua to capture the dynamics of discrete, many-body dynamic systems. This work has led to seven journal submissions (five accepted, two under review), an ASME IDETC/ICE Best Paper Award in the Multibody Systems and Nonlinear Dynamics and Controls technical conference (Cleveland, 2017), and one NSF Graduate Research Fellowships Program (GRFP) Award (2019).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impact: This project provided the funding to train and mentor a group of 60 high-school students through the ?Promoting the Computational Science Initiative? (ProCSI) program, which seeks to broaden participation in computing. ProCSI was started by PI Negrut and lab students in 2008 and concluded its 10<sup>th</sup>, 11<sup>th</sup>, and 12<sup>th</sup> editions under funding from NSF project CMMI-1635004. In this program, high-school students from underrepresented socioeconomic groups, who most often come from low-income families, spend an inspiring week on-campus at UW-Madison having room and board covered. The high school students spend this week participating in Computational Science related activities, including: introduction to computational dynamics through development of a basic video game, aspects of Computer Aided Design, and concepts of Computer Graphics. A thorough description of ProCSI's statement of purpose, activities, schedule, and more than 500 pictures are available at the online event website (<a href="https://sbel.wisc.edu/procsi/">https://sbel.wisc.edu/procsi/</a>).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The outcomes of this research project are used the PIs in an ongoing NASA project to simulate the mobility of the VIPER rover on lunar soil for its 2024 mission to the moon; its goal is to probe for frozen water. The numerical methods established/software developed under this work is also used by the European Space Agency, for a Phobos 2027 mission. On this moon of Mars, the gravitational pull is 1700 smaller than on Earth. Colleagues from France are using our methods to investigate whether a rover can move on soil under very low gravitational acceleration, when it is questionable whether the compaction of the granular terrain is sufficient to sustain rover mobility.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Under the auspices of this project, the PIs organized the 7<sup>th</sup>, 8<sup>th</sup>, and 9<sup>th</sup> editions of the Machine-Ground Interaction Consortium (MaGIC) annual meeting. These meetings have been exceedingly successful, with the 9<sup>th</sup> edition (virtual, organized between September 29-October 1, 2020) attended by more than 50 organizations, e.g., 360 Med Care, Aarhus University, Advanced Science and Automation Corp., Akamai Technologies, Amazon, Arizona State University, Advanced Solutions Incorporated, ATA Engineering, BAE Systems, Blue River Tech., Caterpillar Inc., Clemson University, CM Labs, Simulations Inc., DSIM TECH, Dynamic Dimension Technologies, FunctionBay ? S. Korea, Georgia Tech University, Harley Davidson Motor Company, Herman Design Works, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, Illinois Institute of, Technology, Indiana University Purdue University Indianapolis, ISAE Supaero, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, John Deere, Johns Hopkins University, KPIT Technologies, Lappeenranta Technical University, MathWorks, McGill University, Michigan Technological, University, Mississippi State University, MIT, Mitsubishi Electric Research Labs, Motesque Inc., MSC Software, Corp., National Science Foundation, Nevada Automotive Test Center, Northwestern University, Ohio State University, OPPO US, Research Institute, Oshkosh Corporation, RAMDO Solutions, Sanikommu, Simertis GmbH, Software Cradle Co., Ltd., South Africa Council of Scientific and Industrial Research, Tesla, Texas A&amp;M University, University of Iowa, University of Parma, University of Wisconsin-Madison, US Army CCDC GVSC, US Army Engineering Research and Development Center.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, most of the findings associated with this research project have been implemented in software in an open source, publicly available software for computational dynamics called Project Chrono (<a href="http://projectchrono.org/">http://projectchrono.org</a>). The software, which stands at approximately 0.5 million lines of code, is available for free use/distribution/commercialization in a public repository on GitHub (<a href="https://github.com/projectchrono/chrono">https://github.com/projectchrono/chrono</a>).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Pictures included:</p> <p>- two pictures from the ?Promoting the Computational Science Initiative? (ProCSI) program (years 2018 and 2019).</p> <p>- picture of an eight-wheeled rover moving over the material that despite its appearance is worked with as a continuum material owing. This is directly related to the core of this project.</p> <p>- two pictures showing granular material impacting a cylinder: once the material is considered fully resolved (a collection of millions of rigid bodies), and once it is represented as a continuum.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/19/2020<br>      Modified by: Dan&nbsp;Negrut</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422381740_procsi2019--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422381740_procsi2019--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ProCSI 2019"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422381740_procsi2019--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ProCSI 2019"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">ProCSI high-school students along with Simulation-Based Engineering Lab students in 2019</div> <div class="imageCredit">Simulation-Based Engineering Lab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dan&nbsp;Negrut</div> <div class="imageTitle">ProCSI 2019</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422311516_procsi2018--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422311516_procsi2018--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ProCSI 2018"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422311516_procsi2018--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ProCSI 2018"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Members of the Simulation-Based Engineering Lab and high-school students participating in ProCSI-2018</div> <div class="imageCredit">Simulation-Based Engineering Lab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dan&nbsp;Negrut</div> <div class="imageTitle">ProCSI 2018</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422550287_roverEightWheelsFSI--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422550287_roverEightWheelsFSI--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Eight-wheeler"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422550287_roverEightWheelsFSI--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Eight-wheeler"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Eight wheel rover operating on terrain that is granular but treated as a continuum for more efficient simulation</div> <div class="imageCredit">Simulation-Based Engineering Lab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dan&nbsp;Negrut</div> <div class="imageTitle">Eight-wheeler</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422665246_lgran20--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422665246_lgran20--rgov-800width.jpg" title="granular dynamics, discrete rep"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422665246_lgran20--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="granular dynamics, discrete rep"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Granular material in a box, colliding with a fixed cylinder. The motion of each element is accounted for, which allows for a fully resolved analysis that looks at the friction and contact of each grain.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Simulation-Based Engineering Lab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dan&nbsp;Negrut</div> <div class="imageTitle">granular dynamics, discrete rep</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422759175_lfluid20--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422759175_lfluid20--rgov-800width.jpg" title="granular dynamics, continuum representation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1635004/1635004_10441337_1608422759175_lfluid20--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="granular dynamics, continuum representation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Granular material in a box, colliding with a fixed cylinder. The motion of granular material is captured via a homogenization approach that captures the overall motion of the system of many-bodies</div> <div class="imageCredit">Simulation-Based Engineering Lab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dan&nbsp;Negrut</div> <div class="imageTitle">granular dynamics, continuum representation</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The hypothesis investigated under NSF project CMMI-1635004 is that one can use a continuum representation to capture the dynamics of discrete, many-body systems made up of elements such as encountered in granular material.     Intellectual Merit: Over four years, the individuals engaged in the project have pursued two research thrusts: under the first one, we fully resolved the dynamics of many-body systems (tens to hundreds of millions of elements), and individually looked at the motion of each body in the system. Under the second one, we homogenized the motion of the many-body system and thus treated the system as a continuum endowed with appropriate constitutive laws. The research effort was successful in proving our hypothesis correct. In doing so, we established an approach that relies on conservation of mass and momentum laws associated with continua to capture the dynamics of discrete, many-body dynamic systems. This work has led to seven journal submissions (five accepted, two under review), an ASME IDETC/ICE Best Paper Award in the Multibody Systems and Nonlinear Dynamics and Controls technical conference (Cleveland, 2017), and one NSF Graduate Research Fellowships Program (GRFP) Award (2019).     Broader Impact: This project provided the funding to train and mentor a group of 60 high-school students through the ?Promoting the Computational Science Initiative? (ProCSI) program, which seeks to broaden participation in computing. ProCSI was started by PI Negrut and lab students in 2008 and concluded its 10th, 11th, and 12th editions under funding from NSF project CMMI-1635004. In this program, high-school students from underrepresented socioeconomic groups, who most often come from low-income families, spend an inspiring week on-campus at UW-Madison having room and board covered. The high school students spend this week participating in Computational Science related activities, including: introduction to computational dynamics through development of a basic video game, aspects of Computer Aided Design, and concepts of Computer Graphics. A thorough description of ProCSI's statement of purpose, activities, schedule, and more than 500 pictures are available at the online event website (https://sbel.wisc.edu/procsi/).     The outcomes of this research project are used the PIs in an ongoing NASA project to simulate the mobility of the VIPER rover on lunar soil for its 2024 mission to the moon; its goal is to probe for frozen water. The numerical methods established/software developed under this work is also used by the European Space Agency, for a Phobos 2027 mission. On this moon of Mars, the gravitational pull is 1700 smaller than on Earth. Colleagues from France are using our methods to investigate whether a rover can move on soil under very low gravitational acceleration, when it is questionable whether the compaction of the granular terrain is sufficient to sustain rover mobility.     Under the auspices of this project, the PIs organized the 7th, 8th, and 9th editions of the Machine-Ground Interaction Consortium (MaGIC) annual meeting. These meetings have been exceedingly successful, with the 9th edition (virtual, organized between September 29-October 1, 2020) attended by more than 50 organizations, e.g., 360 Med Care, Aarhus University, Advanced Science and Automation Corp., Akamai Technologies, Amazon, Arizona State University, Advanced Solutions Incorporated, ATA Engineering, BAE Systems, Blue River Tech., Caterpillar Inc., Clemson University, CM Labs, Simulations Inc., DSIM TECH, Dynamic Dimension Technologies, FunctionBay ? S. Korea, Georgia Tech University, Harley Davidson Motor Company, Herman Design Works, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, Illinois Institute of, Technology, Indiana University Purdue University Indianapolis, ISAE Supaero, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, John Deere, Johns Hopkins University, KPIT Technologies, Lappeenranta Technical University, MathWorks, McGill University, Michigan Technological, University, Mississippi State University, MIT, Mitsubishi Electric Research Labs, Motesque Inc., MSC Software, Corp., National Science Foundation, Nevada Automotive Test Center, Northwestern University, Ohio State University, OPPO US, Research Institute, Oshkosh Corporation, RAMDO Solutions, Sanikommu, Simertis GmbH, Software Cradle Co., Ltd., South Africa Council of Scientific and Industrial Research, Tesla, Texas A&amp;M University, University of Iowa, University of Parma, University of Wisconsin-Madison, US Army CCDC GVSC, US Army Engineering Research and Development Center.     Finally, most of the findings associated with this research project have been implemented in software in an open source, publicly available software for computational dynamics called Project Chrono (http://projectchrono.org). The software, which stands at approximately 0.5 million lines of code, is available for free use/distribution/commercialization in a public repository on GitHub (https://github.com/projectchrono/chrono).     Pictures included:  - two pictures from the ?Promoting the Computational Science Initiative? (ProCSI) program (years 2018 and 2019).  - picture of an eight-wheeled rover moving over the material that despite its appearance is worked with as a continuum material owing. This is directly related to the core of this project.  - two pictures showing granular material impacting a cylinder: once the material is considered fully resolved (a collection of millions of rigid bodies), and once it is represented as a continuum.          Last Modified: 12/19/2020       Submitted by: Dan Negrut]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
