<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Characterizing evolution and subduction of the Juan de Fuca plate: A joint inversion of ambient noise and air-gun shot data</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>90459.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>90459</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Deborah K. Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dksmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927978</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Subduction zones where one of Earth?s tectonic plates is forced beneath another tectonic plate are one of the least understood regions on the planet and yet create major hazards for nearby coastlines and cities. The relatively small size of the Cascadia subduction system off the US west coast provides a unique opportunity to investigate the structure and evolution of the oceanic plate from its formation to subduction, as well as the nature of the sedimentary wedge or forearc that forms just offshore and the volcanic arc that forms on the over-riding plate. The proposed project aims to construct a 3D high-resolution velocity model from the surface through the crust into the mantle lithosphere, extending from trench to arc. Specifically, this project will focus on two scientific questions: (1) What is the structure of the oceanic plate prior to and after subduction - how does the plate structure evolve with time and how hydrated is the oceanic plate prior to subduction? (2) What are the relationships between the structure of the incoming plate and the along-strike variations in the forearc structure? A well-resolved Cascadia seismic velocity model will contribute to many geological and geophysical studies, allowing for better located earthquakes and source mechanisms. The project will support the career development of a female early-career geoscientist, who is in the process of establishing a new seismology group at UMASS-Amherst. The project will support training of undergraduate and graduate students. Research products will be integrated into ongoing public outreach and introductory classes in Earth Science. Wave propagation simulation and ground motion maps are great tools to educate the public in New England about seismic hazards. Results will be introduced to underserved 8th-12th grade girls through the Girls Inc. Eureka! Program, a strong STEM-based collaboration between Girls Inc. of Holyoke, Massachusetts and UMASS.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Seismic imaging provides strong constraints on the geometry and physical properties of the subducting slab and the upper plate. The project will implement a joint 3D full-wave simulation and inversion of ambient noise and air-gun shots to achieve a model with high resolution from crust to uppermost mantle. Data from the Cascadia Initiative ocean bottom seismometers and onshore broadband and short-period seismic stations will be utilized, including air-gun shots of the two active-source seismic experiments. Accuracy of phase travel time in wave propagation simulation is sensitive to shallow structure, such as the sedimentary layers and water column, which will be taken into account in this study. The joint inversion of different types of seismic data into 3D models will provide a higher resolution of the oceanic plate with reduced model uncertainties than is possible with individual datasets. This project will produce a clear and complete picture of the incoming plate and forearc, which is essential for our understanding of the subduction process. More broadly, this project has very significant contribution to the scientific goals and outreach of the Cascadia Initiative community-based experiment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1635903</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Haiying</FirstName>
<LastName>Gao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Haiying Gao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>haiyinggao@geo.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135771250</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000616953</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039297</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[611 North Pleasant St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~90459</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The formation, evolution, and destruction of a subducting plate remains one of the least understood aspects of global subduction zones. The relatively small size of the Cascadia subduction system from formation to subduction provides a unique opportunity to investigate the structure and evolution of the oceanic plate, as well as the forearc and volcanic arc. Seismic imaging provides strong constraints on the geometry and physical properties of the subducting slab and the upper plate. This project constructed a 3D high-resolution velocity model with the use of a joint 3D full-wave simulation and inversion of ambient noise and air-gun shots, from the surface through the crust into the mantle lithosphere, extending from trench to arc. Specifically, this project focused on addressing two scientific questions: (1) What is the structure of the oceanic plate prior to and after subduction? How does the plate structure evolve with time? To what extent is the oceanic plate hydrated prior to subduction? (2) What are the relationships between the structure of the incoming plate and the along-strike variations in the forearc structure (e.g., forearc basins, underthrusting of sediments, and serpentinization of the mantle wedge)?</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The (de)hydration process and the amount of hydrated sediment carried by the downgoing oceanic plate play a key role in the subduction dynamics. A high-resolution shear velocity model from the crust down to the uppermost mantle, extending from trench to forearc, was constructed in the northern Cascadia subduction zone to investigate seismic characteristics related to slab deformation and (de)hydration at the plate boundary. A total of 220 seismic stations were used, including the Cascadia Initiative Amphibious Array and inland broadband and short-period stations. The empirical Green&rsquo;s functions extracted from continuous ambient noise data from 2006-2014 provide high-quality Rayleigh-wave signals at periods of 4-50 s. We simulated wave propagation using finite-difference method to generate station Strain Green&rsquo;s Tensors and synthetic waveforms. The phase delays of Rayleigh waves between the observed and synthetic data were measured at multiple period ranges. We then inverted for the velocity perturbations from the reference model and progressively improve the model resolution. Our tomographic imaging showed many regional- and local-scale low-velocity features, which are possibly related to slab (de)hydration from the oceanic plate to the overriding plate.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We extracted high-frequency seismic waveforms recorded by both offshore and onshore instrumentation, and quantitatively evaluated the data quality in terms of source-to-receiver distance, source parameters, water depth, and sediment thickness. There were two active-source seismic experiments within the Juan de Fuca plate, MGL1211 and MGL1212, during the first year deployment of the Cascadia Initiative Amphibious Array. The common receiver gathering analysis showed that most offshore stations located in deep-water record clear first P-wave arrivals up to 150 km away from the air-gun shot. The first arrival transits from crustal phase Pg to head wave Pn at a source-to-receiver distance of 25-40 km. For stations located at shallow water, the seismic recordings appear much noisier compared to those of deep-water stations. Only 5 inland stations record clear air-gun shot signals up to 200 km away from the source. The signal-to-noise ratio of the first P-arrivals generally decreases from a few hundred down to a single number with increasing source-to-receiver distance, from deep (~3000 m) to shallow water (~100 m), with increasing sediment thickness and decreasing air-gun shot spacing and time interval. On average, the ratio appears 5-10 times lower at inland stations than at offshore stations. The sediment thickness estimated in this study demonstrates significant along-strike variations, which is up to 5 km offshore Oregon and 3.5 km offshore Washington. The coincidence of thick sediments with seismicity suggests the importance of sediments on the coupling of the plate interface.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project produced a clear and complete picture of the incoming plate and the forearc, which is essential for our understanding of the subduction process. We have published two papers so far, including Rathnayaka and Gao (2017, Crustal-scale seismic struc ture from trench to forearc in the Cascadia subduction zone, <em>J. Geophys. Res. Solid Earth</em>, 122, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/2017JB014299">https://doi.org/10.1002/2017JB014299</a>) and Rathnayaka and Gao (2019, Quality analysis of high-frequency air-gun shot seismic recordings in the Juan de Fuca plate, <em>Seismological Res. Lett.</em>, 90(1), doi:10.1785/0220180274). My graduate student, Sampath Rathnayaka, is the leading author for both publications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>More broadly, this project has very significant contribution to the scientific goals and outreach of the Cascadia Initiative community-based experiment. One female early-career geoscientist, who is in the process of establishing a new seismology group at UMass-Amherst, was supported for the career development. This project supported training of undergraduate and graduate students. The related products have been integrated into ongoing public outreach and introductory classes in Earth Science. The outcome has been introduced to underserved 8<sup>th</sup>-12<sup>th</sup> grade girls through the Girls Inc. Eureka! Program, a strong STEM-based collaboration between Girls Inc. of Holyoke, Massachusetts and UMass Amherst.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/19/2019<br>      Modified by: Haiying&nbsp;Gao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1635903/1635903_10458398_1576788780616_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1635903/1635903_10458398_1576788780616_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Distribution of offshore and onshore seismic stations"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1635903/1635903_10458398_1576788780616_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Distribution of offshore and onshore seismic stations"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Distribution of offshore and onshore seismic stations used in this study. The depth contours of the plate interface from 20 - 100 km (gray lines with numbers) are from the model of McCrory et al. [2004].</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sampath Rathnayaka</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Haiying&nbsp;Gao</div> <div class="imageTitle">Distribution of offshore and onshore seismic stations</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1635903/1635903_10458398_1576788926556_Picture2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1635903/1635903_10458398_1576788926556_Picture2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Comparison of the velocity models"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1635903/1635903_10458398_1576788926556_Picture2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Comparison of the velocity models"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Comparison of the initial reference model (the first column), the Gao [2016] model (the second column), and our preferred model (the third column). The fourth column shows the shear wave velocity misfit between the our model and the Gao[2016] model.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sampath Rathnayaka</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Haiying&nbsp;Gao</div> <div class="imageTitle">Comparison of the velocity models</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1635903/1635903_10458398_1576789120571_Picture13png--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1635903/1635903_10458398_1576789120571_Picture13png--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Distribution of seismic stations and two active source seismic experiments (thin white lines) used in this study."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1635903/1635903_10458398_1576789120571_Picture13png--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Distribution of seismic stations and two active source seismic experiments (thin white lines) used in this study."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Distribution of seismic stations and two active source seismic experiments (thin white lines). The depth contours of the Juan de Fuca plate interface from 20-60 km (gray lines) are from the model of McCrory et al. [2004]. The thick black line represents the mid-ocean ridge.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sampath Rathnayaka</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Haiying&nbsp;Gao</div> <div class="imageTitle">Distribution of seismic stations and two active source seismic experiments (thin white lines) used in this study.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1635903/1635903_10458398_1576789299546_Picture4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1635903/1635903_10458398_1576789299546_Picture4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Variation of the average signal-to-noise ratio in terms of sediment thickness and water depth"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1635903/1635903_10458398_1576789299546_Picture4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Variation of the average signal-to-noise ratio in terms of sediment thickness and water depth"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Distribution of sediment thickness estimated beneath each offshore seismic station. (b) Variation of the average SNR in terms of sediment thickness. (c) Variation of the average SNR in terms of water depth.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sampath Rathnayaka</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Haiying&nbsp;Gao</div> <div class="imageTitle">Variation of the average signal-to-noise ratio in terms of sediment thickness and water depth</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The formation, evolution, and destruction of a subducting plate remains one of the least understood aspects of global subduction zones. The relatively small size of the Cascadia subduction system from formation to subduction provides a unique opportunity to investigate the structure and evolution of the oceanic plate, as well as the forearc and volcanic arc. Seismic imaging provides strong constraints on the geometry and physical properties of the subducting slab and the upper plate. This project constructed a 3D high-resolution velocity model with the use of a joint 3D full-wave simulation and inversion of ambient noise and air-gun shots, from the surface through the crust into the mantle lithosphere, extending from trench to arc. Specifically, this project focused on addressing two scientific questions: (1) What is the structure of the oceanic plate prior to and after subduction? How does the plate structure evolve with time? To what extent is the oceanic plate hydrated prior to subduction? (2) What are the relationships between the structure of the incoming plate and the along-strike variations in the forearc structure (e.g., forearc basins, underthrusting of sediments, and serpentinization of the mantle wedge)?     The (de)hydration process and the amount of hydrated sediment carried by the downgoing oceanic plate play a key role in the subduction dynamics. A high-resolution shear velocity model from the crust down to the uppermost mantle, extending from trench to forearc, was constructed in the northern Cascadia subduction zone to investigate seismic characteristics related to slab deformation and (de)hydration at the plate boundary. A total of 220 seismic stations were used, including the Cascadia Initiative Amphibious Array and inland broadband and short-period stations. The empirical Green’s functions extracted from continuous ambient noise data from 2006-2014 provide high-quality Rayleigh-wave signals at periods of 4-50 s. We simulated wave propagation using finite-difference method to generate station Strain Green’s Tensors and synthetic waveforms. The phase delays of Rayleigh waves between the observed and synthetic data were measured at multiple period ranges. We then inverted for the velocity perturbations from the reference model and progressively improve the model resolution. Our tomographic imaging showed many regional- and local-scale low-velocity features, which are possibly related to slab (de)hydration from the oceanic plate to the overriding plate.     We extracted high-frequency seismic waveforms recorded by both offshore and onshore instrumentation, and quantitatively evaluated the data quality in terms of source-to-receiver distance, source parameters, water depth, and sediment thickness. There were two active-source seismic experiments within the Juan de Fuca plate, MGL1211 and MGL1212, during the first year deployment of the Cascadia Initiative Amphibious Array. The common receiver gathering analysis showed that most offshore stations located in deep-water record clear first P-wave arrivals up to 150 km away from the air-gun shot. The first arrival transits from crustal phase Pg to head wave Pn at a source-to-receiver distance of 25-40 km. For stations located at shallow water, the seismic recordings appear much noisier compared to those of deep-water stations. Only 5 inland stations record clear air-gun shot signals up to 200 km away from the source. The signal-to-noise ratio of the first P-arrivals generally decreases from a few hundred down to a single number with increasing source-to-receiver distance, from deep (~3000 m) to shallow water (~100 m), with increasing sediment thickness and decreasing air-gun shot spacing and time interval. On average, the ratio appears 5-10 times lower at inland stations than at offshore stations. The sediment thickness estimated in this study demonstrates significant along-strike variations, which is up to 5 km offshore Oregon and 3.5 km offshore Washington. The coincidence of thick sediments with seismicity suggests the importance of sediments on the coupling of the plate interface.     This project produced a clear and complete picture of the incoming plate and the forearc, which is essential for our understanding of the subduction process. We have published two papers so far, including Rathnayaka and Gao (2017, Crustal-scale seismic struc ture from trench to forearc in the Cascadia subduction zone, J. Geophys. Res. Solid Earth, 122, https://doi.org/10.1002/2017JB014299) and Rathnayaka and Gao (2019, Quality analysis of high-frequency air-gun shot seismic recordings in the Juan de Fuca plate, Seismological Res. Lett., 90(1), doi:10.1785/0220180274). My graduate student, Sampath Rathnayaka, is the leading author for both publications.     More broadly, this project has very significant contribution to the scientific goals and outreach of the Cascadia Initiative community-based experiment. One female early-career geoscientist, who is in the process of establishing a new seismology group at UMass-Amherst, was supported for the career development. This project supported training of undergraduate and graduate students. The related products have been integrated into ongoing public outreach and introductory classes in Earth Science. The outcome has been introduced to underserved 8th-12th grade girls through the Girls Inc. Eureka! Program, a strong STEM-based collaboration between Girls Inc. of Holyoke, Massachusetts and UMass Amherst.          Last Modified: 12/19/2019       Submitted by: Haiying Gao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
