<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>BD Spokes: SPOKE: MIDWEST: Collaborative: Integrative Materials Design (IMaD): Leverage, Innovate, and Disseminate</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47580.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>47580</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alejandro Suarez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alsuarez@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927092</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Materials innovation is a pipeline, deriving from a deep understanding and control of material behavior and properties, leading to advanced materials designs that advance economic prosperity, address national and regional energy needs, and bolster national security. Improving this pipeline requires connecting independent but thematically congruent national and regional materials design efforts to align key stakeholders, consolidate diverse materials data expertise, simplify data access, coalesce on topics of data description and interoperability, enhance and ensure the quality of datasets, and deploy scalable data services to support materials researchers. The Midwest Big Data Spoke (MBD Spoke) for Integrative Materials Design (IMaD) connects researchers in industry, universities, and government to the people and services needed to easily find, access, and use data, tools, and services for materials design. The Midwest is the ideal place for such a program. Many major national materials design efforts funded by DOE, NIST, and NSF as part of the Materials Genome Initiative (MGI) operate in the Midwest, and the Midwest is home to major manufacturing industries that depend critically on materials innovation for their continued competitiveness.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The technical work of IMaD will involve integration of software and services from across the Midwest and beyond, including the Materials Commons, the Materials Data Facility, NIST Materials Resource Registry, and Citrine Informatics, to enable smooth flow of software and data among these different systems. For example, integrated authentication provided by Globus Auth will enable access to different components with common credentials (e.g., institutional credentials), and integration of Globus transfer will allow for rapid and reliable exchange of large datasets. Common schemas and metadata terms will be developed and deployed to permit cross-system searching and display of information. Materials data from partners across the Midwest and beyond will be loaded into the Material Data Facility to permit easy discovery and access. Concurrently with these and other development activities, a series of workshops and meetings will be convened to engage academic, government, and industry participants in defining requirements for, and making use of, the integrated system for materials design.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award received co-funding from the Math and Physical Sciences Directorate (MPS) Division of Materials Research (DMR).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/17/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/17/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1636929</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dallas</FirstName>
<LastName>Trinkle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dallas R Trinkle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dtrinkle@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172446519</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000280420</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/17/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S. Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>024Y</Code>
<Text>BD Spokes -Big Data Regional I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1712</Code>
<Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>028Z</Code>
<Text>BD Spokes Full Awards</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8400</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~47580</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goals of the IMaD project are to 1) leverage and integrate the expertise, services, facilities, and community connections, and unique datasets of the IMaD partners; 2) expedite and advance materials design by promoting and simplifying materials data sharing and discovery across existing services; and 3) to disseminate and distribute Midwest materials datasets. At Illinois, the 4CeeD - MDF Connect was completed and moved into production, so that users of 4CeeD are now able to publish datasets directly from the 4CeeD web user interface to MDF Connect. Subsequently, these data can now be propagated to other community sources via MDF Connect. With the NSF Nanomanufacturing Node project at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, IMaD discusses how to leverage existing data infrastructure to capture and sharing their team efforts. The NanoMFG has submitted hundreds of curated recipes and characterization results for graphene and 2D material preparation through MDF Connect. New datasets encompass advanced ceramics, and data for mechanical and optical properties of polymers. Within the materials science community, the immediate result of IMaD is that researchers have enhanced and simplified means to access to data to support individual research and wider group collaborations. Researchers will also have access to new tools that will enable meta studies and development of machine learning. With an influx of new datasets and tools to simplify usage of these datasets, we expect to see broader usage of the materials science related data services that have been funded by a wide range of agencies (e.g., NSF, DOE, NIST, and more) become more heavily and more efficiently used. Access to these datasets will enable new studies on existing datasets that may lead to more rapid discovery and industrial application of yet unknown materials. These new materials may range from metallic glass biomaterials for uniquely biocompatible and resorbable screws, pins and plates; advanced semiconductor alloys for next generation microchips; new high temperature superconductors to support development of quantum computing Qbits and new medical diagnostic capabilities; lighter, high-strength composite or ceramic materials to decrease warfighter load while maintaining projectile stopping power; or new high performance alloys for next generation military and civil aircraft.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/12/2020<br>      Modified by: Dallas&nbsp;R&nbsp;Trinkle</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goals of the IMaD project are to 1) leverage and integrate the expertise, services, facilities, and community connections, and unique datasets of the IMaD partners; 2) expedite and advance materials design by promoting and simplifying materials data sharing and discovery across existing services; and 3) to disseminate and distribute Midwest materials datasets. At Illinois, the 4CeeD - MDF Connect was completed and moved into production, so that users of 4CeeD are now able to publish datasets directly from the 4CeeD web user interface to MDF Connect. Subsequently, these data can now be propagated to other community sources via MDF Connect. With the NSF Nanomanufacturing Node project at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, IMaD discusses how to leverage existing data infrastructure to capture and sharing their team efforts. The NanoMFG has submitted hundreds of curated recipes and characterization results for graphene and 2D material preparation through MDF Connect. New datasets encompass advanced ceramics, and data for mechanical and optical properties of polymers. Within the materials science community, the immediate result of IMaD is that researchers have enhanced and simplified means to access to data to support individual research and wider group collaborations. Researchers will also have access to new tools that will enable meta studies and development of machine learning. With an influx of new datasets and tools to simplify usage of these datasets, we expect to see broader usage of the materials science related data services that have been funded by a wide range of agencies (e.g., NSF, DOE, NIST, and more) become more heavily and more efficiently used. Access to these datasets will enable new studies on existing datasets that may lead to more rapid discovery and industrial application of yet unknown materials. These new materials may range from metallic glass biomaterials for uniquely biocompatible and resorbable screws, pins and plates; advanced semiconductor alloys for next generation microchips; new high temperature superconductors to support development of quantum computing Qbits and new medical diagnostic capabilities; lighter, high-strength composite or ceramic materials to decrease warfighter load while maintaining projectile stopping power; or new high performance alloys for next generation military and civil aircraft.       Last Modified: 08/12/2020       Submitted by: Dallas R Trinkle]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
