<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Verification Mentoring Workshop II</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30600.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30600</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nina Amla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>namla@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927991</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant will enable students to attend the Verification Mentoring Workshop (VMW 2016) which will be co-located with the International Conference on Computer Aided Verification (CAV), in Toronto (Canada), July 17-23, 2016. CAV is one of the premier conferences in computer science, dedicated to the advancement of the theory and practice of computer-aided formal analysis methods for hardware and software systems. The purpose of Verification Mentoring Workshop is to provide mentoring and career advice to early-stage graduate students, to attract them to pursue research careers in the area of computer-aided verification. Funded students will benefit greatly from the opportunity to engage in the critical technical, professional, and social exchanges that both conferences foster.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Computer-aided verification covers a broad range of applications, from ensuring the correctness and safety of computer systems, to improving design and development productivity. The funded students will attend CAV, a top conference where they will learn about current research problems and interact with leaders in the field, and the VMW workshop which will focus on mentoring and career advice specific to early-stage graduate students who aim to pursue research careers in the area of computer-aided verification.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1636694</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aarti</FirstName>
<LastName>Gupta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aarti Gupta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aartig@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092583090</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000689816</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[87 Prospect Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8206</Code>
<Text>Formal Methods and Verification</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~30600</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Report for Verification Mentoring Workshop (VMW) 2016</p> <p>Aarti Gupta</p> <p>Department of Computer Science, Princeton University</p> <p>The area of computer-aided verification and formal methods is thriving and growing in computer science, fueled by the needs to develop safe and correct computer and information systems, and to improve designer and development productivity. The International Conference on Computer Aided Verification (CAV) is one of the premier conferences in this area, dedicated to the advancement of the theory and practice of computer-aided formal analysis methods for hardware and software systems. We organized the second Verification Mentoring Workshop (VMW) co-located with CAV 2016 (held in Toronto, July 17-23, 2016).</p> <p>The goal of VMW is to attract early-stage graduate students to pursue research careers in the area of computer-aided verification. Since this area is at the intersection of other traditional areas in computer science such as theory and logic, systems, programming languages, compilers, etc., students often have insufficient exposure to the broad range of research problems and career options that exist in the area. The workshop aims to fill this gap by focusing on mentoring and career advice, while providing an opportunity for participants to attend CAV, a top conference where attendees can learn about current research problems and interact with leaders in the field. The workshop particularly encouraged participation of women and under-represented minorities.</p> <p>VMW 2016 (VMW-II) was organized by Aarti Gupta (Princeton, USA), Ruzica Piskac (Yale, USA), and Andrey Rybalchenko (Microsoft Research, UK). We provided travel scholarships to attract students who may not have otherwise attended CAV. The scholarships covered conference and workshops registration, accommodations, plus travel expenses. We are very grateful to NSF for their generous support of VMW 2016. The NSF grant supported the travel of 17 US-based students to VMW and CAV 2016, at an average reimbursement of about $1753 per student. The awardees were reimbursed actual travel costs.&nbsp;</p> <p>CAV 2016 was held July 17-23, 2016, and VMW was held on July 18th, immediately preceding the main conference. The workshop introduced students to a wide range of research themes and career options, and provided career and mentoring advice through talks as well as interactive panels and informal sessions. More details for VMW 2016 can be found at <a href="http://i-cav.org/2016/vmw">http://i-cav.org/2016/vmw</a> .</p> <p>The main CAV conference comprised one full day of in-depth tutorials, followed by four days of technical sessions that include invited keynotes and presentations of papers. The conference also included many social events, including a lunch for women researchers, that provide additional opportunities for interaction. More details for CAV 2016 can be found at <a href="http://i-cav.org/2016/">http://i-cav.org/2016/</a> .</p> <p>After the workshop, we invited all travel awardees to send a brief report about their experience at VMW and CAV. Overall, their feedback was very positive, with many students stating that they benefited greatly from the workshop and the opportunity to attend a top-level conference.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/02/2018<br>      Modified by: Aarti&nbsp;Gupta</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Report for Verification Mentoring Workshop (VMW) 2016  Aarti Gupta  Department of Computer Science, Princeton University  The area of computer-aided verification and formal methods is thriving and growing in computer science, fueled by the needs to develop safe and correct computer and information systems, and to improve designer and development productivity. The International Conference on Computer Aided Verification (CAV) is one of the premier conferences in this area, dedicated to the advancement of the theory and practice of computer-aided formal analysis methods for hardware and software systems. We organized the second Verification Mentoring Workshop (VMW) co-located with CAV 2016 (held in Toronto, July 17-23, 2016).  The goal of VMW is to attract early-stage graduate students to pursue research careers in the area of computer-aided verification. Since this area is at the intersection of other traditional areas in computer science such as theory and logic, systems, programming languages, compilers, etc., students often have insufficient exposure to the broad range of research problems and career options that exist in the area. The workshop aims to fill this gap by focusing on mentoring and career advice, while providing an opportunity for participants to attend CAV, a top conference where attendees can learn about current research problems and interact with leaders in the field. The workshop particularly encouraged participation of women and under-represented minorities.  VMW 2016 (VMW-II) was organized by Aarti Gupta (Princeton, USA), Ruzica Piskac (Yale, USA), and Andrey Rybalchenko (Microsoft Research, UK). We provided travel scholarships to attract students who may not have otherwise attended CAV. The scholarships covered conference and workshops registration, accommodations, plus travel expenses. We are very grateful to NSF for their generous support of VMW 2016. The NSF grant supported the travel of 17 US-based students to VMW and CAV 2016, at an average reimbursement of about $1753 per student. The awardees were reimbursed actual travel costs.   CAV 2016 was held July 17-23, 2016, and VMW was held on July 18th, immediately preceding the main conference. The workshop introduced students to a wide range of research themes and career options, and provided career and mentoring advice through talks as well as interactive panels and informal sessions. More details for VMW 2016 can be found at http://i-cav.org/2016/vmw .  The main CAV conference comprised one full day of in-depth tutorials, followed by four days of technical sessions that include invited keynotes and presentations of papers. The conference also included many social events, including a lunch for women researchers, that provide additional opportunities for interaction. More details for CAV 2016 can be found at http://i-cav.org/2016/ .  After the workshop, we invited all travel awardees to send a brief report about their experience at VMW and CAV. Overall, their feedback was very positive, with many students stating that they benefited greatly from the workshop and the opportunity to attend a top-level conference.          Last Modified: 07/02/2018       Submitted by: Aarti Gupta]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
