<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: Doctoral Consortium at the PETRA 2016 Conference</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>27580.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>27580</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ephraim Glinert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eglinert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This is funding to support a doctoral consortium (workshop) of approximately 11 promising graduate students from U.S. institutions of higher learning along with at least 3 distinguished research faculty as mentors, to be held in conjunction with the Ninth International Conference on Pervasive Technologies Related to Assistive Environments (PETRA 2016), which will take place June 29-July 1 on the island of Corfu, Greece. The PETRA mission is to promote interdisciplinary research on ways to use pervasive ambient intelligent environments to improve the quality of life and enhance human performance with greater capabilities; it is the only annual conference that brings together theoreticians and practitioners from a wide variety of disciplines to focus on the application of pervasive technologies to assistive environments. Outcomes of this conference have a broad impact in diverse application areas such as manufacturing, transportation, energy systems, security and safety, robotics, healthcare, biomedicine, environment and conservation. PETRA brings together very different types of technologies to also address important social and healthcare issues for sensitive populations, such as the elderly, persons suffering from chronic conditions such as Alzheimer's, Parkinson's, Cerebral Palsy, and other disabilities or traumas. The PETRA proceedings are published in the ACM digital library, and the authors of the best papers are invited to submit to special journal issues after the end of the conference. More information about the conference may be found online at http://www.petrae.org.  The PETRA 2016 Doctoral Consortium will afford student authors of papers accepted for presentation at the conference a unique opportunity to gain additional exposure for their innovative ideas while also receiving reinforcement for the importance and value of conducting research with societal impact. The workshop will allow the junior participants to create a social network both among themselves and with senior colleagues. The organizing committee will make a concerted effort to attract participants who are women, members of under-represented minorities, and persons with disabilities; to further assure diversity, NSF funds will be used to support no more than 2 student participants from any one institution, and if 2 students are supported, one of them must be a minority or person with disability. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of the Doctoral Consortium, which will consist of special sessions at the beginning, during, and at the end of the conference, are to increase the exposure and visibility of the participants' work within the community, to help establish a sense of community among this next generation of researchers, and to help foster their research efforts by providing substantive feedback and guidance in a supportive and interactive environment from a group of senior researchers.  The special program organized for the students includes sessions between the doctoral students and the faculty mentors, in which the students will discuss their work and ask questions; the faculty mentors will provide constructive comments on the students' work and address their questions.  Each student will be asked to submit a report that provides feedback about the conference, regarding the benefits they received, which presentations they liked and why, and how certain papers and topics relate to their work. After they finish the report, students will participate in small group breakout sessions and discuss their report; faculty mentors will ensure that each student participant in the doctoral consortium completes this assignment, and will also provide guidance on how to proceed for further journal publication.  Students will also have the option to submit a poster paper and to attend conference workshops on special topics.  Short papers on the participants' work will be published in the conference proceedings, and a summary report on the event will be posted on the conference website.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1636543</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fillia</FirstName>
<LastName>Makedon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Fillia S Makedon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>makedon@cse.uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8172723605</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000191699</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vassilis</FirstName>
<LastName>Athitsos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vassilis Athitsos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>athitsos@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8172722105</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000308836</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vangelis</FirstName>
<LastName>Metsis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vangelis Metsis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vmetsis@txstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5122452314</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000738978</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Arlington</Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>701 S Nedderman Dr, Box 19145</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064234610</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT ARLINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Arlington]]></Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>HCC-Human-Centered Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~27580</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Award Title: </strong>WORKSHOP: Doctoral Consortium at the PETRA 2015 Conference</p> <p><strong>Federal Award ID: </strong>1636543</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Report Submission Period: </strong>05/01/2017 to 06/30/2017</p> <p>PI: Fillia Makedon</p> <p>Awardee: University of Texas at Arlington</p> <p>Program Officer Name: Ephraim P. Glinert</p> <p>Program Officer Email Address: <a href="mailto:eglinert@nsf.gov">eglinert@nsf.gov</a></p> <p>Program Officer Phone Number: (703)292-8930</p> <p>PETRA 2016 was the ninth (9<sup>th</sup>) annual international conference on <em>PErvasive Technologies Related to Assistive Environments. </em>PETRA is a highly interdisciplinary conference that was launched in 2008.&nbsp; It focuses on applying pervasive technologies to assistive environments and merging expertise and tools from many disciplines such as, imaging, machine learning, robotics, computer vision, user interface design, networks, rehabilitation, human computer interaction, vocational assessment, and other areas.</p> <p>The objective of the PETRA conference is to stimulate interdisciplinary research and develop Assistive Technologies (AT) that focus on improving the quality of life by overcoming physical, cognitive and operational obstacles that may prevent a human from reaching his/her full potential and achieve best performance. The findings presented aim at improving the functional capabilities of people with disabilities, as well as enhancing the productivity of well-bodied people.</p> <p>Application areas include smart healthcare, assessment, training and rehabilitation for intelligent manufacturing, energy tracking, conservation, public and personal safety, transportation, robot-based training, vocational assessment and other areas.</p> <p>For example, Petra authors have presented results (see <a href="http://www.petrae.org">www.petrae.org</a>) involving safety in smart homes, robot-based rehabilitation, physiological monitoring with wearables, multimodal assessment of mental health through gaming, and others.&nbsp;</p> <p>Conference results aim to impact the daily life not only of sensitive populations, such as seniors or persons with disabilities, but also to dramatically improve human performance and the quality of life of healthy individuals. Conference findings have impacted other disciplines, such as psychology, and have given technical solutions and insights to emerging social and ethical issues.</p> <p>The PETRA Conference has had a broad and significant technological, as well as social, economic and community impact. From the attendees of the initial conference that took place in 2008, a large percentage has continued to do successful and ground-breaking research in human centered computing with significant contributions in their respective areas. The results presented at the Petra conferences impact different types of environments and applications, at home, in the workplace and in public spaces. &nbsp;&nbsp;Many innovations and inventions have resulted from this conference, as well as many publications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The Doctoral Consortium (DC) and Student Author Travel Award for PETRA 2015 supported 12 student authors from 10 different US universities, who presented their work during the conference. In addition, through Univ. of Texas Arlington and European matching funds, 7 more students were able to join and contribute to the DC events during the conference.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During the conference, several sessions were especially designed for the NSF DC scholars in order to allow them to describe their work, meet each other, exchange ideas and discuss challenges and opportunities in doing interdisciplinary research and receive feedback from participating faculty mentors. The discussions included issues related to making good progress with the Ph.D. thesis. how to best design experiments to collect data, and team work.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Major findings of this project include:</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <ol> <li>PETRA DC students presented their work to a knowledgeable international audience of experts and interacted with the assigned doctoral consortium faculty mentors, who provided them with useful comments and ideas on how to best continue and advance their Ph.D. research.&nbsp; The students learned about how to improve their presentation style and build confidence from this experience.</li> <li>The DC students had the opportunity to network with other graduate students from other universities and share ideas and approaches for a successful career in computing and applications.</li> <li>&nbsp;The students had one-on-one meetings with companies working on assistive technologies and with experts who helped them develop career models and gain motivation from opportunities available after graduation.</li> <li>The students' scientific contributions to assistive technologies provided novel approaches and were publicized widely through the PETRA conference ACM Digital Library proceedings that also gave the students visibility. </li> <li>This funding highlighted the support of NSF towards young researchers and gave visibility to the departments and institutions in the US where the students came from.</li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Conclusions: The project was very successful and beneficial to the DC students. The aims of the project were achieved and the scope of the proposed work has been completed.&nbsp; The PI does not anticipate any further action on this award.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2017<br>      Modified by: Fillia&nbsp;S&nbsp;Makedon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[       Award Title: WORKSHOP: Doctoral Consortium at the PETRA 2015 Conference  Federal Award ID: 1636543              Report Submission Period: 05/01/2017 to 06/30/2017  PI: Fillia Makedon  Awardee: University of Texas at Arlington  Program Officer Name: Ephraim P. Glinert  Program Officer Email Address: eglinert@nsf.gov  Program Officer Phone Number: (703)292-8930  PETRA 2016 was the ninth (9th) annual international conference on PErvasive Technologies Related to Assistive Environments. PETRA is a highly interdisciplinary conference that was launched in 2008.  It focuses on applying pervasive technologies to assistive environments and merging expertise and tools from many disciplines such as, imaging, machine learning, robotics, computer vision, user interface design, networks, rehabilitation, human computer interaction, vocational assessment, and other areas.  The objective of the PETRA conference is to stimulate interdisciplinary research and develop Assistive Technologies (AT) that focus on improving the quality of life by overcoming physical, cognitive and operational obstacles that may prevent a human from reaching his/her full potential and achieve best performance. The findings presented aim at improving the functional capabilities of people with disabilities, as well as enhancing the productivity of well-bodied people.  Application areas include smart healthcare, assessment, training and rehabilitation for intelligent manufacturing, energy tracking, conservation, public and personal safety, transportation, robot-based training, vocational assessment and other areas.  For example, Petra authors have presented results (see www.petrae.org) involving safety in smart homes, robot-based rehabilitation, physiological monitoring with wearables, multimodal assessment of mental health through gaming, and others.   Conference results aim to impact the daily life not only of sensitive populations, such as seniors or persons with disabilities, but also to dramatically improve human performance and the quality of life of healthy individuals. Conference findings have impacted other disciplines, such as psychology, and have given technical solutions and insights to emerging social and ethical issues.  The PETRA Conference has had a broad and significant technological, as well as social, economic and community impact. From the attendees of the initial conference that took place in 2008, a large percentage has continued to do successful and ground-breaking research in human centered computing with significant contributions in their respective areas. The results presented at the Petra conferences impact different types of environments and applications, at home, in the workplace and in public spaces.   Many innovations and inventions have resulted from this conference, as well as many publications.     The Doctoral Consortium (DC) and Student Author Travel Award for PETRA 2015 supported 12 student authors from 10 different US universities, who presented their work during the conference. In addition, through Univ. of Texas Arlington and European matching funds, 7 more students were able to join and contribute to the DC events during the conference.     During the conference, several sessions were especially designed for the NSF DC scholars in order to allow them to describe their work, meet each other, exchange ideas and discuss challenges and opportunities in doing interdisciplinary research and receive feedback from participating faculty mentors. The discussions included issues related to making good progress with the Ph.D. thesis. how to best design experiments to collect data, and team work.     Major findings of this project include:     PETRA DC students presented their work to a knowledgeable international audience of experts and interacted with the assigned doctoral consortium faculty mentors, who provided them with useful comments and ideas on how to best continue and advance their Ph.D. research.  The students learned about how to improve their presentation style and build confidence from this experience. The DC students had the opportunity to network with other graduate students from other universities and share ideas and approaches for a successful career in computing and applications.  The students had one-on-one meetings with companies working on assistive technologies and with experts who helped them develop career models and gain motivation from opportunities available after graduation. The students' scientific contributions to assistive technologies provided novel approaches and were publicized widely through the PETRA conference ACM Digital Library proceedings that also gave the students visibility.  This funding highlighted the support of NSF towards young researchers and gave visibility to the departments and institutions in the US where the students came from.      Conclusions: The project was very successful and beneficial to the DC students. The aims of the project were achieved and the scope of the proposed work has been completed.  The PI does not anticipate any further action on this award.       Last Modified: 05/02/2017       Submitted by: Fillia S Makedon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
