<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>BD Spokes: SPOKE: WEST: Collaborative: MetroInsight: Knowledge Discovery and Real-Time Interventions from Sensory Data Flows in Urban Spaces</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>179117.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>179117</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Beth Plale</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The MetroInsight project is building an end to end system for knowledge discovery from real-time data streams collected through a variety of sensors, data collection and aggregation methods.  These data streams are highly dimensional with multiple sensors observing same or similar phenomena over multiple sensory spectrums and scales. These are also sometimes real-time and/or have strong timing relationships that is necessary to support metropolitan infrastructure through effective analytics and policy support. The project brings together a diverse number of partners utilities, universities, companies and cities with the ability to contribute novel tools and urban sensor data and to translate knowledge into actions. MetroInsight's unique combination of tools, data and partnerships, in part with the MetroLab Network , makes it well poised to set an example for the MetroLab programs across the nation as well as the rest of the municipal governments. The project will explore connections between multimodal datasets and urban infrastructure management to build a practical system consisting of integrated tools, as well as training a new generation of metropolitan workforce. As part of an ambitious plan for community building and workforce development, the project includes creation of new learning modules, certification programs on energy and sustainability, an online courses on sensor data analytics and new capstone projects in a new Data Science master's degree program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To achieve project goals, MetroInsight is building infrastructure for managing data, networks and processing that will support design of new algorithms and tools in the project. Specifically, the project is developing algorithms to transform multimodal urban data to a lower dimensional data that reflects underlying physical and social phenomena. These low dimensional data may consist of population level data suitable for dynamic processing to support real time monitoring and visualization by cityscale operators of various lifelines from transportation, communications to emergency response. To address technical challenges in complex and subtle spatiotemporal dynamics of interdependent urban networks, MetroInsight will develop metadata methods and tools that support discovery of operational interdependencies, quantification of uncertainties for decision support and to provide assurances related to integrity and security of data, compliance related to ethical and legal privacy expectations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1636936</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shade</FirstName>
<LastName>Shutters</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shade T Shutters</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shade.shutters@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4802786098</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000511805</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[AZ Board of Regents on behalf of Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>024Y</Code>
<Text>BD Spokes -Big Data Regional I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>028Z</Code>
<Text>BD Spokes Full Awards</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~179117</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>MetroInsight brings powerful tools and methods from the field of ecology into the field of urban economic planning. In doing so, it unlocks previously hidden value of existing government datasets to help local and regional economic planners prioritize industry targets for job growth. In addition to intuition and legacy analytics, economic planners now have a powerful suite of data tools to better understand which industries are likely to spur job growth and which are likely to fail.&nbsp; With this knowledge, planners can better invest precious tax dollars to grow quality, sustainable jobs for their region.</p> <p>The key to these new tools is bringing the typical holistic, systems-level perspective of ecology to urban economies. Viewing cities as a complex system of interacting industries, occupations, and skills allows new insights into what works and what doesn't for a regional economy.</p> <p>The impact of these better economic decision spills over into the education policy arena, where educational institutions are better able to respond to future economic visions by addressing skills gaps earlier and more accurately in the economic planning process.</p> <p>By increasing the return on local investments, identifying and filling local skills gaps, and unlocking the economic potentail of U.S. regions, the key impact of this project is increasing the competitiveness of American cities.&nbsp; This is a crucial outcome at a time when globalization, rapid technological change, and political dynamism are challenging America's global economic position.</p> <p>However, the benefits are not restricted to U.S. cities. The tools and methods are generalizable and scaleable internationally to any country that collects the required data.&nbsp; To validate this capability, the products of this project include working economic development tools covering all cities in both Australia and Canada - two countries that collect and publish high quality economic data - and can be rapidly implemented and scaled for other countries as they seek guidance with their own economic planning.</p> <p>But perhaps the most important outcome of this project is that it reveals the massive potential of parterships between academic and stakeholder communities.&nbsp; By co-developing both research questions and products, and then working with stakeholder communities to implement those products, this project emphatically demonstrates how investements in academic research can have almost immediate impact on the well-being of communties served by universities.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/20/2019<br>      Modified by: Shade&nbsp;T&nbsp;Shutters</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1636936/1636936_10455984_1574268556684_userengagement--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1636936/1636936_10455984_1574268556684_userengagement--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Users interacting with the project's tools"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1636936/1636936_10455984_1574268556684_userengagement--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Users interacting with the project's tools"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">In one of the first engagements with the tools developed by this project, local users and stakeholder engage with data and visualizations to discuss regional economic development issues.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Arizona State University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shade&nbsp;T&nbsp;Shutters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Users interacting with the project's tools</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1636936/1636936_10455984_1574268460775_stakeholdermeeting--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1636936/1636936_10455984_1574268460775_stakeholdermeeting--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Assessing stakeholder needs"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1636936/1636936_10455984_1574268460775_stakeholdermeeting--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Assessing stakeholder needs"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">During development, stakeholders engaged with the project team to express their needs and desires related to enhancing local economic well-being.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Arizona State University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shade&nbsp;T&nbsp;Shutters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Assessing stakeholder needs</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ MetroInsight brings powerful tools and methods from the field of ecology into the field of urban economic planning. In doing so, it unlocks previously hidden value of existing government datasets to help local and regional economic planners prioritize industry targets for job growth. In addition to intuition and legacy analytics, economic planners now have a powerful suite of data tools to better understand which industries are likely to spur job growth and which are likely to fail.  With this knowledge, planners can better invest precious tax dollars to grow quality, sustainable jobs for their region.  The key to these new tools is bringing the typical holistic, systems-level perspective of ecology to urban economies. Viewing cities as a complex system of interacting industries, occupations, and skills allows new insights into what works and what doesn't for a regional economy.  The impact of these better economic decision spills over into the education policy arena, where educational institutions are better able to respond to future economic visions by addressing skills gaps earlier and more accurately in the economic planning process.  By increasing the return on local investments, identifying and filling local skills gaps, and unlocking the economic potentail of U.S. regions, the key impact of this project is increasing the competitiveness of American cities.  This is a crucial outcome at a time when globalization, rapid technological change, and political dynamism are challenging America's global economic position.  However, the benefits are not restricted to U.S. cities. The tools and methods are generalizable and scaleable internationally to any country that collects the required data.  To validate this capability, the products of this project include working economic development tools covering all cities in both Australia and Canada - two countries that collect and publish high quality economic data - and can be rapidly implemented and scaled for other countries as they seek guidance with their own economic planning.  But perhaps the most important outcome of this project is that it reveals the massive potential of parterships between academic and stakeholder communities.  By co-developing both research questions and products, and then working with stakeholder communities to implement those products, this project emphatically demonstrates how investements in academic research can have almost immediate impact on the well-being of communties served by universities.       Last Modified: 11/20/2019       Submitted by: Shade T Shutters]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
