<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAP: CSCL 2017 Making a Difference: Prioritizing Equity and Access in CSCL Doctoral Consortium and Early Career Workshops</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tatiana Korelsky</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tkorelsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Cyberlearning and Future Learning Technologies Program funds efforts that will help envision the next generation of learning technologies and advance what we know about how people learn in technology-rich environments. Cyberlearning CAP projects build capacity for research and development in the field of cyberlearning by improving technical infrastructure, human capital, and in other ways. The Computer Supported Collaborative Learning conference is the premier conference on how technologies can support collaborative learning, both online and offline. This project supports a Doctoral Consortium and an Early Career Workshop at the conference which allows early career scholars to receive mentoring from established cyberlearning researchers from both computer science and learning research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project supports travel for advanced graduate students and new faculty from U.S. universities to attend the capacity-building activities at the CSCL 2017 conference in Philadelphia. Participants are selected through a competitive process that ensures high intellectual merit in their work. The project not only increases capacity by providing mentoring opportunities to young US researchers, but also supports building connections with peers in other countries (whose participation is supported by their own governments). In addition, the theme of the conference, which will be used to help guide selection of participants and mentors, is research on equity and access in collaborative technology-based learning. Thus the project will also provide vital training on how to better understand and design systems that help all people learn, which is a pressing problem in the area of MOOCs and online or mobile collaborative learning.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1637021</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Yoon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan A Yoon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yoonsa@gse.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2157462526</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000091588</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3451 Walnut St, 5th Flr Franklin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Trustees of the University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046216</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3700 Walnut St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8020</Code>
<Text>Cyberlearn &amp; Future Learn Tech</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8045</Code>
<Text>Cyberlearn &amp; Future Learn Tech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8055</Code>
<Text>Capacity-Building Projects</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p>Early career participants presented their research and received feedback, talked to different mentors in small groups, and discussed possible new international research networks with their peers. In addition, a &ldquo;meeting with the journal editors&ldquo; session was organized. The main contents of the workshop included: Research funding opportunities for post-docs and early career researchers; how to develop a research agenda, and/or consider their own career development; publishing&ndash;where and how much, promotion; how to mentor and supervise graduate students; new research methods; and possibilities for building international research networks. The workshop also focused on specific details of the CSCL community and on the challenges and opportunities that exist in our community (e.g., interdisciplinarity, gaps between different methodological approaches).&nbsp;</p> <p>The doctoral student participants presented their research briefly to familiarize each other with their dissertation projects and highlighted specific aspects they wanted further discussion on. These aspects included specific problems for which the student was seeking advice; issues and tensions for research generally; methodological problems that other Ph.D. students were confronting, or issues that had the potential to stimulate discussions of theoretical and methodological significance. Based on common issues and themes identified (theoretical models, research design and questions, pedagogy and technology, data collection, methods of analysis, etc.) participants formed small groups supported by expert mentors, to engage in further inquiry and discussion. Participants worked on the various problems and issues identified making reference to their own dissertation project and the broader field of the Learning Sciences. They also had the opportunity to raise questions, provide suggestions, and help each other to improve their dissertation research. After the small group interactions, participants reported on their progress and new questions to the whole group. Plans for further joint activity were also discussed.</p> <p>Broader Impacts</p> <p>The funding for this CSCL 2017 Workshop grant supported early career researchers and late stage doctoral students to participate in mentored activities for academic professional development in the field of the learning sciences over the course for 1.5 days. The grant supported 17 early career scholars (7 US-based supported by grant funds) and 5 mentors (3 US-based&nbsp;supported by grant funds). It also supported 14&nbsp;students (9 US-based supported by grant funds) and 5&nbsp;mentors (2 US-based supported by grant funds). The International Society of the Learning Sciences (ISLS) supplied matching funds for non-US-based researchers fulfilling a long-standing partnership between ISLS and NSF. This ongoing partnership has enabled US researchers to garner valuable social and professional capital from other researchers around the world. It has additionally provided global perspectives that help to position US researchers to make a positive impact in educational issues that are facing the international community.</p> <p>There were a number of beneficial outcomes experienced by both the early career and doctoral student researchers.</p> <p>For the early career researchers, with respect to:</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">1. Refinement/reformulation of my research plans and projects, 89% reported substantial or moderate effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">2. Identification of new lines of research, 67% reported substantial or moderate effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">3. Awareness/understanding of new approaches to defining problems and/or new methods for conducting research in the Learning Sciences or CSCL, 67% reported substantial or moderate effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">4. Awareness/understanding of how and where to publish, 63% reported substantial or moderate effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">5. Awareness/understanding of how to develop a research program, write proposals, and find<br /> funding, 83% reported substantial or moderate effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">6. Collaborative network of learning science or CSCL researchers, 89% reported substantial or moderate effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">7. Awareness/understanding of how to teach and mentor graduate students, 89% reported substantial or moderate effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">8. Whether they would recommend the workshop to others, 100% would highly recommend or recommend attending.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">&nbsp;</p> <p>For the doctoral students, with respect to:</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">1. Effect on refinement/reformulation of my dissertation topic, 93% reported a positive effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">2. Effect on my motivation to complete my degree program, 86% reported a positive effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">3. Identification of new lines of research, 71% reported a positive effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">4. Awareness/understanding of important and interesting new lines of theory and research, 77% reported a positive effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">5. Awareness/understanding of new approaches to defining problems and/or new methods for<br /> conducting research in the Learning Sciences or CSCL, 100% reported a positive effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">6. Awareness/understanding of how and where to publish, 93% reported a positive effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">7. Awareness/understanding of research related to my interests in countries other than my own, 71% reported a positive effect.</p> <p style="margin: 0in; margin-bottom: .0001pt;">8. Whether they would recommend the workshop to others, 100% would highly recommend or recommend attending.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <!--    @font-face  {font-family:"Cambria Math";  panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:roman;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536869121 1107305727 33554432 0 415 0;} @font-face  {font-family:Calibri;  panose-1:2 15 5 2 2 2 4 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:swiss;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-1610611985 1073750139 0 0 159 0;}    p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal  {mso-style-unhide:no;  mso-style-qformat:yes;  mso-style-parent:";  margin:0in;  margin-bottom:.0001pt;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  font-family:"Calibri",sans-serif;  mso-ascii-font-family:Calibri;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:Calibri;  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-hansi-font-family:Calibri;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;} p  {mso-style-noshow:yes;  mso-style-priority:99;  mso-margin-top-alt:auto;  margin-right:0in;  mso-margin-bottom-alt:auto;  margin-left:0in;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  font-family:"Times New Roman",serif;  mso-fareast-font-family:"Times New Roman";} .MsoChpDefault  {mso-style-type:export-only;  mso-default-props:yes;  font-family:"Calibri",sans-serif;  mso-ascii-font-family:Calibri;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:Calibri;  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-hansi-font-family:Calibri;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;} @page WordSection1  {size:8.5in 11.0in;  margin:1.0in 1.0in 1.0in 1.0in;  mso-header-margin:.5in;  mso-footer-margin:.5in;  mso-paper-source:0;} div.WordSection1  {page:WordSection1;} --><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/10/2019<br>      Modified by: Susan&nbsp;A&nbsp;Yoon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  Early career participants presented their research and received feedback, talked to different mentors in small groups, and discussed possible new international research networks with their peers. In addition, a "meeting with the journal editors" session was organized. The main contents of the workshop included: Research funding opportunities for post-docs and early career researchers; how to develop a research agenda, and/or consider their own career development; publishing&ndash;where and how much, promotion; how to mentor and supervise graduate students; new research methods; and possibilities for building international research networks. The workshop also focused on specific details of the CSCL community and on the challenges and opportunities that exist in our community (e.g., interdisciplinarity, gaps between different methodological approaches).   The doctoral student participants presented their research briefly to familiarize each other with their dissertation projects and highlighted specific aspects they wanted further discussion on. These aspects included specific problems for which the student was seeking advice; issues and tensions for research generally; methodological problems that other Ph.D. students were confronting, or issues that had the potential to stimulate discussions of theoretical and methodological significance. Based on common issues and themes identified (theoretical models, research design and questions, pedagogy and technology, data collection, methods of analysis, etc.) participants formed small groups supported by expert mentors, to engage in further inquiry and discussion. Participants worked on the various problems and issues identified making reference to their own dissertation project and the broader field of the Learning Sciences. They also had the opportunity to raise questions, provide suggestions, and help each other to improve their dissertation research. After the small group interactions, participants reported on their progress and new questions to the whole group. Plans for further joint activity were also discussed.  Broader Impacts  The funding for this CSCL 2017 Workshop grant supported early career researchers and late stage doctoral students to participate in mentored activities for academic professional development in the field of the learning sciences over the course for 1.5 days. The grant supported 17 early career scholars (7 US-based supported by grant funds) and 5 mentors (3 US-based supported by grant funds). It also supported 14 students (9 US-based supported by grant funds) and 5 mentors (2 US-based supported by grant funds). The International Society of the Learning Sciences (ISLS) supplied matching funds for non-US-based researchers fulfilling a long-standing partnership between ISLS and NSF. This ongoing partnership has enabled US researchers to garner valuable social and professional capital from other researchers around the world. It has additionally provided global perspectives that help to position US researchers to make a positive impact in educational issues that are facing the international community.  There were a number of beneficial outcomes experienced by both the early career and doctoral student researchers.  For the early career researchers, with respect to: 1. Refinement/reformulation of my research plans and projects, 89% reported substantial or moderate effect. 2. Identification of new lines of research, 67% reported substantial or moderate effect. 3. Awareness/understanding of new approaches to defining problems and/or new methods for conducting research in the Learning Sciences or CSCL, 67% reported substantial or moderate effect. 4. Awareness/understanding of how and where to publish, 63% reported substantial or moderate effect. 5. Awareness/understanding of how to develop a research program, write proposals, and find  funding, 83% reported substantial or moderate effect. 6. Collaborative network of learning science or CSCL researchers, 89% reported substantial or moderate effect. 7. Awareness/understanding of how to teach and mentor graduate students, 89% reported substantial or moderate effect. 8. Whether they would recommend the workshop to others, 100% would highly recommend or recommend attending.    For the doctoral students, with respect to: 1. Effect on refinement/reformulation of my dissertation topic, 93% reported a positive effect. 2. Effect on my motivation to complete my degree program, 86% reported a positive effect. 3. Identification of new lines of research, 71% reported a positive effect. 4. Awareness/understanding of important and interesting new lines of theory and research, 77% reported a positive effect. 5. Awareness/understanding of new approaches to defining problems and/or new methods for  conducting research in the Learning Sciences or CSCL, 100% reported a positive effect. 6. Awareness/understanding of how and where to publish, 93% reported a positive effect. 7. Awareness/understanding of research related to my interests in countries other than my own, 71% reported a positive effect. 8. Whether they would recommend the workshop to others, 100% would highly recommend or recommend attending.           Last Modified: 12/10/2019       Submitted by: Susan A Yoon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
