<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RIDIR: Collaborative Research: DAPPR: Diffusion Analytics for Public Policy Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>202820.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>202820</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Stability in social, technical, and financial systems, as well as the capacity of organizations to work across borders, requires consistency in public policy across jurisdictions. However, progress depends upon innovative policy solutions to society's problems. The transmission of laws and regulations across political boundaries averts a conflict between the incentives for innovation and consistency.  The current project will offer a database that allows the tracking of the spread of policies through the US states. The database will be disseminated through project webpages. The web interface will also include advanced analytics that illuminate the pathways through which policies spread. Users will be able to download the data and software for their own custom analysis of policy transmission in the US states. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Policy diffusion has been a topic of focus across the social sciences for several decades, but due to limitations of data and computational technology, researchers have not taken a comprehensive look at patterns of diffusion across many different policies. The investigators propose to combine cutting-edge methods of text and network analysis to understand how policies, as represented in digitized text, spread through networks connecting the American states. The investigators will develop both data and computational methods that address the most pressing limitations to the study of policy diffusion networks. The project will result in two key contributions: (1) a comprehensive source of data with which to track the movement of policies from one state government to another, across three governing branches, and (2) a user-friendly, open source software package for understanding and visualizing diffusion networks from digitized records of policies. These resources will help researchers, public officials, advocacy groups, and other relevant stakeholders understand how to balance the competing goals of innovation and consistency in public policy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1637095</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frederick</FirstName>
<LastName>Boehmke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frederick J Boehmke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>frederick-boehmke@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3193352123</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000187779</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Iowa</Name>
<CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2 GILMORE HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>062761671</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF IOWA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>062761671</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName>Iowa City</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>522421409</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[341 Schaeffer Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8294</Code>
<Text>Data Infrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~202820</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Prof. Boehmke, in collaboration with his co-PIs Bruce Desmarais, Bill Franko, Jeff Harden, Yu-ru Lin, Rob McGrath, and Jason Windett, working on linked proposals, has completed work on his NSF-funded research project, "Collaborative Research: DAPPR: Diffusion Analytics for Public Policy Research." Prof. Boehmke worked for three years and under the original proposal and an extra twelve months under a no-cost extension to assist in building and analyzing a database for the U.S. states with the text of enacted bills (Franko), adopted rules (McGrath), and court of last resort decisions (Windett). Boehmke contributed data on the diffusion of specific policies across the states from the State Policy Innovation and Diffusion (SPID) database. The SPID data includes adoption dates for each of the 50 American states for 728 different policies coded by topic area and are posted online at the Dataverse at <a href="https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataverse/spid">https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataverse/spid</a>. PI Boehmke and his team at the University of Iowa have helped clean the three text databases and prepare consistent documentation in preparation for sharing them in a similar format. While the time period varies across the three branches, they overlap for a decade between 2000 and 2010. During that period the data include information and text on 639,265 legislative bills, 340,194 administrative rules, and 625,983 court decisions.</p> <p>In addition to preparing the full data for release, PI Boehmke and his collaborators have developed and applied new statistical techniques to generate additional information to assist researchers. First, they have used supervised text analysis to code each item by its topic are content. This facilitates comparison of these data to the SPID data and to Federal data on legislation and court decisions available through the Policy Agendas Project. Second, they have used the text of these measures to develop a statistical method to place them in a single left-right ideological dimension. This will allow comparison of the location of bills, rules, and court decisions within and across state and over time. Notably, these results indicate that the vast majority of these documents are centrally located with extreme locations relatively rare. Third, they have used existing text dictionaries to identify documents addressing morality policy. This will provide a more complete picture of the occurrence of morality policy in the US states.</p> <p>In addition to sharing the policy data and related outputs, the work has a produced a number of other broader impacts. The PIs organized a conference for nearly two dozen participants to discuss the data and related methods to be held during the Midwest Political Science Association's annual meeting in April 2020. This was postponed due to the COVID-19 pandemic but PI Lin plans to host this in the future. Along the way they have successfully employed women and minorities on the project, including undergraduates interested in learning more about the application of data analytics in Political Science. Two graduate students and three undergraduates worked on the project at Iowa. Both of the former have taken extensive coursework in data science with one PhD student graduating and receiving a tenure-track job in a data science department. Two of the undergraduates have pursued additional research opportunities with PI Boehmke and plan to pursue advanced degrees.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/25/2021<br>      Modified by: Frederick&nbsp;J&nbsp;Boehmke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1637095/1637095_10454380_1611589063637_graph-report01-topics--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1637095/1637095_10454380_1611589063637_graph-report01-topics--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Policy Activity in the U.S. States by Topic Area"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1637095/1637095_10454380_1611589063637_graph-report01-topics--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Policy Activity in the U.S. States by Topic Area"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Policy Activity in the U.S. States by Topic Area and by Branch of Government, 2000-2010</div> <div class="imageCredit">Frederick J. Boehmke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Frederick&nbsp;J&nbsp;Boehmke</div> <div class="imageTitle">Policy Activity in the U.S. States by Topic Area</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1637095/1637095_10454380_1611588972559_graph-report01-counts-bystate--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1637095/1637095_10454380_1611588972559_graph-report01-counts-bystate--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Policy Activity in the U.S. States by Branch of Government"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1637095/1637095_10454380_1611588972559_graph-report01-counts-bystate--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Policy Activity in the U.S. States by Branch of Government"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Policy Activity in the U.S. States by Branch of Government</div> <div class="imageCredit">Frederick J. Boehmke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Frederick&nbsp;J&nbsp;Boehmke</div> <div class="imageTitle">Policy Activity in the U.S. States by Branch of Government</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Prof. Boehmke, in collaboration with his co-PIs Bruce Desmarais, Bill Franko, Jeff Harden, Yu-ru Lin, Rob McGrath, and Jason Windett, working on linked proposals, has completed work on his NSF-funded research project, "Collaborative Research: DAPPR: Diffusion Analytics for Public Policy Research." Prof. Boehmke worked for three years and under the original proposal and an extra twelve months under a no-cost extension to assist in building and analyzing a database for the U.S. states with the text of enacted bills (Franko), adopted rules (McGrath), and court of last resort decisions (Windett). Boehmke contributed data on the diffusion of specific policies across the states from the State Policy Innovation and Diffusion (SPID) database. The SPID data includes adoption dates for each of the 50 American states for 728 different policies coded by topic area and are posted online at the Dataverse at https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataverse/spid. PI Boehmke and his team at the University of Iowa have helped clean the three text databases and prepare consistent documentation in preparation for sharing them in a similar format. While the time period varies across the three branches, they overlap for a decade between 2000 and 2010. During that period the data include information and text on 639,265 legislative bills, 340,194 administrative rules, and 625,983 court decisions.  In addition to preparing the full data for release, PI Boehmke and his collaborators have developed and applied new statistical techniques to generate additional information to assist researchers. First, they have used supervised text analysis to code each item by its topic are content. This facilitates comparison of these data to the SPID data and to Federal data on legislation and court decisions available through the Policy Agendas Project. Second, they have used the text of these measures to develop a statistical method to place them in a single left-right ideological dimension. This will allow comparison of the location of bills, rules, and court decisions within and across state and over time. Notably, these results indicate that the vast majority of these documents are centrally located with extreme locations relatively rare. Third, they have used existing text dictionaries to identify documents addressing morality policy. This will provide a more complete picture of the occurrence of morality policy in the US states.  In addition to sharing the policy data and related outputs, the work has a produced a number of other broader impacts. The PIs organized a conference for nearly two dozen participants to discuss the data and related methods to be held during the Midwest Political Science Association's annual meeting in April 2020. This was postponed due to the COVID-19 pandemic but PI Lin plans to host this in the future. Along the way they have successfully employed women and minorities on the project, including undergraduates interested in learning more about the application of data analytics in Political Science. Two graduate students and three undergraduates worked on the project at Iowa. Both of the former have taken extensive coursework in data science with one PhD student graduating and receiving a tenure-track job in a data science department. Two of the undergraduates have pursued additional research opportunities with PI Boehmke and plan to pursue advanced degrees.       Last Modified: 01/25/2021       Submitted by: Frederick J Boehmke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
