<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop on the Algorithmic, Mathematical, and Statistical Foundations of Data Science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nandini Kannan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nakannan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928104</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A workshop on the Algorithmic, Mathematical, and Statistical Foundations of Data Science will be held April 28-30, 2016 in Arlington, VA.  The event will bring together leading researchers in computer science, mathematics, and statistics to address foundational issues related to data science.  The objectives of the workshop are three-fold: (i) identify fundamental areas in the emerging discipline of Data Science where collaboration between computer scientists, mathematicians, and statisticians is necessary to achieve significant progress; (ii) Assess how collaboration between computer scientists, mathematicians, and statisticians could potentially contribute to workforce development by advancing and transforming the Data Science research training of Ph.D. students and post-docs; and (iii) Suggest different infrastructure modalities that could significantly promote and advance such collaborations.  The main deliverable of the workshop is a white paper that will serve as a guideline for professional societies and funding agencies.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The rapid emergence of the Big Data phenomenon presents both opportunities and challenges.   While massive data may allow the generation of models and the design of algorithms that have improved inferential power, such models and algorithms may be less successful on modest-sized data sets. The challenge for researchers is to develop theoretical principles that will allow the scaling of inference and learning to massive-scale datasets, and algorithms that control errors even in the presence of heterogeneity in the data generation and data sampling processes.  These challenges will require collaborations between researchers representing theoretical computer science, mathematics, statistics, machine learning and data mining, and high performance computing. This award supports a workshop that brings together leaders from these communities of researchers to discuss the challenges and opportunities for collaborative work in this developing field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1637436</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoming</FirstName>
<LastName>Huo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoming Huo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xiaoming@isye.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043850354</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000276730</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Petros</FirstName>
<LastName>Drineas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Petros Drineas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pdrineas@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2039013682</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000117416</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>2878</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CCF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>ALGORITHMIC FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~99998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A workshop on the Algorithmic, Mathematical, and Statistical Foundations of Data Science was held April 28-30, 2016 in Arlington, VA. The event brought together leading researchers in computer science, mathematics, and statistics to address foundational issues related to Data Science. The objectives of the workshop are threefold: (i) identify fundamental areas in the emerging discipline of Data Science where collaboration between computer scientists, mathematicians, and statisticians is necessary to achieve significant progress; (ii) Assess how collaboration between computer scientists, mathematicians, and statisticians could potentially contribute to workforce development by advancing and transforming the Data Science research training of Ph.D. students and post-docs; and (iii) Suggest different infrastructure modalities that could significantly promote and advance such collaborations. The main deliverable of the workshop is a white paper that will serve as a guideline for professional societies and funding agencies. The white paper can be downloaded at http://cs.rpi.edu/TFoDS/TFoDS_v5.pdf.<br /><br />The rapid emergence of the Big Data phenomenon presents both opportunities and challenges. While massive data may allow the generation of models and the design of algorithms that have improved inferential power, such models and algorithms may be less successful on modest-sized data sets. The challenge for researchers is to develop theoretical principles that will allow the scaling of inference and learning to massive-scale datasets, and algorithms that control errors even in the presence of heterogeneity in the data generation and data sampling processes. These challenges will require collaborations between researchers representing theoretical computer science, mathematics, statistics, machine learning and data mining, and high performance computing. This award supported a workshop that brought together leaders from these communities of researchers to discuss the challenges and opportunities for collaborative work in this developing field.<br /><br />Some major findings from the aforementioned workshop are as follows. Theoretical Foundations of Data Science (TFoDS) broadly refers to the subfield of data science that focuses on its theoretical foundations. These theoretical foundations are necessary in all aspects of Data Science, from the generation and collection of data to the analysis and the decision making processes. TFoDS will be intrinsically inter-disciplinary; Data Science problems do not respect the disciplinary boundaries that academic disciplines often tend to draw around particular domains. There are numerous fundamental areas in the emerging discipline of Data Science where collaboration between computer scientists, mathematicians and statisticians is necessary to achieve significant progress. Data Science is likely to grow into a new discipline, with TFoDS being at its heart, since theoretical foundations are of paramount importance in the development of any new scientific field. TFoDS should have strong interfaces to application domains. A TFoDS center or institute, funded by an agency such as the NSF, would be well-poised to enable and stimulate the formation and growth of TFoDS.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/07/2017<br>      Modified by: Xiaoming&nbsp;Huo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A workshop on the Algorithmic, Mathematical, and Statistical Foundations of Data Science was held April 28-30, 2016 in Arlington, VA. The event brought together leading researchers in computer science, mathematics, and statistics to address foundational issues related to Data Science. The objectives of the workshop are threefold: (i) identify fundamental areas in the emerging discipline of Data Science where collaboration between computer scientists, mathematicians, and statisticians is necessary to achieve significant progress; (ii) Assess how collaboration between computer scientists, mathematicians, and statisticians could potentially contribute to workforce development by advancing and transforming the Data Science research training of Ph.D. students and post-docs; and (iii) Suggest different infrastructure modalities that could significantly promote and advance such collaborations. The main deliverable of the workshop is a white paper that will serve as a guideline for professional societies and funding agencies. The white paper can be downloaded at http://cs.rpi.edu/TFoDS/TFoDS_v5.pdf.  The rapid emergence of the Big Data phenomenon presents both opportunities and challenges. While massive data may allow the generation of models and the design of algorithms that have improved inferential power, such models and algorithms may be less successful on modest-sized data sets. The challenge for researchers is to develop theoretical principles that will allow the scaling of inference and learning to massive-scale datasets, and algorithms that control errors even in the presence of heterogeneity in the data generation and data sampling processes. These challenges will require collaborations between researchers representing theoretical computer science, mathematics, statistics, machine learning and data mining, and high performance computing. This award supported a workshop that brought together leaders from these communities of researchers to discuss the challenges and opportunities for collaborative work in this developing field.  Some major findings from the aforementioned workshop are as follows. Theoretical Foundations of Data Science (TFoDS) broadly refers to the subfield of data science that focuses on its theoretical foundations. These theoretical foundations are necessary in all aspects of Data Science, from the generation and collection of data to the analysis and the decision making processes. TFoDS will be intrinsically inter-disciplinary; Data Science problems do not respect the disciplinary boundaries that academic disciplines often tend to draw around particular domains. There are numerous fundamental areas in the emerging discipline of Data Science where collaboration between computer scientists, mathematicians and statisticians is necessary to achieve significant progress. Data Science is likely to grow into a new discipline, with TFoDS being at its heart, since theoretical foundations are of paramount importance in the development of any new scientific field. TFoDS should have strong interfaces to application domains. A TFoDS center or institute, funded by an agency such as the NSF, would be well-poised to enable and stimulate the formation and growth of TFoDS.       Last Modified: 06/07/2017       Submitted by: Xiaoming Huo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
