<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID:  Migration Waves</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>74787.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74787</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brian Humes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhumes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927284</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>General Summary&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;What sparks sudden migrant outflows?  In 2015, more than a million migrants braved the Mediterranean Sea and other routes seeking asylum in Europe.  Yet, conditions of violence in Syria were not new, dating at least to the start of the civil war in 2011.  Moreover, not just Syrians arrived on European shores; the crisis has attracted migrants from countries with long-standing, largely unchanged conflicts and poverty.  This project explores how sudden waves of migration emerge from persistent conditions.  In contrast to dominant explanations centered on changes in violence in sending countries, the PIs propose a theory rooted in migrants' expectations about their reception in host countries.  Initial signals that migrants will be welcomed, especially if they are perceived to be part of a refugee crisis, lead others to follow, even without any changes in violence or economic conditions in their home country.  They also examine alternative explanations that emphasize the role of social networks and smugglers in migrant waves.  By identifying the factors that cause and perpetuate migrant waves, this project will help policymakers and humanitarian aid organizations better prepare for future waves and better allocate resources to the current crisis. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the factors that begin and perpetuate migrant waves requires real-time information on migrants' experiences, knowledge, and expectations about the policy environment.  The PIs conduct a survey of 1000 migrants in port cities in Turkey and Greece, where migrants have just crossed into or plan to depart for Europe.  The PIs use local refugee registries and translate the survey into several languages to ensure that the survey is representative of the diverse migrants traveling toward Europe.  The PIs ask migrants directly about the conditions under which they left their homes, as well as their decision-making process.  While most theories suggest that direct threats lead migrants to abandon their homes, the PIs propose that migrants will not report such changes.  Instead, the choices of others in their community and perceptions of policy conditions should strongly influence their decisions to migrate. The PIs also use an embedded survey experiment to test how information about the size of the migrant wave, its composition, and the policy environment influence migrants' decisions.  This original survey data on the views of migrants themselves will provide important insight into the largest refugee crisis since World War II.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1638952</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alisha</FirstName>
<LastName>Holland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alisha Holland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aholland@fas.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174955501</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000609861</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/10/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
<LastName>Peters</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Margaret E Peters</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mepeters@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7187570958</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000718390</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
<LastName>Peters</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Margaret E Peters</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mepeters@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7187570958</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000718390</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/10/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thania</FirstName>
<LastName>Sanchez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thania Sanchez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>thania.sanchez@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2037854689</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000718525</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thania</FirstName>
<LastName>Sanchez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thania Sanchez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>thania.sanchez@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2037854689</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000718525</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/10/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 208327]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065118955</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 Prospect St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1371</Code>
<Text>Political Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~74787</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Migration Waves project sought to survey migrants in real time about their decisions to migrate, where to migrate, and their views on various migration policies.&nbsp; The project surveyed 1437 Syrian and Iraqi subjects located in Iraq, Jordan, Syria, and Turkey. We had three main research questions we pursued in this project and will discuss each below.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Explaining Migrant Waves.&nbsp;&nbsp; </span>Why do migrant waves&mdash;sudden large increases in the flow of migrants to a single destination&mdash;form?&nbsp; Conventional wisdom is that violence and economic deprivation spark migrant waves.&nbsp; However, sharp spikes in migration often emerge from long-standing problems of violence and poverty.&nbsp; We propose an alternative theory: conditions of violence and poverty lead individuals to invest in learning about the migration process.&nbsp; In circumstances of high information, a policy opening in a destination country can unleash major migratory flows. To understand why migrant waves form, we asked migrants themselves through a survey of potential and actual migrants during the Syrian refugee crisis. Consistent with our theory, we find that respondents are highly knowledgeable about political conditions in Europe and that expectations about the ability to stay strongly shape desires to migrate.&nbsp; Additionally, when we provide information about welcoming policy conditions to respondents who had less information about migration in a survey experiment, they are more likely to want to migrate. </li> <li><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Destination Choice.&nbsp; </span>Previous research on how migrants choose where to settle has looked at where migrants end up, assuming that they reached their desired location.&nbsp; But many plans change in the migration process. &nbsp;To improve our understanding of the preferred destination choices of migrants, and why they choose certain places, we asked migrants during the Syrian refugee crisis about their desired destinations.&nbsp; This design has the advantage that migrants are actively making destination choices, and their plans have not been changed by logistical challenges.&nbsp; We find that forced migrants seek stability above all else, and are attracted to destinations where they can work and be secure. We used a conjoint survey experiment to see the relative weight of different factors in their decision-making. &nbsp;We found that:<ol> <li>Contrary to many media and political sources, most refugees do not want to permanently migrate to Europe. They want to go back to their home countries when the fighting ends. </li> <li>&nbsp;Among the various factors that migrants consider in choosing a destination, the most important one is the ability to work in the destination country. This is more pronounced for migrants that experienced the worse violence at home. Considerations of welfare benefits or other country attributes like shared religion and political freedoms were secondary. </li> <li><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Ethics of Migration.</span> The project asked migrants about their views on the ethics of various migration policies. For instance, we wanted to how migrants understand which migrants deserve asylum, and given the rapid policy changes, whether receiving countries (like the EU) paying other countries (like Turkey) to keep the refugees was seen as a fair policy. &nbsp;Using a conjoint experiment we examined which factors matter most when deciding who should get asylum.&nbsp; We found that:<ol> <li>Migrants think that those who have suffered death threats at home deserve priority in the asylum process, but other factors such as level of education or religion were not reasons to grant asylum to some rather than others. </li> <li>&nbsp;Migrants think that paying other countries to keep migrants is legitimate as long as they provide sufficient funds for the migrants. &nbsp;The implication is that deals, such as those between the EU and Turkey or the US and Mexico, might be legitimate from the perspective of migrants, as long as they guarantee stable living conditions for migrants.&nbsp; </li> </ol></li> </ol></li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In conclusion, this project shed light on three key issues for understanding migration flows. By understanding when migrants migrate, where they migrate to, and how they view migration policies, the project contributes to a growing body of research on migration through a unique survey of migrants themselves. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/25/2017<br>      Modified by: Thania&nbsp;Sanchez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Migration Waves project sought to survey migrants in real time about their decisions to migrate, where to migrate, and their views on various migration policies.  The project surveyed 1437 Syrian and Iraqi subjects located in Iraq, Jordan, Syria, and Turkey. We had three main research questions we pursued in this project and will discuss each below.     Explaining Migrant Waves.   Why do migrant waves&mdash;sudden large increases in the flow of migrants to a single destination&mdash;form?  Conventional wisdom is that violence and economic deprivation spark migrant waves.  However, sharp spikes in migration often emerge from long-standing problems of violence and poverty.  We propose an alternative theory: conditions of violence and poverty lead individuals to invest in learning about the migration process.  In circumstances of high information, a policy opening in a destination country can unleash major migratory flows. To understand why migrant waves form, we asked migrants themselves through a survey of potential and actual migrants during the Syrian refugee crisis. Consistent with our theory, we find that respondents are highly knowledgeable about political conditions in Europe and that expectations about the ability to stay strongly shape desires to migrate.  Additionally, when we provide information about welcoming policy conditions to respondents who had less information about migration in a survey experiment, they are more likely to want to migrate.  Destination Choice.  Previous research on how migrants choose where to settle has looked at where migrants end up, assuming that they reached their desired location.  But many plans change in the migration process.  To improve our understanding of the preferred destination choices of migrants, and why they choose certain places, we asked migrants during the Syrian refugee crisis about their desired destinations.  This design has the advantage that migrants are actively making destination choices, and their plans have not been changed by logistical challenges.  We find that forced migrants seek stability above all else, and are attracted to destinations where they can work and be secure. We used a conjoint survey experiment to see the relative weight of different factors in their decision-making.  We found that: Contrary to many media and political sources, most refugees do not want to permanently migrate to Europe. They want to go back to their home countries when the fighting ends.   Among the various factors that migrants consider in choosing a destination, the most important one is the ability to work in the destination country. This is more pronounced for migrants that experienced the worse violence at home. Considerations of welfare benefits or other country attributes like shared religion and political freedoms were secondary.  Ethics of Migration. The project asked migrants about their views on the ethics of various migration policies. For instance, we wanted to how migrants understand which migrants deserve asylum, and given the rapid policy changes, whether receiving countries (like the EU) paying other countries (like Turkey) to keep the refugees was seen as a fair policy.  Using a conjoint experiment we examined which factors matter most when deciding who should get asylum.  We found that: Migrants think that those who have suffered death threats at home deserve priority in the asylum process, but other factors such as level of education or religion were not reasons to grant asylum to some rather than others.   Migrants think that paying other countries to keep migrants is legitimate as long as they provide sufficient funds for the migrants.  The implication is that deals, such as those between the EU and Turkey or the US and Mexico, might be legitimate from the perspective of migrants, as long as they guarantee stable living conditions for migrants.          In conclusion, this project shed light on three key issues for understanding migration flows. By understanding when migrants migrate, where they migrate to, and how they view migration policies, the project contributes to a growing body of research on migration through a unique survey of migrants themselves.            Last Modified: 07/25/2017       Submitted by: Thania Sanchez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
