<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support: ACM International Workshop on Big Data in Life Sciences, Seattle, WA, October 2, 2016</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mitra Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928649</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The ACM International Workshop on Big Data in Life Sciences (BigLS) is a workshop series focusing on computational and data challenges in broadly defined life sciences. The workshop was initiated in 2013, and it is hosted together with the ACM Conference on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology and Health Informatics - the flagship conference of the Association for Computing Machinery Special Interest Group on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Biomedical Informatics (SIGBio). The workshop brings together leading researchers and practitioners working on a diverse range of big data problems relating to biology and medicine, and engages them in a discussion about current big data questions, the state of computational tools and analytics, the challenges and the future trends within life sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will support up to ten students and postdoctoral researchers from US academic institutions to attend BigLS 2016 to be held on October 2, 2016 in Seattle, WA. Awardees will be selected via a widely advertised competitive process involving the submission of a travel grant application, and review by the program committee. Preference will be given to women and underrepresented minority groups, first-generation college students, and undergraduate researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Big data problems and challenges have become a reality in modern day computational biology, bioinformatics and biomedical informatics. The workshop will feature peer-reviewed papers and invited talks on five key research themes that underline big data research in life sciences: 1) scalable algorithms and techniques for big data analytics in molecular biology; 2) statistical and integrative approaches to big data biology; 3) emerging machine learning and AI techniques for big data biology; 4) high performance computing methods and software for big data biology; 5) software and hardware foundations for managing big data in biomedical informatics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1638757</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jaroslaw</FirstName>
<LastName>Zola</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jaroslaw S Zola</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jzola@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5157081232</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000572006</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038633251</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142031121</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>Algorithmic Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7931</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant was to broaden students participation in the ACM International Workshop on Big Data in Life Sciences (BigLS, http://www.bigls.org) held in Seattle, WA on October 2, 2016, with the goal of preparing the future generation scientific workforce in the area of big data applications in life sciences. To this end, seven students from the U.S. academic institutions were selected and received support to partially cover the participation costs (e.g. travel, registration free). The selection process was based on the merit criteria, including quality and scope of students' work and its relevance to the ACM BigLS topics of interest. Priority was given to women and underrepresented minority groups, first generation college students, and undergraduate researchers. Selected students participated in multiple educational activities, including presentations of their on-going work, networking with recognized experts and peers in the field, and participation in the dedicated mentoring sessions. During the mentoring sessions, the students freely interacted with the invited top researchers in the big data and life sciences area. These interactions included face-to-face Q&amp;A, review of students posters, and general discussions going beyond pure research, e.g. covering career development, peer-review process, etc. The grant significantly contributed towards building a vibrant community around big data issues in life sciences, a strategically important topic in biomedical informatics and computational biology.<br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/24/2017<br>      Modified by: Jaroslaw&nbsp;S&nbsp;Zola</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant was to broaden students participation in the ACM International Workshop on Big Data in Life Sciences (BigLS, http://www.bigls.org) held in Seattle, WA on October 2, 2016, with the goal of preparing the future generation scientific workforce in the area of big data applications in life sciences. To this end, seven students from the U.S. academic institutions were selected and received support to partially cover the participation costs (e.g. travel, registration free). The selection process was based on the merit criteria, including quality and scope of students' work and its relevance to the ACM BigLS topics of interest. Priority was given to women and underrepresented minority groups, first generation college students, and undergraduate researchers. Selected students participated in multiple educational activities, including presentations of their on-going work, networking with recognized experts and peers in the field, and participation in the dedicated mentoring sessions. During the mentoring sessions, the students freely interacted with the invited top researchers in the big data and life sciences area. These interactions included face-to-face Q&amp;A, review of students posters, and general discussions going beyond pure research, e.g. covering career development, peer-review process, etc. The grant significantly contributed towards building a vibrant community around big data issues in life sciences, a strategically important topic in biomedical informatics and computational biology.         Last Modified: 07/24/2017       Submitted by: Jaroslaw S Zola]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
