<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2016 Solid State Chemistry GRC: Strategies for Materials Discovery: Progress Toward Tomorrow's Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Birgit Schwenzer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschwenz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924771</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON TECHNICAL &lt;br/&gt;The 2014 Gordon Research Conference (GRC) and Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) on 2016 Solid State Chemistry GRC: Strategies for Materials Discovery: Progress Toward Tomorrow's Materials funded by the Solid State and Materials Chemistry Program will be held at Colby-Sawyer College in New London New Hampshire with the GRS meeting on July 16-17 and the GRS immediately following from July 17-22, 2016. The GRC meetings will directly impact all of the attendees by providing an open atmosphere for exchange of ideas on the cutting edge of Solid State Chemistry and it will provide a unique forum to bring together experts, young scientists, and students to disclose unpublished data, to challenge and discuss novel ideas, and to push the frontiers of science and innovation forward. New collaborations can be formed and new ideas generated that would not otherwise occur if not for these important conferences. Speakers are expected to convey cutting edge information to their colleagues with the objective that this disclosure will stimulate expansive discussion among all attendees and progressively advance the field. The inclusive, collegial atmosphere of the meeting, and the emphasis on sharing previously unpublished information, enables the cultivation of innovative approaches to address the most important challenges facing our world. This strategy is a hallmark of GRC and has served the scientific community and facilitated the advancement of science for over eight decades.  The GRS, which is a meeting solely for graduate students and postdoctoral fellows, will promote an environment to introduce new graduate students into a conference atmosphere, allow all students and fellows to present their work in a low stress environment, and promote networking among peers. The GRS will also feature a career panel with mentors from academic, national laboratory, and industrial sources to help empower the future of the solid state community with knowledge. The intent of the GRC meeting is to promote the exchange of ideas and the building of partnerships between researchers from the academic world, industry and government laboratories. Many younger scientists are included in the program along with more senior and distinguished scientists, promising to make the presentations and discussions representative of new directions in the field. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL &lt;br/&gt;The focus of the Solid State Chemistry GRC will be materials for energy and environment applications, and the conference highlights the challenges that we face in producing enough energy while maintaining our environment. To overcome this important problem, we will need to design new compounds, optimize existing materials and understand the relationship of structure and physical properties and it will require a multidisciplinary approach. This conference will bring together array of established scientists and students to discuss the latest advances and challenges in Solid State Chemistry.  Speakers and poster presenters are explicitly encouraged to emphasize advances, unpublished results, new and risky ideas on a variety of current topics. The organizers strongly encourage active contribution to discussions and participation in poster sessions, which offer an excellent opportunity for presenting new and exciting research. Solid State Chemistry is a multidisciplinary field whose importance continues to increase not only with the discovery of new classes of materials, but also through a deeper understanding of the diverse properties of solids made possible by modern techniques. The importance and scope of the field has grown in response to the continuing challenge to understand, control, and predict the structures and properties of solids and the need to synthesize new materials with enhanced physical properties.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/30/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1638235</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hans-Conrad</FirstName>
<LastName>zur Loye</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hans-Conrad zur Loye</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zurloye@mailbox.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8037776916</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000193109</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/30/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075712877</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[512 Liberty Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1762</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8607</Code>
<Text>Solar Energy Capture&amp;Conver</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~25000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Operational Summary</span></strong></p> <p>The Gordon Research Conference (GRC) and Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) on Solid State Chemistry were held at Colby-Sawyer College in New London, New Hampshire from July 16-22, 2016.&nbsp;&nbsp; The meeting covered a variety of scientific topics and the content presented was highly rated by participants.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default"><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">&nbsp;</span></strong><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Participants</span></strong></p> <p>The Conference was well-attended with 177 participants. Scientists from academia represented 91.5% of the participants while attendees from government accounted for 6% and those from industry totaled 2.5%. The meeting also attracted a strong mix of young investigators and senior scientists.&nbsp; Students and post-docs accounted for 37% of all attendees. Approximately 32% of the participants at the 2016 meeting were women.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p class="Default"><strong>Seminar Participants</strong></p> <p>The Seminar was well-attended with 51 participants. Scientists from academia represented 90% of the participants while attendees from government accounted for 6% and attendees from industry accounted for 4%. Students and post docs combined accounted for 84% of all attendees. Approximately 31% of the participants at the 2016 seminar were women.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Program &ndash; GRC</span></strong></p> <p>The discovery of new materials and associated desirable properties has been a driving force behind chemical innovation for centuries. In all cases, there was a <em>First-Material</em>, the archetype in which the phenomenon was first observed, the one that stimulated further investigations and that ultimately became the foundation of new technologies. What are the approaches that we believe are most likely to result in the <em>discovery</em> of new compositions with complex structures and potentially new properties, a new <em>First-Material</em>? And once a new structure/composition has been discovered, how do we take advantage of structure property concepts to transition from this starting point to a successful modification of the structure, the composition and the observed physical properties to create tomorrow's material? <br /> <br /> This conference had a focus on materials discovery, and provided insights via research talks by researchers from industry, national laboratories and academia and provided a perspective on the growing field of solid state chemistry, on novel synthetic approaches, on novel materials, and on emerging applications. The presentation of unpublished research stimulated discussion and the exchange of ideas concerning the synthesis and application of new materials at the frontier of solid state materials chemistry. Emphasis was on synthesis, structure property relationships and their role in promoting material enhancements and material applications. <br /> <br /> Speakers and poster presenters were explicitly encouraged to emphasize advances, unpublished results, and new ideas on materials synthesis, structural analysis, and physical properties characterization. The organizers strongly encouraged active contribution to discussions and participation in poster sessions, which offered an excellent opportunity for presenting and learning about new and exciting research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Program &ndash; GRS</span></strong></p> <p>The discovery of a new functional material is just the beginning of a long process that may culminate in an application. Following the initial discovery, the material must be thoroughly characterized, have its physical properties measured and, undoubtedly, optimized to enable its use in an existing or new application. This deceptively straightforward, yet multifaceted process involves tremendous effort, where every step requires significant amounts of time and success. <br /> <br /> This meeting on solid state chemistry enabled graduate students, post-docs, and other scientists with comparable levels of experience and education to present and discuss the issues faced in materials discovery, optimization of structure or composition, and improvement of the desired properties. By offering a seminar that promotes the sharing of unpublished work, both in poster and oral presentation form, discussions amongst fellow scientists in the field of solid state chemistry lead to the exchange of ideas concerning the process leading to the discovery of new materials.<br /> <br /> This seminar focused on young scientists sharing unpublished research, and gave an opportunity for students and post-docs to present their research via posters and oral presentations. A career panel, including representatives from industry, national laboratories, and academia also took place during the two-day meeting.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Feedback</span></strong></p> <p>Participants had an opportunity to provide feedback at the end of the Conference. The feedback collected from the meeting was extremely positive. Evaluations included numerous positive remarks regarding the excellent speaker sessions, discussion periods, and networking opportunities during the poster sessions.&nbsp; Feedback from the GRS included positive remarks regarding the poster sessions and career panel.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>GRC would like to thank the National Science Foundation for its continued support of the meetings.&nbsp; The contributions received from the National Science Foundation have been critical to the success of the conferences and are having a measurable impact in advancing the frontiers of science worldwide.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/13/2016<br>      Modified by: Hans-Conrad&nbsp;Zur Loye</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Operational Summary  The Gordon Research Conference (GRC) and Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) on Solid State Chemistry were held at Colby-Sawyer College in New London, New Hampshire from July 16-22, 2016.   The meeting covered a variety of scientific topics and the content presented was highly rated by participants.    Conference Participants  The Conference was well-attended with 177 participants. Scientists from academia represented 91.5% of the participants while attendees from government accounted for 6% and those from industry totaled 2.5%. The meeting also attracted a strong mix of young investigators and senior scientists.  Students and post-docs accounted for 37% of all attendees. Approximately 32% of the participants at the 2016 meeting were women.    Seminar Participants  The Seminar was well-attended with 51 participants. Scientists from academia represented 90% of the participants while attendees from government accounted for 6% and attendees from industry accounted for 4%. Students and post docs combined accounted for 84% of all attendees. Approximately 31% of the participants at the 2016 seminar were women.  Conference Program &ndash; GRC  The discovery of new materials and associated desirable properties has been a driving force behind chemical innovation for centuries. In all cases, there was a First-Material, the archetype in which the phenomenon was first observed, the one that stimulated further investigations and that ultimately became the foundation of new technologies. What are the approaches that we believe are most likely to result in the discovery of new compositions with complex structures and potentially new properties, a new First-Material? And once a new structure/composition has been discovered, how do we take advantage of structure property concepts to transition from this starting point to a successful modification of the structure, the composition and the observed physical properties to create tomorrow's material?     This conference had a focus on materials discovery, and provided insights via research talks by researchers from industry, national laboratories and academia and provided a perspective on the growing field of solid state chemistry, on novel synthetic approaches, on novel materials, and on emerging applications. The presentation of unpublished research stimulated discussion and the exchange of ideas concerning the synthesis and application of new materials at the frontier of solid state materials chemistry. Emphasis was on synthesis, structure property relationships and their role in promoting material enhancements and material applications.     Speakers and poster presenters were explicitly encouraged to emphasize advances, unpublished results, and new ideas on materials synthesis, structural analysis, and physical properties characterization. The organizers strongly encouraged active contribution to discussions and participation in poster sessions, which offered an excellent opportunity for presenting and learning about new and exciting research.     Conference Program &ndash; GRS  The discovery of a new functional material is just the beginning of a long process that may culminate in an application. Following the initial discovery, the material must be thoroughly characterized, have its physical properties measured and, undoubtedly, optimized to enable its use in an existing or new application. This deceptively straightforward, yet multifaceted process involves tremendous effort, where every step requires significant amounts of time and success.     This meeting on solid state chemistry enabled graduate students, post-docs, and other scientists with comparable levels of experience and education to present and discuss the issues faced in materials discovery, optimization of structure or composition, and improvement of the desired properties. By offering a seminar that promotes the sharing of unpublished work, both in poster and oral presentation form, discussions amongst fellow scientists in the field of solid state chemistry lead to the exchange of ideas concerning the process leading to the discovery of new materials.    This seminar focused on young scientists sharing unpublished research, and gave an opportunity for students and post-docs to present their research via posters and oral presentations. A career panel, including representatives from industry, national laboratories, and academia also took place during the two-day meeting.     Conference Feedback  Participants had an opportunity to provide feedback at the end of the Conference. The feedback collected from the meeting was extremely positive. Evaluations included numerous positive remarks regarding the excellent speaker sessions, discussion periods, and networking opportunities during the poster sessions.  Feedback from the GRS included positive remarks regarding the poster sessions and career panel.     GRC would like to thank the National Science Foundation for its continued support of the meetings.  The contributions received from the National Science Foundation have been critical to the success of the conferences and are having a measurable impact in advancing the frontiers of science worldwide.       Last Modified: 10/13/2016       Submitted by: Hans-Conrad Zur Loye]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
