<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Proposal: MSB-FRA: Alternative Ecological Futures for the American Residential Macrosystem</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>267001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>267001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Blood</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eblood@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924349</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An apparent, but untested result of changes to the urban landscape is the homogenization of cities, such that neighborhoods in very different parts of the country increasingly exhibit similar patterns in their road systems, residential lots, commercial sites, and aquatic areas; cities have now become more similar to each other than to the native ecosystems that they replaced. This research builds on the team?s prior NSF funded research on the ?ecological homogenization? of the ?American Residential Macrosystem (ARM)? and specifically investigates factors that contribute to stability and/or changes in the ARM. The aim is to determine how factors that effect change?such as shifts in human demographics, desires for biodiversity and water conservation, regulations that govern water use and quality, and dispersal of organisms?will interact with factors that contribute to stability such as social norms, property values, neighborhood and city covenants and laws, and commercial interests. The project will determine ecological implications of alternative futures of the ARM for the assembly of ecological communities, ecosystem function, and responses to environmental change and disturbance at parcel (ecosystem), landscape (city), regional (Metropolitan Statistical Area) and continental scales. Five types of residential parcels as well as embedded semi-natural interstitial ecosystems will be studied, across six U.S. cities (Boston, Baltimore, Miami, Minneapolis-St. Paul, Phoenix, and Los Angeles). Education and outreach work will focus on K-12 teachers and students and on collaborative policy efforts with city, county, and state environmental managers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates urbanization?s impact on the ecological homogenization of the American Residential Macrosystem (ARM) in terms of plant biodiversity, soil carbon and nitrogen cycle pools and processes, microclimate, hydrography, and land cover. This similarity of ecological characteristics is driven by complex and dynamic human actions at multiple scales?e.g., parcel, neighborhood, and region?that will shape the structure and function of the ARM over 50 to 100 year time frames, with potentially significant continental scale effects on ecological processes and environmental quality. This research addresses two core questions. First, what factors contribute to maintenance and change in the ARM? While this macrosystem is a relatively homogeneous mixture of grass lawns, shrubs, trees and impervious surfaces, there is a critical need to determine how drivers of change such as shifts in human population and ethnicity, increasing desires for biodiversity and water conservation, and regulations governing water use and quality will interact with stabilizing factors such as social norms, property values, neighborhood and city covenants and laws, and commercial interests. Researchers will test the hypothesis that that although dispersal from natural and interstitial areas, climate change, and changes in homeowner knowledge will promote ecological change; institutions, norms and values will function as counteracting, stabilizing forces on these ecological dynamics. This hypothesis will be tested by evaluating the factors that motivate change and stability at multiple scales. Results will be used to produce quantitative, data-based scenarios of future land-use patterns in the ARM. Second, what are the ecological implications of alternative futures of this macrosystem for community assembly and ecosystem function at parcel (ecosystem), landscape (city), regional (Metropolitan Statistical Area), and continental scales?  The hypothesis to be tested is that management that promotes nutrient- and water-use efficient and wildlife-supporting plants as well as lower inputs of water and nutrients will give rise to greater regional biodiversity across trophic levels, higher nutrient retention, lower water use, and reduced runoff and losses of soil carbon and nitrogen from residential yards at the regional scale. Five types of residential parcels that vary in management goals and intensity and embedded semi-natural interstitial ecosystems will be studied in six U.S. cities across the U.S. (Boston, Baltimore, Miami, Minneapolis-St. Paul, Phoenix, and Los Angeles), to quantify influences on ecological dynamics. This information will be linked to land use scenarios to address the regional and continental-scale impacts of these effects. Three postdocs will be mentored as co-investigators on this project. The research program will also include interaction with municipal decision makers focused on sustainability and add a new ?Panel of Experts? feature to the YardMap citizen science program developed at Cornell University.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1638657</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Heffernan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James B Heffernan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>james.heffernan@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196814193</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000505299</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277080328</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7959</Code>
<Text>MacroSysBIO &amp; NEON-Enabled Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~137840</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~129161</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this work was to improve our understanding of the capacity for ecological change in residential landscapes.&nbsp; We evaluated this potential at local scale by comparing different yard management approaches (wildlife friendly, low runoff, low intensity lawn, and high intensity lawn) in terms of ecological characteristics.&nbsp; We measured plant, bird, and insect diversity, soil fertility, and plant water use in 30 yards and natural habitats in each of 6 US cities (Boston, Baltimore, Miami, Minneapolis-St. Paul, Phoenix, and Los Angeles).&nbsp; The response of these characteristics to yard management differed among variables and among cities.&nbsp; Plant, insect, and bird diversity all increased in wildlife friendly yards, and bird diversity also depended on abundance of impervious surfaces in the surrounding neighborhood.&nbsp; &nbsp;Species-area relationships varied among yard treatments, suggesting greater species turnover among wildlife-friendly yards than among high-intensity yards.&nbsp; Effects of yard management on soil and plant characteristics were more varied.&nbsp; Overall, these results indicate an important capacity for local yard management to improve urban ecological diversity and soil, air and water quality, but also ultimately points to the need for urban structural change at broader scales.</p> <p>We also evaluated how land cover&nbsp;composition of small watersheds is expected to change, focusing on projections in the SE United States.&nbsp; We found that urban land expansion in the region was greater under a scenario of fossil fuel intensification (ICLUS SSP5) than a business-as-usual scenario (ICLUS SSP2).&nbsp; Importantly, in both scenarios we found minimal loss of natural land covers; instead, urban land is expected to expand into current agricultural land.&nbsp; This finding has a few important conservation implications.&nbsp; First, watersheds with high natural land cover will see relatively little change, suggesting that the best conserved streams and waterways will be least affected by future land use change.&nbsp; Second, the dramatic loss af agricultural land in urban regions has potentially important implications for local and regional food systems and cultures.&nbsp; Finally, our understanding of the ecological consequences of urban land expansion, particularly in the SE United States, must account for the physical, chemical, and biological legacies of antecedent agricultural land uses.&nbsp;</p> <p>Beyond our specific findings, this work has create new collaborative networks and data infrastructure that will motivate and facilitate more studies of urban systems that capture structure and process at scales ranging from the parcel to the continent.&nbsp; Across all participating institutions, this project provided training and experience in urban ecological study for 6 post-docs, 8 graduate students, and dozens of undergraduate students and technicians.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/21/2021<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;B&nbsp;Heffernan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this work was to improve our understanding of the capacity for ecological change in residential landscapes.  We evaluated this potential at local scale by comparing different yard management approaches (wildlife friendly, low runoff, low intensity lawn, and high intensity lawn) in terms of ecological characteristics.  We measured plant, bird, and insect diversity, soil fertility, and plant water use in 30 yards and natural habitats in each of 6 US cities (Boston, Baltimore, Miami, Minneapolis-St. Paul, Phoenix, and Los Angeles).  The response of these characteristics to yard management differed among variables and among cities.  Plant, insect, and bird diversity all increased in wildlife friendly yards, and bird diversity also depended on abundance of impervious surfaces in the surrounding neighborhood.   Species-area relationships varied among yard treatments, suggesting greater species turnover among wildlife-friendly yards than among high-intensity yards.  Effects of yard management on soil and plant characteristics were more varied.  Overall, these results indicate an important capacity for local yard management to improve urban ecological diversity and soil, air and water quality, but also ultimately points to the need for urban structural change at broader scales.  We also evaluated how land cover composition of small watersheds is expected to change, focusing on projections in the SE United States.  We found that urban land expansion in the region was greater under a scenario of fossil fuel intensification (ICLUS SSP5) than a business-as-usual scenario (ICLUS SSP2).  Importantly, in both scenarios we found minimal loss of natural land covers; instead, urban land is expected to expand into current agricultural land.  This finding has a few important conservation implications.  First, watersheds with high natural land cover will see relatively little change, suggesting that the best conserved streams and waterways will be least affected by future land use change.  Second, the dramatic loss af agricultural land in urban regions has potentially important implications for local and regional food systems and cultures.  Finally, our understanding of the ecological consequences of urban land expansion, particularly in the SE United States, must account for the physical, chemical, and biological legacies of antecedent agricultural land uses.   Beyond our specific findings, this work has create new collaborative networks and data infrastructure that will motivate and facilitate more studies of urban systems that capture structure and process at scales ranging from the parcel to the continent.  Across all participating institutions, this project provided training and experience in urban ecological study for 6 post-docs, 8 graduate students, and dozens of undergraduate students and technicians.       Last Modified: 06/21/2021       Submitted by: James B Heffernan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
