<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Enhancing Global Connections:  ICSU, PSA, and the IVO</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1567448.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1567448</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cassandra Dudka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdudka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927250</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the Board on International Scientific Organizations (BISO) of the National Academies of Science (NAS), which functions as the U.S. National Committee to the International Council for Science (ICSU) and serves as the focal point for ICSU-related activities in the United States. It manages U.S. membership in ICSU and has oversight of many of the national committees that serve as liaisons to unions, committees and programs federated under the ICSU umbrella. BISO's primary goal is to support effective U.S. participation and strong leadership in the ICSU network in response to growing needs in international science and technology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ICSU, a non-governmental organization with a global membership of national scientific bodies (122 Members, representing 142 countries) and International Scientific Unions (31 Members).  ICSU?s mission is to strengthen international science for the benefit of society.   To do this, ICSU mobilizes the knowledge and resources of the international science community to 1) identify and address major issues of importance to science and society; 2) facilitate interaction among scientists across all disciplines and from all countries; 3) promote the participation of all scientists in the international scientific endeavor; and 4) provide independent, authoritative advice to stimulate constructive dialogue between the scientific community and governments, civil society, and the private sector.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award also provides dues payment to the Pacific Science Association (PSA). PSA is an interdisciplinary regional organization within ICSU whose goal is to advance science and technology in support of sustainable development in the Pacific region. Based in Honolulu, Hawaii, PSA has a long history of linking scientists in the U.S. with their counterparts on the Pacific's rim and islands. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This three-year award will enable BISO to continue to manage U.S. participation in ICSU. The award provides costs associated with the support and management of the U.S. National Committees to ICSU and organizational activities of adhering U.S. committees representing the diverse disciplines that participate in ICSU activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1639931</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Bailey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katherine E Bailey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kbailey@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023342606</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000345373</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>A. Ester</FirstName>
<LastName>Sztein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>A. Ester Sztein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>esztein@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023343049</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000074607</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 Fifth Street, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7731</Code>
<Text>Other Global Learning &amp; Trng</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5918</Code>
<Text>FRANCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~523410</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~533935</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~510103</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The National Academy of Sciences (NAS), through its Board in International Scientific Organizations (BISO), serves as the national member to the International Science Council (ISC), the Pacific Science Association (PSA), and 15 other ISC-related unions and programs.&nbsp; Through this grant, BISO (1) fulfilled the national member responsibilities to ISC and PSA; (2) coordinated and provided structure to BISO?s larger portfolio of ISC-related scientific unions and programs; and (3) provided visa assistance to the U.S. and international scientific community through the International Visitors Office (IVO).&nbsp;</p> <p>SCIENTIFIC MERIT</p> <p>The International Science Council (ISC) was created in 2018 from a&nbsp;<strong><em>merger</em></strong>of the International Council for Science (ICSU) and the International Social Science Council (ISSC).&nbsp; Joint committees worked throughout 2017 and 2018 on various strategy and transition tasks and documents.&nbsp; BISO invested considerable time in these activities to make sure that the new science organization began in a strong position, fully utilized the strengths of both ICSU and the ISSC, and focused on current and emerging scientific issues and opportunities.&nbsp; BISO nominated four U.S. scientists to serve on key transition planning committees and three were selected.&nbsp; BISO worked closely with them, and many of BISO?s recommendations were included in the final documents.&nbsp; Since the creation of the ISC, BISO has taken the following actions:&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>ISC depends on its members for&nbsp;<strong><em>volunteer leadership</em></strong>.&nbsp; Having U.S. scientists involved on key committees ensures that information flows regularly between the NAS/BISO and the ISC, and that U.S. views are represented in decision-making. NAS/BISO-nominated individuals have been elected or appointed to positions on ISC?s Governing Board, Committee for Science Planning, Committee on Outreach and Engagement, and Ad Hoc Dues Committee.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>The ISC requested member input on its&nbsp;<strong><em>Science Action Plan</em></strong>, 2019-2021, which builds on the high-level strategy document created during the merger.&nbsp; BISO provided a considerable number of suggestions, of which many were incorporated in the final September 2019 plan.&nbsp; The Plan calls for focused action in the following areas:&nbsp; the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development, the digital revolution, science in policy and public discourse, and the evolution of science and science systems.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>In July 2019, ISC organized and BISO hosted the&nbsp;<strong><em>Global Funders Forum</em></strong>. This meeting&nbsp;brought together leaders of national research funding agencies, philanthropic foundations, and development aid agencies from around the world with the goal of building strategic partnerships to increase and accelerate the impact of science and science funding on the achievement of the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development.&nbsp; Half the organizations represented were from the United States, and many of those were identified by BISO and the NAS.&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>In late 2018, BISO undertook a&nbsp;<strong><em>union adherence review</em></strong>&nbsp;that addressed two questions:&nbsp; (1) Given the creation of the new ISC, are there other ISC-related unions or organizations for which national support should be considered? (2) Should any adjustments be made to BISO?s current portfolio of ISC-related unions and organizations?&nbsp; In Part 1 of the review, ISC organizations were reviewed against criteria such as national membership model, NAS and NSF interest, and current representation status.&nbsp; All but two were found to be already represented by the NAS and funded by the NSF. &nbsp;Part 2 of the review examined current roles, responsibilities and programs of the unions; finances of the unions; special roles performed in the U.S. by the associated U.S. national committees; size of relevant U.S. scientific societies, percentages of national and international members, and roles on or with the USNC and/or union; and U.S. leadership in the union and on the USNCs.&nbsp; Most of the unions were found to be robust and effective, but three, including the PSA, were identified as needing closer attention and further review.</p> <p>BROADER IMPACT</p> <p>Continued U.S. involvement with and leadership in ISC, its programs, and its member unions leads to international collaborations for U.S. scientists, as well as enhanced U.S. awareness of international perspectives, policy, and culture.&nbsp; The topics identified in the ISC Science Action Plan present an opportunity for the NAS and U.S. scientists to act cooperatively with scientists and policymakers worldwide on topics of importance to the United States.</p> <p>The&nbsp;<strong><em>IVO</em></strong>&nbsp;assists individual scientists and students in the sciences with visa difficulties; provides advice to organizers of large scientific meetings in the United States; and identifies emerging trends. During this grant, the IVO assisted 2,017 individuals (508 in the first year, 654 in the second year, and 855 in the third year).&nbsp;&nbsp; The benefits from these collaborations and educational exchanges extend to U.S. society at large, and are both intellectual and economic.&nbsp; Foreign scientists and international students bring news ideas and experiences that benefit not only collaborators, but other colleagues, students, and communities.&nbsp; In addition, when these visitors return to their home countries, they carry with them a better understanding of U.S. values and culture as well as international goodwill.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/14/2019<br>      Modified by: Katherine&nbsp;E&nbsp;Bailey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The National Academy of Sciences (NAS), through its Board in International Scientific Organizations (BISO), serves as the national member to the International Science Council (ISC), the Pacific Science Association (PSA), and 15 other ISC-related unions and programs.  Through this grant, BISO (1) fulfilled the national member responsibilities to ISC and PSA; (2) coordinated and provided structure to BISO?s larger portfolio of ISC-related scientific unions and programs; and (3) provided visa assistance to the U.S. and international scientific community through the International Visitors Office (IVO).   SCIENTIFIC MERIT  The International Science Council (ISC) was created in 2018 from a mergerof the International Council for Science (ICSU) and the International Social Science Council (ISSC).  Joint committees worked throughout 2017 and 2018 on various strategy and transition tasks and documents.  BISO invested considerable time in these activities to make sure that the new science organization began in a strong position, fully utilized the strengths of both ICSU and the ISSC, and focused on current and emerging scientific issues and opportunities.  BISO nominated four U.S. scientists to serve on key transition planning committees and three were selected.  BISO worked closely with them, and many of BISO?s recommendations were included in the final documents.  Since the creation of the ISC, BISO has taken the following actions:   ISC depends on its members for volunteer leadership.  Having U.S. scientists involved on key committees ensures that information flows regularly between the NAS/BISO and the ISC, and that U.S. views are represented in decision-making. NAS/BISO-nominated individuals have been elected or appointed to positions on ISC?s Governing Board, Committee for Science Planning, Committee on Outreach and Engagement, and Ad Hoc Dues Committee.   The ISC requested member input on its Science Action Plan, 2019-2021, which builds on the high-level strategy document created during the merger.  BISO provided a considerable number of suggestions, of which many were incorporated in the final September 2019 plan.  The Plan calls for focused action in the following areas:  the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development, the digital revolution, science in policy and public discourse, and the evolution of science and science systems.   In July 2019, ISC organized and BISO hosted the Global Funders Forum. This meeting brought together leaders of national research funding agencies, philanthropic foundations, and development aid agencies from around the world with the goal of building strategic partnerships to increase and accelerate the impact of science and science funding on the achievement of the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development.  Half the organizations represented were from the United States, and many of those were identified by BISO and the NAS.    In late 2018, BISO undertook a union adherence review that addressed two questions:  (1) Given the creation of the new ISC, are there other ISC-related unions or organizations for which national support should be considered? (2) Should any adjustments be made to BISO?s current portfolio of ISC-related unions and organizations?  In Part 1 of the review, ISC organizations were reviewed against criteria such as national membership model, NAS and NSF interest, and current representation status.  All but two were found to be already represented by the NAS and funded by the NSF.  Part 2 of the review examined current roles, responsibilities and programs of the unions; finances of the unions; special roles performed in the U.S. by the associated U.S. national committees; size of relevant U.S. scientific societies, percentages of national and international members, and roles on or with the USNC and/or union; and U.S. leadership in the union and on the USNCs.  Most of the unions were found to be robust and effective, but three, including the PSA, were identified as needing closer attention and further review.  BROADER IMPACT  Continued U.S. involvement with and leadership in ISC, its programs, and its member unions leads to international collaborations for U.S. scientists, as well as enhanced U.S. awareness of international perspectives, policy, and culture.  The topics identified in the ISC Science Action Plan present an opportunity for the NAS and U.S. scientists to act cooperatively with scientists and policymakers worldwide on topics of importance to the United States.  The IVO assists individual scientists and students in the sciences with visa difficulties; provides advice to organizers of large scientific meetings in the United States; and identifies emerging trends. During this grant, the IVO assisted 2,017 individuals (508 in the first year, 654 in the second year, and 855 in the third year).   The benefits from these collaborations and educational exchanges extend to U.S. society at large, and are both intellectual and economic.  Foreign scientists and international students bring news ideas and experiences that benefit not only collaborators, but other colleagues, students, and communities.  In addition, when these visitors return to their home countries, they carry with them a better understanding of U.S. values and culture as well as international goodwill.          Last Modified: 10/14/2019       Submitted by: Katherine E Bailey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
