<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>E2CDA: Type I: Collaborative Research: Energy Efficient Computing with Chip-Based Photonics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>411708.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>411708</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sabasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927843</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Amidst today's data explosion, demand for computing power is accelerating, and the energy requirements for solving critical problems in science, engineering, business, and intelligent processing are increasing dramatically.  In order to address this critical issue, the scientific and engineering community is beginning to explore new approaches to computing, such as mimicking the brain's structure or the dynamical behavior of coupled particles.  However, implementing these approaches with conventional computer architectures is highly inefficient from both energy and computing standpoints. As a result, there is a pressing need to develop revolutionary computer architectures that overcome these severe roadblocks. An ambitious program is to be pursued within the framework of this project in which light, rather than electrons, is used to realize new computing paradigms with superior energy scalability. Specifically, computing architectures will be explored that exploit the wave nature of light (i.e., its amplitude and phase) harnessing the remarkable advancements over the past decade in nanofabrication of complex photonic chips with thousands of high-performance devices. These photonic platforms would have the potential to be computationally powerful, operate with unparalleled energy efficiency, and are scalable and highly reconfigurable.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To fulfill this vision of energy efficient photonic computing, the proposed research efforts will focus on the following two types of photonic processors: (1) Ising Machine and (2) Neuromorphic Computing Machine.  The unifying aspect of these photonic processors is that they consist of dynamic networks of coupled photonic units and rely on the wave nature of light to solve problems which has no analogy in electron-based computing systems. Beyond developing new types of optical processors, photonics technology will be developed as the cornerstone of future computer systems.  A novel architecture will be explored that integrates photonic processors and interconnects with electronic memory and processors to maximize the benefits of each technology. Research will also be undertaken to map complete, challenging problems to combinations of photonic accelerators and electronic processors, and to determine how to best scale them to maximize full-system performance.  By innovating at all levels of the system - from devices to architectures including systems, compilers, and algorithms -  the project would aim to achieve advances that cannot be realized within any single field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1640227</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yeshaiahu</FirstName>
<LastName>Fainman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yeshaiahu Fainman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fainman@ece.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585348909</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000468645</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>015Y</Code>
<Text>Energy Efficient Computing: fr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7945</Code>
<Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~137236</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~137236</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~137236</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this program was to utilize nonlinearly coupled light emitters to implement a neuromorphic processor. Specifically, we investigated Semiconductor Lasers (SLs) and Light Emitting Diodes (LEDs) with programmable couplings for decision making on a chip. We explored a chip-scale integrated optical hardware that uses spatio-temporal patterns that encode the input information signals and generate a corresponding sequential output in response. A canonical model that can be employed for this purpose is generalized Lotka-Volterra (GLV) system of differential equations, which can be realized by exploiting the physics of a network of coupled SL oscillators or LEDs described by the rate equations. To achieve these objectives, we first study a network of N independently controlled and interconnected semiconductor light emitters interacting via mutual non-symmetric inhibitory connections. Given the challenges of achieving phase-locking with these coherent SLs, we had to consider alternative solutions. One involved developing chip-scale integration technology where the network of light emitters is seamlessly integrated with Si photonic circuitry for stabilization and control. Additionally, we also decided to explore computation using incoherent LEDs. Specifically, coupled LED loops were used to help model the spread of epidemics in human populations.</p> <p>In addition to our initial macroscopic approaches to computing, to realize a true neuromorphic processor of any kind, dense integration of components on chip is necessitated. An important component of any future photonic integrated circuit intended to model the brain requires miniature light sources. To this end, we also focused on developing and understanding the behavior of subwavelength-scale nanoscale lasers. We first studied the dynamics for a single such nanolaser that are observed and how these dynamics can help identify the lasing threshold for the lasers. Additionally, we investigate fundamental limitations that such nanoscale lasers might encounter. One such study we conducted was based on understanding the contribution of fundamental thermal fluctuations to the linewidth broadening in nanolasers. We also developed a method to extract the relative intensity noise (RIN) of a low-power nanolaser via an injection locking scheme where the nanolaser serves as a master oscillator and its emission is fed to a low-noise semiconductor serving as a slave oscillator. The slave laser can then inherit the noise characteristics of the master (i.e. the nanolaser). To realize our goal of using these nanolasers for on-chip realization of coupled oscillators, we further developed CW electrically-pumped metal-clad nanolasers and devised an experimental scheme to tune the emission wavelength as well as to modulate the output intensity in-situ. For purposes of computation, multiple such nanolasers would be required to be densely integrated on a single chip. We therefore investigated the electromagnetic coupling that occurs between two such lasers when placed in proximity of each other. In-depth numerical analyses further reveal that nanolasers with high spontaneous emission factors (&beta;&rsquo;s), such as the ones developed in our group, possess wider ranges of stable phase-locking when coupled on-chip than conventional microscale SLs with negligible &beta;&rsquo;s. Therefore, they are excellent building blocks for neuromorphic processors where large-scale laser array systems with stable in-phase locking are required.</p> <p>The project provided scientific training for students at graduate and undergraduate levels. Their training included developing rigorous electromagnetic, electronic and thermal modeling tools to design and analyze nanoscale engineered composite resonant structures with gain, nanoscale light emitters and nanolasers.&nbsp; They also are trained in establishing the advanced tools and techniques required to fabricate these nanoscale materials and devices, and use advanced characterization techniques such as micro photoluminescence, spectroscopy and measurements of statistical properties of light emitters using intensity correlation methods as well as novel measurement techniques of their nonlinear optical properties. We continued our outreach, education and collaborative efforts with San Diego middle and high schools. Through our relationships with the Sweetwater, Preuss, and High Tech High Schools, we successfully engaged students of diverse ethnicity, gender and economic backgrounds in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM). We continued the ongoing REU and COSMOS programs.&nbsp; For this project we used traditional means and develop new mechanisms for data dissemination.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/24/2020<br>      Modified by: Yeshaiahu&nbsp;Fainman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this program was to utilize nonlinearly coupled light emitters to implement a neuromorphic processor. Specifically, we investigated Semiconductor Lasers (SLs) and Light Emitting Diodes (LEDs) with programmable couplings for decision making on a chip. We explored a chip-scale integrated optical hardware that uses spatio-temporal patterns that encode the input information signals and generate a corresponding sequential output in response. A canonical model that can be employed for this purpose is generalized Lotka-Volterra (GLV) system of differential equations, which can be realized by exploiting the physics of a network of coupled SL oscillators or LEDs described by the rate equations. To achieve these objectives, we first study a network of N independently controlled and interconnected semiconductor light emitters interacting via mutual non-symmetric inhibitory connections. Given the challenges of achieving phase-locking with these coherent SLs, we had to consider alternative solutions. One involved developing chip-scale integration technology where the network of light emitters is seamlessly integrated with Si photonic circuitry for stabilization and control. Additionally, we also decided to explore computation using incoherent LEDs. Specifically, coupled LED loops were used to help model the spread of epidemics in human populations.  In addition to our initial macroscopic approaches to computing, to realize a true neuromorphic processor of any kind, dense integration of components on chip is necessitated. An important component of any future photonic integrated circuit intended to model the brain requires miniature light sources. To this end, we also focused on developing and understanding the behavior of subwavelength-scale nanoscale lasers. We first studied the dynamics for a single such nanolaser that are observed and how these dynamics can help identify the lasing threshold for the lasers. Additionally, we investigate fundamental limitations that such nanoscale lasers might encounter. One such study we conducted was based on understanding the contribution of fundamental thermal fluctuations to the linewidth broadening in nanolasers. We also developed a method to extract the relative intensity noise (RIN) of a low-power nanolaser via an injection locking scheme where the nanolaser serves as a master oscillator and its emission is fed to a low-noise semiconductor serving as a slave oscillator. The slave laser can then inherit the noise characteristics of the master (i.e. the nanolaser). To realize our goal of using these nanolasers for on-chip realization of coupled oscillators, we further developed CW electrically-pumped metal-clad nanolasers and devised an experimental scheme to tune the emission wavelength as well as to modulate the output intensity in-situ. For purposes of computation, multiple such nanolasers would be required to be densely integrated on a single chip. We therefore investigated the electromagnetic coupling that occurs between two such lasers when placed in proximity of each other. In-depth numerical analyses further reveal that nanolasers with high spontaneous emission factors (&beta;’s), such as the ones developed in our group, possess wider ranges of stable phase-locking when coupled on-chip than conventional microscale SLs with negligible &beta;’s. Therefore, they are excellent building blocks for neuromorphic processors where large-scale laser array systems with stable in-phase locking are required.  The project provided scientific training for students at graduate and undergraduate levels. Their training included developing rigorous electromagnetic, electronic and thermal modeling tools to design and analyze nanoscale engineered composite resonant structures with gain, nanoscale light emitters and nanolasers.  They also are trained in establishing the advanced tools and techniques required to fabricate these nanoscale materials and devices, and use advanced characterization techniques such as micro photoluminescence, spectroscopy and measurements of statistical properties of light emitters using intensity correlation methods as well as novel measurement techniques of their nonlinear optical properties. We continued our outreach, education and collaborative efforts with San Diego middle and high schools. Through our relationships with the Sweetwater, Preuss, and High Tech High Schools, we successfully engaged students of diverse ethnicity, gender and economic backgrounds in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM). We continued the ongoing REU and COSMOS programs.  For this project we used traditional means and develop new mechanisms for data dissemination.          Last Modified: 10/24/2020       Submitted by: Yeshaiahu Fainman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
