<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research Initiation: Reshaping Engineering Classroom Norms to Diversify the Profession</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Berger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>By some estimates, roughly half the students that graduate with an engineering degree end up employed in a non-engineering field. Attempts to fix this "leaky pipeline" rarely address the fact that the culture, rather than academics, may be driving students away. Throughout their academic careers, students ask themselves, "What are the attributes inherent in being an engineer?" Far too often, the answer to that question is defined by outdated engineering ways of knowing, thinking, and doing. Such lack of inclusivity, especially when college students are forming their professional identity, has a significant impact on their interest and the appeal of an engineering occupation. To better expand the profession, there is a need to identify and understand the impact of social-engineering norms in university programs and in the profession. Reshaping Norms serves to address this need by studying the impacts of a series of classroom interventions. The focus of Reshaping Norms is to identify and reshape the norms that cause a student to form (or not form) an identity of themselves as a future engineer. As a society, we must encourage the creation of new perspectives because the ability to innovate and exploit niche markets is better served by people who bring a wide-range of diverse experiences to the engineering profession. Similarly, the ability of the public to make well-informed decisions is better served by a diverse profession actively engaged within their communities. This project serves to address these needs by broadening the characterization of engineering identity and catalyzing the engagement of students with their communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of Reshaping Norms will be accomplished by reducing barriers to diversity and improving students' sense of belonging through pedagogies, strategies, and initiatives aimed at: 1) creating an inclusive classroom community; and 2) incorporating relevancy into course activities. The creation of an inclusive classroom community will be accomplished by explicitly raising awareness of factors of attrition, democratically establishing norms of participation, and role model case-studies. Relevancy will be incorporated through authentic analysis and design experiences based on student interests, and civic engagement with local community organizations. The research plan is guided by the following questions: 1) To what extent do Reshaping Norms classroom interventions affect underrepresented students' engineering identity?; and 2) To what extent do the Reshaping Norms classroom interventions affect underrepresented engineering students' self-efficacy in engineering? This two-year project will be implemented in three iterations (alpha, beta, and gamma). Data collected during the alpha and beta iterations will be analyzed to assess the effectiveness of the intervention tools, determine evidence of growth of students' interest and/or self-efficacy, inform revisions to subsequent interventions, and develop a full quasi-experimental study (gamma iteration). The study will include data collection from both intervention and control courses within two separate sections of a targeted engineering course. To answer the research questions, the study will utilize two previously developed instruments: one to measure engineering identity and one to measure self-efficacy toward the field of engineering. The results of this study will be used to generate new findings about the formation of engineering students' identity as it relates to their feelings of belonging in the profession.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1640328</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ron</FirstName>
<LastName>Gray</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ron E Gray</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ron.gray@nau.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9285233618</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000576947</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
<LastName>Tuchscherer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robin G Tuchscherer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robin.tuchscherer@nau.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9285238080</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000617414</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northern Arizona University</Name>
<CityName>Flagstaff</CityName>
<ZipCode>860110001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9285230886</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ARD Building #56, Suite 240</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1395 South Knoles Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345542</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHERN ARIZONA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345542</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northern Arizona University]]></Name>
<CityName>Flagstaff</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>860110001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2112 South Huffer Lane, Bldg. 69]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; This project was designed to positively impact the retention of engineering majors in early career engineering courses. We focus on two important aspects of classroom instruction: classroom community and relevancy. In this two-year project, faculty from engineering and science education teamed together to design, implement, and study a number of interventions related to classroom community and relevancy.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;The results of this project were measured quantitatively and qualitatively. Quantitative measures examined three specific constructs: engineering identity, engineering self-efficacy, and sense of community. Also, a standardized classroom observation protocol was used to examine instructional differences between treatment and control courses. In addition to the quantitative measures, student groups and individuals were interviewed and their responses related to engineering identity were examined through the three components of <em>competence</em>, <em>performance</em>, and <em>recognition</em>. Responses related to classroom community were examined through the lenses of <em>learning</em> and <em>connectedness</em>. Qualitative measures compared multiple case-studies in order to explore frequent themes that may transcend each individual case and provide the additional perspective of cross-commonalities.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;In the first two iterations of the project, we examined the impact of micro-interventions aimed solely at increasing the students? sense of community in the early career course. These included, for example, a focus on classroom norms, strategies to increase peer-to-peer interactions, and peer testimonials to enable discussions of the challenges faced by first-year engineering students, among others. For the third and final iteration of the project, we examined the impact of interventions aimed at both classroom community and relevancy.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Based on the findings of this study and considering the context of the research plan, we have the following concluding observations. There were important instructional differences seen between the two courses as shown by the observational data. However, the effect of these differences on the three measured constructs was inconsistent. We measured a statistically significant difference in students? sense of community and engineering self-efficacy for the treatment section during the alpha iteration, but not during the subsequent beta or gamma iterations. Similarly, we found no significant quantitative difference in students? change in engineering identity between the treatment and control sections, for all iterations. It is likely the instrument used to measure identity was insufficient to measure changes over the time scale of one semester. The results of the qualitative study delve deeper into answers to the how and why questions for faculty searching for ways to better support their students.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Our findings provide evidence that an increase in classroom climate can effect students? engineering self-efficacy. It may be the ?micro? nature of our interventions was not effective towards producing significant changes to students? sense of community, engineering self-efficacy, or engineering identity ? in a large lecture-format introductory engineering course. Or, it may be the instruments employed were not sensitive to measuring the change. Nonetheless, this study provides one window into the intersection of two constructs ? engineering identity and classroom community -- that may be critically important in conversations about the steps faculty may take in working with students to promote increased retention of undergraduate students in engineering. The findings in this study add to the current understandings about the influences of classroom community on engineering identity, and suggest that attention to fostering a sense of classroom community may support some students? developing engineering identity.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Products from this study include:</p> <ul> <li>&nbsp;Gray, A. 2019. <em>Engineering Identity Development within a Classroom Community</em>, Ph.D. Dissertation. Northern Arizona University. 149 pp.</li> <li>Tuchscherer, R.; Gray, C. A.; and Gray, R. 2018. "Examining micro-interventions designed to increase classroom community and relevancy in an early career engineering course,"&nbsp;<em>Proceedings of the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) Annual Conference</em>, Summer 2018. No. 21664. 13 pp.</li> <li>Gray, C. A.; Tuchscherer, R.; and Gray, R. 2018. "The challenges and affordances of engineering identity as an analytical lens,"&nbsp;<em>Proceedings of the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) Annual Conference</em>, Summer 2018. No. 21972. 18 pp.</li> <li>Gray, R.; Gray,C. A.; and Tuchscherer, R. 2018. "Improving classroom community in an introductory engineering classroom through targeted micro-interventions,"&nbsp;<em>Proceedings of the National Association for Research in Science Teaching (NARST) Annual Conference</em>, Spring 2018.</li> <li>Tuchscherer, R.; Gray, R.; and Gray, C. A. 2017. "Reshaping engineering classroom norms to expand the profession,"<em>Proceedings of the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) Annual Conference</em>, Summer 2017. No. 18105. 10 pp.</li> <li>Gray, C. A.; Gray, R.; and Tuchscherer, R. 2017. "Examining micro-interventions to improve classroom community in introductory engineering classrooms,"&nbsp;<em>Proceedings of the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) Annual Conference</em>, Summer 2017. No. 18248. 5 pp.</li> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/16/2019<br>      Modified by: Robin&nbsp;G&nbsp;Tuchscherer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1640328/1640328_10446152_1565984129396_outcomesfig--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1640328/1640328_10446152_1565984129396_outcomesfig--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Project Framework"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1640328/1640328_10446152_1565984129396_outcomesfig--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Project Framework"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Framework for Series of Classroom Interventions</div> <div class="imageCredit">Robin Tuchscherer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robin&nbsp;G&nbsp;Tuchscherer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Project Framework</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[         This project was designed to positively impact the retention of engineering majors in early career engineering courses. We focus on two important aspects of classroom instruction: classroom community and relevancy. In this two-year project, faculty from engineering and science education teamed together to design, implement, and study a number of interventions related to classroom community and relevancy.           The results of this project were measured quantitatively and qualitatively. Quantitative measures examined three specific constructs: engineering identity, engineering self-efficacy, and sense of community. Also, a standardized classroom observation protocol was used to examine instructional differences between treatment and control courses. In addition to the quantitative measures, student groups and individuals were interviewed and their responses related to engineering identity were examined through the three components of competence, performance, and recognition. Responses related to classroom community were examined through the lenses of learning and connectedness. Qualitative measures compared multiple case-studies in order to explore frequent themes that may transcend each individual case and provide the additional perspective of cross-commonalities.           In the first two iterations of the project, we examined the impact of micro-interventions aimed solely at increasing the students? sense of community in the early career course. These included, for example, a focus on classroom norms, strategies to increase peer-to-peer interactions, and peer testimonials to enable discussions of the challenges faced by first-year engineering students, among others. For the third and final iteration of the project, we examined the impact of interventions aimed at both classroom community and relevancy.           Based on the findings of this study and considering the context of the research plan, we have the following concluding observations. There were important instructional differences seen between the two courses as shown by the observational data. However, the effect of these differences on the three measured constructs was inconsistent. We measured a statistically significant difference in students? sense of community and engineering self-efficacy for the treatment section during the alpha iteration, but not during the subsequent beta or gamma iterations. Similarly, we found no significant quantitative difference in students? change in engineering identity between the treatment and control sections, for all iterations. It is likely the instrument used to measure identity was insufficient to measure changes over the time scale of one semester. The results of the qualitative study delve deeper into answers to the how and why questions for faculty searching for ways to better support their students.           Our findings provide evidence that an increase in classroom climate can effect students? engineering self-efficacy. It may be the ?micro? nature of our interventions was not effective towards producing significant changes to students? sense of community, engineering self-efficacy, or engineering identity ? in a large lecture-format introductory engineering course. Or, it may be the instruments employed were not sensitive to measuring the change. Nonetheless, this study provides one window into the intersection of two constructs ? engineering identity and classroom community -- that may be critically important in conversations about the steps faculty may take in working with students to promote increased retention of undergraduate students in engineering. The findings in this study add to the current understandings about the influences of classroom community on engineering identity, and suggest that attention to fostering a sense of classroom community may support some students? developing engineering identity.           Products from this study include:   Gray, A. 2019. Engineering Identity Development within a Classroom Community, Ph.D. Dissertation. Northern Arizona University. 149 pp. Tuchscherer, R.; Gray, C. A.; and Gray, R. 2018. "Examining micro-interventions designed to increase classroom community and relevancy in an early career engineering course," Proceedings of the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) Annual Conference, Summer 2018. No. 21664. 13 pp. Gray, C. A.; Tuchscherer, R.; and Gray, R. 2018. "The challenges and affordances of engineering identity as an analytical lens," Proceedings of the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) Annual Conference, Summer 2018. No. 21972. 18 pp. Gray, R.; Gray,C. A.; and Tuchscherer, R. 2018. "Improving classroom community in an introductory engineering classroom through targeted micro-interventions," Proceedings of the National Association for Research in Science Teaching (NARST) Annual Conference, Spring 2018. Tuchscherer, R.; Gray, R.; and Gray, C. A. 2017. "Reshaping engineering classroom norms to expand the profession,"Proceedings of the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) Annual Conference, Summer 2017. No. 18105. 10 pp. Gray, C. A.; Gray, R.; and Tuchscherer, R. 2017. "Examining micro-interventions to improve classroom community in introductory engineering classrooms," Proceedings of the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) Annual Conference, Summer 2017. No. 18248. 5 pp.        Last Modified: 08/16/2019       Submitted by: Robin G Tuchscherer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
