<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>E2CDA: Type I: Excitonic Devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1748772.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1748772</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lawrence Goldberg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lgoldber@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928339</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports a project directed towards the development of an advanced alternative to electronic devices. A special design of the structures on a length scale of a billionth part of a meter allows the creation of new quasi-particles called indirect excitons. The indirect excitons are unique because they can be electronically controlled like electrons in electronic devices and can shine light that electrons cannot do by themselves. The project is directed towards exploring the fundamental limits of excitonic devices and development of excitonic devices that can extend the limits of energy-efficient computation. The students involved with this project have the opportunity to perform exploratory research on the cutting edge of physics, material science, and engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports a project directed towards development of excitonic devices. Excitonic devices are based on computational state variables beyond magnetism and charge, namely on excitons. Excitonic devices are particularly well suited to the development of an advanced alternative to electronics due to the properties of excitons: Excitons are bosons that allows creating energy-efficient computation, excitonic signal processing can be directly coupled to optical communication, and excitonic circuits can be realized at deeply subwavelength scales smaller than for photonic devices. The advantages of excitonic devices require specially designed excitons. A breakthrough was achieved by using indirect excitons, IXs. An IX is a bound pair of an electron and a hole in separated layers. Unique properties of IXs make them different from conventional excitons and suitable for the development of energy-efficient computing: the IX energy, fluxes, and emission rate can be controlled by voltage. Objectives of this project include exploring the fundamental limits of excitonic devices for energy-efficient computing and exploring excitonic devices in III-V structures and in new artificial materials based on 2-D single-atomic-layers of transition-metal dichalcogenide.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1640173</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arthur</FirstName>
<LastName>Gossard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arthur C Gossard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gossard@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058932686</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000103399</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vladimir</FirstName>
<LastName>Bulovic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vladimir Bulovic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bulovic@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172537012</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000169152</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Fogler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael M Fogler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mfogler@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585345978</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000382661</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leonid</FirstName>
<LastName>Butov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leonid V Butov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lvbutov@physics.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8588220362</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000489813</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Loren</FirstName>
<LastName>Pfeiffer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Loren N Pfeiffer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>loren@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092582590</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000524191</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>015Y</Code>
<Text>Energy Efficient Computing: fr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7945</Code>
<Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~582924</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~874386</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~291462</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual merit: <br />The goal of our project was to explore excitonic devices. Excitonic devices are based on computational state variables beyond magnetism and charge, namely on excitons. In our studies, we used indirect excitons (IXs), also known as interlayer excitons or charge transfer excitons, as well as exciton polaritons. IX is a bound pair of an electron and a hole confined in spatially separated layers. We developed and produced high quality GaAs structures and van der Waals structures based on 2D single-atomic-layers of transition-metal dichalcogenide (TMD). GaAs structures form the highest quality material platform for studying basic IX properties and for the development of operation principles of excitonic devices, while TMD structures form the material platform where the excitons have high binding energies and are stable at room temperature. The research results include the following.<br /><br />Theory: <br />- We developed the theory of quantum transport of IXs through quantum-point contacts.<br />- We carried out numerical modelling of ballistic exciton spin transport in the presence of spin-orbit interaction elaborating the acquired Pancharatnam-Berry phase.<br />- We modelled drift-diffusion transport of IXs through split-gate devices.<br />- We considered a transport regime where carriers behave as a hydrodynamic fluid<br /><br />Materials growth: <br />- We achieved rise in the transport mobility of GaAs QWs by 70 percent compared to all previous GaAs material, realized in these QWs the Quantum Hall fractions at filling factors 13/27, 12/25, and 11/23, indicating the highest sample quality.<br />- We achieved the record-high vacuum for MBE machines and developed MBE growth of AlAs structures with record-high mobility.<br />- We developed a scanning photoluminescence technique that can directly map out the local two-dimensional electron density in a GaAs quantum well.<br /><br />Experiment: <br />- We found new phase singularities in IX condensate.<br />- We found the Pancharatnam-Berry phase and long-range spin transport in IX condensate.<br />- We developed new platform for IX devices with record-high IX mobility.<br />- We developed and demonstrated split-gate devices for IXs.<br />- We demonstrated IXs at room temperature in TMD heterostructures.<br />- We observed charged IXs, indirect trions, in TMD heterostructures.<br /><br />Broader impacts: <br />Excitonic devices are suited to the development of an advanced energy-efficient computing due to the properties of excitons: (i) Excitons are bosons and can form a coherent condensate with vanishing resistance for exciton currents and low switching voltage for excitonic transistors. This allows creating energy-efficient computation. (ii) Excitonic signal processing can be directly coupled to optical communication. (iii) The sizes of excitonic devices are scaled by the exciton radius and de Broglie wavelength that are much smaller than the photon wavelength. This gives the opportunity to realize nanoscale excitonic circuit components. IXs have long lifetimes and long spin relaxation times, can cool below the temperature of quantum degeneracy, can travel over large distances before recombination, and can be controlled by voltage. Due to these properties, IXs form a model system for the development of excitonic devices. Education: 12 graduate students contributed to the studies within the project.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/18/2019<br>      Modified by: Leonid&nbsp;V&nbsp;Butov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit:  The goal of our project was to explore excitonic devices. Excitonic devices are based on computational state variables beyond magnetism and charge, namely on excitons. In our studies, we used indirect excitons (IXs), also known as interlayer excitons or charge transfer excitons, as well as exciton polaritons. IX is a bound pair of an electron and a hole confined in spatially separated layers. We developed and produced high quality GaAs structures and van der Waals structures based on 2D single-atomic-layers of transition-metal dichalcogenide (TMD). GaAs structures form the highest quality material platform for studying basic IX properties and for the development of operation principles of excitonic devices, while TMD structures form the material platform where the excitons have high binding energies and are stable at room temperature. The research results include the following.  Theory:  - We developed the theory of quantum transport of IXs through quantum-point contacts. - We carried out numerical modelling of ballistic exciton spin transport in the presence of spin-orbit interaction elaborating the acquired Pancharatnam-Berry phase. - We modelled drift-diffusion transport of IXs through split-gate devices. - We considered a transport regime where carriers behave as a hydrodynamic fluid  Materials growth:  - We achieved rise in the transport mobility of GaAs QWs by 70 percent compared to all previous GaAs material, realized in these QWs the Quantum Hall fractions at filling factors 13/27, 12/25, and 11/23, indicating the highest sample quality. - We achieved the record-high vacuum for MBE machines and developed MBE growth of AlAs structures with record-high mobility. - We developed a scanning photoluminescence technique that can directly map out the local two-dimensional electron density in a GaAs quantum well.  Experiment:  - We found new phase singularities in IX condensate. - We found the Pancharatnam-Berry phase and long-range spin transport in IX condensate. - We developed new platform for IX devices with record-high IX mobility. - We developed and demonstrated split-gate devices for IXs. - We demonstrated IXs at room temperature in TMD heterostructures. - We observed charged IXs, indirect trions, in TMD heterostructures.  Broader impacts:  Excitonic devices are suited to the development of an advanced energy-efficient computing due to the properties of excitons: (i) Excitons are bosons and can form a coherent condensate with vanishing resistance for exciton currents and low switching voltage for excitonic transistors. This allows creating energy-efficient computation. (ii) Excitonic signal processing can be directly coupled to optical communication. (iii) The sizes of excitonic devices are scaled by the exciton radius and de Broglie wavelength that are much smaller than the photon wavelength. This gives the opportunity to realize nanoscale excitonic circuit components. IXs have long lifetimes and long spin relaxation times, can cool below the temperature of quantum degeneracy, can travel over large distances before recombination, and can be controlled by voltage. Due to these properties, IXs form a model system for the development of excitonic devices. Education: 12 graduate students contributed to the studies within the project.       Last Modified: 11/18/2019       Submitted by: Leonid V Butov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
