<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: New Selective Oxidation Catalysts to Reduce Energy Requirements and Waste Products</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Selective oxidation is an important process used to make chemical intermediates for pharmaceutical products, plastics, laboratory chemicals, and industrial fluids. However, some of these selective oxidation processes consume large amounts of energy and produce waste by-products. This I-Corps Project focuses on a technology to reduce co-products and energy requirements during selective oxidation of organic substrates. The proposed innovation aims to improve selective oxidation efficiency by using molecular oxygen as the oxidant without using a co-reductant.  Molecular oxygen is the ideal oxidant, because it is cheap and readily available in air. For many challenging substrates, existing catalysts cannot use molecular oxygen as the oxidant unless a co-reductant is used. However, using a co-reductant produces a co-product. The purpose of this project is to investigate the marketability of step-wise no-reductant (SNR) technology. SNR is a patent-pending computationally designed catalyst system and reaction process that could reduce energy requirements and waste by-products. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed innovation incorporates newly designed zirconium organometallic catalysts into stepwise no-reductant (SNR) processes to extend the selective oxidation process to more challenging organic substrates without requiring a co-reductant and without producing a co-product. These zirconium organometallic catalysts facilitate efficient molecular oxygen activation by passing through ozone intermediates. A catalyst prototype will be synthesized during the I-Corps project. During the I-Corps training program, the team will interview potential customers to gather market feedback that will aid future commercialization. This market feedback will provide valuable information on which chemical products could benefit the most from the proposed innovation. This market feedback will also identify potential development partners and evaluate pricing models. A commercialization plan will be constructed using this information.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1640621</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Manz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas A Manz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tmanz@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5756462503</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000628212</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Mexico State University</Name>
<CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
<ZipCode>880038002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5756461590</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Corner of Espina St. &amp; Stewart</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MSC OGC, Box 30002]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>173851965</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW MEXICO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>861367373</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New Mexico State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>880038002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Corner of Espina St. & Stewart]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The Selective Oxidation I-Corps Team from New Mexico State University (NMSU) consisted of the following team members: Thomas Manz (Principal Investigator), Gina Duttle (Business Mentor), and Bo Yang (Entrepreneur). Tom is an assistant professor in the Chemical &amp; Materials Engineering Department at NMSU. At the start of the project, Bo was a graduate student in Manz's research group. Bo graduated with a Ph.D. in Chemical Engineering (NMSU, May 2016) during the project. Gina works at Arrowhead Center, Inc. which is a technology transfer, business incubation and development, and commercialization center for NMSU. Post-doc Chao Dong joined the project in August 2016 and worked on building a product prototype.</span></p> <p><span>During this project, the Selective Oxidation team explored the commercialization potential for an envisioned new organometallic catalyst that could selectively oxidize some organic substrates using molecular oxygen as the oxidant without requiring a co-reductant. The idea for such a product came from extensive computational chemistry calculations as described in: (a) T. A. Manz and B. Yang, RSC Advances, 4 (2014) 27755-27774, (b) B. Yang and T. A. Manz, RSC Advances, 5 (2015) 12311-12322, (c) B. Yang and T. A. Manz, Theoretical Chemistry Accounts, 135 (2016) 21, and (d) T. A. Manz and B. Yang, RSC Advances, 6 (2016) 108153.</span></p> <p><span>This project had three main objectives. The first objective was to interview companies to find out their needs, challenges, the market potential, and other factors related to assessing whether a viable business venture could be formed. The second objective was for the team to receive training and mentoring through the I-Corps workshops, weekly videoconference calls, and interactions with the I-Corps instructors and other teams. The third objective was to work towards building a product prototype.</span></p> <p><span>All three objectives were mostly met. The team interviewed 78 individuals during the project. These included people from many different chemical companies and other organizations. During this time, all three team members traveled to the International Pharmaceutical Expo (INTERPHEX) in New York City (April 25-28, 2016) to interview individuals from pharma companies.&nbsp;Individuals from about 20 companies were interviewed during this expo. The team traveled to Atlanta, Georgia for the kick-off and wrap-up I-Corps training meetings. During this time, the team interviewed several individuals from the Atlanta, Georgia area. En route to the wrap-up meeting, one of the team members visited the Houston, Texas area for a couple of days to check out the chemical industry in that area. The team participated in all of the I-Corps training activities, including watching all of the online videos, constructing and revising the business model canvas, all of the weekly team presentations and videoconference calls, meetings with the instructors, and the final project presentation and video. During this time, the team learned a great deal about challenges associated with starting a new business venture. The team learned how to systematically approach these challenges with the business model canvas as a tool for evidence-based learning.</span></p> <p><span>From our interviews with potential customers, we learned that the main value propositions to target are: (i) reducing chemical wastes in selective oxidation processes and (ii) simplify chemical manufacturing steps. We learned that value propositions are different for customers that buy in small batch sizes compared to those that buy in large batch sizes. Reducing chemical wastes is most important for large batch size. Simplifying manufacturing steps is most important for small batch size.</span></p> <p><span>At the close of these interviews, the team decided not to form a new company at this time, because the technology was not sufficiently developed. A working prototype is required to demonstrate feasibility of the technology.</span></p> <p><span>Following the wrap-up training session, the project focused on trying to build a working prototype. The first part of this was to complete and publish a computational model. This was accomplished and resulted in the following publication: B. Yang and T. A. Manz, RSC Advances, 6 (2016) 88189-88215. The second part of this involved chemical synthesis. Chao and Tom developed a multi-step method to synthesize the organic ligand. The organic ligand was successfully made and characterized using mass spectroscopy and proton nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy. A procedure was also developed to metallize the ligand to make an organometallic complex. The metallization reaction was tested, but the resulting material has not been fully characterized yet. Samples were sent to a lab for mass spectroscopy, but the results have not been received yet. Therefore, it is unclear to what extent the metallization reaction may or may not have produced the desired organometallic catalyst. As of the completion date of this project, effort to build a working prototype is currently ongoing in Manz&rsquo;s research group.</span></p> <p><span>To date, this project has resulted in one Ph.D. dissertation (Bo Yang), two conference presentations, and one journal article (see previous paragraph). Additional journal articles are in preparation.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2017<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;A&nbsp;Manz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1640621/1640621_10431438_1506543969206_TEAM_members--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1640621/1640621_10431438_1506543969206_TEAM_members--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Selective Oxidation I-Corps Team Members"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1640621/1640621_10431438_1506543969206_TEAM_members--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Selective Oxidation I-Corps Team Members"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Selective Oxidation I-Corps Team Members</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tom Manz</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;A&nbsp;Manz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Selective Oxidation I-Corps Team Members</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1640621/1640621_10431438_1506544429147_INTERPHEX--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1640621/1640621_10431438_1506544429147_INTERPHEX--rgov-800width.jpg" title="International Pharmaceutical Expo at New York City"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1640621/1640621_10431438_1506544429147_INTERPHEX--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="International Pharmaceutical Expo at New York City"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">On April 25-28, 2016, all team members attended the International Pharmaceutial Expo (INTERPHEX) in New York City and interviewed people from approximately twenty different chemical companies.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tom Manz</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;A&nbsp;Manz</div> <div class="imageTitle">International Pharmaceutical Expo at New York City</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1640621/1640621_10431438_1506544562647_companies_interviewed--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1640621/1640621_10431438_1506544562647_companies_interviewed--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Some of the companies interviewed"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1640621/1640621_10431438_1506544562647_companies_interviewed--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Some of the companies interviewed"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The team interviewed people from more than 50 different chemical companies.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Gina Duttle</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;A&nbsp;Manz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Some of the companies interviewed</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Selective Oxidation I-Corps Team from New Mexico State University (NMSU) consisted of the following team members: Thomas Manz (Principal Investigator), Gina Duttle (Business Mentor), and Bo Yang (Entrepreneur). Tom is an assistant professor in the Chemical &amp; Materials Engineering Department at NMSU. At the start of the project, Bo was a graduate student in Manz's research group. Bo graduated with a Ph.D. in Chemical Engineering (NMSU, May 2016) during the project. Gina works at Arrowhead Center, Inc. which is a technology transfer, business incubation and development, and commercialization center for NMSU. Post-doc Chao Dong joined the project in August 2016 and worked on building a product prototype.  During this project, the Selective Oxidation team explored the commercialization potential for an envisioned new organometallic catalyst that could selectively oxidize some organic substrates using molecular oxygen as the oxidant without requiring a co-reductant. The idea for such a product came from extensive computational chemistry calculations as described in: (a) T. A. Manz and B. Yang, RSC Advances, 4 (2014) 27755-27774, (b) B. Yang and T. A. Manz, RSC Advances, 5 (2015) 12311-12322, (c) B. Yang and T. A. Manz, Theoretical Chemistry Accounts, 135 (2016) 21, and (d) T. A. Manz and B. Yang, RSC Advances, 6 (2016) 108153.  This project had three main objectives. The first objective was to interview companies to find out their needs, challenges, the market potential, and other factors related to assessing whether a viable business venture could be formed. The second objective was for the team to receive training and mentoring through the I-Corps workshops, weekly videoconference calls, and interactions with the I-Corps instructors and other teams. The third objective was to work towards building a product prototype.  All three objectives were mostly met. The team interviewed 78 individuals during the project. These included people from many different chemical companies and other organizations. During this time, all three team members traveled to the International Pharmaceutical Expo (INTERPHEX) in New York City (April 25-28, 2016) to interview individuals from pharma companies. Individuals from about 20 companies were interviewed during this expo. The team traveled to Atlanta, Georgia for the kick-off and wrap-up I-Corps training meetings. During this time, the team interviewed several individuals from the Atlanta, Georgia area. En route to the wrap-up meeting, one of the team members visited the Houston, Texas area for a couple of days to check out the chemical industry in that area. The team participated in all of the I-Corps training activities, including watching all of the online videos, constructing and revising the business model canvas, all of the weekly team presentations and videoconference calls, meetings with the instructors, and the final project presentation and video. During this time, the team learned a great deal about challenges associated with starting a new business venture. The team learned how to systematically approach these challenges with the business model canvas as a tool for evidence-based learning.  From our interviews with potential customers, we learned that the main value propositions to target are: (i) reducing chemical wastes in selective oxidation processes and (ii) simplify chemical manufacturing steps. We learned that value propositions are different for customers that buy in small batch sizes compared to those that buy in large batch sizes. Reducing chemical wastes is most important for large batch size. Simplifying manufacturing steps is most important for small batch size.  At the close of these interviews, the team decided not to form a new company at this time, because the technology was not sufficiently developed. A working prototype is required to demonstrate feasibility of the technology.  Following the wrap-up training session, the project focused on trying to build a working prototype. The first part of this was to complete and publish a computational model. This was accomplished and resulted in the following publication: B. Yang and T. A. Manz, RSC Advances, 6 (2016) 88189-88215. The second part of this involved chemical synthesis. Chao and Tom developed a multi-step method to synthesize the organic ligand. The organic ligand was successfully made and characterized using mass spectroscopy and proton nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy. A procedure was also developed to metallize the ligand to make an organometallic complex. The metallization reaction was tested, but the resulting material has not been fully characterized yet. Samples were sent to a lab for mass spectroscopy, but the results have not been received yet. Therefore, it is unclear to what extent the metallization reaction may or may not have produced the desired organometallic catalyst. As of the completion date of this project, effort to build a working prototype is currently ongoing in Manz?s research group.  To date, this project has resulted in one Ph.D. dissertation (Bo Yang), two conference presentations, and one journal article (see previous paragraph). Additional journal articles are in preparation.          Last Modified: 09/27/2017       Submitted by: Thomas A Manz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
