<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT:  Prototyping Microfluidic Very Large Scale Integration Design Automation Tools</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>227999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating the concept of microfluidic design automation software for laboratory-on-a-chips (LoCs) to reduce the cost of designing new LoCs for applications such as medical diagnostics, drug discovery, biothreat detection, and environmental monitoring, and to improve the rate of progress in the biological and biomedical sciences. Computer Aided Design (CAD) software for LoCs is important because many industrial practitioners who desire highly customized LoCs lack the means to obtain them at a low cost and within a reasonable timeframe. Meanwhile current design methodologies cannot keep pace with current Moore's Law-rates of growth in the number of integrated microfluidic components and ever-increasing device complexity. This project will result in a prototype CAD software platform for LoCs, which offers the following unique features: a 2D sketch-based interface, a microfluidic component library, integrated fluid modeling to guide 3D volumization of components and fluid channels, automatic design rule checking, assistance with choosing fabrication technologies and materials, and 3D rendering capabilities. These features provide the key advantage of a platform tailored to meet the needs of users who are trained to design biological experiments, as opposed to engineers and technologists, and to provide improvements in usability and user productivity compared to the leading competing general-purpose CAD tools and finite element analysis software presently employed in this market space. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the following technology gap as it translates from research discovery toward commercial application. Current design practice for microfluidic laboratories-on-a-chip (LoCs) requires the user to create a design using complex engineering CAD software, then iterate through additional flow simulation software to assess correctness of the design. In contrast, this project proposes a new design paradigm wherein fluid modeling algorithms drive an informed design process specific to microfluidic technologies in general, and LoCs in particular. This is considerably more appealing to potential users than iteratively applying an ad-hoc design process and then using formal methods exclusively to establish the (in)correctness of each resulting design. This project will tightly integrate CAD software that employs a sketch-based interface, in-line with current design practices today, with fluid modeling algorithms that can iteratively assist the user in terms of refining the sketch and semi-automatically rendering a 3D image of the working device, which accounts for component and channel geometries, etc. It will also provide the option to employ design automation algorithms to accelerate the design process, automatic design rule checking, and will help guide the user to select appropriate fabrication technologies and materials in line with cost, time-to-market, and product performance objectives. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Personnel involved in this project, one Postdoctoral researcher and one PhD student, will receive innovation, entrepreneurship, and technology translation experiences through training and mentorship on business-related topics provided by project Co-PI Gunnar Hurtig, and a "Technology Transfer Roadshow" spearheaded by UCR's Technology Transfer Office, which are expected to culminate in company formation.  The project engages Lattice Automation, Inc., PharmaSeq, and Potomac Affinity Proteins, LLC, who will permit the project team to use the microfluidic CAD software to reproduce existing products, and possibly to design new products, which can provide initial validation of the CAD software prototype in this technology translation effort from research discovery toward commercial reality.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1640757</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michalis</FirstName>
<LastName>Faloutsos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michalis Faloutsos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>michalis@cs.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518275639</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000487350</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Brisk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philip L Brisk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>philip@cs.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518272030</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000546762</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Grover</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William H Grover</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wgrover@engr.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518274311</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000650145</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gunnar</FirstName>
<LastName>Hurtig III</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gunnar Hurtig III</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gunnarh@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518275535</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000659670</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/21/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research &amp; Economic Development</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[245 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>44</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA44</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627797426</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~199999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-3a62c688-7fff-935f-6c94-7e642848bf14"> <p dir="ltr"><span>This research project aimed to reduce the risk associated with commercialization of design software specific to microfluidics and laboratory on-a-chip technology. </span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>The intellectual merit of the project focused on the creation of a user-friendly graphical interface and effectively integrating fluid modeling algorithms into the design process. This led to a number of high-impact publications in both Computer Science and Chemistry/Microfluidics/Technology-oriented peer-reviewed conferences and journals. The PI and collaborators have founded a company to commercialize the software artifact produced by the research funded by this award. </span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>In terms of broader impacts, microfluidics and Laboratory-on-a-Chip (LoC) technology are used for a wide variety of purposes, the vast majority of which directly benefit society. The key benefits of LoCs compared to traditional benchtop chemistry methods are miniaturization (which reduces the physical volume of samples and reagents used) and automation, which reduces cost and mostly eliminates human errors. Moving forward, it is expected that automation will allow the creation of new bioassays (chemical procedures) that incorporate orders of magnitude more steps than could be carried out by human laboratory technicians. The research conducted under this award aimed to simplify the design process for microfluidic chips. This, in turn, lowers the barrier to entry, thereby increasing the number of scientists who can use microfluidics into their laboratories and the number of companies that sell products that integrate microfluidic features. </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Other broader impacts include the training of Project Scientists, PhD students, and undergraduates studying Bioengineering and Computer Science at the University of California, Riverside. Several of the project participants are from groups typically underrepresented in STEM, including women, African Americans, and Latin(o/a)s; the PI published several peer-reviewed papers with undergraduate co-authors, including several women. Additionally, the project entailed extensive outreach to stakeholders including researchers in the biological and chemical sciences, as well as the Microfluidics Consortium, an industry group comprising ~25 small-to-medium sized companies working on microfluidics. Lastly, the PI and other project participants trained local teachers in California to integrate programming knowledge and concepts into their curriculum, to improve computer literacy and improve the technical capabilities of the next-generation workforce.</span></p> </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/18/2019<br>      Modified by: Philip&nbsp;L&nbsp;Brisk</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This research project aimed to reduce the risk associated with commercialization of design software specific to microfluidics and laboratory on-a-chip technology.    The intellectual merit of the project focused on the creation of a user-friendly graphical interface and effectively integrating fluid modeling algorithms into the design process. This led to a number of high-impact publications in both Computer Science and Chemistry/Microfluidics/Technology-oriented peer-reviewed conferences and journals. The PI and collaborators have founded a company to commercialize the software artifact produced by the research funded by this award.    In terms of broader impacts, microfluidics and Laboratory-on-a-Chip (LoC) technology are used for a wide variety of purposes, the vast majority of which directly benefit society. The key benefits of LoCs compared to traditional benchtop chemistry methods are miniaturization (which reduces the physical volume of samples and reagents used) and automation, which reduces cost and mostly eliminates human errors. Moving forward, it is expected that automation will allow the creation of new bioassays (chemical procedures) that incorporate orders of magnitude more steps than could be carried out by human laboratory technicians. The research conducted under this award aimed to simplify the design process for microfluidic chips. This, in turn, lowers the barrier to entry, thereby increasing the number of scientists who can use microfluidics into their laboratories and the number of companies that sell products that integrate microfluidic features.  Other broader impacts include the training of Project Scientists, PhD students, and undergraduates studying Bioengineering and Computer Science at the University of California, Riverside. Several of the project participants are from groups typically underrepresented in STEM, including women, African Americans, and Latin(o/a)s; the PI published several peer-reviewed papers with undergraduate co-authors, including several women. Additionally, the project entailed extensive outreach to stakeholders including researchers in the biological and chemical sciences, as well as the Microfluidics Consortium, an industry group comprising ~25 small-to-medium sized companies working on microfluidics. Lastly, the PI and other project participants trained local teachers in California to integrate programming knowledge and concepts into their curriculum, to improve computer literacy and improve the technical capabilities of the next-generation workforce.           Last Modified: 03/18/2019       Submitted by: Philip L Brisk]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
