<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research and Assessment on Synergistic Learning of Physics and Programming through Computational Modeling and Problem Solving</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2499682.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2499682</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wu He</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wuhe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927593</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Computing and computational thinking (CT) are an integral part of everyday practice within modern fields of science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM). As a result, the STEM+Computing Partnerships (STEM+C) program seeks to advance new multidisciplinary approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the integration of computing in STEM teaching and learning, and discipline-specific efforts in computing designed to build an evidence base for teaching and learning of computer science in K-12, including within diverse populations. Integrating CT into core science instruction addresses practical constraints in K-12 education, in that there is no room in the curriculum to teach it directly to everyone. But, more importantly, integrating CT into core science provides a synergistic opportunity to deepen instruction in both. This project investigates the synergistic learning of physics and CT concepts and practices through students' construction of and interaction with computational models that visually represent physical systems.  Led by investigators at Vanderbilt University, the project team includes computer scientists, physicists, education developers, and learning scientists SRI International, Stanford, and Salem State University. The project will develop, implement, and study an innovative programming environment, a multi-week computational physics curriculum, and new assessments that are focused on physics concepts of force and motion and CT practices involved in computational modeling. Guided by the programming environment and the curriculum, learners construct models that represent physical systems, analyze and explain model behaviors, and then use models for solving problems. These processes support their abilities to think and act like a scientist as they explore and learn about both the computational and physical systems and phenomena. Assessments will be developed to measure CT-infused physics learning that is targeted in the curriculum, but also what CT learners apply to new physics topics and problem-solving situations they encounter. The educational program will address specific needs of high school students and teachers with regard to relevant disciplinary content, practices, and computation as specified in Next Generation Science Standards, the AP Computer Science Principles, and recent consensus frameworks for computational thinking in STEM. Approximately 450 students will be involved with and benefit from the project in four diverse high school settings. The diverse nature of the participating schools will both engage a demographically diverse student population in STEM and help the project achieve significant broader impacts, by assuring that the findings and products developed reflect the needs of a broad diversity of people and places. The project will develop new educational technologies, curriculum materials, and assessments for integrating physics and computation that will be broadly usable in high school physics and computer science courses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will investigate a method of broadening access to CT through the integration of computational modeling and problem solving in secondary physics courses.  Through constructing computational models that represent complex physical systems, students will learn key concepts of Newtonian physics and CT practices of problem representation, abstraction, decomposition, composition, and verification.  The project will produce a new programming environment that is optimized for modeling physics systems and phenomena, that facilitates collaborative modeling and problem solving, and that diagnoses and responds to users' learning activity with adaptive scaffolds. Three standards-aligned, problem-oriented computational physics units will be developed and used in conjunction with the programming environment. Evidence-centered design will be used to develop and validate assessments that measure CT-infused physics learning that is targeted in the units. A unique set of assessments will be developed independent of the modeling environment to measure whether and what CT students spontaneously transfer to new physics problems and learning situations. The curriculum and assessments with be co-developed by researchers and four teachers from diverse high school settings in Tennessee and California. Quantitative and qualitative analyses of student assessments, surveys, work products, computer-use logs, and videotaped tasks will be used to determine the effectiveness and broad utility of the approach - and its component parts - for integrating physics and computing. By tackling the challenge to align offline and online measures of students' learning and behaviors, the project will generate deeper understanding of how students learn, the difficulties they face, and the promise of adaptive scaffolds for improving learning. The research will also elucidate the potential of explicit CT frameworks for preparing students' for future physics learning and problem solving. The project will provide the field with a strong foundation for designing learning technologies that integrate science and computational modeling. The research findings will be shared with the project team members' respective communities in computer science, technology education, cyberlearning, physics education, science education, and teacher education through papers in peer-reviewed journals and conference presentations. Efforts will be made to disseminate to teachers through practitioners workshops, conferences, and journals. A post-doctoral fellow and three graduate students will be trained through this project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1640199</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gautam</FirstName>
<LastName>Biswas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gautam Biswas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gautam.biswas@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153436204</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000110341</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Schwartz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel L Schwartz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniel.schwartz@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507361514</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000470265</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Akos</FirstName>
<LastName>Ledeczi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Akos Ledeczi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>akos.ledeczi@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153438307</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000348998</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>McElhaney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin W McElhaney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kevin.mcelhaney@sri.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6508592651</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000677331</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shuchi</FirstName>
<LastName>Grover</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shuchi Grover</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shuchi.grover@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175496586</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000688029</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PMB 407749 2301 Vanderbilt Place]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965717143</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004413456</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372122809</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 18th Avenue South]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>005Y</Code>
<Text>STEM + Computing (STEM+C) Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~2499682</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Computation is now considered to be the third pillar of science and engineering disciplines, alongside theory and experimentation. Computing knowledge and skills provide the foundation for modern competency in STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math)-related fields, prompting research on how to best prepare students for the 21st century workforce and lifelong learning. Exploiting the synergies between science and computation can bring about a fundamental change in the way that science learning occurs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The Collaborative, Computational STEM (C2STEM) learning environment is a multi-institutional project led by Vanderbilt University and including partners from Stanford University, SRI International, Salem State University, and Looking Glass Ventures. ETR was the project evaluator. We have designed and developed the C2STEM environment, adopting a learning by modeling paradigm and a CT platform that is based on a novel computational approach. The approach combines visual programming with the concept of domain-specific modeling languages to support K-12 students learning science (e.g., Physics, Marine Biology, and Genetics) by building computational models of scientific processes.&nbsp; Our research has demonstrated that the computational modeling paradigm has been successful in helping students synergistically learn their science and computing concepts and practices. &nbsp;The accompanying.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The C2STEM system adopts a constructive, inquiry and problem-based learning approach. Students are first introduced to an overarching problem domain, e.g., transportation, and an overall challenge problem of delivering medicines to a tribe in a remote Amazon jungle. We have used the notion of evidence-centered design to decompose the overall curriculum into four modules: three in kinematics: (1) 1D land transportation with constant acceleration and deceleration motion, (2) 2D constant velocity motion for transportation across a river, and (3) 2D accelerated motion (with gravity as a factor) for package delivery in a remote area using a flying drone. The fourth module covers 1D and 2D motion with forces (including static and dynamic friction). Similarly, the Marine Biology and Genetics curriculum are decomposed into multiple curricular modules. To support classroom instruction, each topical module is decomposed into sets of instructional, model-building, challenge, and embedded assessment tasks. Classroom teachers have successfully used this system in high school Physics and upper middle school science classrooms. Figures 1-6 illustrate different facets of the C2STEM system.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To assist classroom teachers in assessing synergistic student learning, and to advance our own research we have developed a principled evidence-centered design (ECD) approach to developing STEM and CS assessments. These assessments include summative and formative components that align with (1) the NRC Science Framework, and (2) AP CS Principles and the new K-12 CS framework (k12cs.org). A third innovative research component includes a novel Preparation for Future Learning (PFL) approach to assessing learning by modeling by examining students&rsquo; ability and propensity to apply computational constructs and CT practices while learning new STEM topics and working on new problems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We have evaluated the effectiveness of the C2STEM system and the accompanying curricula and assessments by running a number of studies in high school classrooms in California, Massachusetts, and Tennessee. Similar, but simpler versions of the Physics, Marine Biology, and Genetics curricula have been used in classroom studies in Illinois and Tennessee.&nbsp; Our studies have assessed students&rsquo; synergistic learning processes, especially in the way their model building and model checking (i.e., debugging) processes shift fluidly back and forth between say, &ldquo;doing physics&rdquo; and &ldquo;doing code&rdquo;. This has been especially useful in tracking and understanding students&rsquo; debugging processes, especially understanding the difficulties they have in combining domain and computation concepts to build models. In analyzing students&rsquo; framing, we have also found evidence that students, at least at times, frame their activity as scientific exploration. Our integrated STEM and CT formative and summative assessments have provided deep understanding of how students&rsquo; domain and CT learning of concepts and practices evolve over time, the difficulties they face in their modeling tasks, and how this hinders their learning of essential curricular material. On the other hand, students who become proficient in synergistic practices also demonstrate through our PFL assessments, better learning of domain material and the ability to transfer their learning to new problems and new domains. We have also conducted collaborative learning studies, where students work on their model and knowledge construction tasks in groups of two or three. Analyzing student dialogues have provided us with valuable insights on how students develop and apply synergistic processes to advance in their learning and problem solving tasks.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project has generated a number of journal and conference publications. We have conducted a number of workshops, and overall, we have demonstrated that integrating STEM and CT education can greatly benefit learning in the STEM and computing disciplines. Overall, we hope our work helps educators, researchers, and industry stakeholders recognize that students need to learn computational thinking (CT) to become active learners and creators of the next wave of computing innovations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2020<br>      Modified by: Gautam&nbsp;Biswas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588304570760_Figure1-Solvinga1-DaccelerationprobleminC2STEM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588304570760_Figure1-Solvinga1-DaccelerationprobleminC2STEM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="C2STEM Modeling Environment"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588304570760_Figure1-Solvinga1-DaccelerationprobleminC2STEM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="C2STEM Modeling Environment"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students solve a 1-D acceleration motion challenge, where they have to model a truck starting from rest, speeding up to the speed limit, cruising at the speed limit, and then stopping at the STOP sign</div> <div class="imageCredit">OELE Lab, Vanderbilt University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gautam&nbsp;Biswas</div> <div class="imageTitle">C2STEM Modeling Environment</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588304845986_figure3-2DForces-Mechanics--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588304845986_figure3-2DForces-Mechanics--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2-D Forces Motion Challenge Problem"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588304845986_figure3-2DForces-Mechanics--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2-D Forces Motion Challenge Problem"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students are required to model the combination of a Buggy and Drone working together to move a neavy package on a warehouse floor</div> <div class="imageCredit">OELE Lab - Vanderbilt University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gautam&nbsp;Biswas</div> <div class="imageTitle">2-D Forces Motion Challenge Problem</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588305277130_Figure5-MarineBiologyCoralBleachingUnit--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588305277130_Figure5-MarineBiologyCoralBleachingUnit--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Marine Biology Unit - Modeling Coral Reef Health"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588305277130_Figure5-MarineBiologyCoralBleachingUnit--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Marine Biology Unit - Modeling Coral Reef Health"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students study data of coral reef health as a function of ocean temperature and acidity, and then build a model of coral bleaching and coral health as a function of ocean temperate</div> <div class="imageCredit">OELE Lab - Vanderbilt University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gautam&nbsp;Biswas</div> <div class="imageTitle">Marine Biology Unit - Modeling Coral Reef Health</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588305619953_Figure2-PhyiscsandMarineBiologyDSMLs--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588305619953_Figure2-PhyiscsandMarineBiologyDSMLs--rgov-800width.jpg" title="DSMLs for Physics and Marine Biology"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588305619953_Figure2-PhyiscsandMarineBiologyDSMLs--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="DSMLs for Physics and Marine Biology"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">To facilitate the modeling tasks, and support synergistic learning of STEM and CT, we have created domain specific modeling blocks for each science domain</div> <div class="imageCredit">OELE Lab - Vanderbilt University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gautam&nbsp;Biswas</div> <div class="imageTitle">DSMLs for Physics and Marine Biology</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588305927345_Figure4-ClassroomInstructionwithC2STEM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588305927345_Figure4-ClassroomInstructionwithC2STEM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Teaching Projectile Motion in High School classroom"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588305927345_Figure4-ClassroomInstructionwithC2STEM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Teaching Projectile Motion in High School classroom"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Classroom instruction in a high school Physics Honors classroom with C2STEM</div> <div class="imageCredit">OELE Lab - Vanderbilt University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gautam&nbsp;Biswas</div> <div class="imageTitle">Teaching Projectile Motion in High School classroom</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588306272066_Figure6-KinematicsReviewLinkingtotheRealWorld--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588306272066_Figure6-KinematicsReviewLinkingtotheRealWorld--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Kinematics Review in a High School Physics Class"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1640199/1640199_10456007_1588306272066_Figure6-KinematicsReviewLinkingtotheRealWorld--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Kinematics Review in a High School Physics Class"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Instructor and Researcher  reviewing  high school Physics topics -- working on modeling a key drop to connect equations of motion to real-world observations</div> <div class="imageCredit">OELE Lab - Vanderbilt University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gautam&nbsp;Biswas</div> <div class="imageTitle">Kinematics Review in a High School Physics Class</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Computation is now considered to be the third pillar of science and engineering disciplines, alongside theory and experimentation. Computing knowledge and skills provide the foundation for modern competency in STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math)-related fields, prompting research on how to best prepare students for the 21st century workforce and lifelong learning. Exploiting the synergies between science and computation can bring about a fundamental change in the way that science learning occurs.     The Collaborative, Computational STEM (C2STEM) learning environment is a multi-institutional project led by Vanderbilt University and including partners from Stanford University, SRI International, Salem State University, and Looking Glass Ventures. ETR was the project evaluator. We have designed and developed the C2STEM environment, adopting a learning by modeling paradigm and a CT platform that is based on a novel computational approach. The approach combines visual programming with the concept of domain-specific modeling languages to support K-12 students learning science (e.g., Physics, Marine Biology, and Genetics) by building computational models of scientific processes.  Our research has demonstrated that the computational modeling paradigm has been successful in helping students synergistically learn their science and computing concepts and practices.  The accompanying.     The C2STEM system adopts a constructive, inquiry and problem-based learning approach. Students are first introduced to an overarching problem domain, e.g., transportation, and an overall challenge problem of delivering medicines to a tribe in a remote Amazon jungle. We have used the notion of evidence-centered design to decompose the overall curriculum into four modules: three in kinematics: (1) 1D land transportation with constant acceleration and deceleration motion, (2) 2D constant velocity motion for transportation across a river, and (3) 2D accelerated motion (with gravity as a factor) for package delivery in a remote area using a flying drone. The fourth module covers 1D and 2D motion with forces (including static and dynamic friction). Similarly, the Marine Biology and Genetics curriculum are decomposed into multiple curricular modules. To support classroom instruction, each topical module is decomposed into sets of instructional, model-building, challenge, and embedded assessment tasks. Classroom teachers have successfully used this system in high school Physics and upper middle school science classrooms. Figures 1-6 illustrate different facets of the C2STEM system.     To assist classroom teachers in assessing synergistic student learning, and to advance our own research we have developed a principled evidence-centered design (ECD) approach to developing STEM and CS assessments. These assessments include summative and formative components that align with (1) the NRC Science Framework, and (2) AP CS Principles and the new K-12 CS framework (k12cs.org). A third innovative research component includes a novel Preparation for Future Learning (PFL) approach to assessing learning by modeling by examining students’ ability and propensity to apply computational constructs and CT practices while learning new STEM topics and working on new problems.     We have evaluated the effectiveness of the C2STEM system and the accompanying curricula and assessments by running a number of studies in high school classrooms in California, Massachusetts, and Tennessee. Similar, but simpler versions of the Physics, Marine Biology, and Genetics curricula have been used in classroom studies in Illinois and Tennessee.  Our studies have assessed students’ synergistic learning processes, especially in the way their model building and model checking (i.e., debugging) processes shift fluidly back and forth between say, "doing physics" and "doing code". This has been especially useful in tracking and understanding students’ debugging processes, especially understanding the difficulties they have in combining domain and computation concepts to build models. In analyzing students’ framing, we have also found evidence that students, at least at times, frame their activity as scientific exploration. Our integrated STEM and CT formative and summative assessments have provided deep understanding of how students’ domain and CT learning of concepts and practices evolve over time, the difficulties they face in their modeling tasks, and how this hinders their learning of essential curricular material. On the other hand, students who become proficient in synergistic practices also demonstrate through our PFL assessments, better learning of domain material and the ability to transfer their learning to new problems and new domains. We have also conducted collaborative learning studies, where students work on their model and knowledge construction tasks in groups of two or three. Analyzing student dialogues have provided us with valuable insights on how students develop and apply synergistic processes to advance in their learning and problem solving tasks.     This project has generated a number of journal and conference publications. We have conducted a number of workshops, and overall, we have demonstrated that integrating STEM and CT education can greatly benefit learning in the STEM and computing disciplines. Overall, we hope our work helps educators, researchers, and industry stakeholders recognize that students need to learn computational thinking (CT) to become active learners and creators of the next wave of computing innovations.          Last Modified: 05/02/2020       Submitted by: Gautam Biswas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
