<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Holistic Integration for Arctic Coastal-Marine Sustainability (HIACMS)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1028736.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1028736</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erica Hill</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>erhill@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924521</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This 3-year research project will develop and demonstrate an international, interdisciplinary and inclusive process to enhance the practice of governance for sustainability in Arctic coastal-marine systems, balancing: (a) national interests and common interests, (b) environmental protection, social equity, and economic prosperity, and (c) the needs of present and future generations. We will use geospatial integration and interdisciplinary data aggregation to document biophysical and socioeconomic changes occurring in the Arctic and to develop scenarios exploring how these complex patterns of change are likely to play out over the coming decades. This assessment will include all four ArcSEES themes (Natural and Living Environment; Built Environment; Natural Resource Development; and Governance) and provide a point of departure for the use of institutional diagnostics to examine effective strategies for addressing  current issues of Arctic governance.  To lend substance to the analysis, we will direct attention to three "hot spots": Bering Strait and the Beaufort and Chukchi Seas (United States, Canadian and Russian interests), the Barents Sea (Norwegian and Russian interests), and West Greenland (Greenlandic, Danish, and Canadian interests). In the process, we will engage people associated with bodies like the Convention for the Protection of the Marine Environment of the North-East Atlantic, whose remit extends into the Arctic Ocean.  To enhance cost-effectiveness, the project will collaborate with the SEARCH (Study of Environmental Change: www.arcus.org/search) and ACCESS  (Arctic Climate Change, Economy and Society: www.access-eu.org) projects that are supported extensively within the United States and Europe, respectively. The project, which is jointly funded by the National Science Foundation and Centre Nationale de al Recherche Scientifique, will add value through partnerships with the National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis (www.nceas.ucsb.edu) in the United States and institutions in France associated with the ACCESS project as well as the Ice Atmosphere Arctic Ocean Observing System project (www.iaoos-equipex.upmc.fr). The holistic process we develop to generate and share options for Arctic coastal-marine sustainability will be memorialized by publications and through a video series emphasizing lessons of ?science diplomacy? to further stimulate education by and for the benefit of all stakeholders - representatives of government agencies, academia, industry, non-governmental organizations, and civil society. The sustainability process we develop and demonstrate in this project focusing on the Arctic Ocean will have implications everywhere on Earth where resources, human activities, and their impacts extend across or beyond the boundaries of sovereign states.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/05/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1641241</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul Arthur</FirstName>
<LastName>Berkman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul Arthur Berkman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>paul@evresearch.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6179028361</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000701172</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/05/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tufts University</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>021111817</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176273696</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>136 Harrison Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073134835</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF TUFTS COLLEGE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073134835</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tufts University]]></Name>
<CityName>Medford</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021555807</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Research Administratio]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5219</Code>
<Text>ARCSS-Arctic System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8109</Code>
<Text>ArcSEES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>SEES Unsolicited</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8560</Code>
<Text>ARC-SEES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~1028736</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project on &ldquo;Holistic Integration for Arctic Coastal-Marine Sustainability&rdquo; received funding in 2013 from the ArcSEES (Arctic Science, Engineering, and Education for Sustainability) program and became known operationally as ARCTIC OPTIONS. &nbsp;The geographic scope of this international, interdisciplinary and inclusive (<strong>holistic</strong>) project encompassed the Bering Strait Region, Barents Sea Region, and Arctic High Seas with analytic focus on <strong>governance mechanisms</strong> (laws, agreements and policies as well as regulatory strategies, including insurance, at diverse jurisdictional levels). This project included partners in the United States and France. Throughout, the project recognized <strong>sustainability </strong>as a matter of balancing: (1) environmental protection, economic prosperity and social equity; (2) urgencies of the present and needs of the future; and (3) national interests and common interests to promote cooperation and prevent conflict.&nbsp; In 2015, ARCTIC OPTIONS was formally integrated through the National Science Foundation with the PAN-ARCTIC OPTIONS project (also focusing on &ldquo;Holistic Integration for Arctic Coastal-Marine Sustainability&rdquo;) with expanded: (1) geographic scope to cover the entire coastal-marine region north of the Arctic Circle; and (2) conceptual scope to include <strong>built infrastructure</strong> (fixed, mobile and other assets, including communication, research, observing, information and other systems that require technology plus investment). PAN-ARCTIC OPTIONS received funding through the Belmont Forum with additional program partners in Canada, China, Norway and the Russian Federation. &nbsp;These two intertwined projects considered <strong>options</strong> (without advocacy), which can be used or ignored explicitly, as practical solutions co-produced with decisionmakers through an holistic process of common-interest building, in contrast to recommendations involving advocacy and often-polarizing agendas navigated by conflict resolution. Both projects centered on the development of science diplomacy as an holistic process, characterizing <strong>science as the &lsquo;study of change&rsquo;</strong> to include natural sciences, social sciences and Indigenous knowledge, all of which reveal patterns, trends and processes (albeit with different methodologies) that support decisions.&nbsp; The ARCTIC OPTIONS project leveraged additional resources and created momentum with accelerating knowledge co-production that justified three no-cost extensions through 2019. Synergies from these holistic projects catalyzed the 2016 development of the first Science Diplomacy Center in the world in an academic institution, which co-convened the first dialogues with the Foreign Ministry Science and Technology Advisory Network, involving dozens of foreign ministries that together distilled the framework of a <strong>&lsquo;continuum of urgencies&rsquo;</strong> from <strong>security time scales </strong>(mitigating risks of economic, environmental and societal instabilities that are immediate) to <strong>sustainability time scales </strong>(balancing environmental protection, economic prosperity and societal well-being across generations). This operational framework for informed decisions is memorialized in the new serial, <em>Science Diplomacy Action</em>, with co-authorship from foreign ministries.&nbsp; &nbsp;Together, these holistic projects also introduced the oldest and longest continuous satellite record of Arctic ship traffic, derived from Automatic Identification System (AIS) data collected by SpaceQuest Ltd. from 1 September 2009 through 31 December 2016. &nbsp;Analyses using these &lsquo;big data&rsquo; (with more than 120,000,000 data points) involved the ESRI&trade; &lsquo;Space-Time Cube&rsquo; as a Geographic Information System (GIS) solution implemented in the cloud with Google&trade; &lsquo;BigQuery&rsquo; to generate results in seconds with nominal costs.&nbsp; Results have been interpreted quantitatively as the basis for <em>Next-Generation Arctic Marine Shipping Assessments.&nbsp;&nbsp;</em>Syntheses emanating from ARCTIC OPTIONS &ndash; including the concept of &lsquo;ecopolitical regions&rsquo; (biophysical areas are bisected by jurisdictional boundaries) &ndash; are elaborated in <strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Governing Arctic Seas: Regional Lessons from the Bering Strait and Barents Sea</span>, </strong>which is the first volume in a new book Springer book series on<strong> <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Informed Decisionmaking for Sustainability</span></strong>.&nbsp; Triangulation with research, education and leadership is further reflected by diverse: (1) peer-reviewed journal publications, including in <em>Science</em> (&ldquo;The Arctic Science Agreement Propels Science Diplomacy&rdquo;); (2) high-level dialogues, including with the President and Foreign Minister of Iceland, ambassadors from Arctic and non-Arctic states, Senior Arctic Officials, leaders of Indigenous Peoples Organizations, and heads of international Arctic science programs; and (3) education activities, including: the <em>Science Diplomacy Thematic Network</em> through the University of the Arctic; joint video-conferencing course on &ldquo;Science Diplomacy&rdquo; between American and Russian institutions; and the <em>Science Diplomacy: Dissertation Enhancement Workshop</em> series in Boston. &nbsp;In addition, facilitating international transparency, these holistic projects produced the comprehensive <strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Baseline of Russian Arctic Laws</span></strong> that was published by Springer as the authentic English translation all Russian Arctic laws since the early 19<sup>th</sup> century.&nbsp; The theory, methods and skills of informed decisionmaking are a legacy of ARCTIC OPTIONS, involving close coupling between governance mechanisms and built infrastructure to achieve progress with sustainable development, which is a &lsquo;common Arctic issue&rsquo; (as identified in the 1996 <em>Ottawa Declaration</em> that established the Arctic Council).&nbsp; Broader impacts of the projects are additionally highlighted by adoption of science diplomacy and its engine of informed decisionmaking as a component of diplomatic training from the United Nations Institute of Training and Research (UNITAR) as well as with individual national diplomatic academies, involving informed decisionmaking to balance national interests and common interests for the benefit of all on Earth across generations.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Paul Arthur&nbsp;Berkman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1573164035923_GoverningArcticSeas_cover--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1573164035923_GoverningArcticSeas_cover--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Governing Arctic Seas: Regional Lessons from the Bering Strait and Barents Sea"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1573164035923_GoverningArcticSeas_cover--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Governing Arctic Seas: Regional Lessons from the Bering Strait and Barents Sea"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Young, O.R., Vyelgzhanin, A.N. (eds). 2019. Governing Arctic Seas: Regional Lessons from the Bering Strait and Barents Sea. Springer, Dordrecht. (in press).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Springer</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul Arthur&nbsp;Berkman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Governing Arctic Seas: Regional Lessons from the Bering Strait and Barents Sea</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1573163790416_BaselineofRussianArcticLaws_Berkman-Vylegzhanin-Young_BookCover_Springer2019--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1573163790416_BaselineofRussianArcticLaws_Berkman-Vylegzhanin-Young_BookCover_Springer2019--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Baseline of Russian Arctic Laws"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1573163790416_BaselineofRussianArcticLaws_Berkman-Vylegzhanin-Young_BookCover_Springer2019--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Baseline of Russian Arctic Laws"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Berkman, P.A., Vylegzhanin, A.N and Young, O.R. 2019. Baseline of Russian Arctic Laws. Springer, Dordrecht</div> <div class="imageCredit">Springer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul Arthur&nbsp;Berkman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Baseline of Russian Arctic Laws</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1574430010699_Oldest-longestcontinuoussatelliterecordofArcticshiptraffic--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1574430010699_Oldest-longestcontinuoussatelliterecordofArcticshiptraffic--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Oldest and Longest Continuous Satellite Record of Arctic Ship Traffic"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1574430010699_Oldest-longestcontinuoussatelliterecordofArcticshiptraffic--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Oldest and Longest Continuous Satellite Record of Arctic Ship Traffic"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Oldest and longest continuous satellite record of Arctic ship traffic,  analyzing Automatic Identification System (AIS) big data from 1 September 2009 through 31 December 2016</div> <div class="imageCredit">Prof. Paul Arthur Berkman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul Arthur&nbsp;Berkman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Oldest and Longest Continuous Satellite Record of Arctic Ship Traffic</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1574430159004_Oldest-longestsatelliterecordofship-iceinteractionsintheArcticOcean--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1574430159004_Oldest-longestsatelliterecordofship-iceinteractionsintheArcticOcean--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Oldest and Longest Satellite Record of Ship-Ice Interactions in the Arctic Ocean"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1574430159004_Oldest-longestsatelliterecordofship-iceinteractionsintheArcticOcean--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Oldest and Longest Satellite Record of Ship-Ice Interactions in the Arctic Ocean"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Oldest and longest satellite record of ship-ice interactions in the Arctic Ocean, with 4km2 grid-spacing daily from 1 September 2009 through 31 December 2016</div> <div class="imageCredit">Prof. Paul Arthur Berkman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul Arthur&nbsp;Berkman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Oldest and Longest Satellite Record of Ship-Ice Interactions in the Arctic Ocean</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1574430345438_Informationecologyanddata'ecosystem'--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1574430345438_Informationecologyanddata'ecosystem'--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Information Ecology and Data Ecosystems"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1574430345438_Informationecologyanddata'ecosystem'--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Information Ecology and Data Ecosystems"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conceptual framework of information ecology with operational relationships in an 'ecosystem' of diverse data</div> <div class="imageCredit">Prof. Peter Pulsifer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul Arthur&nbsp;Berkman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Information Ecology and Data Ecosystems</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1574430592100_Sciencediplomacyanditsengineofinformeddecisionmaking--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1574430592100_Sciencediplomacyanditsengineofinformeddecisionmaking--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Science Diplomacy and its Engine of Informed Decisionmaking"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1641241/1641241_10280318_1574430592100_Sciencediplomacyanditsengineofinformeddecisionmaking--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Science Diplomacy and its Engine of Informed Decisionmaking"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Methodologies with science diplomacy (questions - data - evidence - options - informed decisions) that are being applied, trained and refined across a 'continuum of urgencies' at local-global scales</div> <div class="imageCredit">Prof. Paul Arthur Berkman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul Arthur&nbsp;Berkman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Science Diplomacy and its Engine of Informed Decisionmaking</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project on "Holistic Integration for Arctic Coastal-Marine Sustainability" received funding in 2013 from the ArcSEES (Arctic Science, Engineering, and Education for Sustainability) program and became known operationally as ARCTIC OPTIONS.  The geographic scope of this international, interdisciplinary and inclusive (holistic) project encompassed the Bering Strait Region, Barents Sea Region, and Arctic High Seas with analytic focus on governance mechanisms (laws, agreements and policies as well as regulatory strategies, including insurance, at diverse jurisdictional levels). This project included partners in the United States and France. Throughout, the project recognized sustainability as a matter of balancing: (1) environmental protection, economic prosperity and social equity; (2) urgencies of the present and needs of the future; and (3) national interests and common interests to promote cooperation and prevent conflict.  In 2015, ARCTIC OPTIONS was formally integrated through the National Science Foundation with the PAN-ARCTIC OPTIONS project (also focusing on "Holistic Integration for Arctic Coastal-Marine Sustainability") with expanded: (1) geographic scope to cover the entire coastal-marine region north of the Arctic Circle; and (2) conceptual scope to include built infrastructure (fixed, mobile and other assets, including communication, research, observing, information and other systems that require technology plus investment). PAN-ARCTIC OPTIONS received funding through the Belmont Forum with additional program partners in Canada, China, Norway and the Russian Federation.  These two intertwined projects considered options (without advocacy), which can be used or ignored explicitly, as practical solutions co-produced with decisionmakers through an holistic process of common-interest building, in contrast to recommendations involving advocacy and often-polarizing agendas navigated by conflict resolution. Both projects centered on the development of science diplomacy as an holistic process, characterizing science as the ‘study of change’ to include natural sciences, social sciences and Indigenous knowledge, all of which reveal patterns, trends and processes (albeit with different methodologies) that support decisions.  The ARCTIC OPTIONS project leveraged additional resources and created momentum with accelerating knowledge co-production that justified three no-cost extensions through 2019. Synergies from these holistic projects catalyzed the 2016 development of the first Science Diplomacy Center in the world in an academic institution, which co-convened the first dialogues with the Foreign Ministry Science and Technology Advisory Network, involving dozens of foreign ministries that together distilled the framework of a ‘continuum of urgencies’ from security time scales (mitigating risks of economic, environmental and societal instabilities that are immediate) to sustainability time scales (balancing environmental protection, economic prosperity and societal well-being across generations). This operational framework for informed decisions is memorialized in the new serial, Science Diplomacy Action, with co-authorship from foreign ministries.   Together, these holistic projects also introduced the oldest and longest continuous satellite record of Arctic ship traffic, derived from Automatic Identification System (AIS) data collected by SpaceQuest Ltd. from 1 September 2009 through 31 December 2016.  Analyses using these ‘big data’ (with more than 120,000,000 data points) involved the ESRI&trade; ‘Space-Time Cube’ as a Geographic Information System (GIS) solution implemented in the cloud with Google&trade; ‘BigQuery’ to generate results in seconds with nominal costs.  Results have been interpreted quantitatively as the basis for Next-Generation Arctic Marine Shipping Assessments.  Syntheses emanating from ARCTIC OPTIONS &ndash; including the concept of ‘ecopolitical regions’ (biophysical areas are bisected by jurisdictional boundaries) &ndash; are elaborated in Governing Arctic Seas: Regional Lessons from the Bering Strait and Barents Sea, which is the first volume in a new book Springer book series on Informed Decisionmaking for Sustainability.  Triangulation with research, education and leadership is further reflected by diverse: (1) peer-reviewed journal publications, including in Science ("The Arctic Science Agreement Propels Science Diplomacy"); (2) high-level dialogues, including with the President and Foreign Minister of Iceland, ambassadors from Arctic and non-Arctic states, Senior Arctic Officials, leaders of Indigenous Peoples Organizations, and heads of international Arctic science programs; and (3) education activities, including: the Science Diplomacy Thematic Network through the University of the Arctic; joint video-conferencing course on "Science Diplomacy" between American and Russian institutions; and the Science Diplomacy: Dissertation Enhancement Workshop series in Boston.  In addition, facilitating international transparency, these holistic projects produced the comprehensive Baseline of Russian Arctic Laws that was published by Springer as the authentic English translation all Russian Arctic laws since the early 19th century.  The theory, methods and skills of informed decisionmaking are a legacy of ARCTIC OPTIONS, involving close coupling between governance mechanisms and built infrastructure to achieve progress with sustainable development, which is a ‘common Arctic issue’ (as identified in the 1996 Ottawa Declaration that established the Arctic Council).  Broader impacts of the projects are additionally highlighted by adoption of science diplomacy and its engine of informed decisionmaking as a component of diplomatic training from the United Nations Institute of Training and Research (UNITAR) as well as with individual national diplomatic academies, involving informed decisionmaking to balance national interests and common interests for the benefit of all on Earth across generations.        Last Modified: 11/29/2019       Submitted by: Paul Arthur Berkman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
