<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Phase I I/UCRC Iowa State U. Site: Center for Advanced Non-Ferrous Structural Alloys (CANFSA)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/18/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>8909.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>16909</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1134882 Colorado School of Mines; Michael Kaufman &lt;br/&gt;1134873 University of North Texas; Peter Collins &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Center for Advanced Non-Ferrous Structural Alloys will focus on the physical metallurgy of non-ferrous alloys (alloying and processing effects on microstructure, properties and performance) and on the industries that develop, manufacture, and use these alloys. Colorado School of Mines (CSM) and the University of North Texas (UNT) are collaborating to establish the proposed center, with CSM as the lead institution. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed Center aims to establish the industrial support, operational mechanisms, and a prospective research portfolio for a viable research Center that will conduct critical basic and applied physical metallurgy research of direct relevance to the industries that develop, manufacture and use advanced non-ferrous structural alloys. The PIs are proposing the following topical areas: high performance alloys (nickel base super alloys and titanium base alloys), lightweight alloys including aluminum, magnesium (and their composites), and advanced alloys and processes. The PIs will insure that students have the opportunity to work on state-of-the-art projects and to be mentored by both experimental and modeling experts. The management of these focus areas is being modeled after the highly successful Advanced Steel Products and Processing Center at CSM, namely, by having companies designate what portion of their membership fees they wish to have distributed into the three specific focus areas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed Center has the potential to improve sustainability and profitability of US manufacturing by developing advanced non-ferrous alloys that could reduce energy consumption and pollution in the manufacturing of these alloys. The research would also improve the competitiveness of US manufacturers. Given that the focus of the proposed center will be on the physical metallurgy of structural non-ferrous alloys, the associated programs of study at the two institutions will be reexamined and potentially modified in order to insure that the undergraduate and graduate curricula are consistent with this focus. In other words, both institutions will work to insure that the undergraduate and graduate students receive proper education and training in order for them to be well grounded in fundamental principles of physical metallurgy. As a center interacting with industry, the PIs intend to reach out to local communities to bring their attention to the issues facing this particular industry sector and how the institutions can assist these industries as they compete in these global markets. The center will also insure that diversity is one of the criteria in the selection of both undergraduate and graduate students who are considered for the industry relevant projects.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1641143</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Collins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter C Collins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pcollins@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152945127</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000537928</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ames</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1138 Pearson]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~8909</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Center for Advanced Non-Ferrous Structural Alloys (CANFSA) was established at the University of North Texas and the Colorado School of Mines in July 2011 with eight founding members. The goals of the center are four-fold:</p> <p>1. Become      the premier place for research in the area of non-ferrous structural      alloys</p> <p>2. Bring      together university and industry researchers to conduct basic and applied      physical metallurgy research on non-ferrous structural alloys</p> <p>3. Combine      computational modeling, processing, and state-of-the-art characterization      methods address projects of interest to industrial members</p> <p>4. Train      students to become critical players in industries that develop or use      non-ferrous alloys</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To encompass the wide range of non-ferrous alloy used in industrial applications, CANFSA identified three thrust areas that focus on (1) lightweight non-ferrous alloys (aluminum, magnesium), (2) high performance non-ferrous alloys (titanium, superalloys), and (3) advanced alloys and processes (additive manufacturing, thin-film coatings, other alloys).&nbsp; During Phase 1, 25 CANFSA funded and leveraged projects have been performed within these three thrust areas.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During Phase 1, CANFSA moved its second site from the University of North Texas (UNT) to Iowa State University (ISU), following the move of Prof. Peter Collins, the center&rsquo;s Co-Director to ISU. UNT remains active as an affiliated site, with research projects continuing at that university.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The stability of center membership has been excellent during the five years of Phase 1, with annual membership never falling below the initial eight members.&nbsp; Membership has grown to thirteen current members, with membership being stable at this level for the past couple of years.&nbsp; In addition, turnover of membership within CANFSA has been much lower than the median value for I/UCRCs.&nbsp; CANFSA&rsquo;s current members come from a mixture of organizational types, including six large corporations, four government labs, two small companies and a trade association.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To ensure the industrial relevance of the center&rsquo;s research, a strategic system has been implemented to identify and implement projects of interest and relevance to members.&nbsp; &nbsp;The selection process starts in the summer, shortly after the Spring IAB meeting. Members and faculty are asked to provide concepts for new projects, and typically close to 30 separate ideas are collected. For the next step, the IAB is asked to indicate their level of interest for each of the ideas, allowing the list to be culled to 15. A videoconference is then conducted and each of the 15 the project ideas are discussed, to determine if each idea should be continued, shelved, or combined with another idea.&nbsp; During this videoconference, both academic and industrial champions are chosen for each of the project ideas, and tasked to produce short proposals for presentation at the fall IAB meeting. Voting at the meeting results in a prioritized list of new project ideas, which is used to recruit graduate students.&nbsp; Interestingly, the majority of new projects selected by the IAB are typically initiated by member suggestions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Communication is a very important aspect of the center.&nbsp; Along with two face-to-face IAB meetings, CANFSA has initiated two series of videoconferences per year, mid-way between the IAB meetings. In this manner, students for each active project present updates to members four times per year. Videoconferences have proven to be an extremely powerful method for transferring information, as while only one or two employees from each member organization typically attend IAB meetings, an unlimited number of employees from each member organization can participate via videoconferences. For example, during a recent set of videoconferences, one member organization had more than 20 individuals across multiple divisions in multiple states attend one or more of the videoconferences. Mentoring of students by industrial members is another critical aspect of communication, as each student is assigned an official mentor from a CANFSA member. A 5-point instruction guide has been developed to better identify the objectives and functions of mentors, with the overall goal being to enhance the students&rsquo; professional development by providing guidance on the preparation of schedules, technical briefings, and presentations according to commonly accepted professional standards.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>A broader impact of the center is the training and placement of students skilled in non-ferrous metals and alloys.&nbsp; Of the nine CANFSA-funded graduate students that have completed their studies, all have remained within non-ferrous or associated industries, with four being employed by member organizations, three remaining in academia, and two going to work for outside companies.&nbsp; In addition, more than ten undergraduate students have been involved in research projects within the center.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2017<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;C&nbsp;Collins</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Center for Advanced Non-Ferrous Structural Alloys (CANFSA) was established at the University of North Texas and the Colorado School of Mines in July 2011 with eight founding members. The goals of the center are four-fold:  1. Become      the premier place for research in the area of non-ferrous structural      alloys  2. Bring      together university and industry researchers to conduct basic and applied      physical metallurgy research on non-ferrous structural alloys  3. Combine      computational modeling, processing, and state-of-the-art characterization      methods address projects of interest to industrial members  4. Train      students to become critical players in industries that develop or use      non-ferrous alloys     To encompass the wide range of non-ferrous alloy used in industrial applications, CANFSA identified three thrust areas that focus on (1) lightweight non-ferrous alloys (aluminum, magnesium), (2) high performance non-ferrous alloys (titanium, superalloys), and (3) advanced alloys and processes (additive manufacturing, thin-film coatings, other alloys).  During Phase 1, 25 CANFSA funded and leveraged projects have been performed within these three thrust areas.      During Phase 1, CANFSA moved its second site from the University of North Texas (UNT) to Iowa State University (ISU), following the move of Prof. Peter Collins, the center?s Co-Director to ISU. UNT remains active as an affiliated site, with research projects continuing at that university.     The stability of center membership has been excellent during the five years of Phase 1, with annual membership never falling below the initial eight members.  Membership has grown to thirteen current members, with membership being stable at this level for the past couple of years.  In addition, turnover of membership within CANFSA has been much lower than the median value for I/UCRCs.  CANFSA?s current members come from a mixture of organizational types, including six large corporations, four government labs, two small companies and a trade association.      To ensure the industrial relevance of the center?s research, a strategic system has been implemented to identify and implement projects of interest and relevance to members.   The selection process starts in the summer, shortly after the Spring IAB meeting. Members and faculty are asked to provide concepts for new projects, and typically close to 30 separate ideas are collected. For the next step, the IAB is asked to indicate their level of interest for each of the ideas, allowing the list to be culled to 15. A videoconference is then conducted and each of the 15 the project ideas are discussed, to determine if each idea should be continued, shelved, or combined with another idea.  During this videoconference, both academic and industrial champions are chosen for each of the project ideas, and tasked to produce short proposals for presentation at the fall IAB meeting. Voting at the meeting results in a prioritized list of new project ideas, which is used to recruit graduate students.  Interestingly, the majority of new projects selected by the IAB are typically initiated by member suggestions.     Communication is a very important aspect of the center.  Along with two face-to-face IAB meetings, CANFSA has initiated two series of videoconferences per year, mid-way between the IAB meetings. In this manner, students for each active project present updates to members four times per year. Videoconferences have proven to be an extremely powerful method for transferring information, as while only one or two employees from each member organization typically attend IAB meetings, an unlimited number of employees from each member organization can participate via videoconferences. For example, during a recent set of videoconferences, one member organization had more than 20 individuals across multiple divisions in multiple states attend one or more of the videoconferences. Mentoring of students by industrial members is another critical aspect of communication, as each student is assigned an official mentor from a CANFSA member. A 5-point instruction guide has been developed to better identify the objectives and functions of mentors, with the overall goal being to enhance the students? professional development by providing guidance on the preparation of schedules, technical briefings, and presentations according to commonly accepted professional standards.     A broader impact of the center is the training and placement of students skilled in non-ferrous metals and alloys.  Of the nine CANFSA-funded graduate students that have completed their studies, all have remained within non-ferrous or associated industries, with four being employed by member organizations, three remaining in academia, and two going to work for outside companies.  In addition, more than ten undergraduate students have been involved in research projects within the center.         Last Modified: 04/01/2017       Submitted by: Peter C Collins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
