<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WORKSHOP:   Doctoral Symposium at RecSys 2016</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20932.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20932</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ephraim Glinert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eglinert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This is funding to support participation by about 8 promising doctoral students along with about 6 senior members of the research community who will serve as mentors, in a Doctoral Symposium (workshop) to be held in conjunction with and immediately preceding the technical program at the 10th ACM Conference on Recommender Systems (RecSys 2016), which will take place September 15-19 on the MIT and IBM Research campuses in Boston, MA.  The ACM RecSys conferences are the premier international forum for the presentation of new research results, systems and techniques in the broad field of recommender systems.  Recommendation is a particular form of information filtering that exploits past behaviors and user similarities to generate a list of information items that is personally tailored to an end-user's preferences.  RecSys is attended annually by approximately 500 researchers and practitioners from academia and from many of the world's leading e-commerce companies, who come together to present their latest results and identify new trends and challenges in providing recommendation components in a range of innovative application contexts.  In addition to the main technical track, the RecSys 2016 program will feature keynote and invited talks as well as tutorials and workshops covering the state-of-the-art in this domain.  Research reports published in the Conference Proceedings are included in the ACM Digital Library, and are heavily refereed and widely cited.   More information about the conference may be found online at https://recsys.acm.org/recsys16/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the RecSys Doctoral Symposium is to provide PhD students with an opportunity to present their work to a group of mentors and peers from a diverse set of academic and industrial institutions, to receive feedback on their doctoral research plan and progress, and to build a cohort of young researchers interested in similar research topics.  Student participants will each be allotted 45 minutes in which to present their ongoing thesis research (about 20 minutes) and to receive feedback from the other students and the mentors (about 25 minutes).  The feedback will be geared toward helping student participants understand and articulate how their work is positioned relative to other RecSys research, whether their topics are adequately focused for dissertation research projects, whether their methods are correctly chosen and applied, whether their results are being appropriately analyzed and presented, etc.  Discussion will be encouraged.  The symposium will conclude with a group dinner to help solidify new relationships.  In addition to the full day of the Symposium (on Friday September 16), during the main conference students will also present their dissertation work and plans in the form of a poster presentation to get fresh perspectives.  Thus, the Doctoral Symposium will give student participants exposure to their new research community, both by presenting their own work and by observing and interacting with established professionals in the field.  It will encourage students at this critical time in their careers to begin building a social support network of peers and mentors.  The organizers will take steps proactively to achieve diversity among the student participants by institution, country, research topic and approach, and demographics.  To this end, they will limit participation to one or two students per institution, depending on the number of applicants.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1641072</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Konstan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph A Konstan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>konstan@cs.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126251831</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000155041</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 Union Street SE, 4-192 KHKH]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>HCC-Human-Centered Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~20932</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As proposed, we held a doctoral symposium to mentor doctoral students in conjunction with the ACM Recommender Systems Conference in Cambridge, Massachusetts.&nbsp; The symposium was held at an IBM facility in Cambridge (also the venue of the conference workshops).&nbsp; Students were selected based on applications that included an abstract of their dissertation research, a letter explaining how they hoped they could benefit from and contribute to the workshop, and a letter of recommendation from their advisor.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Seven students participated. listed here with the titles of their submissions:</p> <ul> <li><em><strong>Dimitris Paraschakis</strong></em><br />Recommender Systems from an Industrial and Ethical Perspective</li> <li><em><strong>Abhishek Srivastava<br /></strong></em>Gray Sheep, Influential Users, User Modeling and Recommender System Adoption by Startups</li> <li><em><strong>Catalin-Mihai Barbu</strong></em><br />Increasing the Trustworthiness of Recommendations by Exploiting Social Media Sources</li> <li><em><strong>Hanna Sch&auml;fer</strong></em><br />Personalized Support for Healthy Nutrition Decisions</li> <li><em><strong>Marko Ga&scaron;pari?</strong>&nbsp;</em><br />Context-Based IDE Command Recommender System</li> <li><em><strong>Agung T. Wibowo</strong>&nbsp;</em><br />Generating Pseudotransactions for Improving Sparse Matrix Factorization</li> <li><em><strong>Adem Sabic</strong>&nbsp;</em><br />Proactive Recommendation Delivery</li> </ul> <p>The program of the symposium included 45 minutes for each student (20 minutes to present research, research plans, and questions; then 25 minutes for feedback, discussion, and advice).&nbsp; In addition, we held a panel session of symposium faculty to provide a venue for student questions on all topics (from research methods to career advice).&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Beyond the formal program, the symposium included three meals at which students and faculty mixed and were able to discuss their work more formally.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The faculty participating in the symposium were drawn from leaders in the field who were attending the conference, and were selected to represent the diverse nature of the field, whch spans from issues of machine learning to human-computer interaction, from academic research to industrial practice, and more.&nbsp; Each faculty member was assigned 2-3 students on which to focus (based on the proposed work), and the faculty had prepared feedback for the students based on their submissions.&nbsp; Faculty frequently arranged additional meetings during the conference to follow up with the assigned mentees.&nbsp; The participating faculty were:</p> <ul> <li><em><strong>Joseph A. Konstan</strong>&nbsp;(University of Minnesota)</em></li> <li><em><strong>Martijn Willemsen</strong>&nbsp;(Technical University of Eindhoven)</em></li> <li><em><strong>Barry Smyth</strong>&nbsp;(University College Dublin)</em></li> <li><em><strong>Bracha Shapira</strong>&nbsp;(Ben Gurion University)</em></li> <li><em><strong>Xavier Amatriain</strong>&nbsp;(Quora)</em></li> <li><em><strong>Dietmar Jannach</strong>&nbsp;(Technical University of Dortmond)</em></li> </ul> <p>Finally, to extend the impact of the symposium, we invited student volunteers to sit in and observe; these volunteers expressed appreciation for the oppotunity.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Joseph&nbsp;A&nbsp;Konstan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As proposed, we held a doctoral symposium to mentor doctoral students in conjunction with the ACM Recommender Systems Conference in Cambridge, Massachusetts.  The symposium was held at an IBM facility in Cambridge (also the venue of the conference workshops).  Students were selected based on applications that included an abstract of their dissertation research, a letter explaining how they hoped they could benefit from and contribute to the workshop, and a letter of recommendation from their advisor.    Seven students participated. listed here with the titles of their submissions:  Dimitris Paraschakis Recommender Systems from an Industrial and Ethical Perspective Abhishek Srivastava Gray Sheep, Influential Users, User Modeling and Recommender System Adoption by Startups Catalin-Mihai Barbu Increasing the Trustworthiness of Recommendations by Exploiting Social Media Sources Hanna Sch&auml;fer Personalized Support for Healthy Nutrition Decisions Marko Ga&scaron;pari?  Context-Based IDE Command Recommender System Agung T. Wibowo  Generating Pseudotransactions for Improving Sparse Matrix Factorization Adem Sabic  Proactive Recommendation Delivery   The program of the symposium included 45 minutes for each student (20 minutes to present research, research plans, and questions; then 25 minutes for feedback, discussion, and advice).  In addition, we held a panel session of symposium faculty to provide a venue for student questions on all topics (from research methods to career advice).    Beyond the formal program, the symposium included three meals at which students and faculty mixed and were able to discuss their work more formally.    The faculty participating in the symposium were drawn from leaders in the field who were attending the conference, and were selected to represent the diverse nature of the field, whch spans from issues of machine learning to human-computer interaction, from academic research to industrial practice, and more.  Each faculty member was assigned 2-3 students on which to focus (based on the proposed work), and the faculty had prepared feedback for the students based on their submissions.  Faculty frequently arranged additional meetings during the conference to follow up with the assigned mentees.  The participating faculty were:  Joseph A. Konstan (University of Minnesota) Martijn Willemsen (Technical University of Eindhoven) Barry Smyth (University College Dublin) Bracha Shapira (Ben Gurion University) Xavier Amatriain (Quora) Dietmar Jannach (Technical University of Dortmond)   Finally, to extend the impact of the symposium, we invited student volunteers to sit in and observe; these volunteers expressed appreciation for the oppotunity.       Last Modified: 07/30/2018       Submitted by: Joseph A Konstan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
