<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Award: The Role of History in Ethnic Identity Formation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20784.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20784</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this research is to understand the creation of an ethnicity rooted in the past and still very important today, the Balkan Muslim identity established during the Ottoman Empire's control of European lands. In many European historical accounts, the Ottomans are depicted as brutal, foreign invaders. In recent decades, the descendants of these Islamic communities in some areas have been subjected to violence, adverse political policies, and a constant designation as "other" in predominately Christian Europe. The perception is often that these groups did not originate in the lands they occupy today. This notion is questioned however, by historical accounts of the mass conversion of European Christians to Islam, indicating that these communities may in actuality be closely related to those that remained Christian in the Ottoman's European territories. In general, questions of ethnicity and identity are extremely important considerations with far-reaching social and political consequences in both the past and the present. While often thought to be defined by genetics, ethnicity and identity are in actuality dynamic, fluid, and shifting aspects of human groups. The establishment or justification of a modern ethnicity is frequently traced to a group of people in the past, making archaeology a discipline capable of studying these phenomena. Understanding the processes and people who created the Balkan Muslim communities in Southeastern Europe is very important for public understanding and acceptance of the religious heterogeneity in these societies today.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ms. Kathryn Grow Allen and colleagues will investigate the makeup of Ottoman military communities in the hinterlands of the Ottoman Empire's European territory with an aim to better understand the biological and ancestral background of the people from which many modern Muslim communities in the region are descended. The project will utilize the archaeological record of Ottoman garrison towns from three countries with territory formerly ruled by the Islamic empire (Romania, Hungary and Croatia) and focus on a largely under-utilized source of archaeological data-human skeletons previously excavated and stored in regional museums. Understanding the Ottoman group identity and how similar or distinct they were from the local communities will be done using two established techniques: a biodistance analysis and strontium isotope analysis. The first, biodistance, requires the collection of a large number of metric and non-metric traits found on human bones. These biological traits are known to be influenced by genetics and informative on group identity and relatedness. The second method, strontium isotope analysis, is frequently employed by archaeologists to trace the movement of people utilizing isotopic signatures found in human teeth informative of an individual's birthplace. These methods, employed on a regional scale, will provide important information regarding the creation of the Ottoman Muslim communities and ethnicity in Southeastern Europe. They will deliver data regarding the extent to which the immigration of individuals from Anatolia or the conversion of European Christians influenced the biological makeup of these groups.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1642007</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Chevral</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy J Chevral</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tt27@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7166450408</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000119248</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathryn</FirstName>
<LastName>Allen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kathryn G Allen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kegrow@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7166452634</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000710282</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038633251</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142607016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>Archaeology DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~20784</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The focus of this research was a bioarchaeological analysis of human skeletal collections associated with the Ottoman period in Southeast Europe. The presence of the Ottoman Empire in Europe, starting in the 15<sup>th</sup> century, introduced a new religion (Islam) and new people to the region. This complex history has significant modern repercussions on the descendants of Ottoman Europe. Despite known historical and modern influences making it a period imperative to understand, archaeology and anthropology have thus far played only a minor role in research on this subject. Employing an underutilized but available aspect of the archaeological record-human skeletal remains-this work provided insight into this dynamic time period and its influence on historical and modern communities.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;Utilizing analyses of human skeletons previously excavated from archaeological sites, this research analyzed how the transition to Ottoman control in Southeast Europe affected regional demography. Questions of identity associated with this period have traditionally been understood from conflicting historical accounts. These accounts debate either massive migrations of non-European people or large-scale conversions of Europeans to Islam as the singular process defining these Ottoman communities. To contribute biological data to this historical debate, three methods were employed. First, craniometric analysis utilizing metric variation of human crania, a known proxy for genetic data, highlighted demographic trends. Second, the analysis of non-metric cranial variations, also representative of genetic information, further investigate those trends. These two methods were used to analyze eight collections including four Ottoman cemetery populations from Romania, Hungary, and Croatia, as well as four comparative collections with crania that modelled the kind of biological variation expected if these Ottomans were either converted Europeans or immigrants from Anatolia. Statistical treatments of both the craniometric and non-metric data highlighted relationships between the Ottoman populations and the comparative groups. Finally, strontium isotope analysis&mdash;a method frequently used by archaeologists to analyze migration&mdash;tested samples from the Ottoman site in Romania. Together, these three methods revealed that the uniform historical accounts portraying the Ottoman past as a result of either immigration or conversion were at odds with the biological data. The four Ottoman communities displayed distinct heterogeneity, both within and between groups. Likewise, males and females had strikingly different results, indicating they came to the Ottoman communities from diverse backgrounds. This work indicates that a complex interplay of social and political processes transformed heterogeneous people into the Ottomans. Simplified historical interpretations championing migration or conversion as the only driver of demographic change fail to recognize this diversity.&nbsp;</p> <p>In this research, the biological data supports the idea that a combination of religious, social, and political factors came together to create what history would eventually turn into an ethnic identity. The Ottoman populations in Southeast Europe are not only treated as a distinct group historically, the division between Muslims or &lsquo;Turks&rsquo; and Europeans has been maintained in some modern communities as well. With Islamic relations in some regions of contemporary Europe continuing to deteriorate, long-held notions that European Muslims are the &lsquo;other&rsquo;, trespassers on Christian lands, are unlikely to be alleviated. Europe as a territory or identity is often defined in opposition to Islam and in many former Ottoman occupation areas, polarization between Muslims and Christians is based on interpretations of this historical period. A better understanding of the biological diversity of the Ottomans and the different processes that influenced the genetic and cultural character of these groups discredits monolithic views of the European Ottoman past for more dynamic, accurate perspectives.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Kathryn&nbsp;G&nbsp;Allen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The focus of this research was a bioarchaeological analysis of human skeletal collections associated with the Ottoman period in Southeast Europe. The presence of the Ottoman Empire in Europe, starting in the 15th century, introduced a new religion (Islam) and new people to the region. This complex history has significant modern repercussions on the descendants of Ottoman Europe. Despite known historical and modern influences making it a period imperative to understand, archaeology and anthropology have thus far played only a minor role in research on this subject. Employing an underutilized but available aspect of the archaeological record-human skeletal remains-this work provided insight into this dynamic time period and its influence on historical and modern communities.     Utilizing analyses of human skeletons previously excavated from archaeological sites, this research analyzed how the transition to Ottoman control in Southeast Europe affected regional demography. Questions of identity associated with this period have traditionally been understood from conflicting historical accounts. These accounts debate either massive migrations of non-European people or large-scale conversions of Europeans to Islam as the singular process defining these Ottoman communities. To contribute biological data to this historical debate, three methods were employed. First, craniometric analysis utilizing metric variation of human crania, a known proxy for genetic data, highlighted demographic trends. Second, the analysis of non-metric cranial variations, also representative of genetic information, further investigate those trends. These two methods were used to analyze eight collections including four Ottoman cemetery populations from Romania, Hungary, and Croatia, as well as four comparative collections with crania that modelled the kind of biological variation expected if these Ottomans were either converted Europeans or immigrants from Anatolia. Statistical treatments of both the craniometric and non-metric data highlighted relationships between the Ottoman populations and the comparative groups. Finally, strontium isotope analysis&mdash;a method frequently used by archaeologists to analyze migration&mdash;tested samples from the Ottoman site in Romania. Together, these three methods revealed that the uniform historical accounts portraying the Ottoman past as a result of either immigration or conversion were at odds with the biological data. The four Ottoman communities displayed distinct heterogeneity, both within and between groups. Likewise, males and females had strikingly different results, indicating they came to the Ottoman communities from diverse backgrounds. This work indicates that a complex interplay of social and political processes transformed heterogeneous people into the Ottomans. Simplified historical interpretations championing migration or conversion as the only driver of demographic change fail to recognize this diversity.   In this research, the biological data supports the idea that a combination of religious, social, and political factors came together to create what history would eventually turn into an ethnic identity. The Ottoman populations in Southeast Europe are not only treated as a distinct group historically, the division between Muslims or ?Turks? and Europeans has been maintained in some modern communities as well. With Islamic relations in some regions of contemporary Europe continuing to deteriorate, long-held notions that European Muslims are the ?other?, trespassers on Christian lands, are unlikely to be alleviated. Europe as a territory or identity is often defined in opposition to Islam and in many former Ottoman occupation areas, polarization between Muslims and Christians is based on interpretations of this historical period. A better understanding of the biological diversity of the Ottomans and the different processes that influenced the genetic and cultural character of these groups discredits monolithic views of the European Ottoman past for more dynamic, accurate perspectives.          Last Modified: 11/28/2017       Submitted by: Kathryn G Allen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
