<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>"Workshop:  Analysis of Country Conditions and Decision-Making on Asylum Claims."</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>35000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>35000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mark Hurwitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mhurwitz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925366</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>General Summary:&lt;br/&gt;Recent years have witnessed a sharp increase in undocumented migration to the United States by minors and families with children seeking refuge from violence in their home countries. This influx of migrants is straining the capacity of the U.S. immigration system to adjudicate their claims, and is taxing an already overburdened community of attorneys available to provide legal assistance.  One especially challenging issue that arises from these cases is that the nature of the dangers cited by applicants as motivating them to flee their home countries do not fit easily into the categories of persecution that are established in asylum law and related jurisprudence. This conference brings together leading social scientists with expertise on the conditions driving the migration from and on the psycho-social impacts of the migration experience, with legal scholars who specialize on refugee and asylum law. The objective is to share insights across disciplinary perspectives in order to enhance scholarship, and better to inform lawyers and other practitioners working with this population.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary:&lt;br/&gt;In order to foster the cross-disciplinary collaboration that can inform the efficient, equitable adjudication of asylum cases submitted by newly arrived youth and families, this workshop will convene an international group of social scientists and legal scholars with expertise across three key priority areas: 1) country conditions; 2) psychological assessment of asylum seekers; and 3) asylum adjudication and evolving jurisprudence on asylum law in the U.S. The core objectives of the workshop will be to: 1) connect existing networks of researchers on socio-political dynamics in the region with behavioral scientists engaged in asylum seeker assessment and legal scholars on asylum law and adjudication processes; 2) develop an agenda for research to document forms of persecution in the region, informed by legal experts on substantive criteria and evidentiary standards for asylum claims; 3) discuss current scholarship on the applicability of refugee law to present-day humanitarian challenges and on refugee adjudication, and identify gaps in theoretical understandings of legal decision-making and methodological challenges to advancing research in this area; and 4) propose innovative, interdisciplinary approaches to analyzing adjudication outcomes of these cases as well as their influence on evolving jurisprudence on asylum claims.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1642539</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jayesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Rathod</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jayesh M Rathod</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jrathod@wcl.american.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2028853440</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000611499</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Hershberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric Hershberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hershber@american.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2028856172</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000721144</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200168001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2028853440</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 Massachusetts Avenue, NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077795060</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>077795060</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200168001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4400 Massachusetts Avenue, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LSS-Law And Social Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~35000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Tens of thousands of Central Americans have migrated to the United States in recent years, seeking protection from different types of harm perpetrated by powerful gangs, other criminal actors, or the state. This migrant stream, which includes unaccompanied children and families, has inundated the U.S. immigration system. Asylum officers and Immigration Judges are charged with assessing the credibility of their claims and their conformity with existing requirements for asylum or other forms of relief under U.S. immigration law.</p> <p>To persuade adjudicators that they satisfy the legal requirements for relief, asylum applicants and their attorneys frequently rely on country conditions research and/or expert declarations generated by social scientists. Evaluations performed by mental health professionals are also increasingly common in asylum cases. In this context, lawyers and legal scholars find themselves working in collaboration with social scientists and mental health professionals. Despite years of ad hoc partnerships, however, there have been no formal efforts to examine the challenges inherent in these cross-disciplinary collaborations, to systematically measure their impact on case outcomes, or to develop an agenda for shared work in the future. &nbsp;</p> <p>In response to this need, the Center for Latin American &amp; Latino Studies and the Washington College of Law at American University convened a diverse group of researchers and practitioners to focus on country conditions in Central America and asylum decision-making in the U.S. immigration system. The workshop had multiple goals, including the development of cross-disciplinary professional networks, the articulation of plans for future research, and the identification of other collaborative efforts seeking to address challenges in asylum adjudication. With support from the National Science Foundation, the American University team brought together approximately 40 core participants for the two-day workshop in January 2017.</p> <p>The workshop afforded a venue for productive conversations regarding cross-disciplinary collaboration, current country conditions in Central America, and the state of U.S. asylum jurisprudence and adjudication practices. These themes were explored across public and private sessions, and through panel discussions, thematic breakout sessions, discipline-focused working groups, and individual presentations.</p> <p>Workshop participants noted multiple challenges inherent in cross-disciplinary collaborations, including difficulty in identifying possible collaborators, and the lack of sufficient training, particularly of social scientists and mental health professionals serving as experts in immigration cases. Several speakers acknowledged that unique professional approaches and cultures can be a challenge in these collaborations, and that mutual training is needed to bridge disciplinary boundaries and the worlds of scholarship and practice. While these are most effective when sustained, limited time and resources often inhibit effective partnerships.</p> <p>Throughout the workshop, country experts shared information regarding on-the-ground trends in Central America that are especially relevant to asylum claims. Focusing on the three countries of Central America&rsquo;s Northern Triangle &ndash; El Salvador, Guatemala and Honduras &ndash; scholars spoke of the spreading gang violence in the region, and the difficulty of discerning who precisely is a &ldquo;gang member.&rdquo; Presenters also detailed key characteristics of gang recruitment efforts and extortion methods and the culture of violence inherent in gang initiation rituals. Discussion focused as well on other forms of violence endemic in the region, including diverse forms of gender-based violence. The workshop also featured interventions regarding socioeconomic factors that drive migration from Central America &ndash; including the lack of education and employment opportunities &ndash; and about relevant aspects of U.S. foreign policy, including the Alliance for Prosperity announced by the Obama administration in 2014.</p> <p>In a parallel fashion, legal scholars spoke of the current state of asylum jurisprudence and ongoing challenges relating to the adjudication of cases. The presenters spoke of the difficulty in proving the motive of the persecutors(s) &ndash; often gang members &ndash; and called for further research on the conduct of Central American gangs, particularly towards those who refuse their demands. The home country government&rsquo;s inability or unwillingness to control the persecutor is another key element of asylum claims; future research on protective mechanisms that exist, and whether they are accessible and effective, was also named as a priority. More broadly, legal scholars spoke of systemic issues in asylum adjudication, including the existence of &ldquo;asylum-free zones&rdquo; with exceedingly low grant rates. Many of these systemic challenges will require strategic interventions involving resources and expertise from multiple disciplines.</p> <p>Over the course of the workshop, attendees shared numerous ideas for enhanced cross-disciplinary collaboration that could promote more effective representation of asylum-seekers. Broadly speaking, these ideas related to: (1) enhancing databases and improving access to existing information; (2) developing a pipeline of professionals to work on Central American asylum cases, and engaging in cross-disciplinary training; (3) pursuing strategic interventions and partnerships; and (4) undertaking fresh research linking country conditions and asylum adjudication and illuminating factors that shape outcomes for asylum applicants. A full report on workshop proceedings is available at:&nbsp;https://ssrn.com/abstract=2954216.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/24/2017<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;Hershberg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Tens of thousands of Central Americans have migrated to the United States in recent years, seeking protection from different types of harm perpetrated by powerful gangs, other criminal actors, or the state. This migrant stream, which includes unaccompanied children and families, has inundated the U.S. immigration system. Asylum officers and Immigration Judges are charged with assessing the credibility of their claims and their conformity with existing requirements for asylum or other forms of relief under U.S. immigration law.  To persuade adjudicators that they satisfy the legal requirements for relief, asylum applicants and their attorneys frequently rely on country conditions research and/or expert declarations generated by social scientists. Evaluations performed by mental health professionals are also increasingly common in asylum cases. In this context, lawyers and legal scholars find themselves working in collaboration with social scientists and mental health professionals. Despite years of ad hoc partnerships, however, there have been no formal efforts to examine the challenges inherent in these cross-disciplinary collaborations, to systematically measure their impact on case outcomes, or to develop an agenda for shared work in the future.    In response to this need, the Center for Latin American &amp; Latino Studies and the Washington College of Law at American University convened a diverse group of researchers and practitioners to focus on country conditions in Central America and asylum decision-making in the U.S. immigration system. The workshop had multiple goals, including the development of cross-disciplinary professional networks, the articulation of plans for future research, and the identification of other collaborative efforts seeking to address challenges in asylum adjudication. With support from the National Science Foundation, the American University team brought together approximately 40 core participants for the two-day workshop in January 2017.  The workshop afforded a venue for productive conversations regarding cross-disciplinary collaboration, current country conditions in Central America, and the state of U.S. asylum jurisprudence and adjudication practices. These themes were explored across public and private sessions, and through panel discussions, thematic breakout sessions, discipline-focused working groups, and individual presentations.  Workshop participants noted multiple challenges inherent in cross-disciplinary collaborations, including difficulty in identifying possible collaborators, and the lack of sufficient training, particularly of social scientists and mental health professionals serving as experts in immigration cases. Several speakers acknowledged that unique professional approaches and cultures can be a challenge in these collaborations, and that mutual training is needed to bridge disciplinary boundaries and the worlds of scholarship and practice. While these are most effective when sustained, limited time and resources often inhibit effective partnerships.  Throughout the workshop, country experts shared information regarding on-the-ground trends in Central America that are especially relevant to asylum claims. Focusing on the three countries of Central America?s Northern Triangle &ndash; El Salvador, Guatemala and Honduras &ndash; scholars spoke of the spreading gang violence in the region, and the difficulty of discerning who precisely is a "gang member." Presenters also detailed key characteristics of gang recruitment efforts and extortion methods and the culture of violence inherent in gang initiation rituals. Discussion focused as well on other forms of violence endemic in the region, including diverse forms of gender-based violence. The workshop also featured interventions regarding socioeconomic factors that drive migration from Central America &ndash; including the lack of education and employment opportunities &ndash; and about relevant aspects of U.S. foreign policy, including the Alliance for Prosperity announced by the Obama administration in 2014.  In a parallel fashion, legal scholars spoke of the current state of asylum jurisprudence and ongoing challenges relating to the adjudication of cases. The presenters spoke of the difficulty in proving the motive of the persecutors(s) &ndash; often gang members &ndash; and called for further research on the conduct of Central American gangs, particularly towards those who refuse their demands. The home country government?s inability or unwillingness to control the persecutor is another key element of asylum claims; future research on protective mechanisms that exist, and whether they are accessible and effective, was also named as a priority. More broadly, legal scholars spoke of systemic issues in asylum adjudication, including the existence of "asylum-free zones" with exceedingly low grant rates. Many of these systemic challenges will require strategic interventions involving resources and expertise from multiple disciplines.  Over the course of the workshop, attendees shared numerous ideas for enhanced cross-disciplinary collaboration that could promote more effective representation of asylum-seekers. Broadly speaking, these ideas related to: (1) enhancing databases and improving access to existing information; (2) developing a pipeline of professionals to work on Central American asylum cases, and engaging in cross-disciplinary training; (3) pursuing strategic interventions and partnerships; and (4) undertaking fresh research linking country conditions and asylum adjudication and illuminating factors that shape outcomes for asylum applicants. A full report on workshop proceedings is available at: https://ssrn.com/abstract=2954216.        Last Modified: 07/24/2017       Submitted by: Eric Hershberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
