<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Sixth International Brain-Computer Interface Meeting</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>4500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>4500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michele Grimm</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mgrimm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Brain-computer interface (BCI) technology is a potentially powerful communication and control option for people with severe motor disabilities, as well as a hands-free, voice-free control option for mainstream users. The success of this exciting work depends on close and productive multidisciplinary interactions among researchers working in neuroscience, psychology, engineering, mathematics, computer science, and clinical rehabilitation. For this reason, the Sixth International Brain-Computer Interface meeting , themed "BCI Past, Present, and Future", will be held May 30 - June 3, 2016, at the Asilomar Conference Grounds, Pacific Grove, California. The 2016 BCI Meeting will retain the unique, highly interactive, student-friendly, retreat-like atmosphere and high-impact activities that are the hallmarks of the BCI Meeting series, starting with the first BCI meeting in 1999.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NSF award will provide live streaming of presentations made at the meeting.  This will provide access to people who have interests in BCI but are unable to attend. This includes all who may not have the time or funds to attend, but also the large population of people with impairments that hinder or prevent their attendance, exactly the population that would most benefit from the material presented at this meeting.  NSF funds will also support the editing and archiving of the presentations for viewing on-line after the meeting.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1642412</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Anderson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles W Anderson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chuck.anderson@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704917491</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000403856</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>785979618</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>948905492</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Asilomar Conference Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Pacific Grove</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>939503704</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 Asilomar Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5342</Code>
<Text>Disability &amp; Rehab Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~4500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this award was to provide access for professionals and students to major events at the Sixth International Brain-Computer Interface Meeting at the Asilomar  Conference Center, Pacific Grove, California, that took place in June, 2016. Major events that were live streamed and recorded include the following invited talks by leaders in the brain-computer interface field:</p> <ul> <li><em>History of Implantable Bidirectional BCIs,</em> Eb Fetz, Department of Physiology &amp; Biophysics, University of Washington</li> <li><em>History of Non-Invasive BCIs,</em> Jacques Vidal, Department of Computer Science, UCLA</li> <li><em>Future of BCIs</em>, Jon Wolpaw, Wadsworth Center, New York State Department of Health</li> <li><em>BCI for Communication</em>, Nick Ramsey, Department of Neurosurgery, UMC Utrecht</li> <li><em>BCIs for Control</em>, Lee Miller, Departments of Physiology, Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Northwestern University</li> <li><em>BCIs for Rehabilitation,</em> Donatella Mattia, Director of the  Laboratory of Neuroelectrical Imaging and Brain Computer Interface,  Fondazione Santa Lucia, IRCCS, Rome, Italy</li> <li><em>BCI for Basic Research</em>, Aaron Batista, University of Pittsburgh</li> <li><em>BCI for General Population</em>, Jose del R Millan, Defitech Professor at the Ecole Polytechnique Federale de Lausanne (EPFL)</li> <li><em>Virtual Forum of BCI Users</em>. BCI users particpate remotely, including video, audio, and slides.</li> </ul> <p>In addition to these talks, the meeting's Virtual Users Forum was also live-streamed and recorded.</p> <div class="tinyMCEContent"></div> <div class="tinyMCEContent"> <p>The recorded videos are  available to the public at the BCI Society's Youtube channel,&nbsp;  https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCVvQsu9DHlR1kJSgD41DswQ</p> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/27/2017<br>      Modified by: Charles&nbsp;W&nbsp;Anderson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this award was to provide access for professionals and students to major events at the Sixth International Brain-Computer Interface Meeting at the Asilomar  Conference Center, Pacific Grove, California, that took place in June, 2016. Major events that were live streamed and recorded include the following invited talks by leaders in the brain-computer interface field:  History of Implantable Bidirectional BCIs, Eb Fetz, Department of Physiology &amp; Biophysics, University of Washington History of Non-Invasive BCIs, Jacques Vidal, Department of Computer Science, UCLA Future of BCIs, Jon Wolpaw, Wadsworth Center, New York State Department of Health BCI for Communication, Nick Ramsey, Department of Neurosurgery, UMC Utrecht BCIs for Control, Lee Miller, Departments of Physiology, Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Northwestern University BCIs for Rehabilitation, Donatella Mattia, Director of the  Laboratory of Neuroelectrical Imaging and Brain Computer Interface,  Fondazione Santa Lucia, IRCCS, Rome, Italy BCI for Basic Research, Aaron Batista, University of Pittsburgh BCI for General Population, Jose del R Millan, Defitech Professor at the Ecole Polytechnique Federale de Lausanne (EPFL) Virtual Forum of BCI Users. BCI users particpate remotely, including video, audio, and slides.   In addition to these talks, the meeting's Virtual Users Forum was also live-streamed and recorded.    The recorded videos are  available to the public at the BCI Society's Youtube channel,   https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCVvQsu9DHlR1kJSgD41DswQ        Last Modified: 11/27/2017       Submitted by: Charles W Anderson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
