<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>LZ Dark Matter Search</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>60265.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>60265</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan Whitmore</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928908</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Multiple astronomical observations have established that about 85% of the matter in the universe is not made of known particles. Deciphering the nature of this so-called Dark Matter is of fundamental importance to cosmology, astrophysics, and high-energy particle physics. A leading hypothesis is that it is comprised of Weakly Interacting Massive Particles, or WIMPs, that were produced moments after the Big Bang. If WIMPs are the dark matter, then their presence in our galaxy may be detectable via scattering from atomic nuclei in detectors located deep underground to help reject backgrounds due to cosmic rays. LZ is a ~7-tonne liquid xenon (LXe) dark matter detector to be installed at the 4850-foot level of the Sanford Underground Research Facility (SURF) in Lead, South Dakota, to look for dark matter. This work will contribute to the design of that detector.  Development of technology related to LXe will find use in the increasing number of experiments worldwide using noble liquids as detection materials. These projects will also result in technical training in radiation detection, cryogenics, and gas purification for graduate and undergraduate students. LXe has practical applications to gamma ray imaging for astrophysics, Homeland Security, and medical imaging.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This detector will use established liquid xenon time projection chamber technology with readout of primary and secondary scintillation signals for particle identification, together with 3-D position reconstruction to exploit the self-shielding of the liquid xenon, removal of surface artifacts, and calibration of position-dependent response functions. The design also features a gadolinium-loaded liquid scintillator veto that will hermetically enclose the central xenon detector and provide powerful tagging of background neutrons and gammas.  The LZ experiment will have world-leading sensitivity to WIMP dark matter with a sensitivity about 400 times better than current results and covering a substantial range of theoretically motivated candidates. This award will provide funding to enable this research group to continue to contribute to the LZ dark matter experiment with work on the cathode high voltage delivery system.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1642619</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>McKinsey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel McKinsey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniel.mckinsey@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2039886028</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000323902</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7235</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Undergro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~265</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Multiple astronomical observations have established that about 85% of  the matter in the universe is not made of known particles. Deciphering  the nature of this so-called Dark Matter is of fundamental importance to  cosmology, astrophysics, and high-energy particle physics. A leading  hypothesis is that it is comprised of Weakly Interacting Massive  Particles, or WIMPs, that were produced moments after the Big Bang. If  WIMPs are the dark matter, then their presence in our galaxy may be  detectable via scattering from atomic nuclei in detectors located deep  underground to help reject backgrounds due to cosmic rays. LZ is a  ~7-tonne liquid xenon (LXe) dark matter detector to be installed at the  4850-foot level of the Sanford Underground Research Facility (SURF) in  Lead, South Dakota, to look for dark matter. This work contributed  to the design of that detector.  Development of technology related to  LXe will find use in the increasing number of experiments worldwide  using noble liquids as detection materials. These projects also  resulted in technical training in radiation detection, cryogenics, and gas  purification for graduate students. LXe has practical  applications to gamma ray imaging for astrophysics, Homeland Security,  and medical imaging.<br /><br />The LZ detector will use established liquid  xenon time projection chamber technology with readout of primary and  secondary scintillation signals for particle identification, together  with 3-D position reconstruction to exploit the self-shielding of the  liquid xenon, removal of surface artifacts, and calibration of  position-dependent response functions. The design also features a  gadolinium-loaded liquid scintillator veto that will hermetically  enclose the central xenon detector and provide powerful tagging of  background neutrons and gammas.  The LZ experiment will have  world-leading sensitivity to WIMP dark matter and cover a substantial range  of theoretically motivated candidates.</p> <p>This award provided funding  to enable the McKinsey research group at UC Berkeley to contribute to the LZ dark  matter experiment with work on the cathode high voltage delivery system. Work focused on two tasks: 1) Design, construction, and testing of a liquid argon purity monitor to be used during high voltage testing of LZ high voltage components, and 2) Three-dimensional electric field simulations of the full engineering design of the cathode high voltage delivery system. The purity monitor was successfully built and tested, and will be used in upcoming LZ high voltage testing. The 3D electric field simulations were used to iterate on the engineering of the LZ cathode high voltage system, and successfully verified that for the LZ design, all cathodic surfaces in the cathode high voltage delivery system create surface fields less than 50 kV/cm, meeting its design specification.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/24/2017<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Mckinsey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Multiple astronomical observations have established that about 85% of  the matter in the universe is not made of known particles. Deciphering  the nature of this so-called Dark Matter is of fundamental importance to  cosmology, astrophysics, and high-energy particle physics. A leading  hypothesis is that it is comprised of Weakly Interacting Massive  Particles, or WIMPs, that were produced moments after the Big Bang. If  WIMPs are the dark matter, then their presence in our galaxy may be  detectable via scattering from atomic nuclei in detectors located deep  underground to help reject backgrounds due to cosmic rays. LZ is a  ~7-tonne liquid xenon (LXe) dark matter detector to be installed at the  4850-foot level of the Sanford Underground Research Facility (SURF) in  Lead, South Dakota, to look for dark matter. This work contributed  to the design of that detector.  Development of technology related to  LXe will find use in the increasing number of experiments worldwide  using noble liquids as detection materials. These projects also  resulted in technical training in radiation detection, cryogenics, and gas  purification for graduate students. LXe has practical  applications to gamma ray imaging for astrophysics, Homeland Security,  and medical imaging.  The LZ detector will use established liquid  xenon time projection chamber technology with readout of primary and  secondary scintillation signals for particle identification, together  with 3-D position reconstruction to exploit the self-shielding of the  liquid xenon, removal of surface artifacts, and calibration of  position-dependent response functions. The design also features a  gadolinium-loaded liquid scintillator veto that will hermetically  enclose the central xenon detector and provide powerful tagging of  background neutrons and gammas.  The LZ experiment will have  world-leading sensitivity to WIMP dark matter and cover a substantial range  of theoretically motivated candidates.  This award provided funding  to enable the McKinsey research group at UC Berkeley to contribute to the LZ dark  matter experiment with work on the cathode high voltage delivery system. Work focused on two tasks: 1) Design, construction, and testing of a liquid argon purity monitor to be used during high voltage testing of LZ high voltage components, and 2) Three-dimensional electric field simulations of the full engineering design of the cathode high voltage delivery system. The purity monitor was successfully built and tested, and will be used in upcoming LZ high voltage testing. The 3D electric field simulations were used to iterate on the engineering of the LZ cathode high voltage system, and successfully verified that for the LZ design, all cathodic surfaces in the cathode high voltage delivery system create surface fields less than 50 kV/cm, meeting its design specification.          Last Modified: 11/24/2017       Submitted by: Daniel Mckinsey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
