<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CBMS Conference:   Nonlocal Dynamics--Theory, Computation and Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>34999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>34999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This CBMS Conference "Nonlocal Dynamics--Theory, Computation and Applications" is to be held at Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, during June 4-9, 2017.  Various complex systems in engineering and science are under long range or nonlocal interactions. There is a growing recognition of a role for including nonlocal effects in better modeling these systems. As a result, nonlocal partial differential equations are appropriate mathematical models for certain optimal control systems, dislocation dynamics in crystals, porous media flows, anomalous dffusion of particles in fluids, and many other systems. Nonlocal effects and long range diffusion also occur in the cell density evolution in certain biological processes, such as embryological development. In order to better understand nonlocal engineering and scientific systems, we must understand the properties of nonlocal equations. This conference brings a top mathematician as the principal lecturer, together with experts and newcomers from relevant mathematical and scientific communities, to learn, examine and investigate theoretical and computational issues in this subject. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nonlocal partial differential equations are macroscopic models for complex systems under long range interactions. They have led to many mathematically challenging  questions  at the interface of  analysis, computation,  stochastic analysis  and partial differential equations. To realize the full power of nonlocal equations as mathematical models for complex systems, analysis and numerical approximations are crucial. This conference aims to summarize the past achievements in this subject, and discuss future research directions. It further stimulates research in the development of analytical, dynamical and computational tools for nonlocal models and their applications. The Principal Lecturer for this conference is Professor Qiang Du at Columbia University. The conference consists of  ten lectures by Qiang Du, together with supplemental presentations by a few experts, round table discussions, and a session on open problems. The participants include graduate students, postdocs, junior researchers and experts from regional and other institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For more information, please refer to the conference webpage: www.math.iit.edu/nonlocaldynamics.html.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/03/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/03/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1642545</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jinqiao</FirstName>
<LastName>Duan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jinqiao Duan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>duan@iit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3125675335</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000100221</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/03/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaofan</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaofan Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lix@iit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3125675340</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486733</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/03/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Illinois Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606163717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125673035</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10 West 35th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 7D71]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042084434</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ILLINOIS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042084434</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Illinois Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606163717</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~34999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This conference's main themes are modeling, analysis and simulation of nonlocal equations that are<br />mathematical models for science and engineering systems under long-range or non-local interactions. There<br />is a growing recognition of a role for including nonlocal effects in modeling nonlinear systems. This has led to<br />challenging mathematical problems at the interface of analysis, computation, stochastic analysis and partial<br />dierential equations. The investigation of nonlocal equations has attracted a lot of attention<br />recently, from both mathematical and engineering communities.</p> <p><br />The Principal Lecturer for this conference is Professor Qiang Du at Columbia University. This conference<br />has summarized the past achievements, discussed future research directions, and stimulated research in<br />the development of analytical, dynamical and computational tools for nonlocal models and their applications.<br />The session on open problems has provided interesting and significant problems for newcomers in this<br />subject.</p> <p><br />This conference has brought together over two dozens of graduate students and postdocs (including<br />seven women and minority members) and a dozen established researchers. The graduate students have<br />gained valuable training that enhances their education and career development. Graduate students,<br />postdocs and junior researchers from regional universities and institutions have learned from and interacted<br />with leading experts in the subject. They have benefited from networking with colleagues in the region. The<br />lecture notes will be published and will be accessible to a wide audience of professionals interested in the<br />subject. The conference webpage and the emailing list will continue to function. This conference also helps<br />enhance the applied mathematics PhD program at Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/05/2018<br>      Modified by: Jinqiao&nbsp;Duan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This conference's main themes are modeling, analysis and simulation of nonlocal equations that are mathematical models for science and engineering systems under long-range or non-local interactions. There is a growing recognition of a role for including nonlocal effects in modeling nonlinear systems. This has led to challenging mathematical problems at the interface of analysis, computation, stochastic analysis and partial dierential equations. The investigation of nonlocal equations has attracted a lot of attention recently, from both mathematical and engineering communities.   The Principal Lecturer for this conference is Professor Qiang Du at Columbia University. This conference has summarized the past achievements, discussed future research directions, and stimulated research in the development of analytical, dynamical and computational tools for nonlocal models and their applications. The session on open problems has provided interesting and significant problems for newcomers in this subject.   This conference has brought together over two dozens of graduate students and postdocs (including seven women and minority members) and a dozen established researchers. The graduate students have gained valuable training that enhances their education and career development. Graduate students, postdocs and junior researchers from regional universities and institutions have learned from and interacted with leading experts in the subject. They have benefited from networking with colleagues in the region. The lecture notes will be published and will be accessible to a wide audience of professionals interested in the subject. The conference webpage and the emailing list will continue to function. This conference also helps enhance the applied mathematics PhD program at Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago.       Last Modified: 04/05/2018       Submitted by: Jinqiao Duan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
