<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Arctic Floats: A Pilot Effort for Arctic Argo</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>71018.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>71018</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Mercer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmercer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927453</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Arctic Ocean plays an important role in regulating the world ocean's heat, and freshwater, and its nutrient cycles. Understanding, monitoring, and predicting how the Arctic Ocean changes as climate changes are thus imperative, but can only be achieved with a comprehensive observation network. The exceedingly successful global Argo program, which consists of roughly 3000 autonomous instruments distributed throughout the world ocean measuring physical properties of the upper 2000 m of the water column, has demonstrated how such a monitoring system can be maintained using low-cost autonomous profiling floats. Technological advancement has made it possible to deploy Argo-type floats in the deep Arctic basin, but sea ice reduces the floats? ability to surface at regular intervals to determine their position and to transmit data to satellites. Using simulations, we will investigate uncertainties associated with extended "silent times" during which floats are unable to surface. We will determine the reduced accuracies in temperature and salinity measurements as a function of a float?s initial position and length of silent times. Use of auxiliary information to estimate the float's movements during silent times will also be explored. These simulations will help establish the likelihood that floats will report their positions after residing 1-5 years under ice and the number of floats that are needed to reduce the uncertainty in the measurement of water mass properties, helping us design a plan for using Arctic floats in the near future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work leverages much of the high latitude satellite and in situ observations and the use of the Arctic Sub-polar gyre state estimate (ASTE) to extract as much information as possible on: (a) the uncertainty associated with operating near-future float technology, and (b) the geographic distribution of where new observations would have the most impact on better understanding the hydrographic changes occuring in the Arctic. We will quantify several metrics, related to the likelihood of a float?s' surfacing-time as a function of time-mean and time-varying sea ice state, the float's associated position uncertainties, and the implied hydrographic uncertainties. The use of the observations and the state estimate are complementary in that ASTE can inform the initial design of the float deployment, and in turn future float data will be used to further constrain and improve ASTE</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1643339</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Heimbach</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick Heimbach</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>heimbach@utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5122327694</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000098567</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>An</FirstName>
<LastName>Nguyen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>An T Nguyen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>atnguyen@ices.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124714207</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000629571</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5293</Code>
<Text>AON-Arctic Observing Network</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~71018</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Objectives:</strong></p> <p>The project&rsquo;s overarching goal is to assess the value of hydrographic measurements from Argo-type floats in the Arctic, given the constraint of reduced surfacing frequency in the presence of sea ice. With increasing time between two consecutive surfacings position un- certainty of intermediate partial profiling of the water column increases, which translates into increased inferred hydrographic uncertainties. Our goal is to quantify estimate the expected surfacing period as a function of position and sea ice coverage and the implied hydrographic uncertainties of profiles taken without surfacing.The project had five main thrusts:</p> <p>(1) develop a methodology to track synthetic Argo- type float trajectories under ice, (2) develop metrics to quantify accumulated error in float positions and implied hydrographic measurement uncertainties under ice, (3) quantify 3D geographic maps of uncertainty in hydrographic measurements, (4) quantify 2D map of likelihood of float surfacing frequency, (5) initial scientific analyses.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Outcomes:</strong></p> <p>Arctic Argo-type floats have a high chance to surface multiple times every year within their lifetime. The likelihood of surfacing is a strong function of the annual sea ice minimum distribution. If the float transits through the seasonally ice covered region its expected surfacing frequency is every 0&ndash;100 days (Figure 1). If the float drifts into the region of multi-year sea ice cover, it is likely not able to surface for up to several years, until it drifts into a seasonal ice cover area where it can surface during the summer time. While blocked by sea ice, the float is still assumed to take a profile over most of the water column, but unable to relay the data nor its position. The longer the float drifts under ice without surfacing, the larger the error accumulation in position and measured hydrographic properties (Figure 2).</p> <p>Due to the lack of continuous spatial and temporal measurements in the Arctic, uncertainties in the mean and variability of temperature and salinity remain high, in particular along energetic boundary currents, below 800 m in the Western Arctic, and throughout the water column in the Eastern Arctic. In these regions, additional measurements along an approximated path whose only known positions are the beginning and ending points can still potentially help constrain numerical models and reduce hydrographic uncertainties. Specifically, for geographic locations where normalized errors are below 1 (Figure 2), Arctic Argo-type hydrographic measurements can contribute to the improvement of the Arctic Ocean state estimate.</p> <p>The normalized hydrographic error estimates depend on current knowledge of the mean and variability of the Arctic hydrography and flow field. The only way to validate and improve our knowledge of these fields and estimates is with additional observations. Results obtained here should be used to inform a float network design with suggested locations of float deployments and associated expected hydrographic uncertainties. This should be an iterative process, where first a data-constrained model is used to help guide the float initial deployment by providing estimates of where floats are expected to yield useful data (the outcome of this project). The next step would be to deploy test floats to validate if these initial error estimates are accurate and where improvement is needed. The data will then be incorporated into the state estimate to improve the model. An updated usefulness estimation can then be obtained.</p> <p>Lastly, irrespective of the specific result obtained here, studies/approaches such as what is presented here should be explored more widely in quantitative observing system design.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/21/2017<br>      Modified by: An&nbsp;T&nbsp;Nguyen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1643339/1643339_10449383_1491027149588_mean_ST_error_FinalReport--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1643339/1643339_10449383_1491027149588_mean_ST_error_FinalReport--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1643339/1643339_10449383_1491027149588_mean_ST_error_FinalReport--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Mean normalized error eS (top) and eT (bottom) fordepth ranges 0-100m (L), 100-300m (M), and 300-2000m (R).  Black contour shows the 1992-2013 sea ice minimum. When a float can not surface, its trajectory becomes unknown and error accumulates.</div> <div class="imageCredit">An T Nguyen</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">An&nbsp;T&nbsp;Nguyen</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1643339/1643339_10449383_1491026811289_mean_hotspot_FinalReport_nocap--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1643339/1643339_10449383_1491026811289_mean_hotspot_FinalReport_nocap--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1643339/1643339_10449383_1491026811289_mean_hotspot_FinalReport_nocap--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The mean number of days a float is expected to remain drifted under ice before it can surface for 3 open water fraction thresholds, which can be viewed as 3 sea ice minimum thresholds.  Spatial distribution of the # of days  is a strong function of the 2007-2013 sea ice minimum (black contour).</div> <div class="imageCredit">An T Nguyen</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">An&nbsp;T&nbsp;Nguyen</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Objectives:  The project?s overarching goal is to assess the value of hydrographic measurements from Argo-type floats in the Arctic, given the constraint of reduced surfacing frequency in the presence of sea ice. With increasing time between two consecutive surfacings position un- certainty of intermediate partial profiling of the water column increases, which translates into increased inferred hydrographic uncertainties. Our goal is to quantify estimate the expected surfacing period as a function of position and sea ice coverage and the implied hydrographic uncertainties of profiles taken without surfacing.The project had five main thrusts:  (1) develop a methodology to track synthetic Argo- type float trajectories under ice, (2) develop metrics to quantify accumulated error in float positions and implied hydrographic measurement uncertainties under ice, (3) quantify 3D geographic maps of uncertainty in hydrographic measurements, (4) quantify 2D map of likelihood of float surfacing frequency, (5) initial scientific analyses.     Outcomes:  Arctic Argo-type floats have a high chance to surface multiple times every year within their lifetime. The likelihood of surfacing is a strong function of the annual sea ice minimum distribution. If the float transits through the seasonally ice covered region its expected surfacing frequency is every 0&ndash;100 days (Figure 1). If the float drifts into the region of multi-year sea ice cover, it is likely not able to surface for up to several years, until it drifts into a seasonal ice cover area where it can surface during the summer time. While blocked by sea ice, the float is still assumed to take a profile over most of the water column, but unable to relay the data nor its position. The longer the float drifts under ice without surfacing, the larger the error accumulation in position and measured hydrographic properties (Figure 2).  Due to the lack of continuous spatial and temporal measurements in the Arctic, uncertainties in the mean and variability of temperature and salinity remain high, in particular along energetic boundary currents, below 800 m in the Western Arctic, and throughout the water column in the Eastern Arctic. In these regions, additional measurements along an approximated path whose only known positions are the beginning and ending points can still potentially help constrain numerical models and reduce hydrographic uncertainties. Specifically, for geographic locations where normalized errors are below 1 (Figure 2), Arctic Argo-type hydrographic measurements can contribute to the improvement of the Arctic Ocean state estimate.  The normalized hydrographic error estimates depend on current knowledge of the mean and variability of the Arctic hydrography and flow field. The only way to validate and improve our knowledge of these fields and estimates is with additional observations. Results obtained here should be used to inform a float network design with suggested locations of float deployments and associated expected hydrographic uncertainties. This should be an iterative process, where first a data-constrained model is used to help guide the float initial deployment by providing estimates of where floats are expected to yield useful data (the outcome of this project). The next step would be to deploy test floats to validate if these initial error estimates are accurate and where improvement is needed. The data will then be incorporated into the state estimate to improve the model. An updated usefulness estimation can then be obtained.  Lastly, irrespective of the specific result obtained here, studies/approaches such as what is presented here should be explored more widely in quantitative observing system design.       Last Modified: 06/21/2017       Submitted by: An T Nguyen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
