<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: A Living Lab for Smartphone-based Parking Management Services</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Walter Peacock</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wpeacock@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922634</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Searching for parking is a real struggle faced by many drivers, especially in urban areas.  Smartphone-based advanced parking management services may provide information on real-time availability and prices of parking spaces and guide motorists to open parking spaces.  This EArly-concept Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER) project will explore the potential of such smartphone-based parking management services to deepen understanding of travelers' parking behaviors and advance the analytical foundations and methodologies for modeling and assessing parking solutions.  This work integrates various stakeholders (individual travelers, parking industry, transportation agencies, and technology developers) and multiple technologies (retrieving real-time data from both users and agencies, predicting future parking availability, providing information and guidance through smartphone application, and analyzing parking games via both analytical and simulation models). As a living lab, this project will provide unique opportunities to collect data on parking search behaviors, discover emerging scenarios of smartphone-based parking management services, and assess the impacts of such systems in a real environment.  Additionally, it fills a critical gap in validating and calibrating the theoretical and simulation models using real data.  By engaging end users, local transportation agencies, industry, and technology developers, it will generate new knowledge regarding how various stakeholders are interrelated and interact with each other.  The project is expected to promote education and human resources development in STEM fields, contribute resources towards parking information infrastructure, and improve user experience in parking.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project involves three main activities:  1) Staged deployment of a prototype Android parking guidance application. The team will work closely with Arizona State University (ASU) Parking and Transit Services to implement a three-stage pilot deployment around the ASU main campus located in downtown Tempe, AZ. This work will engage end users, local transportation agencies, industry, and technology developers.  2) Model validation and verification.  Through the smartphone application, data on individual travelers' parking preferences will be collected and used to validate the stochastic parking models.  Parking behavior models/parameters will also be examined in order to calibrate an agent-based simulation tool.  3) Assessing improvement of stakeholder experience.  For individual travelers, the process of searching for parking will be quantified in terms of a range of performance measures (such as cruising time, number of parking facilities visited, cruising speed, etc.).  For agencies, the congestion caused by cruising for parking will be assessed using a mix of real data collected from the work and transportation network models, including existing models.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1643175</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yingyan</FirstName>
<LastName>Lou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yingyan Lou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yingyan.lou@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809656361</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000559033</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[AZ Board of Regents on behalf of Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>029E</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE SYSTEMS MGT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~149999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The proposed research aims to explore the potential of smartphone-based parking management services as a Smart and Connected Communities (S&amp;CC) solution to parking problems, to deepen our understandings of travelers? parking behaviors, and to further advance the analytical foundations and methodologies for modeling and assessing parking solutions.</p> <p>We seek to apply the living lab approach to testing the hypothesis that such advanced smartphone-based parking management services, as an S&amp;CC solution, will improve individual drivers? parking searching experience, reduce congestion caused by cruising for parking in downtown areas, and affect travel patterns.&nbsp;</p> <p>One major outcome of the project is a parking information and guidance mobile application for both Android and iOS systems. &nbsp;The mobile app implements advanced algorithms to provide not only real-time but also predicted future parking availability information.&nbsp; The mobile app is also capable of providing parking searching guidance (where to look for parking) to a user based on her preference and the estimated probabilities of finding parking at candidate facilities.&nbsp; Other features include navigation, location based real-time updates of parking guidance, and voice commands, etc.&nbsp; Currently the mobile apps are limited to parking facilities at the Arizona State University (ASU) main campus in Tempe, AZ.&nbsp; The app was alpha-tested at ASU.</p> <p>The algorithmic framework that enables the predictive information was developed through a related previous project, and is validated in this project. &nbsp;The team collected sufficient real-time parking availability data from ASU parking facilities and successfully verified the framework that integrates data-driven and model-based prediction of parking availability.</p> <p>The algorithm that supports parking searching guidance is developed directly as part of the project.&nbsp; The algorithm is specifically designed for parking guidance systems that employ a central server where users of the service interact with the central server through a mobile phone app or alike. &nbsp;The idea is to learn the probabilities of finding parking from user-generated data, and compute a best course of action for each individual user.&nbsp; During a time period where the probabilities of finding parking can be reasonably assumed as constant, the central server first engages in an exploration phase. &nbsp;It gathers information through the app on whether a user successfully finds parking or not either based on location data or user reports, then learns from the parking search experiences from all the users in the same area during this exploration phase to compute an approximated user-optimal strategy.&nbsp; The learning algorithm developed in the project is able to achieve accurate estimation with much faster computation time, due to its unique design that exploits the network topology and properties of the parking searching problem.&nbsp; Our numerical experiments on the ASU network with time-dependent underlying probabilities show that effective searching strategies can be achieved by the proposed algorithm.</p> <p>Another significant outcome is a set of models and algorithms for special event traffic planning and management.&nbsp; The models and algorithms aim to help determine transportation network configuration (lane reversal and ride-sharing drop-off locations) and parking guidance strategies.&nbsp; The models specifically consider the lane changing effect (which would be significant around ride-sharing drop off locations) and parking searching behaviors in modeling traffic dynamics.&nbsp; We also developed effective solution algorithms for the complex problem. &nbsp;The models and solution algorithms were tested using data from Super Bowl XLIX in 2015.&nbsp; Our numerical experiments show that the resulting traffic plan is able to save 39.6% of the total vehicle-hours compared to default network configurations.</p> <p>The project team worked closely with various stakeholders, including relevant units at ASU as well as cities in the Phoenix metropolitan areas that regularly host special events, to obtain feedback on the mobile app and brainstorm use cases for the methods and tools developed in this project.&nbsp; Results from this project have also been presented to the research and professional communities at various conferences as well as through journal publications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Yingyan&nbsp;Lou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The proposed research aims to explore the potential of smartphone-based parking management services as a Smart and Connected Communities (S&amp;CC) solution to parking problems, to deepen our understandings of travelers? parking behaviors, and to further advance the analytical foundations and methodologies for modeling and assessing parking solutions.  We seek to apply the living lab approach to testing the hypothesis that such advanced smartphone-based parking management services, as an S&amp;CC solution, will improve individual drivers? parking searching experience, reduce congestion caused by cruising for parking in downtown areas, and affect travel patterns.   One major outcome of the project is a parking information and guidance mobile application for both Android and iOS systems.  The mobile app implements advanced algorithms to provide not only real-time but also predicted future parking availability information.  The mobile app is also capable of providing parking searching guidance (where to look for parking) to a user based on her preference and the estimated probabilities of finding parking at candidate facilities.  Other features include navigation, location based real-time updates of parking guidance, and voice commands, etc.  Currently the mobile apps are limited to parking facilities at the Arizona State University (ASU) main campus in Tempe, AZ.  The app was alpha-tested at ASU.  The algorithmic framework that enables the predictive information was developed through a related previous project, and is validated in this project.  The team collected sufficient real-time parking availability data from ASU parking facilities and successfully verified the framework that integrates data-driven and model-based prediction of parking availability.  The algorithm that supports parking searching guidance is developed directly as part of the project.  The algorithm is specifically designed for parking guidance systems that employ a central server where users of the service interact with the central server through a mobile phone app or alike.  The idea is to learn the probabilities of finding parking from user-generated data, and compute a best course of action for each individual user.  During a time period where the probabilities of finding parking can be reasonably assumed as constant, the central server first engages in an exploration phase.  It gathers information through the app on whether a user successfully finds parking or not either based on location data or user reports, then learns from the parking search experiences from all the users in the same area during this exploration phase to compute an approximated user-optimal strategy.  The learning algorithm developed in the project is able to achieve accurate estimation with much faster computation time, due to its unique design that exploits the network topology and properties of the parking searching problem.  Our numerical experiments on the ASU network with time-dependent underlying probabilities show that effective searching strategies can be achieved by the proposed algorithm.  Another significant outcome is a set of models and algorithms for special event traffic planning and management.  The models and algorithms aim to help determine transportation network configuration (lane reversal and ride-sharing drop-off locations) and parking guidance strategies.  The models specifically consider the lane changing effect (which would be significant around ride-sharing drop off locations) and parking searching behaviors in modeling traffic dynamics.  We also developed effective solution algorithms for the complex problem.  The models and solution algorithms were tested using data from Super Bowl XLIX in 2015.  Our numerical experiments show that the resulting traffic plan is able to save 39.6% of the total vehicle-hours compared to default network configurations.  The project team worked closely with various stakeholders, including relevant units at ASU as well as cities in the Phoenix metropolitan areas that regularly host special events, to obtain feedback on the mobile app and brainstorm use cases for the methods and tools developed in this project.  Results from this project have also been presented to the research and professional communities at various conferences as well as through journal publications.          Last Modified: 11/30/2020       Submitted by: Yingyan Lou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
