<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Defining the phloem-mobile proteins of Arabidopsis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>282240.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>282240</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathryn Dickson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdickson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927380</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In higher animals, blood moves throughout the body in veins and arteries, carrying nutrients, hormones and signaling molecules that coordinate the functions of different organs.  Plants have an analogous fluid called phloem sap, which moves through phloem vessels to carry sugars from photosynthetic organs to the rest of the plant, and to communicate information about nutritional needs, stress or disease between distant plant organs.  Scientists have only a rudimentary understanding of phloem sap-mediated signaling, primarily because it is extremely difficult to collect a phloem sap sample that is not heavily contaminated by fluids from the surrounding cells.  While evidence suggests that hundreds of proteins exist in the phloem sap, only a small number are confirmed to actually move and only one has a known function.  In this project, the researchers will identify hundreds of phloem sap proteins with confirmed long distance movement.  The researcher's novel approach involves grafting two plants with distinct genetic sequences together and then using protein sequence analysis to identify proteins from plant 1 in the phloem vessels of plant 2.  If successful, this project will generate the first large dataset of mobile phloem sap proteins, overcoming the current bottleneck in the field of intra-plant signaling.  The identity of these proteins will catalyze new research directions and will impact a large number of plant biologists.  Phloem signaling is an essential component of the plant's ability to survive biotic and abiotic stresses.  Therefore, this project will suggest new strategies for improving crop plant growth and yield.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Despite the exciting potential of intra-plant communication via phloem-mobile proteins, there is no current consensus as to the identity of the phloem sap proteome in most plants, including the model plant Arabidopsis thaliana where researchers could best test the function of these proteins.  The PI will use a grafting approach to definitively identify proteins that move long distance through a graft union.  Taking advantage of the extensive sequence data available for over 1000 Arabidopsis accessions, the PI will identify grafting partners where sequence variation leads to amino acid differences in ~1100 predicted phloem sap proteins.  Heterografts will be made, protein samples enriched for phloem sap will be collected from the scion, and Mass Spectrometry will be used to identify rootstock proteins that have travelled to the scion tissue.  The proteome generated by this project will rely on observed protein movement.  This is in contrast to previous attempts in the field to define the phloem sap proteome based on direct phloem sap extraction, a process that is extremely difficult and plagued with technical difficulties.  The definition of hundreds of mobile proteins will overcome the current bottleneck in this field, where the existing phloem sap proteomes are contradictory and generally acknowledged to have large sampling artefacts.  Once in hand, the phloem sap proteome will lead to testable hypotheses about phloem sap signaling based on the identity and function of the mobile proteins.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1643419</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jocelyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Malamy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jocelyn Malamy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmalamy@bsd.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737024651</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000103904</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6054 South Drexel Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606371454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[929 East 57th Street, W519U]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7658</Code>
<Text>Physiolgcl Mechnsms&amp;Biomechnsm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~138165</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~144075</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The phloem sap of plants plays a similar role to the bloodstream in animals, carrying nutrients and signaling molecules that allow the different parts of the organism to talk to eachother and coordinate function and growth.&nbsp; The phloem sap is difficult to study because, like blood, it clots rapidly to prevent loss after an injury.&nbsp; In most plants, scientists have been unable to obtain pure phloem sap for study.&nbsp; As a result, phloem sap contents are incompletely known, although sap has been shown to contain a high concentration of RNAs and proteins in addition to nutrients.&nbsp; The goal of this project was to take a new approach to identify the proteins in phloem sap.&nbsp; This approach included two innovations:&nbsp; 1)&nbsp; Grafting different varieties of the model plant Arabidopsis to eachother so that proteins that moved from the base of the graft to the top could be identified based on their distinct sequences.&nbsp; Sequences would be determined by Mass Spectroscopy.&nbsp; 2)&nbsp; Using a novel technique to try to enrich for phloem sap in plant extracts.&nbsp; Both of these approaches were technically challenging and high risk, since it was unclear if the methods would be powerful enough to detect proteins.&nbsp;</p> <p>Unfortunately, after extensive attempts we were unable to define phloem sap proteins in any useful numbers.&nbsp; However, we found that our novel technique does enrich samples for phloem sap.&nbsp; We determined this by examining RNA in grafted plants - mobile RNA the originated from the bottom of the graft could be detected based on its distinct sequence.&nbsp; We optimized a method in which the plant stem from the top of the graft is punctured and exuded fluid rapidly collected.&nbsp; Using this approach, three different RNAs analyzed were found to derive almost exclusively from the bottom of the graft, indicating that they must be mobile via the phloem sap.&nbsp; Based on these findings we shifted our focus and used our grafted plants to identify phloem sap RNAs.&nbsp; We are at the end of the project and ready to submit samples for RNA sequencing and subsequent publication.</p> <p>Once confirmed, the pipeline that we pioneered in this work will be useful to other plant biologists.&nbsp; The stem puncture fluid is unlikely to represent pure phloem sap, but collected in conjunction with plant grafts it provides an easy and conclusive way to confirm the mobility of an RNA.&nbsp; In addition, this approach will allow researchers to identify RNAs that enter the phloem sap and move in response to wounding, bacterial infection, or other environmental changes.&nbsp; This will be an important breakthough in our ability to study plant signaling.</p> <p>Over the course of this project, one graduate student and two undergraduates gained training in plant physiology and genetics.&nbsp; The graduate student plans to finish her Ph.D. thesis this year.&nbsp; One of the undergraduate students obtained a BS as a result of a thesis written about her contributions to this work.&nbsp; The PI on the project took over responsibility for the Undergraduate Biology Curriculum at The University of Chicago near the time that this project began, becoming a Deputy Dean of the College and Master of the Biological Sciences Collegiate Division.&nbsp; In that role, she has a)&nbsp; worked to create increased opportunities and funding for students to participate in summer research, b) developed eperiential learning programs for UChicago students at the Marine Biological Laboratories in Woods Hole, c) modified the&nbsp; UChicago biology curriculum to emphasize inquiry-based learning for all students, and d) is participating in the development of a new initiative to support the success of first generation students and students from under represented minority groups in STEM majors at UChicago.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/07/2021<br>      Modified by: Jocelyn&nbsp;Malamy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The phloem sap of plants plays a similar role to the bloodstream in animals, carrying nutrients and signaling molecules that allow the different parts of the organism to talk to eachother and coordinate function and growth.  The phloem sap is difficult to study because, like blood, it clots rapidly to prevent loss after an injury.  In most plants, scientists have been unable to obtain pure phloem sap for study.  As a result, phloem sap contents are incompletely known, although sap has been shown to contain a high concentration of RNAs and proteins in addition to nutrients.  The goal of this project was to take a new approach to identify the proteins in phloem sap.  This approach included two innovations:  1)  Grafting different varieties of the model plant Arabidopsis to eachother so that proteins that moved from the base of the graft to the top could be identified based on their distinct sequences.  Sequences would be determined by Mass Spectroscopy.  2)  Using a novel technique to try to enrich for phloem sap in plant extracts.  Both of these approaches were technically challenging and high risk, since it was unclear if the methods would be powerful enough to detect proteins.   Unfortunately, after extensive attempts we were unable to define phloem sap proteins in any useful numbers.  However, we found that our novel technique does enrich samples for phloem sap.  We determined this by examining RNA in grafted plants - mobile RNA the originated from the bottom of the graft could be detected based on its distinct sequence.  We optimized a method in which the plant stem from the top of the graft is punctured and exuded fluid rapidly collected.  Using this approach, three different RNAs analyzed were found to derive almost exclusively from the bottom of the graft, indicating that they must be mobile via the phloem sap.  Based on these findings we shifted our focus and used our grafted plants to identify phloem sap RNAs.  We are at the end of the project and ready to submit samples for RNA sequencing and subsequent publication.  Once confirmed, the pipeline that we pioneered in this work will be useful to other plant biologists.  The stem puncture fluid is unlikely to represent pure phloem sap, but collected in conjunction with plant grafts it provides an easy and conclusive way to confirm the mobility of an RNA.  In addition, this approach will allow researchers to identify RNAs that enter the phloem sap and move in response to wounding, bacterial infection, or other environmental changes.  This will be an important breakthough in our ability to study plant signaling.  Over the course of this project, one graduate student and two undergraduates gained training in plant physiology and genetics.  The graduate student plans to finish her Ph.D. thesis this year.  One of the undergraduate students obtained a BS as a result of a thesis written about her contributions to this work.  The PI on the project took over responsibility for the Undergraduate Biology Curriculum at The University of Chicago near the time that this project began, becoming a Deputy Dean of the College and Master of the Biological Sciences Collegiate Division.  In that role, she has a)  worked to create increased opportunities and funding for students to participate in summer research, b) developed eperiential learning programs for UChicago students at the Marine Biological Laboratories in Woods Hole, c) modified the  UChicago biology curriculum to emphasize inquiry-based learning for all students, and d) is participating in the development of a new initiative to support the success of first generation students and students from under represented minority groups in STEM majors at UChicago.          Last Modified: 05/07/2021       Submitted by: Jocelyn Malamy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
