<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Fundamental mechanisms of removal of stacking fault tetrahedra by mobile low energy boundaries</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>334586.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>334586</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gary Shiflet</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this work is to understand the fundamental mechanisms through which mobile twin boundaries (TBs) actively engage and rapidly remove stacking fault tetrahedra (SFTs). The ultimate goal is to design advanced metallic materials that can effectively remove SFTs at low-to-intermediate temperatures. SFTs are detrimental defects in neutron or proton irradiated structural metallic materials with face-centered-cubic structures as they can induce significant hardening and swelling. The PI will use a combination of in situ radiation and in situ nanoindentation technique to investigate the interaction of SFTs with TBs. These studies can explain the annihilation of SFTs by TBs and provide crucial information to validate annihilation mechanisms predicted by MD simulations. Also significant mobility of TBs may make them attractive candidates to remove radiation induced immobile defects, such as SFTs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the benefits of this research will include discovery of important criteria for the design of swelling resistant structural materials for next generation nuclear reactors, and offer the basis for further exploration of physics of radiation induced twin boundary migrations. This project will provide research training to graduate and undergraduate students at Texas A&amp;M University (TAMU). Special effort will be made to recruit female and other minority students through the "Pathway to Ph.D program" funded by TAMU. The project will also enhance the materials science and nanoengineering curricula by incorporating relevant results into classes when introducing advanced nanomaterials, and benefit the new formed Department of Materials Science and Engineering. The PI will disseminate results to a much broader audience by involving high school teachers in the research project through NSF-RET program, and attending international conferences. Collaborations with McMaster University and several DOE National Laboratories will offer graduate students summer research experience.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1643915</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xinghang</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xinghang Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xzhang98@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654941641</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000250748</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072045</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[701 W. Stadium Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~105699</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~113302</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~115585</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this proposal is to understand the fundamental mechanisms through which mobile twin boundaries (TBs) actively engage and rapidly remove stacking fault tetrahedra (SFTs). The ultimate goal is to design advanced metallic materials that can effectively remove SFTs at low-to-intermediate temperatures. SFTs, frequently encountered nanoscale defects in face centered cubic (fcc) metals with low-to-intermediate stacking fault energy, are one of the most intriguing microstructural defects. These three-dimensional defects can be formed in various ways, including irradiation, rapid quenching and the conservative motion of dislocations in plastically deformed metals and alloys. SFTs are detrimental defects in neutron or proton irradiated structural metallic materials with face-centered-cubic structures as they can induce significant hardening and swelling. What is more, their removal is very challenging, typically requires annealing at very high temperature, injection of interstitials or mobile dislocations. TBs are an important type of low energy defects. High density twins can be synthesized in a variety of fcc metals.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual merit.</strong> The major scientific findings of this NSF project can be summarized as follows. (1) In situ radiation studies (at Argonne National Lab) provide direct evidence for defect cluster-twin boundaries interactions and hence prove that twin boundaries are efficient defect sinks for radiation induced defects. (2) Radiation induces detwinning or twin boundary migration. (3) Certain solute atoms can significantly improve the radiation stability of twin boundaries. (4) The radiation tolerance of nanotwinned metals can be further enhanced by using nanotwin-nanovoid defect networks. (5) Free surface in nanoporous metals and nanowires are powerful defect sinks for radiation induced defects. (6) Layer interface-twin boundary network can enhance the mechanical strength and radiation tolerance of nanostructured metals.</p> <p><strong>Broader impact.</strong> (a) Outreach to scientific community. During this NSF project, we collaborated with scientists from Argonne National Laboratory, Los Alamos National Laboratory, Sandia National Laboratory, Texas A&amp;M University and University of Nebraska, Lincoln. (b) Dissemination of results to broader audience. The PI&rsquo;s team has hosted numerous undergraduate students in consecutive years and involved them in this project. (c) Professional preparation for students. 3 Ph.D. students were directly involved in this project. One of them became a postdoc at Los Alamos National Laboratory, and now a faculty at academia. Another student becomes a postdoc at Purdue. The last student will graduate in one year. (d) Award and recognition. 1 Ph.D. student was awarded MRS graduate student silver medal award and AVS graduate student award. 1 student has been given the best graduate student award from College of Engineering. (e) Research outcome. 23 articles were published in peer-reviewed scientific journals. Numerous invited talks were presented at national and international conferences and national laboratories.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/11/2018<br>      Modified by: Xinghang&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this proposal is to understand the fundamental mechanisms through which mobile twin boundaries (TBs) actively engage and rapidly remove stacking fault tetrahedra (SFTs). The ultimate goal is to design advanced metallic materials that can effectively remove SFTs at low-to-intermediate temperatures. SFTs, frequently encountered nanoscale defects in face centered cubic (fcc) metals with low-to-intermediate stacking fault energy, are one of the most intriguing microstructural defects. These three-dimensional defects can be formed in various ways, including irradiation, rapid quenching and the conservative motion of dislocations in plastically deformed metals and alloys. SFTs are detrimental defects in neutron or proton irradiated structural metallic materials with face-centered-cubic structures as they can induce significant hardening and swelling. What is more, their removal is very challenging, typically requires annealing at very high temperature, injection of interstitials or mobile dislocations. TBs are an important type of low energy defects. High density twins can be synthesized in a variety of fcc metals.  Intellectual merit. The major scientific findings of this NSF project can be summarized as follows. (1) In situ radiation studies (at Argonne National Lab) provide direct evidence for defect cluster-twin boundaries interactions and hence prove that twin boundaries are efficient defect sinks for radiation induced defects. (2) Radiation induces detwinning or twin boundary migration. (3) Certain solute atoms can significantly improve the radiation stability of twin boundaries. (4) The radiation tolerance of nanotwinned metals can be further enhanced by using nanotwin-nanovoid defect networks. (5) Free surface in nanoporous metals and nanowires are powerful defect sinks for radiation induced defects. (6) Layer interface-twin boundary network can enhance the mechanical strength and radiation tolerance of nanostructured metals.  Broader impact. (a) Outreach to scientific community. During this NSF project, we collaborated with scientists from Argonne National Laboratory, Los Alamos National Laboratory, Sandia National Laboratory, Texas A&amp;M University and University of Nebraska, Lincoln. (b) Dissemination of results to broader audience. The PI?s team has hosted numerous undergraduate students in consecutive years and involved them in this project. (c) Professional preparation for students. 3 Ph.D. students were directly involved in this project. One of them became a postdoc at Los Alamos National Laboratory, and now a faculty at academia. Another student becomes a postdoc at Purdue. The last student will graduate in one year. (d) Award and recognition. 1 Ph.D. student was awarded MRS graduate student silver medal award and AVS graduate student award. 1 student has been given the best graduate student award from College of Engineering. (e) Research outcome. 23 articles were published in peer-reviewed scientific journals. Numerous invited talks were presented at national and international conferences and national laboratories.          Last Modified: 11/11/2018       Submitted by: Xinghang Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
