<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Regional Conference Series in Mathematical String Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award, under the direction of Professor Ronen Plesser of Duke University, supports a series of regional conferences in mathematical string theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;String theory is the leading contender to unify general relativity and quantum field theory, two of the most significant developments of twentieth-century physics.   This award provides support for a series of bi-annual regional meetings in North Carolina and Virginia which focus on the mathematical aspects of this subject.  Research in this area not only advances our understanding of fundamental physics but has also proven to have extremely fruitful interactions with mathematics.  As a result, research in this area advances the national interest by promoting the progress of science.   These meetings fill a critical need by regularly bringing together isolated research groups to collaborate and hear research talks on various aspects of mathematical string theory.  These meetings also provide essential training for students and postdocs, both by exposing them to a wide array of ideas as well as giving them a forum in which to give talks, thereby substantially aiding both training and research efforts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1643420</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Sharpe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric R Sharpe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ersharpe@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402317890</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000249129</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>M. Ronen</FirstName>
<LastName>Plesser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>M. Ronen Plesser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>plesser@cgtp.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196609668</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000107963</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Gray</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James A Gray</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jamesgray@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402315281</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000651749</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Heckman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan J Heckman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jheckman@sas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000674542</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277080305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Science Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~4000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~4000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~4000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant provided support for a set of regular regional meetings in mathematical string theory, an attempt to unify general relativity and quantum field theory, the two primary developments of twentieth-century physics.&nbsp; There are several groups in the NC and VA area working on related topics in mathematical string theory, including groups at Duke University, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, NC State University, Virginia Tech, James Madison University, and Virginia Commonwealth University, among others.&nbsp; This grant has provided support for junior people to attend and speak at each of six regional meetings bringing these groups together, two meetings a year for each of the last three years.</p> <p>These meetings inexpensively fill a critical need.&nbsp; Some of the area universities are separated by several hours' driving time, and historically none have had the funding to hold regular technical seminars.&nbsp; By bringing area researchers together for a day or two of technical seminars, not only does this enhance research efforts by helping everyone keep up with current developments in the field, but in addition it also provides a mechanism for area researchers to spend a day talking together, which can spark and further technical collaborations.</p> <p>These meetings also provide opportunitites for training for graduate students and postdocs, in several ways.&nbsp; First, it gives the students and postdocs the opportunity to hear more research talks than they might hear otherwise, as none of the research groups at the separate universities individually have the funding for regular external speakers.&nbsp; Second, it provides an opportunity for those same students and postdocs to give talks themselves, in a less stressful environment than they might encounter when giving research talks outside of the NC/VA area.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/04/2019<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;R&nbsp;Sharpe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant provided support for a set of regular regional meetings in mathematical string theory, an attempt to unify general relativity and quantum field theory, the two primary developments of twentieth-century physics.  There are several groups in the NC and VA area working on related topics in mathematical string theory, including groups at Duke University, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, NC State University, Virginia Tech, James Madison University, and Virginia Commonwealth University, among others.  This grant has provided support for junior people to attend and speak at each of six regional meetings bringing these groups together, two meetings a year for each of the last three years.  These meetings inexpensively fill a critical need.  Some of the area universities are separated by several hours' driving time, and historically none have had the funding to hold regular technical seminars.  By bringing area researchers together for a day or two of technical seminars, not only does this enhance research efforts by helping everyone keep up with current developments in the field, but in addition it also provides a mechanism for area researchers to spend a day talking together, which can spark and further technical collaborations.  These meetings also provide opportunitites for training for graduate students and postdocs, in several ways.  First, it gives the students and postdocs the opportunity to hear more research talks than they might hear otherwise, as none of the research groups at the separate universities individually have the funding for regular external speakers.  Second, it provides an opportunity for those same students and postdocs to give talks themselves, in a less stressful environment than they might encounter when giving research talks outside of the NC/VA area.       Last Modified: 09/04/2019       Submitted by: Eric R Sharpe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
