<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Method for Forming Interlaced Composites During Automated Fiber Placement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This I-Corps project seeks to identify the commercial potential of an automated composite manufacturing technology. The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is that it enables new design options for composites -- impacting a wide range of industries.  This team's technology is an automated method of forming composites that seeks to improve capabilities in the area of composite manufacturing.  The technology allows designers to create new structures that are not currently synthesized or manufactured. Aircraft and automobile industries are typical sectors where composites are used to reduce weight. Through this project's technology, composite designers will be able to realize greater weight savings than they have using traditionally  designed and manufactured composites.  These weight savings will allow designers to meet fuel efficiency standards, increase payload capacity, and extend the range of vehicles or airplanes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Composites formed using traditional automated processes are constrained to 2D laminate structures using unidirectional tapes (narrow, woven fabric materials).  Composites formed this way are vulnerable to impact damage and severely limit the options available to the designer.  This project's technology permits the local manipulation of fabric geometry in a composite, which allows designers to optimize the strength and stiffness of the composite structure.  Additionally, this technology allows interlacing of adjacent layers in the composite, which enhances the impact resistance of the composite.  Participation in I-Corps will allow the proposed technology to be evaluated for commercial merit and enable the development of a commercialization strategy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1643507</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ben</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ben Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ben.wang@gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048944819</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000608325</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During the Summer 2016 NSF I-Corps Program (NYCRIN Node), our team (WEAV3D) conducted 100 customer discovery interviews. Georgia Tech has developed a composite manufacturing machine that combines weaving and composite consolidation into a single process, to increase production rates and reduce manufacturing costs. Coming into the program, we were initially targeting engineers the aerospace industry as our target customer.&nbsp; Within our first 20 interviews, the team discovered that the entry barriers in the aerospace market would prevent us from pursuing aerospace as our initial customer. We pursued a handful of alternative markets including: maritime, construction, and racing, before we pivoted to the automotive market. Automotive manufacturers are required to meet the Corporate Average Fuel Economy Standards, which demands year-over-year improvements to vehicle fuel economy, and vehicle lightweighting is key to achieving this goal. As a result of over 50 interviews within the automotive space, we have discovered that automotive manufacturers will use our manufacturing technology to reduce vehicle weight in order to avoid federal fines from failing to meet fuel economy regulations. This shift from aerospace to automotive assisted us in selecting between two alternative machine designs to pick the machine that had the highest commercial potential.</p> <p>Based on our positive I-Corps experience, the WEAV3D team is currently working to commercialize the composite forming technology and both entrepreneurial leads, Chris Oberste and Lewis Motion, have expressed an interest in starting a company to bring the technology to market. Chris is planning to graduate with a PhD in Materials Science and Engineering in the Summer of 2017 and Lewis is expected to graduate with his MBA in the Spring of 2017. After completing the 6-week I-Corps program, Chris returned to Detroit to conduct additional automotive interviews, while Lewis attended a snow sports trade show to discover alternative markets. As part of their commercialization efforts, Chris and Lewis are participating in several business plan competitions during the Spring 2017 semester, and have already taken second place ($1,250) at the Georgia Bowl Business Plan Competition. The PI, Ben Wang, has received $50,000 from the Georgia Research Alliance to assist with the construction of a prototype of the composite forming machine. Additionally, the team has applied for the NSF PFI:AIR-TT grant ($200,000), which would further assist the team in bringing the technology to commercially ready state.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/24/2017<br>      Modified by: Ben&nbsp;Wang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During the Summer 2016 NSF I-Corps Program (NYCRIN Node), our team (WEAV3D) conducted 100 customer discovery interviews. Georgia Tech has developed a composite manufacturing machine that combines weaving and composite consolidation into a single process, to increase production rates and reduce manufacturing costs. Coming into the program, we were initially targeting engineers the aerospace industry as our target customer.  Within our first 20 interviews, the team discovered that the entry barriers in the aerospace market would prevent us from pursuing aerospace as our initial customer. We pursued a handful of alternative markets including: maritime, construction, and racing, before we pivoted to the automotive market. Automotive manufacturers are required to meet the Corporate Average Fuel Economy Standards, which demands year-over-year improvements to vehicle fuel economy, and vehicle lightweighting is key to achieving this goal. As a result of over 50 interviews within the automotive space, we have discovered that automotive manufacturers will use our manufacturing technology to reduce vehicle weight in order to avoid federal fines from failing to meet fuel economy regulations. This shift from aerospace to automotive assisted us in selecting between two alternative machine designs to pick the machine that had the highest commercial potential.  Based on our positive I-Corps experience, the WEAV3D team is currently working to commercialize the composite forming technology and both entrepreneurial leads, Chris Oberste and Lewis Motion, have expressed an interest in starting a company to bring the technology to market. Chris is planning to graduate with a PhD in Materials Science and Engineering in the Summer of 2017 and Lewis is expected to graduate with his MBA in the Spring of 2017. After completing the 6-week I-Corps program, Chris returned to Detroit to conduct additional automotive interviews, while Lewis attended a snow sports trade show to discover alternative markets. As part of their commercialization efforts, Chris and Lewis are participating in several business plan competitions during the Spring 2017 semester, and have already taken second place ($1,250) at the Georgia Bowl Business Plan Competition. The PI, Ben Wang, has received $50,000 from the Georgia Research Alliance to assist with the construction of a prototype of the composite forming machine. Additionally, the team has applied for the NSF PFI:AIR-TT grant ($200,000), which would further assist the team in bringing the technology to commercially ready state.       Last Modified: 02/24/2017       Submitted by: Ben Wang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
