<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>West Antartctic Ice Shelf- Ocean Interactions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>246809.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>246809</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Milne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmilne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924714</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Overview and Intellectual merit:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project extends and combines historical and recent ocean data sets to investigate ice-ocean-interactions along the Pacific continental margin of the West Antarctic Ice Sheet. The synthesis focuses on the strikingly different environments on and near the cold Ross Sea and warm Amundsen Sea continental shelves, where available measurements reach back to ~1958 and 1994, respectively.&lt;br/&gt;On the more extensively covered Ross Sea continental shelf, multiple reoccupations of ocean stations and transects are used to extend our knowledge of long-term ocean freshening and the mass balance of the world?s largest ice shelf.  On the more rugged Amundsen Sea continental shelf, which contains the earth?s fastest melting ice shelves, continuing research on observed thermohaline variability also pursues connections between outer shelf shoals and vulnerable ice shelf grounding zones. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This interdisciplinary work updates a prior study of ice shelf response to ocean thermal forcing, and uses chemical tracers to measure changes in shelf, deep and bottom water transformations and production rates.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts :&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent and potential future rates of sea level rise are the primary broad-scale impacts of the ice and ocean changes revealed by observations in the study area. The overriding question is whether global and regional sea levels will accelerate gradually, allowing carbon usage reductions to head off the worst consequences, or so rapidly that they will contribute to major social and economic upheavals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Collaborations and data acquired by foreign vessels are also utilized to&lt;br/&gt;better understand the causes of rapid change in these shelf seas and ice shelves, along with associated wider implications. Data that are re-gridded, re-edited or newly collated will be archived, and results made available via presentations, publications, and press releases if warranted. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal does not require fieldwork in the Antarctic&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/13/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1644159</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stanley</FirstName>
<LastName>Jacobs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stanley S Jacobs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sjacobs@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9143658326</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000085164</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Nitsche</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frank O Nitsche</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fnitsche@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8453658746</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000166446</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Smethie Jr.</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William M Smethie Jr.</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bsmeth@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8453658566</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000249325</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Palisades</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>109648000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[61 Route 9W]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANT Ocean &amp; Atmos Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANTARCTIC OCEAN &amp; ATMOSPH SCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~246809</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 'West Antarctic Ice Shelf-Ocean Interactions' project focused on changes that have occurred on adjacent continental shelves of the Ross and Amundsen Seas in the Pacific sector of the Southern Ocean. We compiled a 63-year observational database of ocean temperature and salinity, over a larger area and using a different method than previously employed. Now the longest ocean record near Antarctica, it confirms and extends a persistent long-term freshening&nbsp;in the Ross sector since ~1970. We evaluated potential influences on the salinity decline from reanalysis winds, sea ice formation, the Ross Ice Shelf and other local factors, but found that the freshening can be accounted for by a small fraction of strong ice shelf melting upstream, largest in the Amundsen sector. That 'imbalance' melting thins the floating ice shelves and reduces their constraints on inflowing glaciers, thus adding to sea level rise, as does the freshened seawater. The lower salinity also decreases seawater density, limiting its former ability to modify the deepest levels of the abyssal ocean downstream of the Ross Sea.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our work demonstrates the value of long-term records in a region also influenced by substantial short-term variability. When record lengths are less than a few decades, that variability appears to dominate the observed changes in ocean salinity, heat transport and ice shelf melting. When longer, the changes become increasingly linear and more closely resemble global trends such as the steady rise in surface temperature and anthropogenic CO2 emissions to the atmosphere.&nbsp;The ice shelf changes correlate positively with surface wind forcing near the Amundsen continental shelf break, which is responding in turn to larger scale shifts in the atmospheric circulation, including a tropical Pacific connection. Short-term salinity changes at 500-m depths in the SW Ross Sea display a similar mix of short and long-term variability and trend, in response to the upstream melting.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We show that freshening has been stronger in the Ross Sea than at other locations around Antarctica, in particular the Weddell Sea with its comparable large continental shelf and Filchner-Ronne Ice Shelf. This is relevant because modeling by others of the ocean circulation in that region projects eventual ocean freshening - at a level that has already occurred in the Ross, could erode its large ice shelf. Projecting into the future from past measurements, the iconic High Salinity Shelf Water will disappear by the 1980s, making the Ross continental shelf more like the modeled Weddell sector, or the Amundsen. That would likely thin the relatively stable Ross Ice Shelf, another adverse outcome for sea level change. Ongoing climate changes could strengthen the coastal and slope front currents while increasing the melting rates of glacial ice. But it remains to be seen whether homo ?sapiens? will reduce its carbon footprint before the earth?s beaches are drowned by related thermal expansion and the addition of glacial meltwater to the sea.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This study has supported related work on four published and submitted papers, provided data and samples to other investigators, and generated a Ross Sea Freshening Index. The underlying record is being archived for potential use by others, and we trust will be further augmented and lengthened, in part by those who have contributed, with thanks, to the existing database.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/24/2021<br>      Modified by: Stanley&nbsp;S&nbsp;Jacobs</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 'West Antarctic Ice Shelf-Ocean Interactions' project focused on changes that have occurred on adjacent continental shelves of the Ross and Amundsen Seas in the Pacific sector of the Southern Ocean. We compiled a 63-year observational database of ocean temperature and salinity, over a larger area and using a different method than previously employed. Now the longest ocean record near Antarctica, it confirms and extends a persistent long-term freshening in the Ross sector since ~1970. We evaluated potential influences on the salinity decline from reanalysis winds, sea ice formation, the Ross Ice Shelf and other local factors, but found that the freshening can be accounted for by a small fraction of strong ice shelf melting upstream, largest in the Amundsen sector. That 'imbalance' melting thins the floating ice shelves and reduces their constraints on inflowing glaciers, thus adding to sea level rise, as does the freshened seawater. The lower salinity also decreases seawater density, limiting its former ability to modify the deepest levels of the abyssal ocean downstream of the Ross Sea.     Our work demonstrates the value of long-term records in a region also influenced by substantial short-term variability. When record lengths are less than a few decades, that variability appears to dominate the observed changes in ocean salinity, heat transport and ice shelf melting. When longer, the changes become increasingly linear and more closely resemble global trends such as the steady rise in surface temperature and anthropogenic CO2 emissions to the atmosphere. The ice shelf changes correlate positively with surface wind forcing near the Amundsen continental shelf break, which is responding in turn to larger scale shifts in the atmospheric circulation, including a tropical Pacific connection. Short-term salinity changes at 500-m depths in the SW Ross Sea display a similar mix of short and long-term variability and trend, in response to the upstream melting.     We show that freshening has been stronger in the Ross Sea than at other locations around Antarctica, in particular the Weddell Sea with its comparable large continental shelf and Filchner-Ronne Ice Shelf. This is relevant because modeling by others of the ocean circulation in that region projects eventual ocean freshening - at a level that has already occurred in the Ross, could erode its large ice shelf. Projecting into the future from past measurements, the iconic High Salinity Shelf Water will disappear by the 1980s, making the Ross continental shelf more like the modeled Weddell sector, or the Amundsen. That would likely thin the relatively stable Ross Ice Shelf, another adverse outcome for sea level change. Ongoing climate changes could strengthen the coastal and slope front currents while increasing the melting rates of glacial ice. But it remains to be seen whether homo ?sapiens? will reduce its carbon footprint before the earth?s beaches are drowned by related thermal expansion and the addition of glacial meltwater to the sea.     This study has supported related work on four published and submitted papers, provided data and samples to other investigators, and generated a Ross Sea Freshening Index. The underlying record is being archived for potential use by others, and we trust will be further augmented and lengthened, in part by those who have contributed, with thanks, to the existing database.          Last Modified: 07/24/2021       Submitted by: Stanley S Jacobs]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
