<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER:  Collaborative Research: Role of Citizen Science in Watershed Hydrology Research: Relationships between Volunteer Motivations, Data Quantity and Quality, and Decision-Making</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>52771.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>52771</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karl Rockne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>krockne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925356</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1644860/1644862&lt;br/&gt;Mayer/Jones&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is growing interest in using citizen science projects, public participation in scientific research, to measure hydrologic parameters. Hydrologic variability requires repeated measurements over long periods of time and over a wide range of locations. Citizen science could be a cost-effective approach for hydrologic monitoring, but concerns about data reliability remain; this reliability includes aspects of data quality and quantity, where quantity refers to both temporal frequency and spatial distribution. The overall goal of this project is to advance scientific understanding of the linkages between citizen science project design, the quantity and quality of hydrologic data collected, and the contribution of this method of scientific research to informing payments for watershed services program design and support.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is innovative in that it explores the impact of citizen science data reliability "end-to-end" including, recruitment and retention of citizen science volunteers, citizen science data collection, incorporation of citizen science data in engineering tools, and  informing policy design and decision-making. The project objectives are: (1) to determine the factors affecting retention in citizen science programs, (2) to test the effect that norm-based messaging can have on the quantity and quality of data collected, and, (3) to evaluate the impact of the quantity and quality of citizen science data collected on hydrologic model reliability, corresponding payments for watershed services program decision-making, and support for payments for watershed services programs. These objectives will be met by: (1) recruiting citizen science volunteers in two watersheds in Veracruz, Mexico with ongoing hydrologic data collection and payments for watershed services programs; (2) implementing an experimental design to test the effect of norm messaging by randomly allocating "nudges" to citizen science volunteers; (3) simultaneously collecting rainfall and stream discharge data with citizen science volunteers and accepted hydrologic science protocols; (4) estimating the precision and accuracy of the citizen science data against the data collected with the accepted scientific protocols; (5) calibrating a watershed hydrology model with and without the citizen science data, including the effects of data precision and accuracy; and, (6) determining priority areas for payments for watershed services with and without the citizen science data. Mexico has one of the world?s longest running payments for watershed services programs. The National Forest Commission, responsible for payments for watershed services programs in Mexico, plans to use citizen science volunteers for monitoring hydrologic outcomes of local payments for watershed services programs. Thus, the proposed work could improve payments for watershed services program design and monitoring and evaluation protocols, especially if there are indirect benefits of citizen science participation through improved knowledge, behaviors, and support of payments for watershed services programs. The PIs plan to generate several refereed papers and presentations from this work on the social science, biophysical and integrated aspects of this work. Additionally, this project will support training of two PhD students contributing to at least two dissertations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1644860</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alex</FirstName>
<LastName>Mayer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alex S Mayer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amayer2@utep.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9157478699</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000262386</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heidi</FirstName>
<LastName>Asbjornsen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Heidi Asbjornsen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>heidi.asbjornsen@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2075224261</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000116524</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lyssette Elena</FirstName>
<LastName>Munoz Villers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dra</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lyssette Elena Munoz Villers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lyssette.munoz@atmosfera.unam.mx</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000723240</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carter</FirstName>
<LastName>Berry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carter Berry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zcberry@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6038622172</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000723704</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan Technological University</Name>
<CityName>Houghton</CityName>
<ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9064871885</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 Townsend Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065453268</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN TECHNOLOGICAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065453268</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan Technological University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houghton</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 Townsend Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043Z</Code>
<Text>PPSR- Public Participation in Scientific</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~52771</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The QUIAHUA, M&eacute;xico, community based rainfallmonitoring project carried out in two catchments in theupper Antigua river watershed, central Veracruz, Mexico.The study area has experienced substantial deforestation of cloud forests in the last few decades. Low flows in the 1990s prompted local interest in potential impacts of land use change on hydrologic cycling. While efforts have been made to quantify the hydrological impacts associated withforest conversion in headwater catchments, for larger catchment scales these efforts have been hampered by&nbsp;the paucity of rainfall data. Citizen volunteers were recruited to measure daily rainfall using manual gaugesover an 18-month period. Automated tipping bucket gauges were installed to simultaneously measuredrainfall. Surveys and interviews of volunteers were conducted to understand motivations of CSH volunteersand whether the factors influencing motivations could be linked to measurement accuracy. Manual and automated data were compiled to compare measurement methods.Rainfall spatial distributions over the study area were interpolated with previously existing gauge data only and with the automated and manual rainfall data. The rainfallspatial distributions are used to drive a hydrologic model and estimate the corresponding distribution of rechargerates over the study area.</p> <p>Examining data accuracy, we found that three monitors recorded rainfall with minor deviations from the tippingbucket data, i.e. 150 mm or less of difference on annualbasis. We found eight monitors recorded rainfall withsome deviations with the tipping bucket data, i.e. between 250 and 375 mm of difference. We found that fivemonitors recorded rainfall with major deviations from thetipping bucket data, i.e. 375 mm or more of difference.To understand what the major determinants of this error was, we conducted a general linear model. When we conducted a mixed linear regression to determine dataaccuracy with these three variables we found only age and education to be statistically significant.</p> <p>The results in Figure 1 (attached) show dramatic differences between the rainfall distributions with the national climate stations alone and the distributions usingthe rainfall monitor and automatic gauge with the nationalgauge data. Especially important is that the annual and wet season rainfalls in the central portions of the study area are substantially higher (more than 300 and 400 mm for the wet season and annual rainfall) for the rainfall monitor and automatic gauge and with the national gauge data than for the national gauge data alone. The rainfall monitor with the national gauge data underestimate annual and wet season rainfall by 100 to 200 mm in thecentral portion of the watershed.</p> <p>The three sets of rainfall data used to generate the annual baseflow contribution maps simulated with a SWAT model are shown in Figure 2 (attached). As expected, since the rainfall in the central portion of thestudy area is higher for the rainfall monitor and automaticgauge with the national gauge data, the baseflow contribution rates are substantially higher than fo rbaseflow contribution rates simulated with the national gauge data alone. .As with the rainfall distributions, the simulated baseflow contribution for the rainfall monitor with the national gauge data is substantially lower than that determined forautomatic gauge with the national gauge data are minimal.</p> <p>Maps indicating the areas receiving PSH paymentswere obtained from the PSH program managers in thestudy area. The results indicate that, no matter what rainfall data set is used, the areas receiving payments have similar baseflow contributions to theaverage across the watersheds.To further assess the efficiency of the payments withrespect to capturing baseflow, the areas with the highest baseflow contributions were targeted to the same totalarea (3,990 ha) receiving payments. These results&nbsp; show that more than double the amountof baseflow can be captured if the targeting maximizes baseflow contribution. While using baseflow contributionas the single factor for targeting areas receiving paymentsis likely unrealistic or even undesirable, these results indicate that id baseflow conttirbuiton is considered as animportant hydrologic service, the efficiency of thepayments could be greatly improved.</p> <p>Citizen science data were shown to potentially contributing to more efficient targeting of land areas to be targeted for conservation efforts. This results is important because it shows that information from citizen scientists, which is practically free, can contribute to hydrologic understanding and make for better conservation policy.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/19/2019<br>      Modified by: Alex&nbsp;S&nbsp;Mayer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1644860/1644860_10447786_1555706943485_cbwm1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1644860/1644860_10447786_1555706943485_cbwm1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="cbwm1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1644860/1644860_10447786_1555706943485_cbwm1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="cbwm1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Rainfall distributions (in mm) obtained for annual, wet season (November 2017 - May 2018), and dry season (June - October 2017) from the national climate stations alone, the rainfall monitor data plus the national climate stations, and the automatic gauge data plus the national climate sta</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alex Mayer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alex&nbsp;S&nbsp;Mayer</div> <div class="imageTitle">cbwm1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1644860/1644860_10447786_1555707002753_cbwm2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1644860/1644860_10447786_1555707002753_cbwm2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="cbwm2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1644860/1644860_10447786_1555707002753_cbwm2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="cbwm2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. Annual baseflow contribution distributions (in mm) obtained from SWAT simulations with the national climate stations alone, the rainfall monitor data plus the national climate stations, and the automatic gauge data plus the national climate stations.  Gray overlay indicates the areas recei</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alex Mayer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alex&nbsp;S&nbsp;Mayer</div> <div class="imageTitle">cbwm2</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The QUIAHUA, M&eacute;xico, community based rainfallmonitoring project carried out in two catchments in theupper Antigua river watershed, central Veracruz, Mexico.The study area has experienced substantial deforestation of cloud forests in the last few decades. Low flows in the 1990s prompted local interest in potential impacts of land use change on hydrologic cycling. While efforts have been made to quantify the hydrological impacts associated withforest conversion in headwater catchments, for larger catchment scales these efforts have been hampered by the paucity of rainfall data. Citizen volunteers were recruited to measure daily rainfall using manual gaugesover an 18-month period. Automated tipping bucket gauges were installed to simultaneously measuredrainfall. Surveys and interviews of volunteers were conducted to understand motivations of CSH volunteersand whether the factors influencing motivations could be linked to measurement accuracy. Manual and automated data were compiled to compare measurement methods.Rainfall spatial distributions over the study area were interpolated with previously existing gauge data only and with the automated and manual rainfall data. The rainfallspatial distributions are used to drive a hydrologic model and estimate the corresponding distribution of rechargerates over the study area.  Examining data accuracy, we found that three monitors recorded rainfall with minor deviations from the tippingbucket data, i.e. 150 mm or less of difference on annualbasis. We found eight monitors recorded rainfall withsome deviations with the tipping bucket data, i.e. between 250 and 375 mm of difference. We found that fivemonitors recorded rainfall with major deviations from thetipping bucket data, i.e. 375 mm or more of difference.To understand what the major determinants of this error was, we conducted a general linear model. When we conducted a mixed linear regression to determine dataaccuracy with these three variables we found only age and education to be statistically significant.  The results in Figure 1 (attached) show dramatic differences between the rainfall distributions with the national climate stations alone and the distributions usingthe rainfall monitor and automatic gauge with the nationalgauge data. Especially important is that the annual and wet season rainfalls in the central portions of the study area are substantially higher (more than 300 and 400 mm for the wet season and annual rainfall) for the rainfall monitor and automatic gauge and with the national gauge data than for the national gauge data alone. The rainfall monitor with the national gauge data underestimate annual and wet season rainfall by 100 to 200 mm in thecentral portion of the watershed.  The three sets of rainfall data used to generate the annual baseflow contribution maps simulated with a SWAT model are shown in Figure 2 (attached). As expected, since the rainfall in the central portion of thestudy area is higher for the rainfall monitor and automaticgauge with the national gauge data, the baseflow contribution rates are substantially higher than fo rbaseflow contribution rates simulated with the national gauge data alone. .As with the rainfall distributions, the simulated baseflow contribution for the rainfall monitor with the national gauge data is substantially lower than that determined forautomatic gauge with the national gauge data are minimal.  Maps indicating the areas receiving PSH paymentswere obtained from the PSH program managers in thestudy area. The results indicate that, no matter what rainfall data set is used, the areas receiving payments have similar baseflow contributions to theaverage across the watersheds.To further assess the efficiency of the payments withrespect to capturing baseflow, the areas with the highest baseflow contributions were targeted to the same totalarea (3,990 ha) receiving payments. These results  show that more than double the amountof baseflow can be captured if the targeting maximizes baseflow contribution. While using baseflow contributionas the single factor for targeting areas receiving paymentsis likely unrealistic or even undesirable, these results indicate that id baseflow conttirbuiton is considered as animportant hydrologic service, the efficiency of thepayments could be greatly improved.  Citizen science data were shown to potentially contributing to more efficient targeting of land areas to be targeted for conservation efforts. This results is important because it shows that information from citizen scientists, which is practically free, can contribute to hydrologic understanding and make for better conservation policy.       Last Modified: 04/19/2019       Submitted by: Alex S Mayer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
