<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Tensor Regressions and Applications in Neuroimaging Data Analysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>85599.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>85599</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gabor Szekely</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gszekely@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Rapidly advancing medical imaging technologies are producing massive amounts of complex imaging data, and are imposing unprecedented demands for new statistical methodology. The investigators aim to integrate advanced statistical modeling with modern computational techniques to address some most challenging questions arising from medical imaging analysis. The investigators propose a novel statistical framework and develop accompanying theory and algorithms for tensor regression, i.e., regression with image covariates that are in the form of multidimensional arrays / tensors. They study a variety of regularization schemes in the context of tensor regression to stabilize estimation, improve risk property, and reconstruct sparse signals. They also develop methodology within the tensor regression framework for scientific applications including brain region and connectivity pattern identification, imaging based disease diagnosis, and multiple imaging modalities analysis. The project offers a systematic solution to a family of imaging data problems, and also provides a new class of statistical regression methods.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the most intriguing questions in modern science is to understand human brains, both those of general population and those with neuropsychiatric and neurodegenerative disorders. Advanced medical imaging technologies provide powerful tools to help address the question, producing imaging data of unprecedented size and complexity. The investigators aim to develop a host of novel statistical methods, theories, and highly scalable algorithms for the analysis of massive medical imaging data. The proposed research is expected to make significant contributions on two fronts: timely response to the growing needs and challenges of neuroimaging data analysis, and development of an utterly new and broad statistical framework and the associated methodology that contributes to the advance of the statistical discipline.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1645093</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hua</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hua Zhou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>huazhou@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3107947835</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000614866</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951772</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~47068</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~38531</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Traditional statistical regression analysis takes a vector of variables as predictors. Modern applications such as neuroimaing produce data that are in form of matrices or multi-dimensional arrays (tensors). In this project, we develop a fundamental framework for regression analysis of tensor type data. Our framework encompasses generalized linear model, supervised dimension reduction, generalized estimation equation, support vector machine, and so on. Our methods have been applied to neuroimaing data, longitudinal images, and genetics. We published 20+ peer-reviewed papers under this project. Some of them appeared in top statistical journals such as Journal of American Statistical Association and Journal of Royal Statistical Society Series B. We also released free software, the TensorReg Matlab toolbox, a comprehensive package including all solutions resulting from this proposal, so to provide analysts an easy access to the new methods.</p> <div class="page" title="Page 15"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>Supported by this project, the PIs started collaboration with the neuroscientists at North Carolina Biomedical Research Imaging Center on brain imaging methodological development and applications. The PIs also initiated collaborations with Center for Imaging of Neurodegenerative Diseases at University of California, San Francisco, and Stanford Vision Imaging Sciences and Technologies Lab. The resulting solutions are expected to have a direct impact on scientific development in brain imaging analysis.&nbsp;</span></p> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/05/2018<br>      Modified by: Hua&nbsp;Zhou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Traditional statistical regression analysis takes a vector of variables as predictors. Modern applications such as neuroimaing produce data that are in form of matrices or multi-dimensional arrays (tensors). In this project, we develop a fundamental framework for regression analysis of tensor type data. Our framework encompasses generalized linear model, supervised dimension reduction, generalized estimation equation, support vector machine, and so on. Our methods have been applied to neuroimaing data, longitudinal images, and genetics. We published 20+ peer-reviewed papers under this project. Some of them appeared in top statistical journals such as Journal of American Statistical Association and Journal of Royal Statistical Society Series B. We also released free software, the TensorReg Matlab toolbox, a comprehensive package including all solutions resulting from this proposal, so to provide analysts an easy access to the new methods.     Supported by this project, the PIs started collaboration with the neuroscientists at North Carolina Biomedical Research Imaging Center on brain imaging methodological development and applications. The PIs also initiated collaborations with Center for Imaging of Neurodegenerative Diseases at University of California, San Francisco, and Stanford Vision Imaging Sciences and Technologies Lab. The resulting solutions are expected to have a direct impact on scientific development in brain imaging analysis.           Last Modified: 07/05/2018       Submitted by: Hua Zhou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
