<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Validation and optimization of balance and gait assessment technology in order to identify fall-risk in older adults</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is the ability to quickly and easily identify fall-risk in an aging population. Falls are the leading cause of fatal and non-fatal injuries in older adults, resulting in loss of independence and financial burden (predicted to exceed $54 and $101 billion in 2020 and 2030). There is a critical need for a diagnostic and prognostic tool that can be utilized in large cohorts in a cost-effective manner. Identifying fall risk before a fall occurs is critical for timely deployment of preventive measures, but also so that limited resources can be allocated to those who are most likely to experience a fall. This, in turn, will ultimately reduce the number of falls, prolong independent living for the elderly population, and reduce healthcare costs. Following completion of the project, the device will be a commercially viable product which will lead to the growth and expansion of a start-up company. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will optimize and demonstrate the technical feasibility of an innovative balance and gait assessment device that provides a measure of fall-risk. Primary care physicians report that they do not have the knowledge and time to complete fall-risk assessments. Thus, this project will optimize and validate a fall-risk assessment device that can be easily implemented in multiple settings, including retirement communities, health clinics, and physician offices. The first objective of this project is to optimize and validate the balance assessment capabilities of the device, as the gait assessment capabilities have already been validated. The device will be compared concurrently with a device commonly used in research labs. The second objective is to validate the device with balance-compromised populations; as in the first objective, the device will be compared concurrently with a device commonly used in research labs. The third objective is to establish that the device provides a biomarker for age and disease by demonstrating that the balance and/or gait parameters are different across three groups (young adults, older adults, and people with Parkinson's disease).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1647752</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Babak</FirstName>
<LastName>Ziaie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Babak Ziaie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ziaiebabak@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654040726</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000724067</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/14/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/23/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Manuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Ochoa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Manuel Ochoa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>manny@smartgait.net</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5625462669</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000741302</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SmartGait LLC</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479065285</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654040726</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2620 Bristlecone Dr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079796646</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SMARTGAIT LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SmartGait LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479061074</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3495 Kent Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Falls in older adults are pervasive, adversely impact health, and serve as a leading cause of injury-related death in the U.S. Thus, it is important to identify and apply interventions to those at greatest risk of falling. SmartGait LLC seeks to solve this problem by providing a unique solution to assess balance and gait in an easy and inexpensive way. This is achieved via a wearable smartphone-based balance and gait assessment device (SmartGait&reg;) that can be operated by any caregiver to assess the balance and gait of their patients on a regular basis. The balance and gait assessment through SmartGait&reg; will alert users or caregivers of fall-risk and changing health, in order to take preventive action. SmartGait&reg; has strong potential as a diagnostic and prognostic tool that can be utilized in large cohorts in a cost-effective manner. Identifying fall risk before a fall occurs is critical for timely deployment of preventive measures, but also so that limited resources can be allocated to those who are most likely to experience a fall. This, in turn, will ultimately reduce the number of falls, prolong independent living for the elderly population, and reduce healthcare costs. This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project provided the opportunity to optimize and demonstrate the technical feasibility of SmartGait&reg;, with the long-term goal of commercialization of the device. In Phase I, SmartGait LLC accomplished the following objectives: (1) optimize and validate postural sway assessment capabilities of SmartGait&reg;, (2) validate the device with two balance-compromised populations, and (3) establish that SmartGait&reg; provides a biomarker for age and disease. Overall, we have demonstrated that the technology is valid and reasonably accurate, and it provides a biomarker for age and disease. Additionally, the NSF guided us to conduct over 65 interviews with potential customers as part of Beat-the-Odds-Bootcamp training (Washington, D.C.) and Introduction to Customer Discovery (at Purdue, Midwest I-Corps&trade; Node). These first-hand accounts from potential customers have helped evolve SmartGait&reg; into a balance and gait biometric device which focuses on fast (&lt;10 min) feedback with lab-scale precision. The project objectives have been successfully completed and the results are being used by SmartGait LLC to further develop the system into one that can have a strong social impact. The graduate students who contributed to this interdisciplinary project gained valuable knowledge in gait and balance biomechanics, fall-related biometrics, and wearable medical devices.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/11/2018<br>      Modified by: Manuel&nbsp;Ochoa</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Falls in older adults are pervasive, adversely impact health, and serve as a leading cause of injury-related death in the U.S. Thus, it is important to identify and apply interventions to those at greatest risk of falling. SmartGait LLC seeks to solve this problem by providing a unique solution to assess balance and gait in an easy and inexpensive way. This is achieved via a wearable smartphone-based balance and gait assessment device (SmartGait&reg;) that can be operated by any caregiver to assess the balance and gait of their patients on a regular basis. The balance and gait assessment through SmartGait&reg; will alert users or caregivers of fall-risk and changing health, in order to take preventive action. SmartGait&reg; has strong potential as a diagnostic and prognostic tool that can be utilized in large cohorts in a cost-effective manner. Identifying fall risk before a fall occurs is critical for timely deployment of preventive measures, but also so that limited resources can be allocated to those who are most likely to experience a fall. This, in turn, will ultimately reduce the number of falls, prolong independent living for the elderly population, and reduce healthcare costs. This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project provided the opportunity to optimize and demonstrate the technical feasibility of SmartGait&reg;, with the long-term goal of commercialization of the device. In Phase I, SmartGait LLC accomplished the following objectives: (1) optimize and validate postural sway assessment capabilities of SmartGait&reg;, (2) validate the device with two balance-compromised populations, and (3) establish that SmartGait&reg; provides a biomarker for age and disease. Overall, we have demonstrated that the technology is valid and reasonably accurate, and it provides a biomarker for age and disease. Additionally, the NSF guided us to conduct over 65 interviews with potential customers as part of Beat-the-Odds-Bootcamp training (Washington, D.C.) and Introduction to Customer Discovery (at Purdue, Midwest I-Corps&trade; Node). These first-hand accounts from potential customers have helped evolve SmartGait&reg; into a balance and gait biometric device which focuses on fast (&lt;10 min) feedback with lab-scale precision. The project objectives have been successfully completed and the results are being used by SmartGait LLC to further develop the system into one that can have a strong social impact. The graduate students who contributed to this interdisciplinary project gained valuable knowledge in gait and balance biomechanics, fall-related biometrics, and wearable medical devices.          Last Modified: 04/11/2018       Submitted by: Manuel Ochoa]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
