<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Improving Surface Properties of Stainless Steel for Li-ion Battery Current Collectors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>220014.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>220014</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Debasis Majumdar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dmajumda@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924709</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project intends to improve upon the surface characteristics of stainless steel in demanding environments. Particularly, it may constitute a significant improvement in the field of Li-ion battery current collectors. Today, current collector metal corrodes during repeated cycling leading to diminished capacity and potential safety issues related to cell polarization and over-potentials. This project will incorporate recent advances in nanomaterials and surface metrology into an engineering material with significant improvement in performance. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project lies in using a surface treatment to stainless steel that further modifies the oxide layer in terms of inertness, hydrophobicity, and corrosion resistance. This surface treatment is achieved by acid etching the steel surface after electropolishing in a manner similar to the industrially important pickling process. The resulting passive film will be characterized and prototype surface treated parts will be evaluated as current collectors for Li-ion batteries. These current collectors will not only improve corrosion resistance (and therefore cycling stability and cell safety), but will also allow use of a wider range of electrolytes than currently possible. Additionally, the project can lead to other applications where high performance stainless steel surfaces can be utilized.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1647045</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hector</FirstName>
<LastName>Macpherson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hector A Macpherson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alex@lupinelabs.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5033517442</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000723668</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lupine Laboratories LLC</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803012430</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4436231158</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3550 Frontier Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965571016</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LUPINE LABORATORIES LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FAST Ceramics LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803012430</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3550 Frontier Ave, Unit A]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~220014</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The surface properties of stainless steel can be improved so that the metal becomes much more corrosion resistant. This is done by cleaning foreign material embedded in the metal surface, which is conventionally known as passivation. It may also be done by anodization which is the controlled growth of the oxide layer that exists on the stainless steel surface that protects the underlying metal. However, anodization is not commonly considered possible for stainless steel. The research conducted here has combined these two processes into a single electrochemical surface treatment. This research has dissolved all surface accessible foreign material existing on the metal surface that may become a nucleation point for corrosion. It has also grown the oxide layer and enriched it in chromium, while keeping it compact. These attributes have allowed for the dramatic improvement of corrosion resistance in a simulated marine environment. The accompanying figure shows that this process creates a metal surface that is basically completely impervious to chemical reactions in saltwater at room temperature. That is, practically no electrical current is observed in corrosion testing (black line). Practically, this means that, when this process is applied to stainless steel it is altered to behave as though it is a much more expensive alloy. Additionally, the process created through this research is safe and earth-friendly.</p> <p>Given that stainless steel is one of the most ubiquitous engineering materials, this improvement may have a wide ranging and significant impact. This project initially proposed to address the lithium ion battery market. However, given feedback from potential customers, it now addresses desalination systems as the initial target market. This growth market uses a lot of stainless steel in warm and salty conditions which are very aggressive towards most metals. They are therefore very interested in our reported developments. More broadly, this surface treatment may become of utility to anyone using stainless steel and wanting to maximize its potential performance in an inexpensive way.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/02/2018<br>      Modified by: Hector&nbsp;A&nbsp;Macpherson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1647045/1647045_10467320_1520009025600_new_treatment_linear--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1647045/1647045_10467320_1520009025600_new_treatment_linear--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Surface Treatment Corrosion Testing"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1647045/1647045_10467320_1520009025600_new_treatment_linear--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Surface Treatment Corrosion Testing"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Corrosion testing indicating the result of the developed surface treatment compared to untreated metal (red) and a current state of the art method (blue).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alex Macpherson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hector&nbsp;A&nbsp;Macpherson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Surface Treatment Corrosion Testing</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The surface properties of stainless steel can be improved so that the metal becomes much more corrosion resistant. This is done by cleaning foreign material embedded in the metal surface, which is conventionally known as passivation. It may also be done by anodization which is the controlled growth of the oxide layer that exists on the stainless steel surface that protects the underlying metal. However, anodization is not commonly considered possible for stainless steel. The research conducted here has combined these two processes into a single electrochemical surface treatment. This research has dissolved all surface accessible foreign material existing on the metal surface that may become a nucleation point for corrosion. It has also grown the oxide layer and enriched it in chromium, while keeping it compact. These attributes have allowed for the dramatic improvement of corrosion resistance in a simulated marine environment. The accompanying figure shows that this process creates a metal surface that is basically completely impervious to chemical reactions in saltwater at room temperature. That is, practically no electrical current is observed in corrosion testing (black line). Practically, this means that, when this process is applied to stainless steel it is altered to behave as though it is a much more expensive alloy. Additionally, the process created through this research is safe and earth-friendly.  Given that stainless steel is one of the most ubiquitous engineering materials, this improvement may have a wide ranging and significant impact. This project initially proposed to address the lithium ion battery market. However, given feedback from potential customers, it now addresses desalination systems as the initial target market. This growth market uses a lot of stainless steel in warm and salty conditions which are very aggressive towards most metals. They are therefore very interested in our reported developments. More broadly, this surface treatment may become of utility to anyone using stainless steel and wanting to maximize its potential performance in an inexpensive way.             Last Modified: 03/02/2018       Submitted by: Hector A Macpherson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
