<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Being Black Isn't Enough - How Variation in Black Political Leadership affects Black Mass Political Behavior</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18240.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18240</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brian Humes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhumes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927284</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>General Abstract&lt;br/&gt;This project studies how the ways black politicians show their commitment to political problems in the black community.  In particular, it seeks to establish whether the choices in politicians' presentation of self can lead to changes in the behaviors and attitudes of black voters. Despite the well-established findings about representation and black political leadership, little has been done to investigate how black voters' perceptions of black politicians may change depending on the types of political messages adopted by these politicians. This study utilizes original experimental data to identify why some black politicians gain more support than others from black voters. The research is of particular importance because it allows us to assess the political responses of black voters as some black politicians become more professionalized and employ a greater variety of means to appeal to voters.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;This project's aim is to bridge the study of black political leadership with that of descriptive representation to identify the causal mechanisms that produce the particularly high levels of in-group candidate support generally observed among black Americans. It seeks to show when and how varying content of the messages of black political leaders might lead to variation in candidate support among black voters. This study employs two original experimental tests that enhance our understanding of how perceptions of a candidate's connection and commitment to political inclusion of the black community might lead to changes in mass political behavior among black voters. The experimental research design allows the PI to isolate the causal mechanism at work, thereby providing greater explanatory power about how differences within black political leadership and displays of community commitment can change the political behavior and attitudes of black voters.  Furthermore, it will also allow greater insight into how black representatives are evaluated by black constituents.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1647365</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Antoine</FirstName>
<LastName>Banks</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Antoine Banks</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>abanks12@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056269</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000637328</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julian</FirstName>
<LastName>Wamble</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julian Wamble</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jwamble@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014054557</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000725147</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>009Y</Code>
<Text>Political Science DDRIG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1371</Code>
<Text>POLITICAL SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~18240</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Using experimental methods, I examine whether a politician&rsquo;s signaling of community commitment affects how he is evaluated by black individuals. The two experiments changed the <em>kind</em> of community commitment signals black and white candidates use, and offers a better sense of how these differences in signaling influenced the how black respondents evaluated a candidate. The major finding from this dissertation is that when a candidate, regardless of his race, uses signal of physical sacrifice to show his social accountability to the racial group, he is seen as more trustworthy, genuine, helpful. Respondents are also more willing to support the candidate, and, in the case of the white candidate, more likely to believe that he can represent their interests. &nbsp;I theorize that this outcome is the result of the signals conveyance of a social accountability that has been proven by past actions. When the candidate referenced his physical sacrifice he did so by speaking about a sacrifice he had already made versus showing the potential to be held accountable. I contend that this is an important distinction that black voters consider when choosing candidates to support. Those who can show they have already done something to prove their accountability are more appealing than those who cannot make such a reference.</p> <p>&nbsp;While the effect of the physical sacrifice community commitment signal consistently led to higher evaluations for the candidate, there were some meaningful differences between how black and white candidates were evaluated by black individuals. Namely that when a black candidate referenced that his wife, Kyara, would hold him accountable to the racial group&rsquo;s political expectations, respondents believed him to be less trustworthy and less genuine. However, when a white candidate made the exact same reference to Kyara, black respondents gave higher evaluations that were, in the case of some outcomes, comparable to when he signaled physical sacrifice. This suggests that though some signals are effective for both black and white candidates, black voters do make distinctions based on the race of the candidate despite the use of the exact same signal.</p> <p>It is important to acknowledge that the size of the signals&rsquo; effect is not appear as large as expected, and that is due, in large part, to the fact that the experimental designs only changed one sentence in each of the treatments respondents were exposed to. In truth, given the conventional wisdom about black behavior and the literature on&nbsp; race&rsquo;s role in black political decision-making, we might not expect to see any effect. Moreover, given that the experimental designs control for race, gender, and party, all which are strong influencers of political behavior, any variation within the treatments speaks to how community commitment signaling impacts the way black voters view politicians.</p> <p>Past research has placed a strong focus on race&rsquo;s role in black politics without much engagement of the sophistication with which blacks are holding co-racial candidates accountable to the group&rsquo;s political goals. This dissertation&rsquo;s main contribution is the community commitment signaling framework, which argues that black voters want more than a candidate of similar skin tone, and are prefer candidates that are likely to be held accountable to the racial group. To meet these expectations, black politicians send community commitment signals of sacrifice and/or social connections to the black community to convey an accountability to the black community&rsquo;s norms and expectations. The political consequences of this framework are apparent in many electoral contexts, but most notably in circumstances where candidates&rsquo; race and/or partisan affiliation are held constant thus making other, simpler, signals insufficient to determine one&rsquo;s political choices.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/19/2018<br>      Modified by: Julian&nbsp;Wamble</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Using experimental methods, I examine whether a politician?s signaling of community commitment affects how he is evaluated by black individuals. The two experiments changed the kind of community commitment signals black and white candidates use, and offers a better sense of how these differences in signaling influenced the how black respondents evaluated a candidate. The major finding from this dissertation is that when a candidate, regardless of his race, uses signal of physical sacrifice to show his social accountability to the racial group, he is seen as more trustworthy, genuine, helpful. Respondents are also more willing to support the candidate, and, in the case of the white candidate, more likely to believe that he can represent their interests.  I theorize that this outcome is the result of the signals conveyance of a social accountability that has been proven by past actions. When the candidate referenced his physical sacrifice he did so by speaking about a sacrifice he had already made versus showing the potential to be held accountable. I contend that this is an important distinction that black voters consider when choosing candidates to support. Those who can show they have already done something to prove their accountability are more appealing than those who cannot make such a reference.   While the effect of the physical sacrifice community commitment signal consistently led to higher evaluations for the candidate, there were some meaningful differences between how black and white candidates were evaluated by black individuals. Namely that when a black candidate referenced that his wife, Kyara, would hold him accountable to the racial group?s political expectations, respondents believed him to be less trustworthy and less genuine. However, when a white candidate made the exact same reference to Kyara, black respondents gave higher evaluations that were, in the case of some outcomes, comparable to when he signaled physical sacrifice. This suggests that though some signals are effective for both black and white candidates, black voters do make distinctions based on the race of the candidate despite the use of the exact same signal.  It is important to acknowledge that the size of the signals? effect is not appear as large as expected, and that is due, in large part, to the fact that the experimental designs only changed one sentence in each of the treatments respondents were exposed to. In truth, given the conventional wisdom about black behavior and the literature on  race?s role in black political decision-making, we might not expect to see any effect. Moreover, given that the experimental designs control for race, gender, and party, all which are strong influencers of political behavior, any variation within the treatments speaks to how community commitment signaling impacts the way black voters view politicians.  Past research has placed a strong focus on race?s role in black politics without much engagement of the sophistication with which blacks are holding co-racial candidates accountable to the group?s political goals. This dissertation?s main contribution is the community commitment signaling framework, which argues that black voters want more than a candidate of similar skin tone, and are prefer candidates that are likely to be held accountable to the racial group. To meet these expectations, black politicians send community commitment signals of sacrifice and/or social connections to the black community to convey an accountability to the black community?s norms and expectations. The political consequences of this framework are apparent in many electoral contexts, but most notably in circumstances where candidates? race and/or partisan affiliation are held constant thus making other, simpler, signals insufficient to determine one?s political choices.             Last Modified: 06/19/2018       Submitted by: Julian Wamble]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
