<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>New CISE REU PI Resources</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>79499.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>79499</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Harriet Taylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds a new Directorate of Computer &amp; Information Science &amp; Engineering (CISE) special project at Iowa State University.  The project provides resources and services to the community of new investigators organizing CISE Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Sites at their universities. The team at Iowa State will work with other experienced CISE REU Site leaders to create the REU PI Guide, a set of web-based resources to help new CISE REU Site researchers prepare and run and effective and efficient REU Sites.  CISE REU Sites typically involve universities hosting a cohort of 8-10 undergraduate students from around the country for summer research in state-of-the art labs with faculty teams.  REU Sites often target students who do not have such research opportunities available to them at their home institutions.  This project will provide resources so that faculty can organize and run quality summer research experiences that will be of long-lasting benefit to undergraduates as they complete their degrees, pursue graduate school opportunities, or enter the computing workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team will undertake a series of five activities to implement their vision: assess needs, collect and refine resources, create video overviews, create and refine the REU PI Guide website, and evaluate the impact.  The project is led by a team that has significant experience in conducting a CISE REU Site as well as extensive interactions with the CISE REU Site PI community.  The team also has the design expertise and evaluation expertise needed to fully implement the REU PI Guide vision.  The team will consider all stakeholders including the faculty site leaders, the faculty project mentors, REU program coordinators, graduate student mentors, and the REU students and provide resources to meet all of their needs.  The resource should enhance the quality of undergraduate research experiences which are valuable components in the of preparation of undergraduates to become the computing professionals needed in the future.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1647742</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eliot</FirstName>
<LastName>Winer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eliot H Winer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ewiner@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5159891750</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000149354</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Gilbert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen Gilbert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gilbert@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152946782</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000504477</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ames</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[537 Bissell Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~79499</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="tinyMCEContent"> <p>This research sought to raise the overall quality of Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) site implementation by creating the <strong>REU PI Guide</strong>, a set of web-based resources developed to help new CISE REU site PIs prepare and run an effective REU site efficiently. A secondary goal was to aid non-CISE REU PIs as well.</p> <p>The resources were developed through a user-centered process of software&nbsp; development: we assessed users' needs, created online resources and then iteratively gathered feedback and refined them. Because the CISE community has a relatively close-knit network of experienced REU site PIs, as well as a new set of them that could benefit from the wisdom of experience each year, the goal was to harvest that wisdom and share it online.</p> <p>The research team (Stephen Gilbert, Jamie Payton, and Eliot Winer) gathered data from a new REU PI workshop held with 26 new REU PIs, interviews with six veteran REU PIs, and survey feedback from the 22 REU PIs who responded after 737 were surveyed.</p> <p>Graduate student Mariangeley Iglesias Pena used these data to create the REU PI Guide as part of her Masters thesis in Human Computer Interaction.&nbsp; Subsequently, after gathering feedback from users, graduate student Wonsil Jang redesigned the site.</p> <p>This online REU PI Guide is a well-designed representation of the best practices within CISE REU sites, and by creating it, other PIs can ensure that their REU sites achieve the high quality that these practices support, which in turn will mentor more students into CISE and STEM research careers.</p> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Stephen&nbsp;Gilbert</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553897845491_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.14.54PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553897845491_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.14.54PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU PI Guide: Homepage"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553897845491_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.14.54PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU PI Guide: Homepage"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This screenshot illustrates the homepage of the REU PI Guide.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Stephen Gilbert</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;Gilbert</div> <div class="imageTitle">REU PI Guide: Homepage</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898009467_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.07PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898009467_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.07PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU PI Guide: Calendar"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898009467_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.07PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU PI Guide: Calendar"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This screenshot shows the top of the REU PI Guide Calendar, which contains a list of activities that an REU PI should do throughout the year.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Stephen Gilbert</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;Gilbert</div> <div class="imageTitle">REU PI Guide: Calendar</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898121779_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.17PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898121779_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.17PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU PI Guide: Recruitment"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898121779_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.17PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU PI Guide: Recruitment"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This screenshot shows the top of the recruitment page, which has red anchor links to guidance on recruiting participants.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Stephen Gilbert</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;Gilbert</div> <div class="imageTitle">REU PI Guide: Recruitment</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898202309_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.25PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898202309_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.25PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU PI Guide: Logistics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898202309_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.25PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU PI Guide: Logistics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This screenshot shows the Logistics page, which has many anchor links to a variety of logistics concerns, ranging from food and housing to homesickness.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Stephen Gilbert</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;Gilbert</div> <div class="imageTitle">REU PI Guide: Logistics</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898319817_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.32PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898319817_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.32PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU PI Guide: Mentoring"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898319817_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.32PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU PI Guide: Mentoring"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This page on Mentoring resources illustrates the focus both on mentoring undergraduates on what research is and on mentoring graduate students and faculty on how to work with undergraduates.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Stephen Gilbert</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;Gilbert</div> <div class="imageTitle">REU PI Guide: Mentoring</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898470292_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.46PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898470292_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.46PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU PI Guide: Dissemination"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1647742/1647742_10450023_1553898470292_ScreenShot2019-03-29at5.15.46PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU PI Guide: Dissemination"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This screenshot of the Dissemination page illustrates an REU site's focus on teaching undergraduates how to write up and present research. Also, this screenshot features a "Pro Tip," which appear on every page of the REU PI Guide. These Pro Tips have been complimented in particular by PIs.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Stephen Gilbert</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;Gilbert</div> <div class="imageTitle">REU PI Guide: Dissemination</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This research sought to raise the overall quality of Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) site implementation by creating the REU PI Guide, a set of web-based resources developed to help new CISE REU site PIs prepare and run an effective REU site efficiently. A secondary goal was to aid non-CISE REU PIs as well.  The resources were developed through a user-centered process of software  development: we assessed users' needs, created online resources and then iteratively gathered feedback and refined them. Because the CISE community has a relatively close-knit network of experienced REU site PIs, as well as a new set of them that could benefit from the wisdom of experience each year, the goal was to harvest that wisdom and share it online.  The research team (Stephen Gilbert, Jamie Payton, and Eliot Winer) gathered data from a new REU PI workshop held with 26 new REU PIs, interviews with six veteran REU PIs, and survey feedback from the 22 REU PIs who responded after 737 were surveyed.  Graduate student Mariangeley Iglesias Pena used these data to create the REU PI Guide as part of her Masters thesis in Human Computer Interaction.  Subsequently, after gathering feedback from users, graduate student Wonsil Jang redesigned the site.  This online REU PI Guide is a well-designed representation of the best practices within CISE REU sites, and by creating it, other PIs can ensure that their REU sites achieve the high quality that these practices support, which in turn will mentor more students into CISE and STEM research careers.        Last Modified: 03/29/2019       Submitted by: Stephen Gilbert]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
