<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Hyper-Personalized Clinical Evidence-based Blood Transfusion Decision Support Tool to Drive Value-Based Care</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224414.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224414</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop a hyper-personalized, clinical, and evidence-based blood transfusion decision support tool to reduce unnecessary transfusions, transfusion-related complications, and transfusion related expenditures. Blood transfusions are the most commonly prescribed medical procedure in the US, and cost our healthcare system $30 billion annually. The cost of unnecessary transfusions is estimated at no less than $15 billion each year. These figures double when including the cost of treating transfusion-related complications. In the era of evidence-based medicine, transfusion practices remain highly subjective with significant clinical variation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project aims to address a critical un-met need in the hospitals related to blood transfusion by developing a comprehensive clinical evidence-driven decision support system that would empower the physician with a near real-time laboratory, clinical, diagnostic and prognostic information, integrated within a usable interface. The long-term goal of the project is to minimize the incidence of unnecessary blood transfusions to improve patient outcomes and reduce healthcare expenditures. The goal of this project is to develop a comprehensive patient blood-management suite of tools that can be implemented across all clinical fields and can be easily deployed in most any hospital. &lt;br/&gt;The following specific aims will be pursued: a) To develop and implement scalable HIPAA-compliant methodologies for the extraction, storage, and management of blood transfusion-related data from electronic medical record systems; and b) to derive patient-centered algorithms to create clinical decision support tools for the electronic medical record system and drive hyper-personalized blood transfusion practice.&lt;br/&gt;Successful completion of the proposed work may revolutionize the way physicians approach the decision to order a blood transfusion and ultimately change and eliminate the culture of over-transfusion. Subsequent widespread implementation throughout the US could save thousands of lives each year, on par with the goals of the Institute of Medicine?s initiative to reduce inappropriate antibiotic prescribing and medication related adverse drug events.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1648233</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Ereth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark Ereth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mark@aprihealth.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5072541425</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000725840</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/14/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Apri Health</Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<ZipCode>559023125</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5072541425</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>221 First Ave SW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 202]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079317296</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>APRIHEALTH, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regional One Health]]></Name>
<CityName>Memphis</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>381032807</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[877 Jefferson Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~224414</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Executive Summary: </span></p> <p>Our Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project was aimed at developing a HIPAA-compliant clinical decision support tool for blood transfusions using laboratory, clinical, diagnostic, and prognostic information to be deployed at the point-of-care in hospitals. Through the research and development performed by Apri Health during this period of Phase I funding, we have validated our business model hypothesis, built the framework for our minimum viable product, completed pilot studies, and are refining our product and our business model to commercialize our blood transfusion decision support tool.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Working Hypothesis:</span></p> <p>There is a conspicuous void of an accurate, objective, data-driven decision support tool to intervene the widespread culture of over-transfusion in clinical practices across the country. Hospitals would be interested in seeking solutions to address these unnecessary transfusions that would result in annual savings of as much as $1-2 million per hospital in direct product costs and as much as $15 billion each year for United States. Additionally, the fact that our solution would enable reducing complications, improve clinical outcomes, reduce length of stay and increase overall value in healthcare delivery.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Progress and Outcome:</span></p> <p>Since January 2017, our team had pursued research and development of a hyper-personalized tool to drive a data- and evidence-driven blood transfusion decision support tool in three different areas:</p> <p><em>Market Research/Validation</em>: To confirm our hypothesis on the current culture of over-transfusion, absence of a data-driven practice, and of an existing unmet need to improve blood transfusion decisions in hospitals, we employed the Lean Startup methodology and performed customer discovery interviews with over 50 thought leaders, surgeons, clinicians and potential users/customers in approximately 30 health systems around the country. Based on these interviews, we have revised our Business Model, identified the critical gap in blood transfusion decision making, and the requirements for an optimal tool to address this challenge. Furthermore, we have optimized our tool, are now aware of the value chain for potential sales in hospitals, and have defined our go-to-market strategy</p> <p><em>Product Development:</em> During the Phase I of our grant, our research team, comprising of a data scientist, a software engineer, a Transfusion-trained Pathologist, an Anesthesiologist, and a Surgeon, were focused on developing a minimum viable product for the hyper-personalized blood transfusion decision support tool by our core research team.&nbsp; Having recognized that technological competency varied among healthcare delivery systems around the country, we partnered with two different healthcare providers:</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; a large academic medical center housing an integrated electronic medical record system with robust technological resources and support;</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; a medium-sized community hospital with minimal technological resources including disparate recording systems for clinical, laboratory and diagnostic information for their patients.</p> <p>To date, we have successfully extracted and aggregated the different data sets from each of these provider groups to develop our blood transfusion decision support tool. In addition, we have created a template dashboard (based on our market research summary) with capability of benchmarking transfusion practices over different service lines for our hospital clients viz. a viz. regional and national average, established clinical guidelines, and for the appropriate clinical conditions (surgical procedure, patient co-morbidities, etc.). We are focusing on identifying the best form factor for deploying this tool at our partner hospitals to mitigate risks related to storage, accessibility of confidential clinical information, and for delivering actionable real-time intelligence in the future.</p> <p><em>Commercialization Strategy:</em> Concurrently, our business development team, comprising of the Project Manager and Principal Investigator, have initiated discussions with potential partners to help scale and deploy this technology in hospitals around the country. Our go-to-market strategy would be driven, in part, by our two strategic partners, namely a leading solution provider for hospital supply chain and a leading clinical and diagnostic laboratory. Based on these discussions with our partners, potential clients and our customers, we have identified that our initial product-build would be focused on blood transfusion decision support for anemia management, cardiac surgery and sepsis, considered by Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality&rsquo;s Healthcare Cost and Utilization Projects as conditions responsible for increased duration and cost of hospitalization stays.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conclusion:</span></p> <p>In summary, the Phase I SBIR grant was pivotal in validating the urgent need of blood transfusion decision support tools at point-of-care in hospitals to reduce inappropriate transfusions, lower patient complications and thereby costs of care, and to further augment value in delivery of patient care. Additionally, our research and development performed during this phase of funding has resulted in development of a framework toward the clinical decision support tool that enables visualization of a hospital&rsquo;s current blood transfusion practice, and opportunities for improvement. Our subsequent research would be focused on deployment of predictive analytics and integration of actionable intelligence within this decision support dashboard to drive a true hyper-personalized blood transfusion practice.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/29/2018<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;Ereth</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Executive Summary:   Our Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project was aimed at developing a HIPAA-compliant clinical decision support tool for blood transfusions using laboratory, clinical, diagnostic, and prognostic information to be deployed at the point-of-care in hospitals. Through the research and development performed by Apri Health during this period of Phase I funding, we have validated our business model hypothesis, built the framework for our minimum viable product, completed pilot studies, and are refining our product and our business model to commercialize our blood transfusion decision support tool.  Working Hypothesis:  There is a conspicuous void of an accurate, objective, data-driven decision support tool to intervene the widespread culture of over-transfusion in clinical practices across the country. Hospitals would be interested in seeking solutions to address these unnecessary transfusions that would result in annual savings of as much as $1-2 million per hospital in direct product costs and as much as $15 billion each year for United States. Additionally, the fact that our solution would enable reducing complications, improve clinical outcomes, reduce length of stay and increase overall value in healthcare delivery.  Progress and Outcome:  Since January 2017, our team had pursued research and development of a hyper-personalized tool to drive a data- and evidence-driven blood transfusion decision support tool in three different areas:  Market Research/Validation: To confirm our hypothesis on the current culture of over-transfusion, absence of a data-driven practice, and of an existing unmet need to improve blood transfusion decisions in hospitals, we employed the Lean Startup methodology and performed customer discovery interviews with over 50 thought leaders, surgeons, clinicians and potential users/customers in approximately 30 health systems around the country. Based on these interviews, we have revised our Business Model, identified the critical gap in blood transfusion decision making, and the requirements for an optimal tool to address this challenge. Furthermore, we have optimized our tool, are now aware of the value chain for potential sales in hospitals, and have defined our go-to-market strategy  Product Development: During the Phase I of our grant, our research team, comprising of a data scientist, a software engineer, a Transfusion-trained Pathologist, an Anesthesiologist, and a Surgeon, were focused on developing a minimum viable product for the hyper-personalized blood transfusion decision support tool by our core research team.  Having recognized that technological competency varied among healthcare delivery systems around the country, we partnered with two different healthcare providers:  1)     a large academic medical center housing an integrated electronic medical record system with robust technological resources and support;  2)     a medium-sized community hospital with minimal technological resources including disparate recording systems for clinical, laboratory and diagnostic information for their patients.  To date, we have successfully extracted and aggregated the different data sets from each of these provider groups to develop our blood transfusion decision support tool. In addition, we have created a template dashboard (based on our market research summary) with capability of benchmarking transfusion practices over different service lines for our hospital clients viz. a viz. regional and national average, established clinical guidelines, and for the appropriate clinical conditions (surgical procedure, patient co-morbidities, etc.). We are focusing on identifying the best form factor for deploying this tool at our partner hospitals to mitigate risks related to storage, accessibility of confidential clinical information, and for delivering actionable real-time intelligence in the future.  Commercialization Strategy: Concurrently, our business development team, comprising of the Project Manager and Principal Investigator, have initiated discussions with potential partners to help scale and deploy this technology in hospitals around the country. Our go-to-market strategy would be driven, in part, by our two strategic partners, namely a leading solution provider for hospital supply chain and a leading clinical and diagnostic laboratory. Based on these discussions with our partners, potential clients and our customers, we have identified that our initial product-build would be focused on blood transfusion decision support for anemia management, cardiac surgery and sepsis, considered by Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality?s Healthcare Cost and Utilization Projects as conditions responsible for increased duration and cost of hospitalization stays.  Conclusion:  In summary, the Phase I SBIR grant was pivotal in validating the urgent need of blood transfusion decision support tools at point-of-care in hospitals to reduce inappropriate transfusions, lower patient complications and thereby costs of care, and to further augment value in delivery of patient care. Additionally, our research and development performed during this phase of funding has resulted in development of a framework toward the clinical decision support tool that enables visualization of a hospital?s current blood transfusion practice, and opportunities for improvement. Our subsequent research would be focused on deployment of predictive analytics and integration of actionable intelligence within this decision support dashboard to drive a true hyper-personalized blood transfusion practice.          Last Modified: 01/29/2018       Submitted by: Mark Ereth]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
