<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Development and Validation of the SafeClose Mesh Augmentation System for Hernia Prevention</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This STTR Phase I project looks to create a solution to the vast problem that hernia has become in the United States by developing a system that prevents hernia before it occurs. There are an estimated 300,000 hernia repairs performed each year in the US. Incisional hernia (IH) occurs in up to 70% in high-risk populations. The hernia epidemic is significant and is linked to reduced quality of life and $3.2 billion/year in healthcare expenditures for hernia repair. IH can be prevented using prophylactic mesh, which involves placement of tensioned mesh to reinforce abdominal fascia closures before herniation occurs. Prophylactic mesh has been shown to reduce the risk of IH from 35.9% to 1.5%. However, although prophylactic mesh produces outstanding results, it has not become widely adopted in part due to the technical challenge that the procedure poses and added operative time. This project aims to create a system that makes the prophylactic mesh procedure simpler, more reliable, and faster. This project offers an efficient solution to the hernia epidemic by addressing key surgeon-level barriers to adoption of prophylactic mesh and therefore will foster more widespread use of the procedure. Broader use of hernia prevention will improve outcomes, quality of life, and reduce the costs associated with IH.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project proposes the development of a hand-held system that simplifies and reduces the time to perform prophylactic mesh augmentation by integrating multiple discrete operative tasks including locating, tensioning, and affixing mesh onto the abdominal fascia. The system provides an optimized strategy for prophylactic mesh placement by leveraging biomechanical principles of both the abdominal wall and mesh to provide a quick, standardized, and reliable method to strengthen abdominal incisions and as a result minimize the risk of herniation. The system is comprised of three main components: the applicator, the fastener-anchor, and the mesh itself. The fastener-anchor represents a core functionality of the technology while serving two purposes: (1.) interaction/engagement and subsequent tension-setting of the mesh via the applicator system; and (2.) penetration of the fascia and affixation of the mesh onto the fascia. The applicator is a simple, ergonomic tool that interfaces with the fastener-anchors, allowing the surgeon to control the spatial position, tension, and placement of the mesh. This project aims to accomplish two main goals: (1.) to refine the device design, including achieving optimal security and reliability of engagement between the applicator and the fastener-anchors and (2.) to assess the biomechanical strength and speed of the proposed technology compared to current standards of care. Through iterative device prototyping, testing, and refinement, a fully functional device will be developed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/17/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1648854</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Fischer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Fischer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>john.fischer2@uphs.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2156626156</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000713314</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marc-Alan</FirstName>
<LastName>Levine</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marc-Alan Levine</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marcalan1294@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2156626156</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000713315</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/17/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rex</FirstName>
<LastName>Peters</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rex Peters</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>compass1@pipeline.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000744321</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/17/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Paradigm Surgical LLC</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191462701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2156626156</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3401 Grays Ferry Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Bldg 212-113]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079540864</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PARADIGM SURGICAL LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191045127</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3400 Civic Center Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Incisional hernia (IH) can be prevented using prophylactic mesh placement (PMP), a procedure in which elastic mesh is affixed onto the abdominal wall so that it can shield the fascia from excessive tension and as a result minimize the chance for hernia formation. Despite the benefits of the PMP procedure, there are many barriers to adoption that prevent many surgeons from conducting the procedure. The SafeClose Mesh Augmentation system addresses these issues by simplifying the technical challenges and minimizing the added time associated with PMP. By integrating several key steps of the PMP procedure including positioning, tensioning, and affixation, into one system, the SafeClose is able to easily, quickly, and effectively affix mesh onto abdominal fascia.</p> <p>The goals of this Phase I grant study were to develop multiple functional prototypes of the SafeClose technology (mechanical fascial reinforcement with mesh), bench test them, and iteratively mature the design until a device that optimally fulfilled all of the design requirements was produced. This optimized functional prototype would then be tested in a study using senior surgical residents to comparatively evaluate the biomechanical properties and the time-savings achieved with the optimized SafeClose device against the current standard-of-care (hand-sewing the mesh onto the fascia), and assess factors relating to clinical feasibility and adoptability.</p> <p>Over the course of the grant period six functional prototypes were developed, bench tested, studied and sequentially improved. The sixth and final system developed was comparatively tested in a clinical setting by nine surgical residents for time efficiency, procedural complexity (hand movements), biomechanical factors (load strength, closure stiffness) and placement uniformity.&nbsp; These tests yielded positive results, demonstrating statistically significant improvement over current standard-of-care (hand sewn mesh augmentation).&nbsp; A quick summary of the results showed:</p> <ul> <li>The SafeClose system performed thirteen times quicker,&nbsp; (<strong>Figure 6)</strong></li> <li>Required twenty-four times fewer hand movements than the hand-sewn technique. (<strong>Figures 7,8</strong>)</li> <li>SafeClose mediated closures were also able to withstand about 12% more tensile load on average than a hand-sewn closure, (<strong>Figure 10</strong>)</li> <li>While increasing the stiffness of the fascial closure. (<strong>Figure 11</strong>)</li> <li>Mesh placed by the SafeClose system was visibly more uniform and smoother (&nbsp;<strong>Figure 9</strong>).</li> </ul> <p>These results indicate that SafeClose device-mediated mesh placement is efficient, reliable, more uniform, and associated with better biomechanical characteristics than hand-sewn mesh techniques while requiring much less time and fewer operative maneuvers.&nbsp;</p> <p>User feedback further indicated that there is a need in the market for this technology- in post-op questionnaires each of our 9 participants said that they were either "Likely" or "Very Likely" to use the SafeClose system in practice if it goes to market.</p> <p>The system achieved the goals of reducing barriers to adoption for prophylactic mesh placement.&nbsp; These included reduced procedure time, procedure complexity, and improvement of closure strength in the hands of surgical residents rather than reconstructive surgeons.&nbsp; This represents a solid proof-of-principle with promising implications for clinical feasibility and adoptability. Further study will be undertaken to demonstrate additional progress in achieving these goals, undertaking formal development and commercialization.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/18/2019<br>      Modified by: Rex&nbsp;Peters</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597507478_Figure_6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597507478_Figure_6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Time Efficeincy Data"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597507478_Figure_6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Time Efficeincy Data"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This Figure shows how much time was saved using the Omega Device compared to the hand-sewn technique.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonathan Sanchez</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rex&nbsp;Peters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Time Efficeincy Data</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597596342_Figure_7--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597596342_Figure_7--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Average Number of Hand Movements"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597596342_Figure_7--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Average Number of Hand Movements"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This figure shows the average number of hand movements required to use the Omega device as compared to the hand-sewn technique.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonathan Sanchez</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rex&nbsp;Peters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Average Number of Hand Movements</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597704431_Figure_8--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597704431_Figure_8--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hand-Sewn vs. Omega"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597704431_Figure_8--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hand-Sewn vs. Omega"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Comparison of number of hand motions between device mediated and hand-sewn group. Each dot represents a movement of the hand.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonathan Sanchez</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rex&nbsp;Peters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hand-Sewn vs. Omega</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597803561_Figure_10--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597803561_Figure_10--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Biomechanical Data - Load Strength"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597803561_Figure_10--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Biomechanical Data - Load Strength"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This figure shows the biomechanical performance of a device-mediated closure compared to hand-sewn closure and suture-only closure.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonathan Sanchez</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rex&nbsp;Peters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Biomechanical Data - Load Strength</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597907377_Figure_11--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597907377_Figure_11--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Biomechanical Data - Stiffness"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597907377_Figure_11--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Biomechanical Data - Stiffness"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This figure shows the stiffness data comparing device-mediated closures with hand-sewn and suture-only closures.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonathan Sanchez</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rex&nbsp;Peters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Biomechanical Data - Stiffness</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597997354_Figure_9--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597997354_Figure_9--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hand-Sewn vs. Omega - Mesh Placement"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1648854/1648854_10467693_1555597997354_Figure_9--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hand-Sewn vs. Omega - Mesh Placement"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a.) Hand-sewn mesh, non-uniform and wrinkled, (b.) Omega placed mesh, much more uniform and nearly no wrinkles.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonathan Sanchez</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rex&nbsp;Peters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hand-Sewn vs. Omega - Mesh Placement</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Incisional hernia (IH) can be prevented using prophylactic mesh placement (PMP), a procedure in which elastic mesh is affixed onto the abdominal wall so that it can shield the fascia from excessive tension and as a result minimize the chance for hernia formation. Despite the benefits of the PMP procedure, there are many barriers to adoption that prevent many surgeons from conducting the procedure. The SafeClose Mesh Augmentation system addresses these issues by simplifying the technical challenges and minimizing the added time associated with PMP. By integrating several key steps of the PMP procedure including positioning, tensioning, and affixation, into one system, the SafeClose is able to easily, quickly, and effectively affix mesh onto abdominal fascia.  The goals of this Phase I grant study were to develop multiple functional prototypes of the SafeClose technology (mechanical fascial reinforcement with mesh), bench test them, and iteratively mature the design until a device that optimally fulfilled all of the design requirements was produced. This optimized functional prototype would then be tested in a study using senior surgical residents to comparatively evaluate the biomechanical properties and the time-savings achieved with the optimized SafeClose device against the current standard-of-care (hand-sewing the mesh onto the fascia), and assess factors relating to clinical feasibility and adoptability.  Over the course of the grant period six functional prototypes were developed, bench tested, studied and sequentially improved. The sixth and final system developed was comparatively tested in a clinical setting by nine surgical residents for time efficiency, procedural complexity (hand movements), biomechanical factors (load strength, closure stiffness) and placement uniformity.  These tests yielded positive results, demonstrating statistically significant improvement over current standard-of-care (hand sewn mesh augmentation).  A quick summary of the results showed:  The SafeClose system performed thirteen times quicker,  (Figure 6) Required twenty-four times fewer hand movements than the hand-sewn technique. (Figures 7,8) SafeClose mediated closures were also able to withstand about 12% more tensile load on average than a hand-sewn closure, (Figure 10) While increasing the stiffness of the fascial closure. (Figure 11) Mesh placed by the SafeClose system was visibly more uniform and smoother ( Figure 9).   These results indicate that SafeClose device-mediated mesh placement is efficient, reliable, more uniform, and associated with better biomechanical characteristics than hand-sewn mesh techniques while requiring much less time and fewer operative maneuvers.   User feedback further indicated that there is a need in the market for this technology- in post-op questionnaires each of our 9 participants said that they were either "Likely" or "Very Likely" to use the SafeClose system in practice if it goes to market.  The system achieved the goals of reducing barriers to adoption for prophylactic mesh placement.  These included reduced procedure time, procedure complexity, and improvement of closure strength in the hands of surgical residents rather than reconstructive surgeons.  This represents a solid proof-of-principle with promising implications for clinical feasibility and adoptability. Further study will be undertaken to demonstrate additional progress in achieving these goals, undertaking formal development and commercialization.       Last Modified: 04/18/2019       Submitted by: Rex Peters]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
