<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Painting and Overspray Capture System</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project focused on an automated painting and overspray capture system is a significant increase in the health/safety of construction workers and profitability/production efficiency of the construction industry. Painting workers suffer from increased short and long term health problems due to exposure to paint fumes, including increased potential for certain cancers and cognitive damage. Construction projects are delayed due to injuries, lack of available skilled labor, and prohibitive costs. A system that can eliminate major health and safety risks by capturing harmful fumes as well as increase productivity by autonomously working alongside skilled workers will have a significant positive impact on the construction industry and workers. This innovation could open the construction industry up to myriads of intelligent, autonomous solutions that improve health, safety, quality, and production.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will work to establishing the technical and commercial feasibility of an automated system to paint and capture overspray. The SBIR project will focus on the device responsible for directing paint from the spraying apparatus to the surface to be painted and containment of overspray and harmful volatile organic compounds (VOCs). The health hazards of paint fumes and airborne VOCs are apparent through the increased risk of certain cancers and long-term cognitive damage suffered by painters. Additionally, painting at heights on ladders or other lift equipment presents a safety and efficiency problem. The research objectives of this SBIR are to develop a system that can effectively contain overspray/paint fumes while being small/lightweight enough for use by a robotic platform. Extensive flow analysis will be conducted with experimental geometry and flow visualization techniques on benchtop test rigs to evaluate geometry and flow characteristics. Successful benchtop test designs will be further tested on a robotic platform to evaluate system-level performance for paint quality, over spray containment, and airborne VOCs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1648288</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sreenivas</FirstName>
<LastName>Raman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sreenivas Raman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sid@ice-aec.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9734505161</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000697122</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Integrated Construction Ent., Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Belleville</CityName>
<ZipCode>071093217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9734505161</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>259 Stephens Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>782975247</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INTEGRATED CONSTRUCTION ENTERPRISES INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Integrated Construction Ent., Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>071093217</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6840</Code>
<Text>ROBOTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~224999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The original objective of research for Phase 1 was to design and demonstrate a shroud mechanism for a robotic painting system to increase paint transfer and reduce paint overspray byproducts into the environment.&nbsp; Industry-accepted metrics put losses of paint by a human painter in excess of 40%.&nbsp; Increasing the transfer efficiency of sprayed paint onto a surface therefore is highly desirable.&nbsp; The shroud was designed to increase the paint transfer rate to 90%, an increase of 30% when compared to manual spraying.</p> <p>Over the course of the research, it was determined the shroud provided negligible benefits largely due to the efficiency of the robotic painting system itself.&nbsp; With the inherent overspray reduction afforded by the consistency of the robot, a shroud would not be necessary to achieve these objectives.<br /> <br /> With the NSF Program Director&rsquo;s support, the focus of Phase 1 was shifted to investigate navigation and position sensing of the robotic painting system.&nbsp; Several navigation technologies and techniques were investigated focusing on ease of setup, reliability, and performance.&nbsp; Techniques including; dead reckoning, wheel encoder-based correction, fiducial tracking-based correction, and fiducial tracking with encoder bias correction were investigated.&nbsp; In addition, optical tape line-following, and absolute positioning sensor system (ABSS, indoor GPS) were explored, along with laser line-following, and sensorial navigation (ultrasonics, proximity, and LiDAR) which showed the most promise. &nbsp;</p> <p>The path forward is to take what was learned during the Phase 1 process and incorporate into a commercially viable product.&nbsp; Working with our business partner (Graco), ICE will continue to develop and refine this robotic painting system.&nbsp; Benefits to the user are numerous; faster applications, significantly less over-spray, higher rates of paint transfer, lower application costs, and little to no exposure to spray byproducts to the painter.&nbsp; The ultimate goal is to develop this platform into an autonomous robotic painting tool which will free up a painter to work on other parts of the project. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/12/2018<br>      Modified by: Sreenivas&nbsp;Raman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The original objective of research for Phase 1 was to design and demonstrate a shroud mechanism for a robotic painting system to increase paint transfer and reduce paint overspray byproducts into the environment.  Industry-accepted metrics put losses of paint by a human painter in excess of 40%.  Increasing the transfer efficiency of sprayed paint onto a surface therefore is highly desirable.  The shroud was designed to increase the paint transfer rate to 90%, an increase of 30% when compared to manual spraying.  Over the course of the research, it was determined the shroud provided negligible benefits largely due to the efficiency of the robotic painting system itself.  With the inherent overspray reduction afforded by the consistency of the robot, a shroud would not be necessary to achieve these objectives.    With the NSF Program Director?s support, the focus of Phase 1 was shifted to investigate navigation and position sensing of the robotic painting system.  Several navigation technologies and techniques were investigated focusing on ease of setup, reliability, and performance.  Techniques including; dead reckoning, wheel encoder-based correction, fiducial tracking-based correction, and fiducial tracking with encoder bias correction were investigated.  In addition, optical tape line-following, and absolute positioning sensor system (ABSS, indoor GPS) were explored, along with laser line-following, and sensorial navigation (ultrasonics, proximity, and LiDAR) which showed the most promise.    The path forward is to take what was learned during the Phase 1 process and incorporate into a commercially viable product.  Working with our business partner (Graco), ICE will continue to develop and refine this robotic painting system.  Benefits to the user are numerous; faster applications, significantly less over-spray, higher rates of paint transfer, lower application costs, and little to no exposure to spray byproducts to the painter.  The ultimate goal is to develop this platform into an autonomous robotic painting tool which will free up a painter to work on other parts of the project.                    Last Modified: 04/12/2018       Submitted by: Sreenivas Raman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
