<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Nondestructive high-resolution measurement of semiconductor carrier density</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224543.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224543</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer Phase I project will develop advanced tools for semiconductor metrology that are essential for high accuracy at finer resolution as progress continues to the finer lithography nodes. This progress is essential to satisfy the demand for greater performance in numerous consumer products as well as many other applications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project lies in a newly-discovered optoelectronic effect which will provide much finer resolution in measuring the local density of the charge carriers in semiconductors, and this new method shows promise for achieving sub-nanometer resolution. Roadmaps for the semiconductor industry call for finer resolution, and this project is responding to specific needs outlined therein.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/13/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1648811</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Hagmann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark J Hagmann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mhagmann@newpathresearch.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015739853</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000212919</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NewPath Research L.L.C.</Name>
<CityName>Salt Lake City</CityName>
<ZipCode>841153552</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015739853</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2880 S. Main Street, Suite 214</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>623793614</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEWPATH RESEARCH LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Center for Integrated Nanotechnologies]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Alamos</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871851315</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[MPA-CINT, MS K771, LANL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~224543</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Background:</strong>&nbsp;In measurements at Los Alamos National Laboratory the PI previously discovered that a mode-locked laser superimposes a microwave frequency comb (MFC) on the DC tunneling current in a Scanning Tunneling Microscope (STM). The MFC has hundreds of harmonics at integer multiples of the laser pulse repetition frequency, each setting the present state-of-the-art for a narrow-linewidth microwave source [1]. &nbsp;Figure 1 shows the power of the 200<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;harmonic at 14.85 GHz as a function of the offset from the peak in Hz.&nbsp; Note that the 3-dB linewidth is 1 Hz. Initially we used metal samples in the STM, but later we measured the harmonics with intrinsic gallium nitride (GaN) [2].&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Results at the Research Institution:</strong></p> <p>1. Scanning Electron Microscope images show tip-crash is common using intrinsic GaN as the sample, but is rare with metal samples.&nbsp;</p> <p>2. With metal samples, the MFC is measured with a Bias-T in the tip circuit of the STM, but with a semiconductor a fine wire must be used as a surface probe within 0.1 mm of the STM tip. The MFC was seldomly seen with the semiconductors and the surface probe prevents the possibility of making scanned measurements.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Results at NewPath Research:&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>1. Detailed numerical models simulating an STM with a resistive sample showed that much lower tunneling currents, with greater tip-sample distances that would cause images to have less clarity, are necessary to avoid tip-crash with a resistive sample such as a semiconductor in an STM [See Fig. 2].&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>2. Detailed numerical modeling and measurements with our in-house STM showed that the "integral" function in conventional proportion + integral (PI) feedback control potentiates tip-crash.&nbsp;This is the method used in the STM at Los Alamos. We invented a new method for feedback control that is simpler to use and provides greater stability [3].&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>3. We developed a LabVIEW virtual instrument (VI) simulating the full operation of a scanning tunneling microscope and placed it on our website (www.newpathresearch.com) as a free download. This VI enables comparing four new methods for feedback control to the accepted method of PI.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>4. Detailed numerical modeling shows that the MFC is generated by optical rectification in the tunneling junction. That is, the non-linear current-voltage characteristics of the tunneling junction cause a current having a waveform that is equivalent to the envelope of the field produced by the laser.&nbsp;The MFC is the representation of this envelope in the frequency-domain.</p> <p>5. The tip-enhanced quasistatic near field of the laser causes a potential across the series circuit that consists of the tunneling junction and the spreading resistance in the sample. Please see the scaled drawing of the tip and the spreading resistance in Fig. 3, and the corresponding equivalent circuit in Fig. 4. Changing the tip-sample distance varies the power in the MFC, and this power is maximum at the distance where the tunneling resistance equals the spreading resistance. Figure 5 shows the microwave power as a function of the tip-sample distance for samples having 9 different values for the resistivity. Please compare Fig. 5 with Fig. 2 to note the improvement in control caused by using the power instead of the DC tunneling current.&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>6. The sole function of the applied DC bias and the DC tunneling current is to vary the tip-sample distance to maximize the microwave power.&nbsp;<strong>Thus, it is not necessary to have a DC tunneling current.</strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;Feedback control of the tip-sample distance is possible by maximizing the power in the MFC, which has a signal-to-noise ratio of 20-dB, instead of adjusting the noisy sub-microampere tunneling current to approximate a given set-point value for the tunneling current.&nbsp;Figure 6 is a block diagram for the system that we will use for Scanning Frequency Comb Microscopy (SFCM)<strong>.</strong>&nbsp;</p> <p>7. Our simulations suggest that the peak value of the tip-enhanced near-field from the laser at the tunneling junction is comparable with the DC electric field that is required with an STM.&nbsp; However, the duty cycle for the laser is 10<sup>-6</sup>, so there would be less damage to the tip and sample than with an STM.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>References:</strong></p> <p>1. M.J. Hagmann, F.S. Stenger and D.A. Yarotski, &ldquo;Linewidth of the harmonics in a microwave frequency comb generated by focusing a mode-locked ultrafast laser on a tunneling junction&rdquo;, J. Appl. Phys. 114 (2013) 223107.</p> <p>2. C. Rhoades, J. Rasmussen, P.H. Bowles, M.J. Hagmann, and D.A. Yarotski, &ldquo;First measurements of a microwave frequency comb with a semiconductor sample in a scanning tunneling microscope&rdquo;, IEEE Workshop on Microelectronics and Electron Devices (WMED), Boise, ID, April 15, 2016 (DOI:1109/WMED.2016.7458278).</p> <p>3. M.J. Hagmann, &ldquo;Electrode control methodology for a scanning tunneling microscope&rdquo;, U.S. 9,885,736, issued February 6, 2018.</p> <p>4. M.J. Hagmann, "Scanning Frequency Comb Microscopy--A new method in Scanning Probe Microscopy", post-deadline poster at the Microscopy &amp; Microanalysis meeting, August 5-9, 2018, Baltimore, MD.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/10/2018<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;J&nbsp;Hagmann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533936617099_Fig.1-200thHarmonic--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533936617099_Fig.1-200thHarmonic--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533936617099_Fig.1-200thHarmonic--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">200th harmonic of the microwave frequency comb with a gold sample in an STM</div> <div class="imageCredit">M.J. Hagmann, Appl. Phys. Lett. (2012) 241102</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mark&nbsp;J&nbsp;Hagmann</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533937105948_Fig.5-SFCM-EquivalentCircuit--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533937105948_Fig.5-SFCM-EquivalentCircuit--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533937105948_Fig.5-SFCM-EquivalentCircuit--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Equivalent circuit for the measurements.</div> <div class="imageCredit">M.J. Hagmann, Microscopy & Microanalysis 2018.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mark&nbsp;J&nbsp;Hagmann</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533937209062_Fig.3-PowerVsDistance&amp;Resistance--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533937209062_Fig.3-PowerVsDistance&amp;Resistance--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 5"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533937209062_Fig.3-PowerVsDistance&amp;Resistance--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 5"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Microwave power vs. tip-sample distance.</div> <div class="imageCredit">M.J. Hagmann, Microscopy & Microanalysis 2018.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mark&nbsp;J&nbsp;Hagmann</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 5</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533937856523_Fig.6-SFCM-BlockDiagram--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533937856523_Fig.6-SFCM-BlockDiagram--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 6"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533937856523_Fig.6-SFCM-BlockDiagram--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 6"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Block diagram of the System for Scanning Frequency Comb Microscopy (SFCM).</div> <div class="imageCredit">M.J. Hagmann, Microscopy & Microanalysis 2018.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mark&nbsp;J&nbsp;Hagmann</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 6</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533936841165_Fig.2-STM-CurrentVsDistance--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533936841165_Fig.2-STM-CurrentVsDistance--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533936841165_Fig.2-STM-CurrentVsDistance--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Tunneling current vs. tip-sample distance in an STM</div> <div class="imageCredit">M.J. Hagmann, Microscopy & Microanalysis 2018.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mark&nbsp;J&nbsp;Hagmann</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533936988082_Fig.4-Tip-SampleJunction--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533936988082_Fig.4-Tip-SampleJunction--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1648811/1648811_10469193_1533936988082_Fig.4-Tip-SampleJunction--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Scaled diagram of the tip-sample junction, including the spreading resistance.</div> <div class="imageCredit">M.J. Hagmann, Microscopy & Microanalysis 2018.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mark&nbsp;J&nbsp;Hagmann</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 3</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Background: In measurements at Los Alamos National Laboratory the PI previously discovered that a mode-locked laser superimposes a microwave frequency comb (MFC) on the DC tunneling current in a Scanning Tunneling Microscope (STM). The MFC has hundreds of harmonics at integer multiples of the laser pulse repetition frequency, each setting the present state-of-the-art for a narrow-linewidth microwave source [1].  Figure 1 shows the power of the 200th harmonic at 14.85 GHz as a function of the offset from the peak in Hz.  Note that the 3-dB linewidth is 1 Hz. Initially we used metal samples in the STM, but later we measured the harmonics with intrinsic gallium nitride (GaN) [2].   Results at the Research Institution:  1. Scanning Electron Microscope images show tip-crash is common using intrinsic GaN as the sample, but is rare with metal samples.   2. With metal samples, the MFC is measured with a Bias-T in the tip circuit of the STM, but with a semiconductor a fine wire must be used as a surface probe within 0.1 mm of the STM tip. The MFC was seldomly seen with the semiconductors and the surface probe prevents the possibility of making scanned measurements.    Results at NewPath Research:   1. Detailed numerical models simulating an STM with a resistive sample showed that much lower tunneling currents, with greater tip-sample distances that would cause images to have less clarity, are necessary to avoid tip-crash with a resistive sample such as a semiconductor in an STM [See Fig. 2].    2. Detailed numerical modeling and measurements with our in-house STM showed that the "integral" function in conventional proportion + integral (PI) feedback control potentiates tip-crash. This is the method used in the STM at Los Alamos. We invented a new method for feedback control that is simpler to use and provides greater stability [3].    3. We developed a LabVIEW virtual instrument (VI) simulating the full operation of a scanning tunneling microscope and placed it on our website (www.newpathresearch.com) as a free download. This VI enables comparing four new methods for feedback control to the accepted method of PI.    4. Detailed numerical modeling shows that the MFC is generated by optical rectification in the tunneling junction. That is, the non-linear current-voltage characteristics of the tunneling junction cause a current having a waveform that is equivalent to the envelope of the field produced by the laser. The MFC is the representation of this envelope in the frequency-domain.  5. The tip-enhanced quasistatic near field of the laser causes a potential across the series circuit that consists of the tunneling junction and the spreading resistance in the sample. Please see the scaled drawing of the tip and the spreading resistance in Fig. 3, and the corresponding equivalent circuit in Fig. 4. Changing the tip-sample distance varies the power in the MFC, and this power is maximum at the distance where the tunneling resistance equals the spreading resistance. Figure 5 shows the microwave power as a function of the tip-sample distance for samples having 9 different values for the resistivity. Please compare Fig. 5 with Fig. 2 to note the improvement in control caused by using the power instead of the DC tunneling current.       6. The sole function of the applied DC bias and the DC tunneling current is to vary the tip-sample distance to maximize the microwave power. Thus, it is not necessary to have a DC tunneling current.  Feedback control of the tip-sample distance is possible by maximizing the power in the MFC, which has a signal-to-noise ratio of 20-dB, instead of adjusting the noisy sub-microampere tunneling current to approximate a given set-point value for the tunneling current. Figure 6 is a block diagram for the system that we will use for Scanning Frequency Comb Microscopy (SFCM).   7. Our simulations suggest that the peak value of the tip-enhanced near-field from the laser at the tunneling junction is comparable with the DC electric field that is required with an STM.  However, the duty cycle for the laser is 10-6, so there would be less damage to the tip and sample than with an STM.    References:  1. M.J. Hagmann, F.S. Stenger and D.A. Yarotski, "Linewidth of the harmonics in a microwave frequency comb generated by focusing a mode-locked ultrafast laser on a tunneling junction", J. Appl. Phys. 114 (2013) 223107.  2. C. Rhoades, J. Rasmussen, P.H. Bowles, M.J. Hagmann, and D.A. Yarotski, "First measurements of a microwave frequency comb with a semiconductor sample in a scanning tunneling microscope", IEEE Workshop on Microelectronics and Electron Devices (WMED), Boise, ID, April 15, 2016 (DOI:1109/WMED.2016.7458278).  3. M.J. Hagmann, "Electrode control methodology for a scanning tunneling microscope", U.S. 9,885,736, issued February 6, 2018.  4. M.J. Hagmann, "Scanning Frequency Comb Microscopy--A new method in Scanning Probe Microscopy", post-deadline poster at the Microscopy &amp; Microanalysis meeting, August 5-9, 2018, Baltimore, MD.                     Last Modified: 08/10/2018       Submitted by: Mark J Hagmann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
