<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Development of a novel bioabsorbable clip and applicator for rapid closure of the dura mater during open and minimally invasive spine surgery</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop a novel, bioabsorbable surgical clip and applicator for rapid closure of the dura mater in open and minimally invasive spine surgery. The dura mater is the protective membrane that covers the brain and spinal cord and contains cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). Openings in the dura (durotomy) can result in CSF leakage which, if not repaired, can cause potentially fatal complications including spinal headaches, pseudomeningocele, and meningitis. Currently, the dura is closed using fine suture in a difficult and time-consuming process requiring upwards of 30 minutes of additional operating room time. Durotomies occur in approximately 10% of spinal surgeries and with 1.7M spinal surgeries, closure of incidental durotomies costs the healthcare system an estimated $408M each year. Utilization of a bioabsorbable clip and applicator system for dural closure will significantly increase the rate of repair, simplify the work of clinicians, and reduce surgery time and overall costs to the healthcare system. Use of this technology could be expanded to closure of cranial dura, as well as other surgical specialties such as urology, OB/GYN, and general surgery. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project aims to develop a bioabsorbable, non-penetrating clip for rapid closure of the dura mater in spine surgery. The goal is to produce clips capable of closing dura and holding a water tight seal as compared to the current standard of care. This project will include developing a clip made entirely out of a biocompatible, bioabsorbable polymer that will safely degrade in the body after the dura has healed. The clips will also be radiolucent (invisible to x-ray and computed tomography imaging) to allow for unobstructed imaging of the surgical site. In addition, the clips will be non-penetrating to avoid lacerating the dura, reducing the risk of CSF leakage and possible fatal medical complications. This project also aims to develop an inexpensive, disposable applicator system that will apply the clips for dural closure. The applicator will be designed for use in both open and minimally invasive surgery and will house a reservoir of clips for complete dural closure without removal of the applicator from the surgical site for reloading.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1648203</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Dreilinger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel Dreilinger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rachel@NeuraMedica.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5037840312</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000721063</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NeuraMedica LLC</Name>
<CityName>Oregon City</CityName>
<ZipCode>970452201</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5037840312</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>319 4th St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079885939</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEURAMEDICA INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NeuraMedica LLC]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>970048832</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF SBIR Phase I project supported the development of a novel bioabsorbable surgical clip and applier for rapid closure of the dura mater in open and minimally invasive spine surgery.</p> <p>The dura mater is the protective membrane that covers the brain and spinal cord and contains cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). Intentional or accidental openings in the dura (durotomy) can result in CSF leakage which, if not repaired, can cause potentially fatal medical complications, including spinal headaches, meningitis, pseudomeningocele, dura-cutaneous fistula, arachnoiditis, epidural abscess, intracranial subdural hematoma, nerve root entrapment, and wound healing complications.</p> <p>Currently, durotomy closure is time-consuming and labor intensive as it involves closing the dural opening with very fine suture, often while working through narrow corridors. Minimally invasive surgery (MIS) has been increasingly used in spinal procedures, however, the smaller openings of MIS can make suturing dural tissue extremely difficult. Moreover, the current standard of care (SOC) of suturing requires penetration and laceration of the dural tissue by the needle, frequently leading to CSF leakage from the closure site. To reduce the risk of CSF leakage after suturing, surgeons will often use dural substitutes or sealants that are overlaid on the suture, adding surgical time and cost. Both penetrating and non-penetrating metal devices have been used previously to close the dura, however, metallic devices are permanent, can cause CSF leakage, become dislodged, and create imaging artifacts that block visibility of the surgical site during follow-up imaging.</p> <p>NeuraMedica aims to fully develop and commercialize a novel dural clip and applier that delivers small, bioabsorbable, non-penetrating clips for rapid closure of dural openings. The clips are designed to be made entirely out of a biocompatible and bioabsorbable polymeric material that will degrade in the body. The dural clip polymeric material is also radiolucent (i.e., invisible to x-ray imaging) so no imaging artifact is created in post-operative imaging and will not prevent the use of subsequent MRI, which is not compatible with ferrous metallic clips (e.g., stainless steel).</p> <p>The dural clips are designed to evert the dural tissue outwards to reduce the risk of spinal adhesion formation and to be small enough for use in tight spaces in the spine, reducing the risk of spinal nerve compression and nerve pinching. The dural clips are also designed to create a watertight seal without the use of costly dural substitutes, adhesives, or dural sealants, reducing surgical time and expense. In addition, the dural clip is non-penetrating in order to avoid laceration of the dura and to reduce the risk of CSF leakage. The dural clip applier is designed to have a narrow, low profile for use in the deep and confined surgical corridors of MIS.</p> <p>During Phase I, NeuraMedica aimed to deliver functional prototypes of the dural clip and applier that have undergone proof-of-concept bench testing and that meet the current design specifications. Various dural clip designs and polymeric materials were evaluated with finite element analysis and mechanical bench testing. Prototypes of the dural clip underwent pressure testing on harvested animal tissue and human cadaver dura to ensure the clips can maintain dural closure at normal physiological spinal CSF pressure. Additionally, prototypes of the dural clips and applier were successfully used in an <em>in vivo</em> large animal pilot study. The developed dural clip and applier will be used in future preclinical testing and continued commercialization.</p> <p>Advances in neurosurgical and orthopedic spine surgery techniques, such as MIS, are becoming routinely employed. The desired societal benefit of the dural clip and applier is to facilitate, simplify, and expedite the durotomy closure process for MIS. Benefits include decreased anesthesia time, decreased risk of a dislodged metallic foreign body, ease of use, reduced surgical operating room time for durotomies, and increased operating room availability. This device will enable rapid closure of complex dural openings, reducing surgeon frustration, minimizing patient risk, and maximizing economic return in numerous clinical settings.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Rachel&nbsp;Dreilinger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF SBIR Phase I project supported the development of a novel bioabsorbable surgical clip and applier for rapid closure of the dura mater in open and minimally invasive spine surgery.  The dura mater is the protective membrane that covers the brain and spinal cord and contains cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). Intentional or accidental openings in the dura (durotomy) can result in CSF leakage which, if not repaired, can cause potentially fatal medical complications, including spinal headaches, meningitis, pseudomeningocele, dura-cutaneous fistula, arachnoiditis, epidural abscess, intracranial subdural hematoma, nerve root entrapment, and wound healing complications.  Currently, durotomy closure is time-consuming and labor intensive as it involves closing the dural opening with very fine suture, often while working through narrow corridors. Minimally invasive surgery (MIS) has been increasingly used in spinal procedures, however, the smaller openings of MIS can make suturing dural tissue extremely difficult. Moreover, the current standard of care (SOC) of suturing requires penetration and laceration of the dural tissue by the needle, frequently leading to CSF leakage from the closure site. To reduce the risk of CSF leakage after suturing, surgeons will often use dural substitutes or sealants that are overlaid on the suture, adding surgical time and cost. Both penetrating and non-penetrating metal devices have been used previously to close the dura, however, metallic devices are permanent, can cause CSF leakage, become dislodged, and create imaging artifacts that block visibility of the surgical site during follow-up imaging.  NeuraMedica aims to fully develop and commercialize a novel dural clip and applier that delivers small, bioabsorbable, non-penetrating clips for rapid closure of dural openings. The clips are designed to be made entirely out of a biocompatible and bioabsorbable polymeric material that will degrade in the body. The dural clip polymeric material is also radiolucent (i.e., invisible to x-ray imaging) so no imaging artifact is created in post-operative imaging and will not prevent the use of subsequent MRI, which is not compatible with ferrous metallic clips (e.g., stainless steel).  The dural clips are designed to evert the dural tissue outwards to reduce the risk of spinal adhesion formation and to be small enough for use in tight spaces in the spine, reducing the risk of spinal nerve compression and nerve pinching. The dural clips are also designed to create a watertight seal without the use of costly dural substitutes, adhesives, or dural sealants, reducing surgical time and expense. In addition, the dural clip is non-penetrating in order to avoid laceration of the dura and to reduce the risk of CSF leakage. The dural clip applier is designed to have a narrow, low profile for use in the deep and confined surgical corridors of MIS.  During Phase I, NeuraMedica aimed to deliver functional prototypes of the dural clip and applier that have undergone proof-of-concept bench testing and that meet the current design specifications. Various dural clip designs and polymeric materials were evaluated with finite element analysis and mechanical bench testing. Prototypes of the dural clip underwent pressure testing on harvested animal tissue and human cadaver dura to ensure the clips can maintain dural closure at normal physiological spinal CSF pressure. Additionally, prototypes of the dural clips and applier were successfully used in an in vivo large animal pilot study. The developed dural clip and applier will be used in future preclinical testing and continued commercialization.  Advances in neurosurgical and orthopedic spine surgery techniques, such as MIS, are becoming routinely employed. The desired societal benefit of the dural clip and applier is to facilitate, simplify, and expedite the durotomy closure process for MIS. Benefits include decreased anesthesia time, decreased risk of a dislodged metallic foreign body, ease of use, reduced surgical operating room time for durotomies, and increased operating room availability. This device will enable rapid closure of complex dural openings, reducing surgeon frustration, minimizing patient risk, and maximizing economic return in numerous clinical settings.          Last Modified: 02/07/2018       Submitted by: Rachel Dreilinger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
