<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF INCLUDES: Building Diverse and Integrative STEM Continua Using Socio-environmental Systems In and Out of Neighborhoods (DISCUSSION)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99982.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99982</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cynthia Phillips</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cphillip@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922235</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Lead Proposal ID:  HRD 16-1649263&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Gregory D Goins&lt;br/&gt;Lead Institution:  North Carolina Agricultural &amp; Technical State University &lt;br/&gt;Proposal Title: Building Diverse and Integrative STEM Continua Using Socio-environmental Systems In and Out of Neighborhoods (DISCUSSION)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Collaborative Proposal ID: 16-49255&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator: Caesar Jackson&lt;br/&gt;Institution: North Carolina Central University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This collaboration between two Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) will form a networked improvement community located within the Piedmont Region of North Carolina.  In close partnership with community colleges and civic organizations, the project will reach families and students that lead to broader participation of underrepresented groups in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) fields. The overall goal is to build and sustain a scalable, inquiry-based network with the purpose of increasing the academic success of underrepresented ethnic minorities and women in the STEM continuum. By engaging in culturally relevant socio-environmental frameworks, project outcomes will positively impact student retention, knowledge, and quantitative skills in STEM across socio-economic divides and STEM disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Launch Pilot phase will focus on evidence-based teaching and learning approaches for middle school students. The core structure of the network will serve as a platform to launch and guide other age- and level-specific educational instruction, research, and assessment initiatives.  Student understanding of the nature of science will be enhanced by adapting structure, behavior, and function (SBF) theory and system thinking hierarchical (STH) models.  Ultimately, the network will represent a driver for social innovation that positively impacts broadening participation in STEM.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1649255</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tonya</FirstName>
<LastName>Gerald-Goins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tonya Gerald-Goins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tgerald@nccu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195306455</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000590600</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Caesar</FirstName>
<LastName>Jackson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Caesar R Jackson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>crjackson@nccu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195305583</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000603658</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>McGinn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher McGinn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cmcginn@nccu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195306269</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000702330</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Weems</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberly Weems</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ksweems@nccu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195307333</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000717505</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina Central University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277073129</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195307333</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 Fayetteville Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>783691801</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA CENTRAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina Central University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277073129</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1801 Fayetteville Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>NSF INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>029Z</Code>
<Text>Launch Pilots INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~99982</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF INCLUDES Launch Pilot called <em>Diverse and Integrative STEM Continua Using Socio-environmental Systems In and Out of Neighborhoods</em> (<strong>DISCUSSION</strong>) <em>Network</em>, is a driver for social innovation that positively impacts broadening participation in STEM. A collaboration between two Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs), North Carolina A&amp;T State University (NCAT) and North Carolina Central University (NCCU) and in close partnership with community colleges and civic organizations, the DISCUSSION Network reaches and engages families and students from underrepresented groups to provide easier access to high-quality STEM learning opportunities particularly for informal learning settings.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>A guiding theme of DISCUSSION Network&rsquo;s educational material development was to provide inquiry-based, active learning approaches that is interdisciplinary, low-cost, and connected to cultural and community interest. The Food-Energy-Water (FEW) Nexus emerged as a framework to create, connect, and sustain an integrated low-cost training environment for communities. The FEW science learning materials emphasized the connectivity of the science taught with the real life issues in the community and highlighted the intersection of science with policy, culture, the economy, sustainable, agriculture, the environment, water quality, and various other constructs from a System Thinking Hierarchical (STH) Model approach to science. We applied Structure, Behavior, and Function (SBF) theory models in the science engagement activities to simplify complexity and reveal multi-disciplinary nature. The approximate cost to implement the six FEW learning workbooks is less than $300 for a class size of 30 elementary or middle school students. When utilized for informal science learning such as in a summer science enrichment camp, this curriculum made a very positive impact on their perceptions and perspectives about science, college study, and science careers for the youths who were from socioeconomically challenged backgrounds and groups underrepresented in STEM.&nbsp; The intervention also positively influences the parents who became more confident in a science career path for their child.</p> <p>&nbsp;<strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p>Tied to Next Generation Science Standards, and implemented through innovative strategies, a food, energy, and water nexus learning curricula (FEWLC) developed by the DISCUSSION Network assists the STEM Education field in stimulating and motivating student learning of science. An effective practice for expanding the DISCUSSION Network project&rsquo;s reach is linked to the content and context of the DISCUSSION Network&rsquo;s backbone organization with respect to the target population being served. Two HBCUs form the backbone organization; the institutional mission of each of these institution is aligned with that of the DISSCUSION Network, particularly for broadening participation in STEM. Both institutions serving as the backbone are co-located near the communities where the target population live, essentially in the same neighborhoods. Therefore, the DISCUSSION Network is replicable and scalable for similar other HBCUs that are generally in close proximity of neighborhoods of the service populations.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Caesar&nbsp;Jackson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF INCLUDES Launch Pilot called Diverse and Integrative STEM Continua Using Socio-environmental Systems In and Out of Neighborhoods (DISCUSSION) Network, is a driver for social innovation that positively impacts broadening participation in STEM. A collaboration between two Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs), North Carolina A&amp;T State University (NCAT) and North Carolina Central University (NCCU) and in close partnership with community colleges and civic organizations, the DISCUSSION Network reaches and engages families and students from underrepresented groups to provide easier access to high-quality STEM learning opportunities particularly for informal learning settings.  Intellectual Merit:  A guiding theme of DISCUSSION Network’s educational material development was to provide inquiry-based, active learning approaches that is interdisciplinary, low-cost, and connected to cultural and community interest. The Food-Energy-Water (FEW) Nexus emerged as a framework to create, connect, and sustain an integrated low-cost training environment for communities. The FEW science learning materials emphasized the connectivity of the science taught with the real life issues in the community and highlighted the intersection of science with policy, culture, the economy, sustainable, agriculture, the environment, water quality, and various other constructs from a System Thinking Hierarchical (STH) Model approach to science. We applied Structure, Behavior, and Function (SBF) theory models in the science engagement activities to simplify complexity and reveal multi-disciplinary nature. The approximate cost to implement the six FEW learning workbooks is less than $300 for a class size of 30 elementary or middle school students. When utilized for informal science learning such as in a summer science enrichment camp, this curriculum made a very positive impact on their perceptions and perspectives about science, college study, and science careers for the youths who were from socioeconomically challenged backgrounds and groups underrepresented in STEM.  The intervention also positively influences the parents who became more confident in a science career path for their child.   Broader Impacts:  Tied to Next Generation Science Standards, and implemented through innovative strategies, a food, energy, and water nexus learning curricula (FEWLC) developed by the DISCUSSION Network assists the STEM Education field in stimulating and motivating student learning of science. An effective practice for expanding the DISCUSSION Network project’s reach is linked to the content and context of the DISCUSSION Network’s backbone organization with respect to the target population being served. Two HBCUs form the backbone organization; the institutional mission of each of these institution is aligned with that of the DISSCUSION Network, particularly for broadening participation in STEM. Both institutions serving as the backbone are co-located near the communities where the target population live, essentially in the same neighborhoods. Therefore, the DISCUSSION Network is replicable and scalable for similar other HBCUs that are generally in close proximity of neighborhoods of the service populations.       Last Modified: 01/30/2020       Submitted by: Caesar Jackson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
