<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop Proposal: 23rd West Antarctic Ice Sheet Workshop and Science Plan Development</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>22855.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>22855</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Burns</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) is a key region of scientific interest in ice-ocean interaction, global connections and influences on the climate system, and polar climate change. In addition, the region is one of the largest potential contributors to sea-level rise in the coming centuries. The overall goal of this workshop is to foster multi-disciplinary discussion and planning among a broad array of scientists from different backgrounds and career stages.  The priorities for discussion and further development are guided by a 2015 National Academy of Sciences (NAS) report.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific goals for this 23rd WAIS workshop are to (1) air the latest WAIS science, (2) discuss potential next steps in community planning to respond to the top priority in the 2015 NAS report, (3) engage students and early career scientists, (4) discuss new technologies, modeling approaches, and potential field targets for future research, and (5) encourage research data submission and good metadata practices.  The workshop will be held on 3-6 October, 2016 near Washington, DC.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1649109</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ted</FirstName>
<LastName>Scambos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ted A Scambos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tascambos@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034921113</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000240405</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803090216</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street, Room 479]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5292</Code>
<Text>ANT Integrated System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~22855</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The award provided approximately 50% of the required suppport for the 23rd West Antarctic Ice Sheet Workshoop, held in the Algonkian Regional Park in Sterling VA, on October 3-6 of 2016. The meeting had ~95 attendees, and a number of observers (e.g., NSF and NASA program mangers, media reporters).&nbsp;</p> <p>The WAIS Workshop provided an engaging and interactive forum for discussion of the latest NSF- and NASA- sponsored reserach on West Antarctica, with some related studies of similar regions of East Antarctica and Greenland. A totall of 40 talks were given, and approximatley 40 posters in two poster sessions.&nbsp;</p> <p>The WAIS Workshops have a multi-disciplinary focus, spanning climate science, ice dynamics and geophysics, polar oceanography, and polar ecology and marine habitats. This broad range of investigations, integrated by their intent to better understand a single key region of the earth's cryosphere, has led to many new partnerships and research directions, in this year and over the series of Workshops.</p> <p>A major focus of the 23rd Workshop was an extended discussion about how to investigate the Thwaites Glacier / Amundsen Sea Embayment region, moderated by the organizers but open to the entire group of attendees. This discussion reviewed the major sciece questions about the region, and underscored the need for a focussed NSF/ NERC program to explore the region, merging the logistical capabilities of both nations (and potentially other partners) to facilitate a number of major observational programs in the region.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/04/2017<br>      Modified by: Ted&nbsp;A&nbsp;Scambos</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The award provided approximately 50% of the required suppport for the 23rd West Antarctic Ice Sheet Workshoop, held in the Algonkian Regional Park in Sterling VA, on October 3-6 of 2016. The meeting had ~95 attendees, and a number of observers (e.g., NSF and NASA program mangers, media reporters).   The WAIS Workshop provided an engaging and interactive forum for discussion of the latest NSF- and NASA- sponsored reserach on West Antarctica, with some related studies of similar regions of East Antarctica and Greenland. A totall of 40 talks were given, and approximatley 40 posters in two poster sessions.   The WAIS Workshops have a multi-disciplinary focus, spanning climate science, ice dynamics and geophysics, polar oceanography, and polar ecology and marine habitats. This broad range of investigations, integrated by their intent to better understand a single key region of the earth's cryosphere, has led to many new partnerships and research directions, in this year and over the series of Workshops.  A major focus of the 23rd Workshop was an extended discussion about how to investigate the Thwaites Glacier / Amundsen Sea Embayment region, moderated by the organizers but open to the entire group of attendees. This discussion reviewed the major sciece questions about the region, and underscored the need for a focussed NSF/ NERC program to explore the region, merging the logistical capabilities of both nations (and potentially other partners) to facilitate a number of major observational programs in the region.             Last Modified: 09/04/2017       Submitted by: Ted A Scambos]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
