<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: The Intersections of Health and Wealth: Socioeconomic Status, Frailty, and Mortality</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24074.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24074</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Socioeconomic status (SES) has long been known to mediate exposure to hazards and disease, as well as access to those resources necessary for growth, development, tissue maintenance, and immune response. However, the connection between SES and mortality is often oversimplified, and, in extreme cases, could misinform health policy and treatment protocols about the risks faced by individuals in a variety of contexts. Biological anthropology is well-equipped to explore the variability of patterns of SES and heath in the past by interpreting the results of bioarchaeological research in light of current theoretical perspectives espoused by public health researchers investigating the connection between SES and health in living populations. This project provides a novel model for exploring SES in past societies and will broaden understanding of the effects of SES across time by focusing on a context that differs from the modern, industrialized populations to which these theoretical perspectives have been applied. As a result, this multidisciplinary project will advance research in biological anthropology and extend the temporal purview of public health research by incorporating intersectionality theory into a study of past health. Moreover, the work will train a female graduate student and contribute to public science outreach efforts in both the United States and the United Kingdom.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This dissertation project uses skeletal samples to examine the interactions of SES, demographic characteristics (such as age and sex), exposure to physiological stressors, and mortality in the context of industrialization in 19th century England. Skeletal data from four industrial-era cemeteries (Coach Lane, St. Bride's Fleet Street, St. Peter's Wolverhampton, and New Bunhill Fields) will be analyzed with paleodemographic approaches (hazard modeling, hierarchical log-linear analysis, and analysis of variance) to determine how morbidity and mortality patterns in industrial England differed between SES groups; investigate how physiological stressors throughout life interacted with socially meaningful categories such as age and sex to produce layered marginalizations that influenced frailty and mortality in industrial England; and evaluate the potential of stressors underrepresented in biological anthropology literature to enhance understanding of marginalization, intersectionality, and mortality in the past.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1649757</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
<LastName>DeWitte</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharon DeWitte</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dewittes@mailbox.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8037776940</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000420317</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samantha</FirstName>
<LastName>Yaussy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samantha L Yaussy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>syaussy@email.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8037777093</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000722399</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Carolina at Columbia</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Awards Management</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1600 Hampton Street, Suite 414]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041387846</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH CAROLINA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041387846</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Carolina at Columbia]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbia</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~24074</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Because it mediates access to resources and exposure to hazards and disease, socioeconomic status (SES) is considered one of the most powerful predictors of mortality. However, the connection between SES and mortality is often oversimplified and overlooks the potential for multiple types of marginalization to be layered within a single individual. To avoid uncritically applying modern patterns of SES and health onto the past, this study integrated theoretical perspectives used in modern public health research with analytical tools and methodologies from bioarchaeology and paleodemography to evaluate how age, sex, SES, and previous health influenced morbidity and mortality in industrializing England. In an analysis of over 1140 individuals, this project compared a high SES skeletal sample in London (St. Bride&rsquo;s Fleet Street, 1740-1852) to middle- and low-SES skeletal collections from London (New Bunhill Fields, 1821-1853), North Shields (Coach Lane, 1711-1857), and Wolverhampton (St. Peter&rsquo;s Wolverhampton, c. 1819-1850s) to examine the interactions of SES, demographic characteristics (such as age and sex), exposure to physiological stressors, and mortality in the context of industrialization in 19th-century England.</p> <p>The results of this project are informative about how, historically, industrialization and the rigidification of SES groups affected health in human populations and which subpopulations are most at risk during this process. The results of the 2- and 3-way ANOVA tests and the hierarchical log-linear analyses indicate that indicators of physiological stress in childhood and adolescence (fluctuating asymmetry, tooth size, vertebral neural canal size, linear enamel hypoplasia, and cribra orbitalia) were significantly associated with particular SES, sex, and age groups. Asymmetry of the face and skull, for example, was more pronounced among males in the samples, suggesting that males were particularly prone to environmental disturbances during development or were less able to buffer against them. This result may be linked to biological factors that may make males more prone to disease and physiological disruption, or may be linked to a cultural factors that predisposed developing males to hazardous working conditions and environments. Importantly, some of the results indicated key intersections of multiple categorizations at which individuals be at greater risk than if the two categories (e.g., sex and age) were considered separately. For example, the presence of periosteal lesions on the tibia was not associated with sex or age as distinct subjects of inquiry, but the periosteal lesions were associated with the intersection of sex and age. This result suggests that sex and age combined to influence the risk of developing the lesions in industrializing England despite not being significantly associated with the lesion&rsquo;s presence on their own.</p> <p>The results of this project demonstrate the importance of analytical approaches that allow for the examination of heterogeneity and intersectionality in past populations. Approaches like hazard modeling, hierarchical log-linear analysis, and multi-way ANOVA tests expose variation in mortality patterns among subpopulations, revealing the disproportionate effects of industrialization and SES-inequality. Importantly, this project provides a model for how bioarchaeological techniques may be used to communicate with and historically contextualize the findings of intersectional studies of modern populations. The results from this project can potentially benefit modern populations by informing public health strategies in areas currently experiencing industrialization or that have experienced industrialization in the past, specifically by identifying groups that may be or have been disproportionally affected by the process.</p> <p>This project contributed to diversity in STEM research by supporting the continued training of a female doctoral student in data collection and interpretation and providing additional experience with the use of advanced paleodemographic and statistical techniques, as well as sex estimation and age estimation using transition analysis. This project facilitated public outreach, as the results have been and will continue to be presented in several talks that are open to the general public. Further, the results will be presented in full at professional conferences and published in several peer-reviewed articles, and an effort will be made to ensure that as many of the articles as possible are open access and thus freely available to the general public.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/28/2018<br>      Modified by: Sharon&nbsp;Dewitte</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Because it mediates access to resources and exposure to hazards and disease, socioeconomic status (SES) is considered one of the most powerful predictors of mortality. However, the connection between SES and mortality is often oversimplified and overlooks the potential for multiple types of marginalization to be layered within a single individual. To avoid uncritically applying modern patterns of SES and health onto the past, this study integrated theoretical perspectives used in modern public health research with analytical tools and methodologies from bioarchaeology and paleodemography to evaluate how age, sex, SES, and previous health influenced morbidity and mortality in industrializing England. In an analysis of over 1140 individuals, this project compared a high SES skeletal sample in London (St. Bride?s Fleet Street, 1740-1852) to middle- and low-SES skeletal collections from London (New Bunhill Fields, 1821-1853), North Shields (Coach Lane, 1711-1857), and Wolverhampton (St. Peter?s Wolverhampton, c. 1819-1850s) to examine the interactions of SES, demographic characteristics (such as age and sex), exposure to physiological stressors, and mortality in the context of industrialization in 19th-century England.  The results of this project are informative about how, historically, industrialization and the rigidification of SES groups affected health in human populations and which subpopulations are most at risk during this process. The results of the 2- and 3-way ANOVA tests and the hierarchical log-linear analyses indicate that indicators of physiological stress in childhood and adolescence (fluctuating asymmetry, tooth size, vertebral neural canal size, linear enamel hypoplasia, and cribra orbitalia) were significantly associated with particular SES, sex, and age groups. Asymmetry of the face and skull, for example, was more pronounced among males in the samples, suggesting that males were particularly prone to environmental disturbances during development or were less able to buffer against them. This result may be linked to biological factors that may make males more prone to disease and physiological disruption, or may be linked to a cultural factors that predisposed developing males to hazardous working conditions and environments. Importantly, some of the results indicated key intersections of multiple categorizations at which individuals be at greater risk than if the two categories (e.g., sex and age) were considered separately. For example, the presence of periosteal lesions on the tibia was not associated with sex or age as distinct subjects of inquiry, but the periosteal lesions were associated with the intersection of sex and age. This result suggests that sex and age combined to influence the risk of developing the lesions in industrializing England despite not being significantly associated with the lesion?s presence on their own.  The results of this project demonstrate the importance of analytical approaches that allow for the examination of heterogeneity and intersectionality in past populations. Approaches like hazard modeling, hierarchical log-linear analysis, and multi-way ANOVA tests expose variation in mortality patterns among subpopulations, revealing the disproportionate effects of industrialization and SES-inequality. Importantly, this project provides a model for how bioarchaeological techniques may be used to communicate with and historically contextualize the findings of intersectional studies of modern populations. The results from this project can potentially benefit modern populations by informing public health strategies in areas currently experiencing industrialization or that have experienced industrialization in the past, specifically by identifying groups that may be or have been disproportionally affected by the process.  This project contributed to diversity in STEM research by supporting the continued training of a female doctoral student in data collection and interpretation and providing additional experience with the use of advanced paleodemographic and statistical techniques, as well as sex estimation and age estimation using transition analysis. This project facilitated public outreach, as the results have been and will continue to be presented in several talks that are open to the general public. Further, the results will be presented in full at professional conferences and published in several peer-reviewed articles, and an effort will be made to ensure that as many of the articles as possible are open access and thus freely available to the general public.        Last Modified: 06/28/2018       Submitted by: Sharon Dewitte]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
