<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: A Novel Theoretical Study of Mid-latitude Atmospheric Predictability</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>222018.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>222018</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020106</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Varavut Limpasuvan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlimpasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922746</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This EAGER project will develop a deeper physical understanding of how predictability is fundamentally limited and why it may vary from forecast to forecast. New insights into the connection between the nature of turbulence and predictability will be an important component of this project. Unlike most  earlier work on atmospheric predictability that has predominantly relied on linearization and instability techniques, this research will adopt a fully non-linear and probabilistic approach. Consequently insights into the nature of atmospheric predictability when non-linearity is important is be a particular focus of this research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A newly developed theoretical methodology from statistical physics will be applied to the problem of atmospheric predictability in the mid latitudes. This will enable exploration of the nature of statistical predictability limits and variability. Connections between these aspects of statistical predictability and features of the atmosphere such as the mean vertical shear; boundary layer damping and geostrophic turbulence will be thoroughly analyzed. Additionally a new non-diffusive method of parameterizing the fine unresolved scales of motion will be developed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1649457</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Kleeman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard Kleeman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kleeman@cims.nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2129983233</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000171030</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100121110</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[251 Mercer Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8012</Code>
<Text>CR, Earth System Models</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1303</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE MODELING &amp; PREDICTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>SEES Unsolicited</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~222018</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A question of great interest to the general public concerns the accuracy and reliability of weather forecasts. Developing an understanding of this is an ongoing area of research across the discipline of atmospheric science. It is a very difficult problem on a fundamental level because it requires an in depth understanding of the phenomenon of turbulence. This remains one of the great unsolved problems of modern physics and any advances in it's understanding are likely to have widespread application across many scientific disciplines.</p> <p>The particular work carried out with this grant was focussed on fundamental factors in the atmosphere limiting useful weather forecasts to 2-3 weeks. These factors can vary substantially according to the current state of the atmosphere and so can vary enormously according to the time of year.</p> <p>Within turbulent systems such as the atmosphere variables that change slowly are usually of practical interest while those which vary rapidly are only generally of interest in that they influence the slow variables. Developing a framework for predicting how the slow variables evolve in the presence of the confounding (and "random") fast variables is fundamental to understanding turbulence. The research in this grant tackled this problem in a novel fashion using fundamental tools from information theory and statistical physics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The machinery developed will potentially enable the analysis of a widespread set of different turbulent systems across many different fields of study. More particularly it will potentially enable us to figure out what causes the limits to our ability to make accurate weather forecasts.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/06/2019<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;Kleeman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A question of great interest to the general public concerns the accuracy and reliability of weather forecasts. Developing an understanding of this is an ongoing area of research across the discipline of atmospheric science. It is a very difficult problem on a fundamental level because it requires an in depth understanding of the phenomenon of turbulence. This remains one of the great unsolved problems of modern physics and any advances in it's understanding are likely to have widespread application across many scientific disciplines.  The particular work carried out with this grant was focussed on fundamental factors in the atmosphere limiting useful weather forecasts to 2-3 weeks. These factors can vary substantially according to the current state of the atmosphere and so can vary enormously according to the time of year.  Within turbulent systems such as the atmosphere variables that change slowly are usually of practical interest while those which vary rapidly are only generally of interest in that they influence the slow variables. Developing a framework for predicting how the slow variables evolve in the presence of the confounding (and "random") fast variables is fundamental to understanding turbulence. The research in this grant tackled this problem in a novel fashion using fundamental tools from information theory and statistical physics.     The machinery developed will potentially enable the analysis of a widespread set of different turbulent systems across many different fields of study. More particularly it will potentially enable us to figure out what causes the limits to our ability to make accurate weather forecasts.          Last Modified: 08/06/2019       Submitted by: Richard Kleeman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
