<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: CIRTL INCLUDES - Toward an Alliance to Prepare a National Faculty for Broadening Success of Underrepresented 2-Year and 4-Year STEM Students</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>6828.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>6828</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ICER</Abbreviation>
<LongName>ICER</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandon Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbjones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924713</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of Wisconsin-Madison, Iowa State University, University of Pittsburgh, University of Texas at El Paso, Michigan State University, University of Georgia and University of California, Los Angeles will lead this Design and Development Launch Pilot to build the foundation for a national alliance that will prepare a new national STEM faculty, spanning all of post-secondary education, able to use evidence-based teaching, mentoring and advising practices that yield greater learning, persistence and completion of women and historically underrepresented minorities (URM) undergraduates in STEM. This project was created by this group of institutions, who are members of the Center for the Integration of Research, Teaching and Learning (CIRTL), in response to the Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science (NSF INCLUDES) program solicitation (NSF 16-544). The INCLUDES program is a comprehensive national initiative designed to enhance U.S. leadership in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) discoveries and innovations focused on NSF's commitment to diversity, inclusion, and broadening participation in these fields.  The INCLUDES Design and Development Launch Pilots represent bold, innovative ways for solving a broadening participation challenge in STEM.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The full participation of all of America's STEM talent is critical to the advancement of science and engineering for national security, health and prosperity.  Our nation is advancing knowledge and practices to address a STEM achievement and the graduation gap between undergraduate STEM students who are women and men, and between those who are URMs and non-URMs. At the same time U.S. universities and colleges struggle to recruit, retain and promote a diverse STEM graduate student body, and a diverse STEM faculty, who serve as role models and academic leaders for URM and female students to learn from, to work with and to emulate.  This project, the CIRTL INCLUDES - Toward an Alliance to Prepare a National Faculty for Broadening Success of Underrepresented 2-Year and 4-Year STEM Students, has the potential to advance a national network of organizations to improve the success of future STEM faculty who will educate a diverse undergraduate body and contribute to the learning, retention and graduation of women and URMs in STEM fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The collaborating CIRTL universities will work closely with multiple organizations to address key goals, including Achieving the Dream, Advanced Technological Education Central, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the American Mathematical Society of Two-Year Colleges, the American Physical Society, the American Society for Engineering Education, the Association of American Universities, the Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities, the Council of Graduate Schools, the Council for the Study of Community Colleges, Excelencia in Education, the Infrastructure for Broadening Participation in STEM, the Louis Stokes Midwest Center for Excellence, the Math Alliance, the National Institute for Staff and Organizational Development, the National Research Mentoring Network, the Partnership for Undergraduate Life Science Education, the Southern Regional Education Board, the Summer Institutes on Scientific Teaching, and the Women in Engineering Programs and Advocates Network.  Together, this extensive collaborative network will three goals: (1) To deepen the preparation of future STEM faculty in teaching, mentoring and advising practices that promote the success of undergraduates who are women and URMs; (2) To expand and strengthen faculty preparation specifically for 2-year colleges; and (3) To target the preparation of future STEM faculty who are members of underrepresented groups for effective teaching and mentoring, contributing to their early-career success.  The seven universities who are partnering to lead this project will work to: (1) Form active partnerships and national coalitions for each of the three goals; (2) Employ a collective impact framework for each goal team and the entire alliance, ensuring common agendas, shared metrics, mutually reinforcing activities and an integrated process using data improvement cycles; and (3) Achieve pilot outcomes that position the alliance for future work.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1649105</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Besterfield-Sacre</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary Besterfield-Sacre</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mbsacre@engr.pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126249836</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000305791</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>NSF INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~6828</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many research studies attribute attrition from STEM of undergraduates in underrepresented groups (URG) to uneven quality of teaching, mentoring and advising. Research also points to the close connection between the quality of learning experiences and equitable student achievement and persistence in STEM. Non-inclusive classrooms, ineffective teaching, poor mentoring in undergraduate research experiences and unprepared advising negatively affect learners, and especially marginalized students, from succeeding in STEM courses and persisting in STEM majors. The challenge in higher education is&nbsp;<em>not</em>&nbsp;lack of research understanding about which teaching, mentoring and advising practices will yield greater and more equitable undergraduate learning and persistence. The challenge is that most faculty, at all career stages, are not using these practices.</p> <p>A powerful leverage point for change is the preparation of new STEM faculty. For example, teaching professional development for future faculty at graduate universities has been shown to be strongly associated with use of effective instructional practices as early-career faculty. Further, 80% of the U.S. STEM Ph.D. and master&rsquo;s degrees are granted at only 187 universities, allowing targeted intervention before graduates flow into faculty positions at 4400 U.S. 2- and 4-year colleges and universities.</p> <p><em>The overarching goal of CIRTL INCLUDES is to develop STEM faculty, for all sectors of postsecondary education, who are able to use and adapt evidence-based, inclusive teaching, mentoring and advising practices that yield increased success of URG students.</em></p> <p>To build such a national STEM faculty, CIRTL INCLUDES has three mutually reinforcing strategic goals:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Strategic Goal 1 (SG1) &ndash;&nbsp;</strong>Deepen the preparation of&nbsp;<em>all</em>&nbsp;future STEM faculty in evidence-based teaching, mentoring and advising practices that promote URG undergraduate success;</li> <li><strong>Strategic Goal 2 (SG2) &ndash;&nbsp;</strong>Increase the number and diversify the pool of graduate students and qualified professionals who are interested in pursuing a teaching career in STEM at 2-year colleges and to expand and strengthen the preparation of current and future STEM faculty to teach the diverse student population at 2-year colleges.</li> <li><strong>Strategic Goal 3 (SG3) &ndash;&nbsp;</strong>Target the preparation of future URG STEM faculty for effective teaching and mentoring, contributing to earlier success across the spectrum of their early-career responsibilities.</li> </ul> <p>To accomplish these goals, the alliance synthesized and built upon an extensive research base around broadening participation across STEM fields, to develop a research agenda to extend our knowledge about how to use that research base for impact toward broadening participation.&nbsp; The specific focus of this effort was Strategic Goal 1.</p> <p>The specific objectives of SG1 were to:</p> <ol> <li>Develop and mutually agree upon frameworks for the needs and attributes of evidence-based pedagogy, undergraduate research mentoring and advising practices that support URG success, and synthesize such practices both from literature and evaluated programs.</li> <li>Prepare a strategic plan for applying the knowledge syntheses to professional development of future faculty in Phase III; and pilot professional development based on the frameworks produced in the first objective. </li> <li>Finally, drawing from extensive prior evaluation work, define agreed-upon metrics and an evaluation plan to determine if such professional development yields future faculty learning and early-career practice of teaching, mentoring and advising that improves URG undergraduate success. </li> </ol> <p>To accomplish this, the SG1 worked with a team of both Action Partners, as well as a larger National Coalition.&nbsp; Specifically, the Action Partnership was a learning community that carried out the tasks of the strategic goal that used collective impact processes.&nbsp; The SG1 National Coalition then provided the SG1 Action Partnership with the national perspective on institutional needs and on the design for national impact through both evaluation of the dissemination plan and scale up plan.</p> <p>In addition to the dissemination and scale up plans, the primary result of the SG1 effort were three frameworks.&nbsp; The frameworks provide tools that can be used in preparing professional development for faculty (i.e., future faculty, faculty at two year and four year institutions) in evidence-based <strong><em>inclusive</em></strong> pedagogy, undergraduate research mentoring, and advising practices. Undergraduate students seeking degrees in STEM areas has been trending towards increasingly diverse populations, however retention of under-represented groups (URG) in STEM continues to be a greater challenge than enrollment. Thus, the frameworks were designed to collate evidence-based practices that have been demonstrated to support and reduce barriers to URG STEM undergraduate success. The frameworks along with a guide for using the frameworks for professional development of faculty and future faculty can be accessed at <a href="https://cirtlincludes.net/sg1/">https://cirtlincludes.net/sg1/</a>.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/18/2018<br>      Modified by: Mary&nbsp;Besterfield-Sacre</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many research studies attribute attrition from STEM of undergraduates in underrepresented groups (URG) to uneven quality of teaching, mentoring and advising. Research also points to the close connection between the quality of learning experiences and equitable student achievement and persistence in STEM. Non-inclusive classrooms, ineffective teaching, poor mentoring in undergraduate research experiences and unprepared advising negatively affect learners, and especially marginalized students, from succeeding in STEM courses and persisting in STEM majors. The challenge in higher education is not lack of research understanding about which teaching, mentoring and advising practices will yield greater and more equitable undergraduate learning and persistence. The challenge is that most faculty, at all career stages, are not using these practices.  A powerful leverage point for change is the preparation of new STEM faculty. For example, teaching professional development for future faculty at graduate universities has been shown to be strongly associated with use of effective instructional practices as early-career faculty. Further, 80% of the U.S. STEM Ph.D. and master?s degrees are granted at only 187 universities, allowing targeted intervention before graduates flow into faculty positions at 4400 U.S. 2- and 4-year colleges and universities.  The overarching goal of CIRTL INCLUDES is to develop STEM faculty, for all sectors of postsecondary education, who are able to use and adapt evidence-based, inclusive teaching, mentoring and advising practices that yield increased success of URG students.  To build such a national STEM faculty, CIRTL INCLUDES has three mutually reinforcing strategic goals:  Strategic Goal 1 (SG1) &ndash; Deepen the preparation of all future STEM faculty in evidence-based teaching, mentoring and advising practices that promote URG undergraduate success; Strategic Goal 2 (SG2) &ndash; Increase the number and diversify the pool of graduate students and qualified professionals who are interested in pursuing a teaching career in STEM at 2-year colleges and to expand and strengthen the preparation of current and future STEM faculty to teach the diverse student population at 2-year colleges. Strategic Goal 3 (SG3) &ndash; Target the preparation of future URG STEM faculty for effective teaching and mentoring, contributing to earlier success across the spectrum of their early-career responsibilities.   To accomplish these goals, the alliance synthesized and built upon an extensive research base around broadening participation across STEM fields, to develop a research agenda to extend our knowledge about how to use that research base for impact toward broadening participation.  The specific focus of this effort was Strategic Goal 1.  The specific objectives of SG1 were to:  Develop and mutually agree upon frameworks for the needs and attributes of evidence-based pedagogy, undergraduate research mentoring and advising practices that support URG success, and synthesize such practices both from literature and evaluated programs. Prepare a strategic plan for applying the knowledge syntheses to professional development of future faculty in Phase III; and pilot professional development based on the frameworks produced in the first objective.  Finally, drawing from extensive prior evaluation work, define agreed-upon metrics and an evaluation plan to determine if such professional development yields future faculty learning and early-career practice of teaching, mentoring and advising that improves URG undergraduate success.    To accomplish this, the SG1 worked with a team of both Action Partners, as well as a larger National Coalition.  Specifically, the Action Partnership was a learning community that carried out the tasks of the strategic goal that used collective impact processes.  The SG1 National Coalition then provided the SG1 Action Partnership with the national perspective on institutional needs and on the design for national impact through both evaluation of the dissemination plan and scale up plan.  In addition to the dissemination and scale up plans, the primary result of the SG1 effort were three frameworks.  The frameworks provide tools that can be used in preparing professional development for faculty (i.e., future faculty, faculty at two year and four year institutions) in evidence-based inclusive pedagogy, undergraduate research mentoring, and advising practices. Undergraduate students seeking degrees in STEM areas has been trending towards increasingly diverse populations, however retention of under-represented groups (URG) in STEM continues to be a greater challenge than enrollment. Thus, the frameworks were designed to collate evidence-based practices that have been demonstrated to support and reduce barriers to URG STEM undergraduate success. The frameworks along with a guide for using the frameworks for professional development of faculty and future faculty can be accessed at https://cirtlincludes.net/sg1/.       Last Modified: 07/18/2018       Submitted by: Mary Besterfield-Sacre]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
