<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Georgia Institute of Technology Planning Grant: I/UCRC for Unmanned Aircraft Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Behrooz Shirazi</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bshirazi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928343</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Georgia Institute of Technology (Georgia Tech) proposes to join the up-and-running NSF-sponsored Industry/University Cooperative Research Center (I/UCRC) in unmanned aircraft systems:  The Center for Unmanned Aircraft Systems: C-UAS (c-uas.byu.edu) was established by Brigham Young University (BYU) and the University of Colorado (CU) in 2012, and now also includes Virginia Tech (VT).   This center provides innovative solutions to key technical challenges and superb training for future leaders in the unmanned aircraft system industry.  Georgia Tech will bring specific expertise in airspace management, system engineering, cognitive engineering, and fault tolerant guidance/navigation/control systems.  This specific effort includes a planning meeting with current and prospective members of the industrial advisory board and representatives of Georgia Tech; allowing the establishment of effective new partnerships for C-UAS between industry, government, and academia in the field of UAS.  &lt;br/&gt;Georgia Tech brings expertise in a number of areas to the center:&lt;br/&gt;(1) Airspace management and control for safe UAS integration, concepts of operation (CONOPS), including prior research in designing airspace organization and procedures.  &lt;br/&gt;(2) System engineering and system integration, including:  system-of-systems design and analysis, safety assurance, and avionics integration.&lt;br/&gt;(3) Operator interface, human factors, and automation design for UAS, including extensive experience performing research test flights with many different levels of automation and operator interface concepts.&lt;br/&gt;(4) Detect and avoid systems, including both cooperative and non-cooperative methods.&lt;br/&gt;(5) Obstacle avoidance and path planning systems, including analysis and testing with a wide-array of sensor modalities and guidance/control concepts.&lt;br/&gt;(6) Fault tolerant estimation and control, including extensive work in GPS-denied operations as well as adaptive and reconfigurable guidance and control methods.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To facilitate the inclusion of Georgia Tech to this center, a planning meeting with current and prospective members of the industrial advisory board (IAB) and representatives of Georgia Tech, VT, BYU and CU will be held in February 2017.  The planning meeting will gather top researchers and leading industry and government players to establish the foundation for an effective partnership between industry, government, and academia in the field of UAS.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/08/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1650352</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric N Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eric.johnson@engr.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148653813</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000441345</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/15/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John-Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Clarke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John-Paul Clarke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>johnpaul@utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124714371</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000081673</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/15/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~14999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary activity during the grant period was a planning meeting held in conjunction with a normal Center meeting, where current and prospective members of the industrial advisory board (IAB) and representatives of Georgia Tech, VT, BYU and CU explored the inclusion of Georgia Tech in the center.</p> <p>The researchers and leading industry and government players at the meeting discussed several research models, and the specifics of how Georgia Tech might establish the foundation for an effective partnership between industry, government, and academia in the field of UAS.</p> <p>Several project and collaborations were proposed over the 24-month duration of ther grant. These include:</p> <ul> <li style="text-align: left;">Automation as a Good Teammate in the Control of UAS&nbsp;</li> <li style="text-align: left;">Designing Next Generation Transports Using Environmental Design Space</li> <li style="text-align: left;">Designing UAS to Meet Trajectory Tracking Requirements</li> <li style="text-align: left;">Meta Aircraft Flight Dynamics and Control</li> <li style="text-align: left;">Mission-Optimal Hybrid Air-Ground Package Delivery Network</li> <li style="text-align: left;">Robotic Legged Landing Systems (Mark Costello)250Planning the Use Cases for UAS</li> <li style="text-align: left;">System of System Approach for Unmanned Aircraft Separation Assurance in an Urban Environment</li> <li style="text-align: left;">UAS-Based Beyond-Line-of-Sight Surveillance System for Improving Railway Safety and Efficiency</li> </ul> <p style="text-align: left;">Our efforts to simultaneously determine the most appropriate research projects and obtain the corporate sponsorship required to ensure a robust research program were stymied by the departure of Eric Johnson (the original PI) and Amy Pritchett from Georgia Tech in Summer of 2017, and the change in status&nbsp;(leaves of absences, etc.)&nbsp;of several relevant faculty during 2018.</p> <!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 10.0px Helvetica} --> <p class="p1">Georgia Tech has decided not to join the Center at this time.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/24/2019<br>      Modified by: John-Paul&nbsp;Clarke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary activity during the grant period was a planning meeting held in conjunction with a normal Center meeting, where current and prospective members of the industrial advisory board (IAB) and representatives of Georgia Tech, VT, BYU and CU explored the inclusion of Georgia Tech in the center.  The researchers and leading industry and government players at the meeting discussed several research models, and the specifics of how Georgia Tech might establish the foundation for an effective partnership between industry, government, and academia in the field of UAS.  Several project and collaborations were proposed over the 24-month duration of ther grant. These include:  Automation as a Good Teammate in the Control of UAS  Designing Next Generation Transports Using Environmental Design Space Designing UAS to Meet Trajectory Tracking Requirements Meta Aircraft Flight Dynamics and Control Mission-Optimal Hybrid Air-Ground Package Delivery Network Robotic Legged Landing Systems (Mark Costello)250Planning the Use Cases for UAS System of System Approach for Unmanned Aircraft Separation Assurance in an Urban Environment UAS-Based Beyond-Line-of-Sight Surveillance System for Improving Railway Safety and Efficiency  Our efforts to simultaneously determine the most appropriate research projects and obtain the corporate sponsorship required to ensure a robust research program were stymied by the departure of Eric Johnson (the original PI) and Amy Pritchett from Georgia Tech in Summer of 2017, and the change in status (leaves of absences, etc.) of several relevant faculty during 2018.  Georgia Tech has decided not to join the Center at this time.          Last Modified: 08/24/2019       Submitted by: John-Paul Clarke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
