<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Collaborative 3D Materials Science Research in the Cloud</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Beverly</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rbeverly@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927068</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The discovery and widespread implementation of advanced materials have long been challenged by the overwhelmingly complex combinations of elements and transformation paths that result in a plethora of material properties.  Materials research projects generate datasets that range from a few tens of Gigabytes to terabytes, making it difficult to organize, share and analyze. This project brings new big data management and analysis techniques to materials research, giving scientists access to previously unwieldy datasets with new tools that accelerate the pace of innovation by allowing sharing of both complex data and analysis tools. The software will be deployed on the web, making it accessible to researchers worldwide to collaboratively explore the structure of materials.  These tools and methods allow for the integration of experimental measurements in 3 dimensions (3-D) and 4 dimensions (4-D) with computational modeling of materials in extreme environments, such as aerospace engine components and the development of high efficiency thermoelectric materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will push the boundary of large-scale web-based image and data analysis in multiple directions. First, the execution of complex scientific workflows on heterogeneous compute clusters will be simplified by exploiting virtualization techniques and modern cluster computing frameworks such as Apache Spark. We will compare overheads for parallel execution strategies on different frameworks for realistic workflows. Second, we will add provenance tracking and versioning for scientific workflows including a web-based browser that aids in making sense of past analysis runs and improves repeatability of experiments. We will extend graph query systems and graph visualization frameworks for this purpose. Third, we will integrate the capability to run Dream.3D pipelines in parallel across parameter ranges. This will enable the Materials Science community to rapidly explore effects of input parameters on the analysis results. The system will track sub-results and allow users to browse and query both metadata (e.g., "instrument name") and the complex output data in HDF tables. A new query system that spans modalities (tables, graphs, text, images) will be added.  Towards achieving these goals, we will extend the existing BisQue image analysis platform that is widely used for large scale image informatics. The BisQue platform and the associated Materials Research tools will be distributed as open source.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1650972</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Pollock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tresa Pollock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pollock@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058933810</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000276845</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bangalore</FirstName>
<LastName>Manjunath</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bangalore S Manjunath</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>manj@ece.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058937112</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000468919</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931069560</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1712</Code>
<Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8292</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8004</Code>
<Text>Software Institutes</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8400</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">A broad objective in Materials Science (MS) is to understand and control the structure of materials for the discovery of new materials and optimization of existing materials. Recent instrument developments enable the routine 3D evaluation of materials, dramatically improving the connection between the structure and properties. In order to capitalize on the newly available 3D views of material structure, entirely new sets of algorithms and data analysis codes have been developed. However, there are significant challenges to sharing and working collaboratively on the massive amounts of data that is generated by the instruments and the data analysis methods. Our EAGER project?s primary objective is to address this critical requirement for Materials Science research by creating an extensive resource for the curation, distribution, and sharing of MS processing methods.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #283c46; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The project leverages extensively on the ongoing work by the team members on building a robust framework for the analysis and sharing of large-scale scientific image data. Specifically, the BisQue software infrastructure is used to create complex, reproducible workflows. Further, a state-of-the-art MS data processing software, DREAM.3D, &nbsp;is deployed within the  BisQue cloud-based distributed computing environment, thus enabling researchers to easily share and collaborate with large scale datasets. During the course of the two year project, the following major goals were accomplished:</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul style="margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;"> <li style="list-style-type: disc; font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #283c46; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #283c46; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Goal 1: Adding support in BisQue to create and explore complex, reproducible workflows. </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The way in which the BisQue executes workflows is generalized such that more diverse sets of softwares modules can be executed to operate on a dataset. As more software and scientific code is incorporated into BisQue, a critical responsibility is to capture both the physical code and versions being executed, as well as the overarching collection of codes executed on data, which is captured in the workflow. The ability to capture workflows, code versioning, and the parameters used to analyze each new dataset is transformative to the extent of data provenance that can captured and for reproducibility of results between labs and in technical publications. </span> </li> <li style="list-style-type: disc; font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #283c46; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #283c46; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Goal 2: Integration of Dream.3D and analysis of outputs into BisQue. Dream.3D is an extensive collection of MS tools routinely used for the interrogation of a material?s 3D structure. Integration of this toolkit with BisQue facilitates collaboration and data provenance when working with large 3D datasets. </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Other tools include web-based 3D data visualizers, data array viewers and table viewers, which make possible data analysis exclusively in the cloud.</span> </li> <li style="list-style-type: disc; font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #283c46; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #283c46; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Goal 3: Demonstration on a testbed: Application of BisQue-Materials platform to real case studies. </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The impact of Dream.3D with BisQue is demonstrated by the ability to perform large scale computations on 3D materials data. One example application is searching a large parameter space and reconstruct a dataset collected from an additively manufactured component. The analysis of these additive manufactured 3D datasets is crucial for understanding what material defects emerge from the printing process and the structure that results from different printing parameters. A material strength prediction tool is also developed using 3D microstructures as inputs. This tool is being used to search for materials with structural configurations that will result in enhanced properties.</span> </li> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/24/2018<br>      Modified by: Bangalore&nbsp;S&nbsp;Manjunath</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1650972/1650972_10460907_1545679953714_bisque_workflow--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1650972/1650972_10460907_1545679953714_bisque_workflow--rgov-800width.jpg" title="BisQue Workflow"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1650972/1650972_10460907_1545679953714_bisque_workflow--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="BisQue Workflow"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An example BisQue workflow. Workflows also have their own viewer that shows all steps and details of each step. Since the workflow runner itself is a BisQue module, it can be called from another workflow. This allows workflows to execute other workflows, whereby constructing larger and more complex</div> <div class="imageCredit">BisQue-Materials Team, UCSB</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bangalore&nbsp;S&nbsp;Manjunath</div> <div class="imageTitle">BisQue Workflow</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1650972/1650972_10460907_1545680181822_304L_SS_3D_Reconstruction_2deg_Segmentation_Toerance--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1650972/1650972_10460907_1545680181822_304L_SS_3D_Reconstruction_2deg_Segmentation_Toerance--rgov-800width.jpg" title="An additively manufactured 304 stainless steel."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1650972/1650972_10460907_1545680181822_304L_SS_3D_Reconstruction_2deg_Segmentation_Toerance--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="An additively manufactured 304 stainless steel."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">3D reconstruction of an additively manufactured 304L stainless steel using a 2? grain segmentation tolerance determined from testing a wide range of angular tolerances (1? to 30?).</div> <div class="imageCredit">BisQue-Materials Team, UCSB</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bangalore&nbsp;S&nbsp;Manjunath</div> <div class="imageTitle">An additively manufactured 304 stainless steel.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A broad objective in Materials Science (MS) is to understand and control the structure of materials for the discovery of new materials and optimization of existing materials. Recent instrument developments enable the routine 3D evaluation of materials, dramatically improving the connection between the structure and properties. In order to capitalize on the newly available 3D views of material structure, entirely new sets of algorithms and data analysis codes have been developed. However, there are significant challenges to sharing and working collaboratively on the massive amounts of data that is generated by the instruments and the data analysis methods. Our EAGER project?s primary objective is to address this critical requirement for Materials Science research by creating an extensive resource for the curation, distribution, and sharing of MS processing methods.  The project leverages extensively on the ongoing work by the team members on building a robust framework for the analysis and sharing of large-scale scientific image data. Specifically, the BisQue software infrastructure is used to create complex, reproducible workflows. Further, a state-of-the-art MS data processing software, DREAM.3D,  is deployed within the  BisQue cloud-based distributed computing environment, thus enabling researchers to easily share and collaborate with large scale datasets. During the course of the two year project, the following major goals were accomplished:     Goal 1: Adding support in BisQue to create and explore complex, reproducible workflows. The way in which the BisQue executes workflows is generalized such that more diverse sets of softwares modules can be executed to operate on a dataset. As more software and scientific code is incorporated into BisQue, a critical responsibility is to capture both the physical code and versions being executed, as well as the overarching collection of codes executed on data, which is captured in the workflow. The ability to capture workflows, code versioning, and the parameters used to analyze each new dataset is transformative to the extent of data provenance that can captured and for reproducibility of results between labs and in technical publications.   Goal 2: Integration of Dream.3D and analysis of outputs into BisQue. Dream.3D is an extensive collection of MS tools routinely used for the interrogation of a material?s 3D structure. Integration of this toolkit with BisQue facilitates collaboration and data provenance when working with large 3D datasets. Other tools include web-based 3D data visualizers, data array viewers and table viewers, which make possible data analysis exclusively in the cloud.  Goal 3: Demonstration on a testbed: Application of BisQue-Materials platform to real case studies. The impact of Dream.3D with BisQue is demonstrated by the ability to perform large scale computations on 3D materials data. One example application is searching a large parameter space and reconstruct a dataset collected from an additively manufactured component. The analysis of these additive manufactured 3D datasets is crucial for understanding what material defects emerge from the printing process and the structure that results from different printing parameters. A material strength prediction tool is also developed using 3D microstructures as inputs. This tool is being used to search for materials with structural configurations that will result in enhanced properties.         Last Modified: 12/24/2018       Submitted by: Bangalore S Manjunath]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
