<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IOS: The Function and Evolution of Plant Phased siRNAs in Signaling Pathways and Microbial Interactions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>422715.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>422715</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Mishkind</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmishkin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928413</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this work is to investigate in plants the function and evolution of a novel class of regulatory small RNAs. Prior work demonstrated that plant genes like those known to confer resistance to pathogens are the targets of a set of "microRNAs"--suppressive regulatory RNAs just 22 nucleotides in length. These microRNAs are believed to function as master regulators of a very large family of protein coding disease-resistance genes, and part of their activity is to trigger the production of additional small RNAs (21 nucleotides in length) that have an unusual, regularly spaced pattern, or "phasing" of biogenesis. The regulation of this gene family, and several others targeted by microRNAs in the same way, is a new paradigm for microRNA function. The investigators have identified these small RNAs as conserved in many crop plants, including soybean, an alfalfa relative, tomato and potato. The aim of this project is to investigate this novel gene regulatory circuit to understand its function in plants, its role in plant defenses or beneficial microbial interactions, and whether it can ultimately be developed as a tool for improving plants or altering plant-microbe interactions to reduce disease or improve beneficial interactions. The project will utilize methods that include plant genomics, plant cell biology, plant-microbial interactions, and RNA analysis. The expected result is the dissection and understanding of a novel and complex gene regulatory mechanism. The broader impacts of the project range from a local impact on the training of students and a post-doc who will be directly involved in the project, to national and international impact to the scientific community in the databases and web tools that the project will release.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1650843</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Blake</FirstName>
<LastName>Meyers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Blake C Meyers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bmeyers@danforthcenter.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3145871000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000241552</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Donald Danforth Plant Science Center</Name>
<CityName>St. Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631322918</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3145871041</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>975 N. Warson Rd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044193006</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DONALD DANFORTH PLANT SCIENCE CENTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044193006</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Donald Danforth Plant Science Center]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631322918</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[975 N. Warson Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7656</Code>
<Text>Symbiosis Infection &amp; Immunity</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~257801</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~164914</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project focused on the function and evolution of RNA in plants, specifically small RNAs (21 nucleotides in length) that have an unusual, regularly spaced pattern, or "phasing" of biogenesis. Prior work demonstrated that plant genes like those known to confer resistance to pathogens are the targets of a set of "microRNAs"--suppressive regulatory RNAs just 22 nucleotides in length. These microRNAs are believed to function as master regulators of disease resistance genes, perhaps with the function to coordinately co-regulate these potent components of the plant immune system. The regulation of this gene family, and several others targeted by microRNAs in the same way, is a new paradigm for microRNA function. Most of the results were important basic research discoveries about how plant genes are regulated, how signaling occurs, and how these processes are shared or diversified across the broad range of flowering and seed plants that humans use for food, fuel and fiber. As an outcome of this project, the work characterized the presence and activity of this novel gene regulatory circuit in a broad range of flowering and seed plants, its role in plant defense gene function, and developed new tools that may help improve crop plants by altering plant-microbe interactions to reduce diseases.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Among the more exciting basic research outcomes were the demonstration in a relative of alfalfa (Medicago) that even within closely related families of microRNAs, each member tends to target a somewhat narrow and non-overlapping class of genes, despite their theoretical capability to target a much broader set of genes. The project also characterized numerous aspects of plant microRNA activity. Another important observation was that in the genome of Norway spruce, and important tree for human uses and ecology, there is a remarkably strong engagement of this genetic circuitry, utilized by over 2000 genes. This was a striking observation, because it demonstrates that this mode of gene regulation is heavily employed in some plant species and less so in others.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To assess variation across diverse crop and model plants, the project team members focused on disease resistance genes from over 70 sequenced plant genomes, finding that microRNA diversification is driven largely by the functional constraints on the disease resistance genes. In other words, the primary importance of this gene family in detecting pathogens forces microRNA divergence to keep pace. This knowledge will be useful in the future for improved design of genes to confer resistance against pests and pathogens.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>An additional, important outcome of this work was the data that was shared across many collaborating laboratories, and the shared training of numerous undergraduates, graduate students, and early-career post-doctoral scientists. Project team members were trained in cutting-edge techniques in gene editing, genomics, and bioinformatics.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/09/2018<br>      Modified by: Blake&nbsp;C&nbsp;Meyers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project focused on the function and evolution of RNA in plants, specifically small RNAs (21 nucleotides in length) that have an unusual, regularly spaced pattern, or "phasing" of biogenesis. Prior work demonstrated that plant genes like those known to confer resistance to pathogens are the targets of a set of "microRNAs"--suppressive regulatory RNAs just 22 nucleotides in length. These microRNAs are believed to function as master regulators of disease resistance genes, perhaps with the function to coordinately co-regulate these potent components of the plant immune system. The regulation of this gene family, and several others targeted by microRNAs in the same way, is a new paradigm for microRNA function. Most of the results were important basic research discoveries about how plant genes are regulated, how signaling occurs, and how these processes are shared or diversified across the broad range of flowering and seed plants that humans use for food, fuel and fiber. As an outcome of this project, the work characterized the presence and activity of this novel gene regulatory circuit in a broad range of flowering and seed plants, its role in plant defense gene function, and developed new tools that may help improve crop plants by altering plant-microbe interactions to reduce diseases.     Among the more exciting basic research outcomes were the demonstration in a relative of alfalfa (Medicago) that even within closely related families of microRNAs, each member tends to target a somewhat narrow and non-overlapping class of genes, despite their theoretical capability to target a much broader set of genes. The project also characterized numerous aspects of plant microRNA activity. Another important observation was that in the genome of Norway spruce, and important tree for human uses and ecology, there is a remarkably strong engagement of this genetic circuitry, utilized by over 2000 genes. This was a striking observation, because it demonstrates that this mode of gene regulation is heavily employed in some plant species and less so in others.     To assess variation across diverse crop and model plants, the project team members focused on disease resistance genes from over 70 sequenced plant genomes, finding that microRNA diversification is driven largely by the functional constraints on the disease resistance genes. In other words, the primary importance of this gene family in detecting pathogens forces microRNA divergence to keep pace. This knowledge will be useful in the future for improved design of genes to confer resistance against pests and pathogens.     An additional, important outcome of this work was the data that was shared across many collaborating laboratories, and the shared training of numerous undergraduates, graduate students, and early-career post-doctoral scientists. Project team members were trained in cutting-edge techniques in gene editing, genomics, and bioinformatics.       Last Modified: 09/09/2018       Submitted by: Blake C Meyers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
