<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Fundamental Physics from Primordial Seeds</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/23/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>69454.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>69454</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds the research activities of Professor Xingang Chen at the University of Texas at Dallas.    In recent years, experiments and theoretical studies have established a six-parameter Standard Model for the Big Bang cosmology, and provided strong support for the existence of an inflationary epoch as the origin of Big Bang. The details of this epoch are now being explored.   In addition, various tantalizing anomalies have been observed that can potentially provide us the knowledge beyond the Standard Model. This project will systematically study different beyond-Standard-Model signals in terms of both the theoretical model-building and the interpretation of data.  The primary data comes from detailed studies of the cosmic microwave background(CMB) and of the large scale structure (LSS) of the universe.   This research motivates new connections between theory and data, and facilitates discoveries of new physics.  In addition, this will provide training for undergraduates and graduate students, and there will be an outreach program to high school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will investigate and classify a variety of possible new phenomena in the inflationary density perturbations, such as primordial anisotropies, features and non-Gaussianities. He will systematically classify different types of anisotropic pre-inflationary relic and study their effects on density perturbations, will study different inflation models with oscillating spectator massive fields and predict their effects on the CMB and LSS, and will extend work on primordial non-Gaussiantiies and study the effects on the CMB and LSS.   He will emphasize important connections between the beyond-Standard-Model signals and fundamental physics. Methods of model building, first-principle derivation and data analyses are combined to effectively carry out this program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1650217</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xingang</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xingang Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xingang.chen@cfa.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174955501</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000726637</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021385366</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1288</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics &amp; Cosmol</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~29454</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>In recent years, experiments and theoretical studies have established the Standard Model of the Big Bang cosmology, and imposed an open question on the origin of Big Bang. Future experiments can potentially provide us the knowledge beyond the Standard Model. This proposal proposes to systematically study different beyond-Standard-Model signals in terms of theoretical model-building and data analysis. This research motivates new connections between theory and data, and facilitates discoveries of new physics.</span></p> <p><span><br /></span><span>We have investigated and classified a variety of possible new phenomena in the inflationary density perturbations, such as primordial anisotropies, primordial features and primordial non-Gaussianities. We have proposed and/or developed several new research directions, such as primordial standard clocks and quasi-single field inflation models. We have emphasized important connections between the beyond-Standard-Model signals and fundamental physics.&nbsp;We have shown how the future experiments may be able to distinguish model-independently the inflation scenario and alternative-to-inflation scenario using the signals of primordial standard clocks. We have shown how aspects of high energy physics unreachable in the man-made colliders can be studied in cosmology.</span></p> <p><span><br /></span><span>We have provided education and professional training on cosmology to undergraduate, graduate students and postdoc researchers. We have organized introductory lecture series to high school intern students who have interests in physics, and help them with their professional choices.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Xingang&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In recent years, experiments and theoretical studies have established the Standard Model of the Big Bang cosmology, and imposed an open question on the origin of Big Bang. Future experiments can potentially provide us the knowledge beyond the Standard Model. This proposal proposes to systematically study different beyond-Standard-Model signals in terms of theoretical model-building and data analysis. This research motivates new connections between theory and data, and facilitates discoveries of new physics.   We have investigated and classified a variety of possible new phenomena in the inflationary density perturbations, such as primordial anisotropies, primordial features and primordial non-Gaussianities. We have proposed and/or developed several new research directions, such as primordial standard clocks and quasi-single field inflation models. We have emphasized important connections between the beyond-Standard-Model signals and fundamental physics. We have shown how the future experiments may be able to distinguish model-independently the inflation scenario and alternative-to-inflation scenario using the signals of primordial standard clocks. We have shown how aspects of high energy physics unreachable in the man-made colliders can be studied in cosmology.   We have provided education and professional training on cosmology to undergraduate, graduate students and postdoc researchers. We have organized introductory lecture series to high school intern students who have interests in physics, and help them with their professional choices.       Last Modified: 07/30/2018       Submitted by: Xingang Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
