<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Securing ICS Systems in the IIoT</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ralph Wachter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rwachter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In today's world, power plants, chemical plants, and manufacturing systems are all managed by computer systems called Industrial Control Systems (ICS).  These consist of sensors (e.g. thermostats, level sensors) that measure important properties of the plant, actuators (e.g. valves, pumps) that change the state of the plant and computer systems that in real time use the sensor data to make decisions about to operate the actuators.  Like other computer systems industrial control systems have been shown to be vulnerable to cyber attacks; what is unique to ICS is that cyber attacks can result in physical effects.  It is completely possible that a cyber attack on an ICS could result in major power blackouts, disruption of supply, or the release of dangerous chemicals.  The IIot (Industrial Internet of Things) is a rapidly emerging new type of ICS in which the sensors, actuators and the computer that control them communicate through the Internet.  There is a serious worry that these new IIoT systems are being deployed before we understand how to protect them from internet based cyber attacks.  This effort is intended to develop new technologies that can prevent such attacks.   The goal is the project is to develop a set of architectural principles governing the design of IIoT systems such that if these principles are adhered to, the design is guaranteed to behave in a safe manner in the face of cyber attacks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will illustrate these architectural principles by prototyping simple IIoT systems built in accordance with them and then demonstrating that the prototypes are resilient in the presence of cyber attacks.  The first principle is that the actual control system must be coupled with a computational model of how it is intended to behave. These two are executed in tandem; when the actual system's behavior differs from that sanctioned by the model, this is a system of a partially successful cyber attack.  The monitor then must diagnose the cause of the failure and take corrective action.  A second principle is that the control system must be accompanied by a library of multi-step attack plans and must be able to recognize the early steps so that it can mitigate the effects of the attack while it is still unfolding and before the most serious consequences have happened.  A final set of architectural principles requires the use of low cost cryptographic techniques to guarantee authorization, authentication and non-tampering in all communications between the sensors, actuators, and the control computers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1650276</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
<LastName>Shrobe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Howard Shrobe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hes@csail.mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172537877</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000112223</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Cambridge, MA]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goals of this EAGER project was to explore the challenges and opportunities for developing secure cyber physical systems, particularly in the context of the emerging Industrial Internet of Things. &nbsp;Of particular concern is the question of how network enabled control systems can be protected from cyber attack. &nbsp;Control systems are susceptible to all of the attack types that we have witnessed in conventional computing technology, but they are in addition subject to attacks based on corrupting sensor data, timing and commands to effectors.<br />Our project wished to explore two complemenatry approachs: 1) Model based diagnosis in which an abstract model, or executable speciication, of the system is used to predict expected behavior and in which deviations from these predications are treated as symptoms of a penetration. &nbsp;The model is then used to reason retrospectively about how the attack might have been effected. &nbsp;2) Attack graph generation which is the dual of model based diagnosis. &nbsp;In this case, we hypothesize a target for the attacker, such as effecting the performance of a component, and the use planning techniques to develop a coarse of action for the attacker that is capable of achieving the desired degradation of the target system.<br />These two approaches draw on the same background knowledge of how computing systems, and control systems in particular are organized. &nbsp;They also share the same models of the control system and of the surrounding computational ecosystem.<br />Our goal is to 1) clarify what consittutes such knowledge 2) Develop effective encodings of this knowledge 3) Demonstrate the ability to both conduct diagnosis and attack planning 4) Clarify what would be necessary to scale these approaches up to realistic commercial scale application.<br />During the course of the project we developed implementtions of computing systems that illustrate the viability of both approaches. &nbsp;<br />In the case of model-based diagnosis we implemented a security monitor for a basic type of control system (called a PID controller) and showed that our monitor is capable of detecting attacks that modify either the control parameters or the code of the controller. &nbsp;We also demonstrated that in some circumstances the monitor can detect attacks that corrupt sensor data, leaving the control system with an incorrect picture of the world that then leads to issuing incorrect control commands. &nbsp;In general, it has been shown that an attacker with complete knowledge of the control system can craft an attack that is both effective and undetectable by normal techniques. Our technique is not capable of detecting such attacks but less skillful attacks can indeed be detected.<br />Our attack planner is intended to be used as a tool for auditing the cyber vulnerability of a system. &nbsp;In effect, it captures the reasoning process of an attacker, starting with high level goals (e.g. to comprimse the privacy of certain data) and the repeatedly reducing this goal to sub-goals (e.g. breaking into a particular computer) until it finds specific actions that can achieve those goals. &nbsp;This type of planning is a common AI technique but the knowledge of the types of goals and techniques is unique to the cyber-security domain. &nbsp;Also in contrast to most planner that attempt to find the optimal plan, our system's goal is to find all possible plans. &nbsp;Our system also "knows" a great deal about how computer systems and networks are structured and how one element of a larger system depends on other elements. &nbsp;During the course of this effort, we enlarged the system's knowledge of attacker strategies and tactics. &nbsp;We demonstrated the effectiveness of the planning algorithm and of the knowledge base by applying it to several different examples that have strong similarities to real world systems. &nbsp;These include a quad-copter UAV, a mock-up of the controls of a commercial ocean going vessel (called TRUDI and provided by the Naval Post-Graduate School) and a system similar to an urban surveillance system.<br />One PhD and one Master of Engineering degree projects were supported by this project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/04/2019<br>      Modified by: Howard&nbsp;Shrobe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goals of this EAGER project was to explore the challenges and opportunities for developing secure cyber physical systems, particularly in the context of the emerging Industrial Internet of Things.  Of particular concern is the question of how network enabled control systems can be protected from cyber attack.  Control systems are susceptible to all of the attack types that we have witnessed in conventional computing technology, but they are in addition subject to attacks based on corrupting sensor data, timing and commands to effectors. Our project wished to explore two complemenatry approachs: 1) Model based diagnosis in which an abstract model, or executable speciication, of the system is used to predict expected behavior and in which deviations from these predications are treated as symptoms of a penetration.  The model is then used to reason retrospectively about how the attack might have been effected.  2) Attack graph generation which is the dual of model based diagnosis.  In this case, we hypothesize a target for the attacker, such as effecting the performance of a component, and the use planning techniques to develop a coarse of action for the attacker that is capable of achieving the desired degradation of the target system. These two approaches draw on the same background knowledge of how computing systems, and control systems in particular are organized.  They also share the same models of the control system and of the surrounding computational ecosystem. Our goal is to 1) clarify what consittutes such knowledge 2) Develop effective encodings of this knowledge 3) Demonstrate the ability to both conduct diagnosis and attack planning 4) Clarify what would be necessary to scale these approaches up to realistic commercial scale application. During the course of the project we developed implementtions of computing systems that illustrate the viability of both approaches.   In the case of model-based diagnosis we implemented a security monitor for a basic type of control system (called a PID controller) and showed that our monitor is capable of detecting attacks that modify either the control parameters or the code of the controller.  We also demonstrated that in some circumstances the monitor can detect attacks that corrupt sensor data, leaving the control system with an incorrect picture of the world that then leads to issuing incorrect control commands.  In general, it has been shown that an attacker with complete knowledge of the control system can craft an attack that is both effective and undetectable by normal techniques. Our technique is not capable of detecting such attacks but less skillful attacks can indeed be detected. Our attack planner is intended to be used as a tool for auditing the cyber vulnerability of a system.  In effect, it captures the reasoning process of an attacker, starting with high level goals (e.g. to comprimse the privacy of certain data) and the repeatedly reducing this goal to sub-goals (e.g. breaking into a particular computer) until it finds specific actions that can achieve those goals.  This type of planning is a common AI technique but the knowledge of the types of goals and techniques is unique to the cyber-security domain.  Also in contrast to most planner that attempt to find the optimal plan, our system's goal is to find all possible plans.  Our system also "knows" a great deal about how computer systems and networks are structured and how one element of a larger system depends on other elements.  During the course of this effort, we enlarged the system's knowledge of attacker strategies and tactics.  We demonstrated the effectiveness of the planning algorithm and of the knowledge base by applying it to several different examples that have strong similarities to real world systems.  These include a quad-copter UAV, a mock-up of the controls of a commercial ocean going vessel (called TRUDI and provided by the Naval Post-Graduate School) and a system similar to an urban surveillance system. One PhD and one Master of Engineering degree projects were supported by this project.             Last Modified: 02/04/2019       Submitted by: Howard Shrobe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
