<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: AGNES: Algebraic Geometry NorthEastern Series</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>34200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>34200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Spiroff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspiroff@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in six AGNES (Algebraic Geometry Northeastern Series) conferences which will be held at Stony Brook University on April 21-23, 2017, at Northeastern University in Fall 2017, at Rutgers University in Spring 2018, at Brown University in Fall 2018, at University of Massachusetts Amherst in Spring 2019, and at Boston College in Fall 2019. AGNES is a semi-annual algebraic geometry meeting organized at a rotating location by an association of northeastern universities. A guiding goal of AGNES is to introduce graduate students to a broad spectrum of current research in algebraic geometry. While meeting this goal, AGNES has become an important center for algebraic geometry in the US. The conference has an extensive record of promoting collaboration and has developed new tools for training and mentoring future leaders in algebraic geometry. These consist of graduate mini-schools, career panels, poster presentations for junior participants (including undergraduate students), and events specifically targeting members of groups that are under-represented in the mathematical sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Algebraic geometry is a sub-field of mathematical sciences that studies solution sets of polynomial equations. It has deep connections to many other areas of pure mathematics, such as topology, arithmetic, number theory, differential geometry, dynamical systems, and homological algebra. At the same time algebraic geometry has found important applications in applied mathematics and computer science (computer vision, geometric complexity theory, numerical methods in algebraic statistics, etc). The centerpiece research activity of each AGNES meeting will be 7-8 invited lectures given by speakers showcasing different facets of algebraic geometry. The scientific scope of AGNES will be further expanded by lectures from neighboring mathematical subjects (such as arithmetic geometry, dynamics, complex geometry, and computational geometry) and by the various supporting activities described above. Further information can be found at the conference website: http://www.agneshome.org/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/05/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1651082</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dawei</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dawei Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dawei.chen@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175523755</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000511957</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maksym</FirstName>
<LastName>Fedorchuk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maksym Fedorchuk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maksym.fedorchuk@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175523757</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574412</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Lehmann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Lehmann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lehmannb@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175523750</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000628872</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>Newton</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~100</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~34100</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>AGNES (Algebraic Geometry NorthEastern Series) is a biannual conference in algebraic geometry.&nbsp; The conference is hosted by a consortium of colleges and universities in the Northeast on a rotating basis.</p> <p>Over the past decade AGNES has become part of the landscape of the algebraic geometry community in the Northeast.&nbsp; Due to its popularity and longevity, AGNES has become an important platform for networking and building community.&nbsp; Averaging around 150 participants per meeting, AGNES is one of the largest biannual meetings in the field of algebraic geometry in the country.&nbsp; Since about 75% of participants are pre-tenure track, AGNES also plays a crucial role in supporting the graduate student and postdoc communities.</p> <p>AGNES has two overarching goals.&nbsp; The first is excellence in research: every meeting features hosts eight lectures highlighting recent advances by leading mathematicians.&nbsp; The spectrum of research presented at AGNES is broad and often includes results from neighboring fields.&nbsp; Several of the invited lectures include a &ldquo;pre-talk,&rdquo; an introductory session for junior mathematicians.</p> <p>The second goal is to promote the development of young researchers and a STEM workforce.&nbsp; AGNES has a long history of educating and training graduate students with events such as pre-talks, mini-workshops, poster sessions, and discussion panels.&nbsp; In the past funding cycle there were several Women@AGNES events to encourage the participation and representation of women.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/12/2020<br>      Modified by: Brian&nbsp;Lehmann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ AGNES (Algebraic Geometry NorthEastern Series) is a biannual conference in algebraic geometry.  The conference is hosted by a consortium of colleges and universities in the Northeast on a rotating basis.  Over the past decade AGNES has become part of the landscape of the algebraic geometry community in the Northeast.  Due to its popularity and longevity, AGNES has become an important platform for networking and building community.  Averaging around 150 participants per meeting, AGNES is one of the largest biannual meetings in the field of algebraic geometry in the country.  Since about 75% of participants are pre-tenure track, AGNES also plays a crucial role in supporting the graduate student and postdoc communities.  AGNES has two overarching goals.  The first is excellence in research: every meeting features hosts eight lectures highlighting recent advances by leading mathematicians.  The spectrum of research presented at AGNES is broad and often includes results from neighboring fields.  Several of the invited lectures include a "pre-talk," an introductory session for junior mathematicians.  The second goal is to promote the development of young researchers and a STEM workforce.  AGNES has a long history of educating and training graduate students with events such as pre-talks, mini-workshops, poster sessions, and discussion panels.  In the past funding cycle there were several Women@AGNES events to encourage the participation and representation of women.          Last Modified: 08/12/2020       Submitted by: Brian Lehmann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
