<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Assessing the role of trophic interactions on peatland carbon cycling under varied nutrient availability</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>297879.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>297879</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927186</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Peatlands in the far north store a very large amount of carbon in their cold (sometimes frozen) and wet soils. While the cold, wet environment is clearly important, the biological factors that cause so much peat to accumulate in these ecosystems are not entirely understood. This project will study how changes in peat carbon cycling at the Bonanza Creek Long-Term Ecological Research site vary with nutrient availability.  Researchers will conduct experiments to test hypotheses concerning the importance of algae and the food web of insects and invertebrates that algal production supports, to accumulation of carbon in peatlands. Food webs are a poorly know aspect of peatland ecology, and a better understanding of what controls biotic interactions within them will have profound implications for understanding the global carbon cycle. In addition to charting new conceptual ground in ecosystem science, this project will support two early career researchers, involve undergraduate students from under-represented groups, and train two graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Early-concept Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER) project challenges the notion that energy flow within the food web of boreal peatlands is limited to detrital pathways. Through a contribution of carbon subsidies and by modifying redox potential for heterotrophic microorganisms, the investigators propose that algal photosynthesis fuels a microbial loop and contributes to ecosystem carbon and nitrogen fluxes. The research will evaluate the relative importance of bottom-up versus top-down effects (and their interactions) on boreal peatland food webs using a factorial experiment to test three hypotheses: 1) Under low nutrient availability, algal biomass is constrained and decomposition is primarily regulated by detrital pathways. 2) Increasing nutrient availability promotes algal biomass and the transfer of energy to grazers, releasing higher trophic levels from resource limitation. 3) The presence of a second energy pathway in algae (edible vs. inedible) mutes the trophic cascade, leading to greater stability (i.e., lower coefficients of variance) in food web structure than would be expected with strong top-down control of a homogenous edible community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1651195</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Wyatt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin H Wyatt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>khwyatt@bsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7652851600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000639957</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allison</FirstName>
<LastName>Rober</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allison R Rober</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>arrober@bsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7652851600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000629861</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ball State University</Name>
<CityName>Muncie</CityName>
<ZipCode>473060155</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7652851600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2000 West University Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065540726</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BALL STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065540726</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bonanza Creek LTER]]></Name>
<CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>997757530</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AK00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~297879</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Early-concept Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER) project challenged the notion that energy flow within the food web of boreal peatlands was limited to detrital pathways. The objective of this project was to evaluate the ability for food web interactions to influence carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) emissions from peatland surface waters by regulating the microbial biofilm that develops on peat surface layers. The research evaluated the relative importance of bottom-up versus top-down effects (and their interactions) on boreal peatland food webs using a factorial experiment to test three hypotheses: 1) Under low nutrient availability, algal biomass is constrained and decomposition is primarily regulated by detrital pathways. 2) Increasing nutrient availability promotes algal biomass and the transfer of energy to grazers, releasing higher trophic levels from resource limitation. 3) The presence of a second energy pathway in algae (edible vs. inedible) mutes the trophic cascade, leading to greater stability (i.e., lower coefficients of variance) in food web structure than would be expected with strong top-down control of a homogenous edible community.</p> <p>By disassembling the food chain, we were able to show that animals, through trophic interactions, contribute to the carbon sink potential (i.e. net ecosystem carbon exchange) of a northern peatland ecosystem. Specifically, we found that: (1) in the absence of top-down regulation (i.e. consumption by herbivores), elevated levels of algal biomass offset CO<sub>2</sub> emissions associated with greater organic matter decomposition, (2) herbivory accelerated nutrient-enhanced CO<sub>2</sub> respiration by reducing algal biomass, and (3) predators indirectly increased algal biomass and reduced NEE by muting herbivory in a trophic cascade. Furthermore, we observed an increase in inedible algae and decrease in stability when bottom-up constraints were alleviated and herbivory was unregulated (2-tiered food web) that was absent in the presence of a trophic cascade (3-tiered food web). These findings show that predators indirectly prevented morphological changes in the algal assemblage by limiting herbivory, thereby increasing stability. The results of this study highlight the need to consider animal food-chain interactions with biogeochemistry (i.e. zoogeochemical effects) in carbon cycle models aimed to predict how global change will affect net ecosystem carbon uptake and storage. In addition to charting new conceptual ground in ecosystem science, this project supported 2 early-career researchers and facilitated the training and development of 11 undergraduate and 6 graduate students.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/24/2021<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;H&nbsp;Wyatt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Early-concept Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER) project challenged the notion that energy flow within the food web of boreal peatlands was limited to detrital pathways. The objective of this project was to evaluate the ability for food web interactions to influence carbon dioxide (CO2) emissions from peatland surface waters by regulating the microbial biofilm that develops on peat surface layers. The research evaluated the relative importance of bottom-up versus top-down effects (and their interactions) on boreal peatland food webs using a factorial experiment to test three hypotheses: 1) Under low nutrient availability, algal biomass is constrained and decomposition is primarily regulated by detrital pathways. 2) Increasing nutrient availability promotes algal biomass and the transfer of energy to grazers, releasing higher trophic levels from resource limitation. 3) The presence of a second energy pathway in algae (edible vs. inedible) mutes the trophic cascade, leading to greater stability (i.e., lower coefficients of variance) in food web structure than would be expected with strong top-down control of a homogenous edible community.  By disassembling the food chain, we were able to show that animals, through trophic interactions, contribute to the carbon sink potential (i.e. net ecosystem carbon exchange) of a northern peatland ecosystem. Specifically, we found that: (1) in the absence of top-down regulation (i.e. consumption by herbivores), elevated levels of algal biomass offset CO2 emissions associated with greater organic matter decomposition, (2) herbivory accelerated nutrient-enhanced CO2 respiration by reducing algal biomass, and (3) predators indirectly increased algal biomass and reduced NEE by muting herbivory in a trophic cascade. Furthermore, we observed an increase in inedible algae and decrease in stability when bottom-up constraints were alleviated and herbivory was unregulated (2-tiered food web) that was absent in the presence of a trophic cascade (3-tiered food web). These findings show that predators indirectly prevented morphological changes in the algal assemblage by limiting herbivory, thereby increasing stability. The results of this study highlight the need to consider animal food-chain interactions with biogeochemistry (i.e. zoogeochemical effects) in carbon cycle models aimed to predict how global change will affect net ecosystem carbon uptake and storage. In addition to charting new conceptual ground in ecosystem science, this project supported 2 early-career researchers and facilitated the training and development of 11 undergraduate and 6 graduate students.       Last Modified: 05/24/2021       Submitted by: Kevin H Wyatt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
