<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Transforming Access and Archiving for Endangered Language Data Through Exploratory Methodologies of Curation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>248039.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>288985</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joan Maling</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmaling@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928046</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The digital revolution of the 21st Century has brought many advances in technology along with an accompanying increase in the number and size of digital records.  This increase has outpaced the existing organizational and preservation practices used by archives, especially where it is the repositories and their staff who organize long-term preservation and access for deposited collections.  In 2011 the National Science Foundation issued a mandate that every researcher who applies for these federal research funds must submit a Data Management Plan to explain exactly how the collected research data would be stored, secured, preserved, and accessed. A 2013 memorandum from the White House's Office of Science and Technology Policy specified that scientific research collected with federal funds must be made open and available for use by the public. These moves have overwhelmed the existing infrastructures for digital archives, especially those focusing on endangered languages. This project will investigate a potentially transformative methodology and set of best practices to solve this challenge that enables researchers in linguistics and language documentation to organize and curate their own data collections. If successful, results will be broadly useful to endangered language researchers as well as related disciplines like anthropology, sociology and the digital humanities.  A transformation that facilitates the access and archiving of endangered language and other social science data would have a major positive impact on dissemination of data and further scholarship through re-use of the data. Exploring a solution that minimizes the financial impact while maximizing open access will offer a high value solution to a major challenge of the digital era.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Archive of the Indigenous Languages of Latin America (AILLA) is perfectly poised to carry out this project and confront the issue of the logjam of data.  AILLA is the foremost example of a regional digital language archive whose holdings are both large and easily accessible.  Founded in 2001 at the University of Texas at Austin, AILLA covers all of Latin America, home to several hundred endangered languages and the location of numerous language documentation projects, many funded by NSF and other federal agencies.  With portals in both English and Spanish, AILLA holdings are accessible to a wider audience than those of English-portal-only archives.  Project activities target a specific set of data collections, first to assess number and size of files and the level of organization for each individual deposit, and then to curate them. To gauge the extent of the data backlog facing the discipline on a wider scale, fellow member archives from the Digital Endangered Languages and Musics Archives Network (DELAMAN) will be surveyed regarding their workflows, repository organization, and types of backlogged collections. The information gleaned will be synthesized into a shared set of best practices, metadata, and methodologies, refined in consultation with DELAMAN archivists and disseminated through video tutorials on YouTube in both English and Spanish.  The resulting training has the potential to enable digital archives staff to quickly and easily add new data collections to the digital repositories. Faster and easier ingestion of data into digital repositories will both streamline the ingestion processes at digital repositories as well as increase accessibility and discoverability of data to fulfill the open access mandate. Additionally, the project will co-convene a gathering of representatives DELAMAN archives in 2018 at the Institute on Collaborative Language Research (CoLang) to highlight newly developed methodologies and to facilitate connections between archivists and the researchers with unarchived data collections. Archivist and CoPI Susan Smythe Kung will also conduct a CoLang workshop to disseminate results and train researchers. Other deliverables include a presentation at the Linguistic Society of America, designed to reach a broad audience in the language sciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1653380</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Woodbury</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony C Woodbury</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>acw@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124711701</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000155087</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Kung</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Kung</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>skung@austin.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124954604</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000640307</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~248039</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~40946</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In funding and academic environments where researchers are increasingly required to archive and share their research data, we saw a need to train language documenters to do this work so that the resulting archived language data collections would be well organized, well described, easy to navigate, and available for reuse in further research and education. To fill this gap in training, the PIs and the team at the Archive of the Indigenous Languages of Latin American (AILLA, <a href="https://ailla.utexas.org/">https://ailla.utexas.org/</a>) at the University of Texas at Austin, created a free, online open educational resource (OER) called Archiving for the Future: Simple Steps for Archiving Language Documentation Collections, available at <a href="https://archivingforthefuture.teachable.com/">https://archivingforthefuture.teachable.com/</a>.</p> <p>The course, which is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license, is a resource to aid people of all backgrounds in organizing born-digital and digitized language materials and data for deposit into <em>any</em> digital repository (not just AILLA) for long-term preservation and accessibility. The curriculum follows simple steps to guide participants through three phases of work to organize, appraise, and process language documentation materials for archiving, and it explains in detail what to do before, during, and after data collection to facilitate the long-term preservation of the data. The course is designed to be informative, engaging, and accessible to anyone, especially to those with no previous experience archiving collections of language materials or anything else. The target audience for this course is anyone who is engaged in creating materials in or about Indigenous, endangered, under-documented, or minority languages as part of language documentation efforts, including language rights, maintenance, and revitalization. It was designed particularly for individuals or groups made up of academic researchers and/or Indigenous or endangered language speakers and community members, though anyone who has any sort of data to manage and archive may benefit from it.&nbsp;</p> <p>This course was developed by four members of the AILLA team: Susan Smythe Kung, AILLA Manager and grant co-PI; Ryan Sullivant, AILLA Language Data Curator; Alicia Niwabaga, Graduate Research Assistant 2017-2018; and Elena Pojman, Undergraduate Research Assistant 2019-2020. The first steps were to research best practices in digital data management and archiving, and to interview representatives of various DELAMAN (<a href="https://www.delaman.org/">https://www.delaman.org/</a>) archives and other digital data repositories in the United States, the United Kingdom, the European Union, Australia, and Cameroon. Based on the research and interviews, we created a series of educational animated videos to illustrate key concepts of the work. These videos are available in English and Spanish on the AILLA YouTube channel (see the playlist at&nbsp;<a href="http://bit.ly/AFTFvideos">http://bit.ly/AFTFvideos</a>), and some of these videos have Portuguese subtitles. We incorporated the instructional videos and best practices into a four-day workshop on how to archive language documentation data, and we taught the workshop at the Institute on Collaborative Language Research (CoLang 2018) at the University of Florida in Gainesville during June 18-22, 2018. The next step was to adapt the live workshop into an online open educational resource. This work involved researching course management platforms and selecting one that could be adapted easily to accommodate translations of the course into additional languages; selecting photographs and creating graphics to illustrate the course content; writing additional lectures; and building and testing the course site.</p> <p>The final product, the OER Archiving for the Future: Simple Steps for Archiving Language Documentation Collections, is the first widely available guide for how to organize and archive language documentation data. Since the OER launched, the course has been completed by language documenters all over the world, and it is being used in language documentation training programs and field methods courses at the graduate, undergraduate, and professional levels in the United States, the United Kingdom, Mexico, and India. The availability of this OER means that more researchers will have the training and tools that they need to manage, organize and archive their research data. As more researchers archive their own research data, incrementally more data will be accessible for reuse by other researchers, allowing for research funding to have a broader impact overall.&nbsp;</p> <p>Additional work that was completed as part of this grant includes the addition of Indigenous language research data to over 30 collections in AILLA. These materials comprise data on 122 endangered Indigenous language varieties from nine Latin American countries. These research data are now accessible and may be reused by researchers and Indigenous Peoples to promote research and education in and about these languages. The catalog records in the AILLA digital repository are publicly accessible over the Internet; to access the digital files, a user must register for a free account and log in. Access to AILLA and the materials it contains is always free of charge, and the site has user interfaces in both English and Spanish. We invite you to explore the collections at <a href="https://ailla.utexas.org/">https://ailla.utexas.org/</a>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/22/2020<br>      Modified by: Susan&nbsp;Kung</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1653380/1653380_10454013_1608329055884_simple-steps-infographic--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1653380/1653380_10454013_1608329055884_simple-steps-infographic--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Simple Steps for Archiving Language Documentation Collections"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1653380/1653380_10454013_1608329055884_simple-steps-infographic--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Simple Steps for Archiving Language Documentation Collections"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The OER curriculum is based on 9 steps across 3 phases of research, as detailed in this infographic</div> <div class="imageCredit">Susan Kung, Ryan Sullivant, Elena Pojman, and Alicia Niwagaba</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Susan&nbsp;Kung</div> <div class="imageTitle">Simple Steps for Archiving Language Documentation Collections</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1653380/1653380_10454013_1608329388406_AFTF-OER--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1653380/1653380_10454013_1608329388406_AFTF-OER--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Screenshot of the OER"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1653380/1653380_10454013_1608329388406_AFTF-OER--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Screenshot of the OER"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This screenshot of the student interface shows the table of contents on the left, an embedded video at the top, and the text of the lecture at the bottom.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Susan Kung, Ryan Sullivant, Elena Pojman, and Alicia Niwagaba</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Susan&nbsp;Kung</div> <div class="imageTitle">Screenshot of the OER</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In funding and academic environments where researchers are increasingly required to archive and share their research data, we saw a need to train language documenters to do this work so that the resulting archived language data collections would be well organized, well described, easy to navigate, and available for reuse in further research and education. To fill this gap in training, the PIs and the team at the Archive of the Indigenous Languages of Latin American (AILLA, https://ailla.utexas.org/) at the University of Texas at Austin, created a free, online open educational resource (OER) called Archiving for the Future: Simple Steps for Archiving Language Documentation Collections, available at https://archivingforthefuture.teachable.com/.  The course, which is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license, is a resource to aid people of all backgrounds in organizing born-digital and digitized language materials and data for deposit into any digital repository (not just AILLA) for long-term preservation and accessibility. The curriculum follows simple steps to guide participants through three phases of work to organize, appraise, and process language documentation materials for archiving, and it explains in detail what to do before, during, and after data collection to facilitate the long-term preservation of the data. The course is designed to be informative, engaging, and accessible to anyone, especially to those with no previous experience archiving collections of language materials or anything else. The target audience for this course is anyone who is engaged in creating materials in or about Indigenous, endangered, under-documented, or minority languages as part of language documentation efforts, including language rights, maintenance, and revitalization. It was designed particularly for individuals or groups made up of academic researchers and/or Indigenous or endangered language speakers and community members, though anyone who has any sort of data to manage and archive may benefit from it.   This course was developed by four members of the AILLA team: Susan Smythe Kung, AILLA Manager and grant co-PI; Ryan Sullivant, AILLA Language Data Curator; Alicia Niwabaga, Graduate Research Assistant 2017-2018; and Elena Pojman, Undergraduate Research Assistant 2019-2020. The first steps were to research best practices in digital data management and archiving, and to interview representatives of various DELAMAN (https://www.delaman.org/) archives and other digital data repositories in the United States, the United Kingdom, the European Union, Australia, and Cameroon. Based on the research and interviews, we created a series of educational animated videos to illustrate key concepts of the work. These videos are available in English and Spanish on the AILLA YouTube channel (see the playlist at http://bit.ly/AFTFvideos), and some of these videos have Portuguese subtitles. We incorporated the instructional videos and best practices into a four-day workshop on how to archive language documentation data, and we taught the workshop at the Institute on Collaborative Language Research (CoLang 2018) at the University of Florida in Gainesville during June 18-22, 2018. The next step was to adapt the live workshop into an online open educational resource. This work involved researching course management platforms and selecting one that could be adapted easily to accommodate translations of the course into additional languages; selecting photographs and creating graphics to illustrate the course content; writing additional lectures; and building and testing the course site.  The final product, the OER Archiving for the Future: Simple Steps for Archiving Language Documentation Collections, is the first widely available guide for how to organize and archive language documentation data. Since the OER launched, the course has been completed by language documenters all over the world, and it is being used in language documentation training programs and field methods courses at the graduate, undergraduate, and professional levels in the United States, the United Kingdom, Mexico, and India. The availability of this OER means that more researchers will have the training and tools that they need to manage, organize and archive their research data. As more researchers archive their own research data, incrementally more data will be accessible for reuse by other researchers, allowing for research funding to have a broader impact overall.   Additional work that was completed as part of this grant includes the addition of Indigenous language research data to over 30 collections in AILLA. These materials comprise data on 122 endangered Indigenous language varieties from nine Latin American countries. These research data are now accessible and may be reused by researchers and Indigenous Peoples to promote research and education in and about these languages. The catalog records in the AILLA digital repository are publicly accessible over the Internet; to access the digital files, a user must register for a free account and log in. Access to AILLA and the materials it contains is always free of charge, and the site has user interfaces in both English and Spanish. We invite you to explore the collections at https://ailla.utexas.org/.             Last Modified: 12/22/2020       Submitted by: Susan Kung]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
