<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Judicial Independence and Interbranch Conflict in the American States</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>118367.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>118367</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brian Bornstein</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>All three branches of government play an important role within the system of separation of powers that defines government in the American states. While the judicial branch has been thought to be a check on the majoritarian power of the legislative and executive branches, state legislatures and executives have the ability to challenge the authority of state supreme (or high) courts through court-curbing legislation. Examples of court-curbing measures include shortening the terms of justices, allowing legislative review of judicial decisions, and eliminating the power of judicial review. This legislation is designed to limit the power of state courts, and to demonstrate the other branches' disapproval with judicial decisions. Consequently, this project will examine court-curbing legislation in the states, which will provide significant information on which branch controls policy outcomes in the American states, and on the extent of judicial independence.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will collect and make publicly available an original dataset on all court-curbing legislation and constitutional judicial decisions in the American states between 2005 and 2015. Analysis of the data will focus on how legislative and executive branches use court-curbing measures to constrain state high courts, and whether such legislation influences judicial decision making by limiting the power of judicial review. Institutional rules such as methods of judicial selection will be considered within the statistical analysis. Most prior research on judicial independence in the states primarily involves the selection and retention of judges. Instead, this project will focus on court-curbing legislation in order to examine judicial independence, interbranch conflict, and how states balance their legislative, executive and judicial powers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/03/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/03/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1654934</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Meghan</FirstName>
<LastName>Leonard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Meghan Leonard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mleonar@IllinoisState.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000700766</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Board of Trustees of Illinois State University</Name>
<CityName>Normal</CityName>
<ZipCode>617603040</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3094382528</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 S Fell Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Campus Box 3040]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001898142</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF TRUSTEES OF ILLINOIS STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001898142</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Illinois State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Normal</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>617903040</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Research and Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LSS-Law And Social Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~118367</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project <em>Judicial Independence and Interbranch Conflict in the American States</em> I undertake significant data collection efforts in order to research how court-curbing works in the American states.&nbsp; Court-curbing legislation is designed to reduce the power of a court, here state supreme courts, in a separation of powers system.&nbsp; In doing so, legislatures have the ability to limit the policy-making power of the court. &nbsp;We collected and coded over 1,900 court-curbing bills in the 50 states during the 2008-2016 period. In addition, over 4,000 state supreme court decisions were read to determine if the court exercised their power of judicial review. &nbsp;This data has been used in a series of conference papers and working papers that provide insights into the interactions between state supreme courts and their state legislative counterparts.</p> <p>Included here are four figures that provide some general information about this court-curbing legislation. Figure 1 shows the number of court-curbing bills introduced in each of the states over the nine-year period.&nbsp; Figure 2 provides information on who is introducing this court-curbing legislation.&nbsp; Here we can see that in the current moment, court-curbing legislation is introduced by Republican members of lower houses of the state legislatures. These bills have an average of 3.2 cosponsors, but only 17% of the bills have cosponsors of both parties. Figure 3 provides evidence that this legislation is introduced in states with all types of methods of selection and retention, but that court-curbing is most common in states with merit selection systems. Figure 4 demonstrates, as expected, that this legislation rarely moves passed the introductory stage, and very few pieces of it become law.</p> <p>In further examining the data, initial results show that court-curbing legislation is used as a threat in states with more independent judicial branches. Early results indicate that legislators introduce court-cubing bills when they are ideologically distant from the state supreme court. Figure 5 shows this relationship. Indeed, I have also found that in cases where a piece of court-curbing legislation became law, state supreme court are less likely to engage in (their central power) judicial review. From this, it is important to be clear that what is at stake is the balance of power in the American states. Checks on the court from the state legislature and governor are already built into the system of separation of powers. Should court-curbing be an additional check on the state supreme courts in the state, this could significantly limit the role of the court in the system.</p> <p>State supreme courts that lose independence and policy-making power in the separation of powers system in the states lose their ability to make decisions that protect political minorities. State supreme courts make decisions in all areas of law, including civil rights, civil liberties, and criminal law. In death penalty cases, they consider no less than life and death. While elected courts are designed to be responsive to the public, initial results from this project indicate that all courts are responsive to state legislatures that introduce court-curbing legislation. If our courts are supposed to be institutions designed to protect the rights of all, what we have learned can have enormous implications for how we understand the role of the courts as venues for voices that are otherwise unheard in state politics.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/23/2019<br>      Modified by: Meghan&nbsp;Leonard</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566600912878_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566600912878_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566600912878_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Court-curbing bills per state</div> <div class="imageCredit">Meghan Leonard</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Meghan&nbsp;Leonard</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566599225241_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566599225241_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566599225241_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Who introduces court curbing legislation</div> <div class="imageCredit">Meghan Leonard</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Meghan&nbsp;Leonard</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566601130424_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566601130424_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566601130424_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Introductions by method of selection and retention</div> <div class="imageCredit">Meghan Leonard</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Meghan&nbsp;Leonard</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566601178798_Figure4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566601178798_Figure4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566601178798_Figure4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Progress of court-curbing introductions</div> <div class="imageCredit">Meghan Leonard</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Meghan&nbsp;Leonard</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566601235398_Figure5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566601235398_Figure5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 5"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1654934/1654934_10485319_1566601235398_Figure5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 5"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Ideological distance and expected counts of court-curbing legislation</div> <div class="imageCredit">Meghan Leonard</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Meghan&nbsp;Leonard</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 5</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project Judicial Independence and Interbranch Conflict in the American States I undertake significant data collection efforts in order to research how court-curbing works in the American states.  Court-curbing legislation is designed to reduce the power of a court, here state supreme courts, in a separation of powers system.  In doing so, legislatures have the ability to limit the policy-making power of the court.  We collected and coded over 1,900 court-curbing bills in the 50 states during the 2008-2016 period. In addition, over 4,000 state supreme court decisions were read to determine if the court exercised their power of judicial review.  This data has been used in a series of conference papers and working papers that provide insights into the interactions between state supreme courts and their state legislative counterparts.  Included here are four figures that provide some general information about this court-curbing legislation. Figure 1 shows the number of court-curbing bills introduced in each of the states over the nine-year period.  Figure 2 provides information on who is introducing this court-curbing legislation.  Here we can see that in the current moment, court-curbing legislation is introduced by Republican members of lower houses of the state legislatures. These bills have an average of 3.2 cosponsors, but only 17% of the bills have cosponsors of both parties. Figure 3 provides evidence that this legislation is introduced in states with all types of methods of selection and retention, but that court-curbing is most common in states with merit selection systems. Figure 4 demonstrates, as expected, that this legislation rarely moves passed the introductory stage, and very few pieces of it become law.  In further examining the data, initial results show that court-curbing legislation is used as a threat in states with more independent judicial branches. Early results indicate that legislators introduce court-cubing bills when they are ideologically distant from the state supreme court. Figure 5 shows this relationship. Indeed, I have also found that in cases where a piece of court-curbing legislation became law, state supreme court are less likely to engage in (their central power) judicial review. From this, it is important to be clear that what is at stake is the balance of power in the American states. Checks on the court from the state legislature and governor are already built into the system of separation of powers. Should court-curbing be an additional check on the state supreme courts in the state, this could significantly limit the role of the court in the system.  State supreme courts that lose independence and policy-making power in the separation of powers system in the states lose their ability to make decisions that protect political minorities. State supreme courts make decisions in all areas of law, including civil rights, civil liberties, and criminal law. In death penalty cases, they consider no less than life and death. While elected courts are designed to be responsive to the public, initial results from this project indicate that all courts are responsive to state legislatures that introduce court-curbing legislation. If our courts are supposed to be institutions designed to protect the rights of all, what we have learned can have enormous implications for how we understand the role of the courts as venues for voices that are otherwise unheard in state politics.       Last Modified: 08/23/2019       Submitted by: Meghan Leonard]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
