<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Optimized Content Delivery Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project includes the commercialization of content delivery technology which enables a new generation of video streaming services and emerging services such as virtual reality, as well as accelerated web performance, media delivery, and cloud networking services.  This commercialization is expected to dramatically decrease bandwidth usage and operating cost for network operators.  It is expected to have direct and long-term impact on network architectures for content delivery and cloud computing applications.  It will also impact the training of graduate students in the areas of technology transition, intellectual property management, business development, and marketing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is expected to significantly advance the state of the art in algorithms and protocols which optimally use bandwidth and storage to improve content delivery performance in reducing user delay and decreasing bandwidth costs, in a scalable, distributed, and adaptive manner. Unlike most current solutions, the algorithms used here are optimized for multi-hop, multiple-data-source network settings.  When properly deployed, they will enable the delivery of a new generation of data-rich content and cloud computing services.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/18/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1654532</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edmund</FirstName>
<LastName>Yeh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edmund M Yeh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eyeh@ece.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173735400</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000413920</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[177-500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This I-Corps project focused on the commercialization of advanced algorithms and protocols for improving content delivery performance in a scalable, distributed, and adaptive manner, leading to reduced bandwidth costs and user delay for various network environments.&nbsp;</p> <p>Outcomes in the intellectual merit area include (1) development of jointly optimal, distributed, and adaptive request routing and caching algorithms for arbitrary network topologies, (2) enhancement of adaptive caching algorithms for improved latency performance, (3) online algorithms for physical-layer caching for improving wireless network performance, (4) integration and experimentation of advanced caching algorithms within local testbed environments.</p> <p>Outcomes in the broader impact area include (1) the potential commercialization of content delivery technology which enables a new generation of services such as virtual reality/augmented reality, high-resolution video streaming, automated driving, advanced manufacturing, implemented within content delivery networks and wireless cellular networks; (2) potentially dramatic decrease in bandwidth usage and operator cost for wireline and wireless network operators; (3) long-term impact on network architectures for content delivery and distributed computation, fog and mobile edge computing; (4) new architectures and algorithms for data access and delivery, as well as computation scheduling, in data-intensive science and engineering fields; (5) the training of graduate students in the areas of technology transition, intellectual property management, business development, and marketing.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/11/2020<br>      Modified by: Edmund&nbsp;M&nbsp;Yeh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This I-Corps project focused on the commercialization of advanced algorithms and protocols for improving content delivery performance in a scalable, distributed, and adaptive manner, leading to reduced bandwidth costs and user delay for various network environments.   Outcomes in the intellectual merit area include (1) development of jointly optimal, distributed, and adaptive request routing and caching algorithms for arbitrary network topologies, (2) enhancement of adaptive caching algorithms for improved latency performance, (3) online algorithms for physical-layer caching for improving wireless network performance, (4) integration and experimentation of advanced caching algorithms within local testbed environments.  Outcomes in the broader impact area include (1) the potential commercialization of content delivery technology which enables a new generation of services such as virtual reality/augmented reality, high-resolution video streaming, automated driving, advanced manufacturing, implemented within content delivery networks and wireless cellular networks; (2) potentially dramatic decrease in bandwidth usage and operator cost for wireline and wireless network operators; (3) long-term impact on network architectures for content delivery and distributed computation, fog and mobile edge computing; (4) new architectures and algorithms for data access and delivery, as well as computation scheduling, in data-intensive science and engineering fields; (5) the training of graduate students in the areas of technology transition, intellectual property management, business development, and marketing.       Last Modified: 06/11/2020       Submitted by: Edmund M Yeh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
