<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Reactive Processes and Turbulent Flows</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>85573.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>85573</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Holmer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The focus of the research component of this project is analytical study of models of reactive processes, such as combustion, taking place in fluid flow.  In recent years, there has been significant progress in the mathematical understanding of the effects of flow on combustion.  Nevertheless, the inherent complexity and richness of the phenomena continues to present a challenge to our study of this problem.  These models are given by nonlinear partial differential equations, in particular, by reaction-diffusion equations which may also be coupled to equations of fluid dynamics.  One of the goals of the proposed research  is a continuation of previous work on passive combustion in periodic, random, as well as general inhomogeneous media.  The main questions of interest include the effects of flows on mixing and on speed-up of propagation of reaction.  In addition, simplified models will be considered and experience gained from their study will be applied to the original problems.  Another goal of the project is the study of propagation of reaction in a model of active combustion, with direct feedback of reaction on the fluid motion via the buoyancy force and gravity-induced mixing.  In many situations this effect cannot be ignored, particularly in highly turbulent combustion regimes.  Although this is a very difficult problem, limited progress has been achieved recently and it is proposed here to build upon these results.  The developed techniques will also be applied to the study of other related models, including systems of reaction-diffusion equations and a model of liquid suspensions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Reactive processes, such as burning in internal combustion engines, nuclear reactions in stars, and forest fires, are ubiquitous in nature.  Their study is relevant to several branches of science and engineering such as astrophysics, biology, environmental science, and chemical engineering.  The research proposed here focuses on the influence of the motion of the underlying medium, such as fluid flow, on the speed of spreading of reactive processes.  It aims at improving our understanding of fundamental mathematical models describing such processes, which may provide useful qualitative insights into real life phenomena.  An important part of this proposal is its educational component.  The principal investigator (PI) plans to develop an undergraduate partial differential equations (PDE) course at the University of Wisconsin, mentor undergraduate mathematics majors in the study of advanced topics, and organize a Research Experience for Undergraduates program in analysis and PDEs.  The PI will also teach specialized graduate courses and involve graduate students in working under his supervision.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1656269</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrej</FirstName>
<LastName>Zlatos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrej Zlatos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>azlatos@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585344419</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488185</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~85573</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The PI's research supported under this award involved study of mathematical models for reactive processes, mixing, and fluid dynamics.&nbsp; <br /><br />Reactive processes such as forest fires, chemical kinetics, or population dynamics are modeled by reaction-diffusion equations, and the PI studied the dynamics of their solutions.&nbsp; He showed that in one spatial dimension, modeling propagation of reactions in narrow channels, most solutions eventually propagate in the same way under fairly general hypotheses.&nbsp; In particular, there frequently is a special solution called transition front that attracts the dynamics of most other solutions.&nbsp; He also showed that in one as well as several dimensions, homogenization frequently occurs when the reactive medium has a periodic or random structure.&nbsp; This means that effects of the small scale structure average out on large space-time scales, and solutions to the equation appear to propagate in an averaged homogeneous (i.e., devoid of structure) environment on these scales.<br /><br />Mixing of substances in fluid media is modeled by transport equations, and the PI studied those transporting velocity fields that are most efficient in mixing.&nbsp; One of the main contributions is construction of universal mixers in all dimensions, incompressible flows that mix arbitrarily well all possible initial distributions of the mixed substance as time grows.&nbsp; Moreover, the scales to which the substance is sufficiently well mixed decrease very quickly - exponentially - in time, which is the best possible mixing rate.<br /><br />The motion of fluids is modeled by equations such as Euler or SQG equations.&nbsp; These are some of the longest studied partial differential equations in mathematics and physics, yet some fundamental open questions about their solutions remain unanswered.&nbsp; One of the most important is the question of possibility of finite time singularities in these models.&nbsp; The PI studied it for the related modified SQG patch equations and showed that in some od them, finite time singularities can indeed occur.&nbsp; This is the first result of this type, and a springboard to future work in the area.<br /><br />The research resulting from this award is important from the theoretical perspective but also has an interdisciplinary character.&nbsp; In particular, it contributed to a better understanding of mathematical models describing physical phenomena of interest to several branches of science and engineering such as astrophysics, biology, environmental science, or fluid mechanics.&nbsp; The PI also mentored the research work of twelve students and postdocs supported by the award, some of whom are members of groups underrepresented in mathematics.&nbsp; This effort, which resulted in ten research papers, has contributed to the training of future workforce in one of the crucial STEM areas.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/05/2018<br>      Modified by: Andrej&nbsp;Zlatos</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The PI's research supported under this award involved study of mathematical models for reactive processes, mixing, and fluid dynamics.    Reactive processes such as forest fires, chemical kinetics, or population dynamics are modeled by reaction-diffusion equations, and the PI studied the dynamics of their solutions.  He showed that in one spatial dimension, modeling propagation of reactions in narrow channels, most solutions eventually propagate in the same way under fairly general hypotheses.  In particular, there frequently is a special solution called transition front that attracts the dynamics of most other solutions.  He also showed that in one as well as several dimensions, homogenization frequently occurs when the reactive medium has a periodic or random structure.  This means that effects of the small scale structure average out on large space-time scales, and solutions to the equation appear to propagate in an averaged homogeneous (i.e., devoid of structure) environment on these scales.  Mixing of substances in fluid media is modeled by transport equations, and the PI studied those transporting velocity fields that are most efficient in mixing.  One of the main contributions is construction of universal mixers in all dimensions, incompressible flows that mix arbitrarily well all possible initial distributions of the mixed substance as time grows.  Moreover, the scales to which the substance is sufficiently well mixed decrease very quickly - exponentially - in time, which is the best possible mixing rate.  The motion of fluids is modeled by equations such as Euler or SQG equations.  These are some of the longest studied partial differential equations in mathematics and physics, yet some fundamental open questions about their solutions remain unanswered.  One of the most important is the question of possibility of finite time singularities in these models.  The PI studied it for the related modified SQG patch equations and showed that in some od them, finite time singularities can indeed occur.  This is the first result of this type, and a springboard to future work in the area.  The research resulting from this award is important from the theoretical perspective but also has an interdisciplinary character.  In particular, it contributed to a better understanding of mathematical models describing physical phenomena of interest to several branches of science and engineering such as astrophysics, biology, environmental science, or fluid mechanics.  The PI also mentored the research work of twelve students and postdocs supported by the award, some of whom are members of groups underrepresented in mathematics.  This effort, which resulted in ten research papers, has contributed to the training of future workforce in one of the crucial STEM areas.       Last Modified: 10/05/2018       Submitted by: Andrej Zlatos]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
