<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I/UCRC:  Full Center Grant: I/UCRC for Cyber-Physical Systems for the Hospital Operating Room</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>475508.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>674995</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Behrooz Shirazi</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bshirazi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928343</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed center seeks to establish a new Industry/University Cooperative Research Center (I/UCRC) addressing the research of cyber-physical systems for use in the hospital and operating room environments. The center will focus on computational science and technologies to advance, develop and promote research into the principles and technology of computational surgery science.  This will be achieved through research, development, education, and technology exchange among academic, industry, hospitals and government entities via the I/UCRC framework.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The new center seeks to address an interdisciplinary area of central national economic importance. The center will endeavor to create a confluence of computational science, robotics, biomedical engineering, and medical expertise to positively impact the delivery of quality procedural and surgical interventions.  The proposed center has the potential to bring together a diverse set of member companies and academics to achieve its goals as well as spawn new start-ups.  The center plans to leverage an international network and new curriculum in computational surgery in order to achieve research and student impact.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1657550</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
<LastName>Garbey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marc Garbey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mgarbey2@houstonmethodist.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7134493693</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000311076</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The Methodist Hospital Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770302703</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7134417885</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6565 Fannin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MGJ4-024]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>185641052</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>METHODIST HOSPITAL, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>074172719</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Methodist Hospital research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770302703</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8039</Code>
<Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~270639</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~204869</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~199487</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>The Center for CyBer-physical systems for the Hospital Operating Room (CyBHOR) vision is to provide the forum for industry/hospital/university cooperative research on the further development, validation, and industrial implementation of the emerging concepts in the design of operating rooms, and in the optimization of procedural and surgical interventions. This center is the strong arm of Modern Surgery enabled by computational science and technologies.</p> <p>The Mission of the NSF Center for CyBHOR is:</p> <p>?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To advance, develop and promote research into the principles and technologies of computational surgery science through research, development, education, and technology exchange among academic, industry, hospital and government entities;</p> <p>?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To increase the quantity and quality of the professionals prepared to work in the area;</p> <p>?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To involve the faculty of the Houston Methodist Research Institute (HMRI) and the University of Florida (UF) and affiliated hospitals in research in areas of common interest to Sponsors;</p> <p>?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To perform research that will allow CyBHOR facilities and new procedural and surgical interventions to be competitive in the world economy.</p> <p>The center benefits from a vibrant interdisciplinary team of computational scientists and faculties in surgery who will work in synergy with the health industry to improve patient care.&nbsp; This center promotes the application of mathematics and algorithm design, enabling imaging, robotics, informatics, and simulation technologies incorporating biological and physical principles, to improve surgery.</p> <p><strong>Broad Impact</strong></p> <p>The center operates at the core of the Texas Medical Center that is the largest medical center in the world, and benefits from the site in the University of Florida Gainesville that has been a champion to attract business startups in bioengineering and encourage technology transfer. The center benefits from the forty-million-dollar infrastructure of the Methodist Institute for Technology Innovation and Education (MITIE) that trains about 4000 surgeons per year coming from all over the world. The center benefits of an international network in computational surgery that funded multiple exchange program for graduate students and an international master degree and is expanding with the ENMED program of Texas A&amp;M (<a href="https://enmed.tamu.edu/">https://enmed.tamu.edu/</a>).</p> <p>CyBHOR encourages the transfer of technologies to the marketplace with spin-off startup companies and keeps growing its alumni network with graduate students who found their way to a number of medical devices and health IT companies, and hospital systems.</p> <p>To the extent that projects funded under the CyBHOR improve effectiveness and efficiency of healthcare, a $2.6-trillion-per-year industry that employs 15 million people, and has the potential for a very positive societal impact. Resulting in improved patient outcomes through better equipment and hands-on surgical training may reduce an estimated 200,000 preventable deaths per year and provide substantial cost savings to hospitals and patients alike. CyBHOR contribute to the development of human resources by improving training and broader access to novel surgical techniques. CyBHOR projects has provided funding for approximately 8 graduate students per year and involved as many as twenty students per year through our new curriculum in computational surgery with Texas A&amp;M, including unfunded or otherwise-funded collaborating students. As medical research is inherently interdisciplinary, these students are exposed to multiple facets of academia, medicine, and the medical industry. These graduate students will be encouraged to interact with industrial partners and others within the center to promote professional development. Students have been included in center meetings and periodic seminars from industrial, clinical, and scientific partners.</p> <p>Beyond the healthcare effects and development of human resources (both clinicians and researchers), novel pre-competitive research projects funded through the center will lead to products that help to increase the competitiveness of U.S. industry, specifically providers of healthcare products, through increased innovation. This center foster research that will be eligible for STTR/SBIR funding opportunities, thus generating the translation of these high-risk, high-reward projects.</p> <p>While students involved in research through the center have learned directly through that participation, publishable results from center-funded projects will provide engaging case studies of health-care applications that can be incorporated into courses at the undergraduate and graduate levels, and thus reach even more students.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/25/2019<br>      Modified by: Marc&nbsp;Garbey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  The Center for CyBer-physical systems for the Hospital Operating Room (CyBHOR) vision is to provide the forum for industry/hospital/university cooperative research on the further development, validation, and industrial implementation of the emerging concepts in the design of operating rooms, and in the optimization of procedural and surgical interventions. This center is the strong arm of Modern Surgery enabled by computational science and technologies.  The Mission of the NSF Center for CyBHOR is:  ?           To advance, develop and promote research into the principles and technologies of computational surgery science through research, development, education, and technology exchange among academic, industry, hospital and government entities;  ?           To increase the quantity and quality of the professionals prepared to work in the area;  ?           To involve the faculty of the Houston Methodist Research Institute (HMRI) and the University of Florida (UF) and affiliated hospitals in research in areas of common interest to Sponsors;  ?           To perform research that will allow CyBHOR facilities and new procedural and surgical interventions to be competitive in the world economy.  The center benefits from a vibrant interdisciplinary team of computational scientists and faculties in surgery who will work in synergy with the health industry to improve patient care.  This center promotes the application of mathematics and algorithm design, enabling imaging, robotics, informatics, and simulation technologies incorporating biological and physical principles, to improve surgery.  Broad Impact  The center operates at the core of the Texas Medical Center that is the largest medical center in the world, and benefits from the site in the University of Florida Gainesville that has been a champion to attract business startups in bioengineering and encourage technology transfer. The center benefits from the forty-million-dollar infrastructure of the Methodist Institute for Technology Innovation and Education (MITIE) that trains about 4000 surgeons per year coming from all over the world. The center benefits of an international network in computational surgery that funded multiple exchange program for graduate students and an international master degree and is expanding with the ENMED program of Texas A&amp;M (https://enmed.tamu.edu/).  CyBHOR encourages the transfer of technologies to the marketplace with spin-off startup companies and keeps growing its alumni network with graduate students who found their way to a number of medical devices and health IT companies, and hospital systems.  To the extent that projects funded under the CyBHOR improve effectiveness and efficiency of healthcare, a $2.6-trillion-per-year industry that employs 15 million people, and has the potential for a very positive societal impact. Resulting in improved patient outcomes through better equipment and hands-on surgical training may reduce an estimated 200,000 preventable deaths per year and provide substantial cost savings to hospitals and patients alike. CyBHOR contribute to the development of human resources by improving training and broader access to novel surgical techniques. CyBHOR projects has provided funding for approximately 8 graduate students per year and involved as many as twenty students per year through our new curriculum in computational surgery with Texas A&amp;M, including unfunded or otherwise-funded collaborating students. As medical research is inherently interdisciplinary, these students are exposed to multiple facets of academia, medicine, and the medical industry. These graduate students will be encouraged to interact with industrial partners and others within the center to promote professional development. Students have been included in center meetings and periodic seminars from industrial, clinical, and scientific partners.  Beyond the healthcare effects and development of human resources (both clinicians and researchers), novel pre-competitive research projects funded through the center will lead to products that help to increase the competitiveness of U.S. industry, specifically providers of healthcare products, through increased innovation. This center foster research that will be eligible for STTR/SBIR funding opportunities, thus generating the translation of these high-risk, high-reward projects.  While students involved in research through the center have learned directly through that participation, publishable results from center-funded projects will provide engaging case studies of health-care applications that can be incorporated into courses at the undergraduate and graduate levels, and thus reach even more students.             Last Modified: 04/25/2019       Submitted by: Marc Garbey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
