<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Hydraulic Control and Mixing of the Deep Ocean Flow through the Samoan Passage</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>247880.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>247880</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Baris Uz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bmuz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924557</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The large-scale circulation of the ocean also known as the Meridional Overturning Circulation (MOC) comprises a series of shallow and deep water currents that transport mass, heat, carbon, and nutrients around the globe. The Samoan Passage, which carries the majority of the transport in its deep northward branch, is an important element of the Pacific Ocean circulation system. Recent observations supported by a previously funded NSF project have identified a previously unknown split of the flow between a deeper eastern channel and multiple shallower, western pathways within the Samoan Passage complex. Additional changes such as a warming and weakening of the flow through the passage have also been observed over the past twenty years, which supports the need for long-term observations.  This project will examine the dynamics of the flow through the Samoan Passage in detail using a combination of observations, theory and numerical models. Currently, there are no deep ocean monitoring system deployed in the Pacific MOC and this project has the potential to aid in the development of an observing system that can complement the one currently deployed in the Atlantic. Climate models predict a weakening of the global overturning circulation, which could be confirmed or refuted with these observing systems. The knowledge gained from the proposed work can likely be applied to similar deep passages and fracture zones around the world. Two early career scientists, summer undergraduates, a graduate student and a post-doctoral researcher will gain valuable training in modern methods used in oceanography through this project.  Diverse outreach activities are planned to engage the public with the results and knowledge gained from this project through collaborations with a modern dance company, and the Birch Aquarium and a high school in San Diego.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Extensive measurements collected under previous NSF funding, including a combination of moored time series and deep towed measurements will be used to study hydraulic effects on the flow in the Samoan Passage. Strong turbulent mixing was observed as the flow passes through and over various constrictions and sills, thereby substantially altering its water mass characteristics. The recent measurements indicate hydraulic criticality of the flow through the Samoan Passage, at least at one major sill. The three specific objectives of this project include: investigating the influence of hydraulic processes on mixing and friction at various sills, studying hydraulic criticality and implications for transport and partition of the flow through and around the Samoan Passage, and informing an efficient monitoring strategy for the flow through the Samoan Passage. As a result of this project, hydraulic theory will be improved and observationally validated, making it applicable to dense overflows in other passages and to the flow in the multitude of fracture zones that are believed to be important drivers for abyssal upwelling.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1657870</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
<LastName>Pratt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lawrence J Pratt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lpratt@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5082892540</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000336603</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<ZipCode>025431535</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082892623</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>266 Wood Hole Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Fenno House, MS#39]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001766682</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WOODS HOLE OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTITUTION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001766682</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution]]></Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>025431535</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[266 Woods Hole Road, MS #21]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~247880</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The ocean has an overturning circulation in which dense waters that form at high latitudes as a result of cooling and ice formation sink and become part of a complex network of deep currents that carry water all over the globe and eventually back to the surface. The overturning circulation is an important player in determination of Earth's climate. &nbsp;The North Pacific Ocean is unusual in that it does not produce water that sinks all the way to the bottom: the bottom water instead comes the Southern Ocean in the form of a deep northward current. All of this water is funneled through a choke point just south of the Equator: the Samoan Passage and two neighboring passages (Figures 1 and 2). The main purpose of this project was to analyze recent measurements of the flow in Samoan Passage in order to quatify and better understand the volume transport and its variability, the causes of mixing with other water masses and the overall importance of this mixing, and the factors that determine how the flow is distributed betwenn the two main passages: the Samoan Passage and the region east of the Manihiki Plateau. The data had previously been collected as part of a three-year campaign that involved three cruises and an array of measurements of water properties, velocities, and turbulence.&nbsp;</p> <p>The main advancements include an idealized model (FIg. 3) explaing why roughly 5-6 Sv. (1 Sv. = 1 million cubic meters per second) of transpoft passes directly through the Samoan Passage, whereas another 2.8 Sv. is diverted around the Manihiki Plateau. This partitioning is important because the flow through the Samoan Passage spills over multiple sills (Figure 4), creating turbulent mixing with warmer overlying water, whereas the Manihiki branch is slower and does not esperience overflows. Another outcome of the project is a map showing where mixing hotspots occur within the Samoan Passage (Figure 5). &nbsp;As one can see, the topography is complex and there are several routs that the throughflow can take, each with its own set of sills and bumps. Identificaiton of the hotspots leads to evaluation of the physical mechnisms responsible for the mixing. This list includes hydraulic jumps, shear flow instabilities, breaking of lee waves, and generation at the bottom. &nbsp;A surprising finding is that the general level of mixing remains temporally constant even as the overall volume transport fluctuates. &nbsp;We also present an estimate suggesting that the mixing accounts for more than half of the total mixing that bottom waters experience during their transit through the South and North Pacific.&nbsp;</p> <p>We have also tried to better understand how it is possible that one branch of a deep flow can be hydraulically controlled while the other not so. &nbsp;An idealized model suggests that while possible, this situation requires a rethinking of the that deep sill flow play in the regulation of abyssal flows. Instead of influencing the flow far upstream, the way that a dam backs up the flow in a reservoir, the sills in the Samoan Passage influence how much water is diverted around the Manihiki Plateau. These considerations would inform the use of hydraulic principles to design an instrument array for monitoring the deep transport, a desirable activity for those interested in detecting climate change in the deepenst limb of the Pacific overturning circulation. &nbsp;</p> <p>Our project also engaged in an outreach activity intended to bring ocean science to disadvantaged youth in a fun way (Figure 6). &nbsp;We set up a two-week class for 5th and 6th grade students who live in southern California and come from families that live beneith the poverty level. The course was offered though A Step Beyond, an Escondido, CA nonprofit, and we used lectures, embodied learning &nbsp;and a field tripin to excite interest among the students in physical oceanography. The group was largely hispanic and was co-taught with a dance instructor. &nbsp;The class was co-taught by Pratt and Roxanne Rojas de Blanco, a dance teacher who works in the San Diego public school system. &nbsp;Gunnar Voet from the Samoan Passage team guided the students on a field trip to the Scripps Institute of Oceanography.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/06/2020<br>      Modified by: Lawrence&nbsp;J&nbsp;Pratt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591478748165_Figure1_Map--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591478748165_Figure1_Map--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591478748165_Figure1_Map--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map showing the location of the Samoan Passage and the Manihiki Plateau.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Larry Pratt</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lawrence&nbsp;J&nbsp;Pratt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591486930504_Figure2_transports--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591486930504_Figure2_transports--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591486930504_Figure2_transports--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The three main passages that channel the deepest limb of the Pacific meridional overturning circulation northward. The volume fluxes are historical estimates taken from Roemmich et al. 1996.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Samoan Passage Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lawrence&nbsp;J&nbsp;Pratt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591487348822_Figure3_Idealized_Samoan_Mahihiki.v3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591487348822_Figure3_Idealized_Samoan_Mahihiki.v3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591487348822_Figure3_Idealized_Samoan_Mahihiki.v3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The model used to estimate the volume transport to the east of the Manihiki Plateau is based on an integral constraint. The path of the integration is a closed contour (dashed curve) that circles the plateau and touches the equator, shown in an idealized setting.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Pratt, et al. (2019)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lawrence&nbsp;J&nbsp;Pratt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591487867005_Figure4_overflows--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591487867005_Figure4_overflows--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591487867005_Figure4_overflows--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A side view of northward (left-to-right) flow in the eastern channel of the Samoan Passage. Velocities are shown by colors and energy dissipation values are shown in the stick diagrams. The flow accelerates and experiences enhanced dissipation where it spills over the two sills.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Pratt et al. (2019) and based on Alford et al. (2013)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lawrence&nbsp;J&nbsp;Pratt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591488038342_Figure5_mixing--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591488038342_Figure5_mixing--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 5"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591488038342_Figure5_mixing--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 5"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A detailed plan view showing the mixing hot spots in the Samoan Passage. Each box shows a vertical profile of the rates of energy dissipation measured at a particular location.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Carter et al., 2020.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lawrence&nbsp;J&nbsp;Pratt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 5</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591488730194_Figure6_Workshop_for_Kids--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591488730194_Figure6_Workshop_for_Kids--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 6"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1657870/1657870_10476065_1591488730194_Figure6_Workshop_for_Kids--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 6"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students who participated in the two-week class on ocean science, taught by Larry Pratt and Roxanne Rojas de Blanco through A Step Beyond (Escondido CA.) The student were from families living below the poverty level. Dr. Gunnar Voet and Pratt stand in the rear.</div> <div class="imageCredit">photo by R. Rojas de Blanco</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lawrence&nbsp;J&nbsp;Pratt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 6</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The ocean has an overturning circulation in which dense waters that form at high latitudes as a result of cooling and ice formation sink and become part of a complex network of deep currents that carry water all over the globe and eventually back to the surface. The overturning circulation is an important player in determination of Earth's climate.  The North Pacific Ocean is unusual in that it does not produce water that sinks all the way to the bottom: the bottom water instead comes the Southern Ocean in the form of a deep northward current. All of this water is funneled through a choke point just south of the Equator: the Samoan Passage and two neighboring passages (Figures 1 and 2). The main purpose of this project was to analyze recent measurements of the flow in Samoan Passage in order to quatify and better understand the volume transport and its variability, the causes of mixing with other water masses and the overall importance of this mixing, and the factors that determine how the flow is distributed betwenn the two main passages: the Samoan Passage and the region east of the Manihiki Plateau. The data had previously been collected as part of a three-year campaign that involved three cruises and an array of measurements of water properties, velocities, and turbulence.   The main advancements include an idealized model (FIg. 3) explaing why roughly 5-6 Sv. (1 Sv. = 1 million cubic meters per second) of transpoft passes directly through the Samoan Passage, whereas another 2.8 Sv. is diverted around the Manihiki Plateau. This partitioning is important because the flow through the Samoan Passage spills over multiple sills (Figure 4), creating turbulent mixing with warmer overlying water, whereas the Manihiki branch is slower and does not esperience overflows. Another outcome of the project is a map showing where mixing hotspots occur within the Samoan Passage (Figure 5).  As one can see, the topography is complex and there are several routs that the throughflow can take, each with its own set of sills and bumps. Identificaiton of the hotspots leads to evaluation of the physical mechnisms responsible for the mixing. This list includes hydraulic jumps, shear flow instabilities, breaking of lee waves, and generation at the bottom.  A surprising finding is that the general level of mixing remains temporally constant even as the overall volume transport fluctuates.  We also present an estimate suggesting that the mixing accounts for more than half of the total mixing that bottom waters experience during their transit through the South and North Pacific.   We have also tried to better understand how it is possible that one branch of a deep flow can be hydraulically controlled while the other not so.  An idealized model suggests that while possible, this situation requires a rethinking of the that deep sill flow play in the regulation of abyssal flows. Instead of influencing the flow far upstream, the way that a dam backs up the flow in a reservoir, the sills in the Samoan Passage influence how much water is diverted around the Manihiki Plateau. These considerations would inform the use of hydraulic principles to design an instrument array for monitoring the deep transport, a desirable activity for those interested in detecting climate change in the deepenst limb of the Pacific overturning circulation.    Our project also engaged in an outreach activity intended to bring ocean science to disadvantaged youth in a fun way (Figure 6).  We set up a two-week class for 5th and 6th grade students who live in southern California and come from families that live beneith the poverty level. The course was offered though A Step Beyond, an Escondido, CA nonprofit, and we used lectures, embodied learning  and a field tripin to excite interest among the students in physical oceanography. The group was largely hispanic and was co-taught with a dance instructor.  The class was co-taught by Pratt and Roxanne Rojas de Blanco, a dance teacher who works in the San Diego public school system.  Gunnar Voet from the Samoan Passage team guided the students on a field trip to the Scripps Institute of Oceanography.        Last Modified: 06/06/2020       Submitted by: Lawrence J Pratt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
