<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CRII: Cyberlearning: Automatic Discovery of Optimal Progressions of Language Content</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>174999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>190999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tatiana Korelsky</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tkorelsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A key challenge in education is determining the optimal sequence of concepts to present to a student. This is particularly important for second language learning, where there is a huge amount of content to learn and it is difficult for learners to stay engaged. Although researchers in education and psychology have identified guiding principles for sequencing learning materials, there is a lack of pragmatic techniques that can apply these principles to build effective learning progressions automatically. To address this gap, this project will: (1) develop techniques for estimating the difficulty of language learning content, (2) identify important characteristics of various expert-crafted progressions, and (3) experiment to find optimal progressions for individual students. These progressions will enhance the effectiveness of online interactive learning tools that are freely accessible to the public. The anticipated discovery of general principles of pacing will benefit educators and provide the foundation for maximizing engagement in adaptive learning systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will conduct three investigations in order to build adaptive learning progressions. First, the project will build a library of language materials that are organized by difficulty. To do this, the PI will explore procedural models of target linguistic knowledge such as grammar, identify which procedural steps are necessary for understanding specific materials, and organize these materials into skill trees. Second, the project will develop a set of control parameters that capture key aspects of pacing and sequencing. This will allow the PI to extract pacing strategies from expert-crafted progressions, and map these strategies onto other progressions. Third, the project will optimize progressions for individual learners by conducting large-scale multivariate experiments in online interactive learning tools.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1657176</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
<LastName>Andersen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erik L Andersen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ela63@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9193572291</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000688780</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148537501</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[107 Hoy Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>026Y</Code>
<Text>CRII CISE Research Initiation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8045</Code>
<Text>Cyberlearn &amp; Future Learn Tech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8228</Code>
<Text>CISE Resrch Initiatn Initiatve</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~190999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A key challenge in education is determining the optimal sequence of concepts to present to a student. This is particularly important for second language learning, where there is a huge amount of content to learn and it is difficult for learners to stay engaged. Although researchers have identified guiding principles for sequencing learning materials, there is a lack of pragmatic techniques that can apply these principles to build effective learning progressions automatically. To address this gap, this project: (1) developed techniques for estimating the difficulty of language learning content, (2) identified important characteristics of various expert-crafted progressions, and (3) experimented to find optimal progressions for individual students. These techniques will enhance the effectiveness of online games and tools that are freely accessible to the public. Discovery of general principles of pacing will hopefully benefit educators and provide the foundation for maximizing engagement in adaptive learning systems.</p> <p><br />In order to build adaptive learning progressions, this project conducted three investigations. First, we explored data structures that can facilitate the construction of smooth learning progressions for individual learners who have mastered specific subsets of language skills. More specifically, we attempted to identify when the language skills required to understand one material are a subset or superset of the skills required to understand another material, and used these hierarchical relationships to organize materials into skill trees. Since strict subsets and supersets become rarer in a corpus as the knowledge model grows to incorporate additional language skills, we examined how far we could relax these difficulty ordering constraints before the quality of stipulated difficulty relationships deteriorated to an unacceptable level. Using these techniques, we built two language-based skill trees: one that organizes online Japanese news articles based on vocabulary, and one that organizes simple Korean noun phrases based on both vocabulary and grammar.</p> <p><br />Second, the project developed a set of control parameters that capture key aspects of pacing and sequencing. In particular, we identified a key feature of some successful progressions: goal-drivenness, or the degree to which the progression rapidly builds to difficult problems to provide a sense of accomplishment. We designed an algorithm that generates goal-driven progressions automatically and applied this to our Korean noun phrase skill tree to generate goal-based progressions for a video game.</p> <p><br />Third, the project optimized progressions for individual learners by conducting experiments in online tools and games. An experiment in an online article recommendation tool showed that an adaptive recommendation-based algorithm and an assessment-based recommendation algorithm led users to read more articles than a non-adaptive recommendation algorithm that started from the simplest phrases and grew more complicated. An experiment in a Korean language game showed that our automatically generated goal-driven progression performed similarly to a human-designed progression.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/31/2019<br>      Modified by: Erik&nbsp;L&nbsp;Andersen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A key challenge in education is determining the optimal sequence of concepts to present to a student. This is particularly important for second language learning, where there is a huge amount of content to learn and it is difficult for learners to stay engaged. Although researchers have identified guiding principles for sequencing learning materials, there is a lack of pragmatic techniques that can apply these principles to build effective learning progressions automatically. To address this gap, this project: (1) developed techniques for estimating the difficulty of language learning content, (2) identified important characteristics of various expert-crafted progressions, and (3) experimented to find optimal progressions for individual students. These techniques will enhance the effectiveness of online games and tools that are freely accessible to the public. Discovery of general principles of pacing will hopefully benefit educators and provide the foundation for maximizing engagement in adaptive learning systems.   In order to build adaptive learning progressions, this project conducted three investigations. First, we explored data structures that can facilitate the construction of smooth learning progressions for individual learners who have mastered specific subsets of language skills. More specifically, we attempted to identify when the language skills required to understand one material are a subset or superset of the skills required to understand another material, and used these hierarchical relationships to organize materials into skill trees. Since strict subsets and supersets become rarer in a corpus as the knowledge model grows to incorporate additional language skills, we examined how far we could relax these difficulty ordering constraints before the quality of stipulated difficulty relationships deteriorated to an unacceptable level. Using these techniques, we built two language-based skill trees: one that organizes online Japanese news articles based on vocabulary, and one that organizes simple Korean noun phrases based on both vocabulary and grammar.   Second, the project developed a set of control parameters that capture key aspects of pacing and sequencing. In particular, we identified a key feature of some successful progressions: goal-drivenness, or the degree to which the progression rapidly builds to difficult problems to provide a sense of accomplishment. We designed an algorithm that generates goal-driven progressions automatically and applied this to our Korean noun phrase skill tree to generate goal-based progressions for a video game.   Third, the project optimized progressions for individual learners by conducting experiments in online tools and games. An experiment in an online article recommendation tool showed that an adaptive recommendation-based algorithm and an assessment-based recommendation algorithm led users to read more articles than a non-adaptive recommendation algorithm that started from the simplest phrases and grew more complicated. An experiment in a Korean language game showed that our automatically generated goal-driven progression performed similarly to a human-designed progression.       Last Modified: 05/31/2019       Submitted by: Erik L Andersen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
