<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Advanced imaging techniques combined with in situ analyses used to assess diagenesis in benthic foraminifera</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>297274.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>297274</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Candace Major</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cmajor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927597</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Much of our knowledge of the Earth's climate of the past ~100 million years is deduced from shells of marine microorganisms called foraminifera. These single-celled organisms are ubiquitous in the world's oceans and live either in the upper water column (planktic) or on the sea floor (benthic). After their life-cycle is completed, the sand-grain-sized calcite shells are fossilized and contribute substantially to marine sediments. This rich fossil record, combined with the well-studied relationship between environmental parameters and shell-chemistry, make foraminifera a primary climate archive. While chemical and isotopic data collected from benthic and planktic foraminifer shells provide a largely consistent record of the Earth's past climate variability, these paleorecords may be slightly biased, as the chemical composition of fossil shells may be modified after being deposited for millions of years in the sediment column. A precise assessment of this bias could significantly improve critical applications of societal importance such as model simulation of past sea level or ice sheets, as these models strongly rely on the quality of paleoclimate data.  This project will apply advanced technological analytical tools to document the magnitude of this bias in chemical composition resulting from alteration of fossil shells. The project will support and train a female graduate student in the research.  Project outreach activities include museum quality displays for the Lamont Core Repository and Open House.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Previous studies suggest that certain domains within foraminifera shells are better preserved than the remaining material, and thus provide a robust record of past environmental parameters. However, these well-preserved domains are inaccessible by conventional analytical approaches that require analysis of whole shells. Thus, conventional "whole-shell" data represent the averaged chemical composition of different generations of shell calcite from a potentially large preservational range. Recent innovations in the combined use of high-magnification imaging by scanning electron microscope (SEM), cathodoluminescence (CL)-spectrometry, secondary ion mass spectrometry (SIMS), and electron probe microanalyzer (EPMA) now allows the identification and chemical analyses of both well-preserved and altered domains in single foraminifera shells. This project will apply this state-of-the-art approach on benthic foraminiferal shells from climate events relevant for climate model simulations, such as the last glacial-interglacial intervals and the Mid Pliocene Warm Period (MPWP), a potential climate analogue ~3.2 - 2.9 m.y. ago. This study will provide model simulations with more robust paleoclimate data, further, a comparison with conventional measurements will permit quantification of the potential bias in published records and thus establish corrections. This is the first study investigating potential alteration in benthic foraminifera with an unprecedented level of detail, and the anticipated outcome will be the compilation of more accurate paleoclimate records, which have a direct impact on the performance of model simulations for long-term forecasts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/12/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1658230</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maureen</FirstName>
<LastName>Raymo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maureen E Raymo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>raymo@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8453658801</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000591214</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Reinhard</FirstName>
<LastName>Kozdon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Reinhard Kozdon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rk2858@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8453658619</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000697301</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Palisades</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>109641707</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[61 Route 9W]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1304</Code>
<Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~297274</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Foraminifera are minute, single-celled organisms that are ubiquitous in the world&rsquo;s oceans. Planktic foraminifera dwell in the upper water column, whereas benthic specimens live on the seafloor. Most foraminifera species precipitate a sandgrain-sized calcite shell that can be preserved in seafloor sediments for millions of years. These fossil shells are among the most important archives of past climates, as their isotopic and chemical composition allows for the reconstruction of important parameters such as past water temperature, global ice volume, pH, or changes in ocean circulation.</p> <p>Since more than 60 years, isotopic analyses of benthic and planktic foraminifera provide a comprehensive picture of the Earth&rsquo;s past climate variations, and climate models predicting the rate and magnitude of future climate change are calibrated on data from past climate analogues. With the rapid evolution of climate models and the necessity to compute more robust forecasts about fundamental questions such as future sea level rise, it is equally essential to produce robust paleorecords to test and validate these models.</p> <p>Until recently, it was generally assumed that benthic foraminifera shells are not susceptible to diagenetic alteration, and their isotopic and chemical composition remains in most cases well-preserved over millions of years. Thus, when sandgrain-sized foraminifera shells were selected under the binocular microscope for analyses, they were typically not carefully screened for their quality of preservation. In addition, objective, well-documented and reproducible criteria to quantitatively assess the quality of preservation were missing, and it was based on the subjective interpretation of the worker to decide which foraminifer shells appear well-preserved under the binocular microscope and are therefore suitable for geochemical analysis.</p> <p>In carefully screening several thousands of benthic foraminifer shells of the most commonly used genera <em>Cibicidoides </em>and <em>Uvigerina</em> from three Atlantic and three Pacific Integrated Ocean Drilling Program (IODP) sites spanning major glacial/interglacial peaks of the past ~3 million years, we developed the Foraminiferal Preservation Index (FPI), a new metric to visually quantify preservation quality of foraminiferal assemblages using only a binocular microscope and well-defined and well-documented objective criteria. Tests have shown that the assessment of the preservation quality (&ldquo;FPI-Scoring&rdquo;) using the criteria outlined in this study is largely independent from the scientific background or level of experience of the worker, and results are highly reproducible.</p> <p>In this respect, it is notable that the preservation quality of foraminiferal assemblages (i.e. all shells within a core sample) at the cores investigated changes over glacial/interglacial cycles as the chemical composition of the deep ocean water seems to be the main driver of diagenesis through time. However, in the vast majority of all core samples investigated, well-preserved shells coexist next to poorly preserved specimens, presumably because some shells may have been shielded in small pockets of clay-rich sediments from chemical interactions with pore waters. Thus, well-preserved shells are not &ndash; at least in the cores investigated for this study &ndash; extremely scarce.</p> <p>In using the screening techniques outlined in this study, scientist now have a tool to carefully select only the best-preserved foraminiferal shells for analysis based on objective, well-documented, and reproducible criteria, which has the potential to greatly improve the robustness of future paleorecords.</p> <p>In order to estimate the impact of preservation on the veracity of proxy records, we acquired single-shell stable isotope data (&delta;<sup>18</sup>O and &delta;<sup>13</sup>C) from individual Cibicidoides shells of various preservation quality from the same core samples and compared the data to published paleorecords form other sites covering the same time span. These comparisons demonstrate that in particular during periods of rapid climate change such as glacial/interglacial transitions, poorly-preserved shells can significantly bias the proxy record.</p> <p>We hypothesize that poorly-preserved shells incorporate a certain amount of inorganic calcite, formed after burial of the empty shell in the sediment column. The source of this inorganic calcite is likely aqueous carbonate species in porewaters, which we believe migrates upwards through the sediment column towards the sediment-water interface during sediment compaction. Such aqueous carbonate species in porewaters would likely resemble the isotopic composition of carbonate materials being dissolved deeper in the sediment column. Thus, poorly-preserved shells may incorporate some calcite that features the chemical signature of the climate or ocean parameters that persisted several thousands of years before at this site.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2020<br>      Modified by: Reinhard&nbsp;Kozdon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Foraminifera are minute, single-celled organisms that are ubiquitous in the world’s oceans. Planktic foraminifera dwell in the upper water column, whereas benthic specimens live on the seafloor. Most foraminifera species precipitate a sandgrain-sized calcite shell that can be preserved in seafloor sediments for millions of years. These fossil shells are among the most important archives of past climates, as their isotopic and chemical composition allows for the reconstruction of important parameters such as past water temperature, global ice volume, pH, or changes in ocean circulation.  Since more than 60 years, isotopic analyses of benthic and planktic foraminifera provide a comprehensive picture of the Earth’s past climate variations, and climate models predicting the rate and magnitude of future climate change are calibrated on data from past climate analogues. With the rapid evolution of climate models and the necessity to compute more robust forecasts about fundamental questions such as future sea level rise, it is equally essential to produce robust paleorecords to test and validate these models.  Until recently, it was generally assumed that benthic foraminifera shells are not susceptible to diagenetic alteration, and their isotopic and chemical composition remains in most cases well-preserved over millions of years. Thus, when sandgrain-sized foraminifera shells were selected under the binocular microscope for analyses, they were typically not carefully screened for their quality of preservation. In addition, objective, well-documented and reproducible criteria to quantitatively assess the quality of preservation were missing, and it was based on the subjective interpretation of the worker to decide which foraminifer shells appear well-preserved under the binocular microscope and are therefore suitable for geochemical analysis.  In carefully screening several thousands of benthic foraminifer shells of the most commonly used genera Cibicidoides and Uvigerina from three Atlantic and three Pacific Integrated Ocean Drilling Program (IODP) sites spanning major glacial/interglacial peaks of the past ~3 million years, we developed the Foraminiferal Preservation Index (FPI), a new metric to visually quantify preservation quality of foraminiferal assemblages using only a binocular microscope and well-defined and well-documented objective criteria. Tests have shown that the assessment of the preservation quality ("FPI-Scoring") using the criteria outlined in this study is largely independent from the scientific background or level of experience of the worker, and results are highly reproducible.  In this respect, it is notable that the preservation quality of foraminiferal assemblages (i.e. all shells within a core sample) at the cores investigated changes over glacial/interglacial cycles as the chemical composition of the deep ocean water seems to be the main driver of diagenesis through time. However, in the vast majority of all core samples investigated, well-preserved shells coexist next to poorly preserved specimens, presumably because some shells may have been shielded in small pockets of clay-rich sediments from chemical interactions with pore waters. Thus, well-preserved shells are not &ndash; at least in the cores investigated for this study &ndash; extremely scarce.  In using the screening techniques outlined in this study, scientist now have a tool to carefully select only the best-preserved foraminiferal shells for analysis based on objective, well-documented, and reproducible criteria, which has the potential to greatly improve the robustness of future paleorecords.  In order to estimate the impact of preservation on the veracity of proxy records, we acquired single-shell stable isotope data (&delta;18O and &delta;13C) from individual Cibicidoides shells of various preservation quality from the same core samples and compared the data to published paleorecords form other sites covering the same time span. These comparisons demonstrate that in particular during periods of rapid climate change such as glacial/interglacial transitions, poorly-preserved shells can significantly bias the proxy record.  We hypothesize that poorly-preserved shells incorporate a certain amount of inorganic calcite, formed after burial of the empty shell in the sediment column. The source of this inorganic calcite is likely aqueous carbonate species in porewaters, which we believe migrates upwards through the sediment column towards the sediment-water interface during sediment compaction. Such aqueous carbonate species in porewaters would likely resemble the isotopic composition of carbonate materials being dissolved deeper in the sediment column. Thus, poorly-preserved shells may incorporate some calcite that features the chemical signature of the climate or ocean parameters that persisted several thousands of years before at this site.       Last Modified: 09/27/2020       Submitted by: Reinhard Kozdon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
