<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: System for Sampling of Powder Blends in Pharmaceutical Manufacturing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pamela McCauley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project will be realized first in pharmaceutical manufacturing where powder blends are required to prepare tablets. The new sampler will bring products to market in less time providing benefit to patients and pharmaceutical companies. The proposed device (sampler) will potentially protect employees in pharmaceutical plants from exposure to potentially toxic drugs. It will potentially be useful across a wide variety of industries and be suitable for powder blends such as vitamins, nutraceuticals, powdered milk, and other food products. The sampler will improve quality control and potentially lead to representative sampling in quality control, thereby reducing risk to customers and patients.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project will define the essential components and features for sampling powders in pharma and food manufacturing applications. The current technology does not provide representative samples from these important commercial products. Current approaches use a spear (thief sampler) to obtain samples from only a few pre-selected locations within the manufacturing equipment, and will typically fail to detect variations or problems outside of these locations. The spear also often alters the composition of the material that is sampled, providing inaccurate measurements of the composition of the powdered product.  The new device will be based on best practices first established within the mining industry, which have not been adapted to the pharmaceutical and food industries due to lack of suitable sampling devices. The goal of the I-corps project is to develop powder sampling methods to improve the quality of powder based products, and avoid unnecessary product loss due to poor sampling practices.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/24/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/24/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1659082</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rodolfo</FirstName>
<LastName>Romanach</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rodolfo J Romanach</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rodolfoj.romanach@upr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7873235106</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000358702</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/24/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez</Name>
<CityName>Mayaguez</CityName>
<ZipCode>006809000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7878312065</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Call Box 9000</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Road 108 Km 1.0]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>175303262</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PUERTO RICO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>090051616</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>006809000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: left;">This project has investigated the need for developing a powder sampler for pharmaceutical powder mixtures. Federal regulations require pharmaceutical companies to obtain in-process samples of the powder mixtures that become the tablets and capsules that many patients take. This regulation is important because tablets and capsules are a mixture of particles of an active pharmaceutical ingredient and excipients. The excipients are added for various reasons such as improving powder flow, avoiding sticking of tablets to compressing machines, and many other reasons. Tablets and capsules often have four or five excipients, and these may constitute 50% of the tablet weight, but sometimes provide more than 99% of the tablet weight in potent drugs. The proper evaluation of pharmaceutical powder mixtures reduces the risk that a patient will receive an over or sub dose of a drug. The Food and Drug Administration does not currently have a guidance for industry on how to sample or establish specifications for powder mixtures. This project has been developed to address these needs.&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">The intellectual merits of the project are in the development of a new sampler where the entire powder mixture will have the same opportunity of being selected as a sample. This new approach is different from the current approach that obtains samples from pre-selected sampling locations. The new method also obtains samples as the powder mixture is flowing, while the current approach relies on inserting a spear into a static powder mixture. The new sampler is being developed for pharmaceutical processes, but future applications include detergent formulations and powdered infant milk.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">The broader impacts of the project lie in the possibility of improving quality control of pharmaceutical products. The researchers have identified pharmaceutical companies that are very interested in improving the quality of their products. The researchers found that powder sampling problems have delayed the approval of new pharmaceutical products. Thus, the new sampler could facilitate the approval and manufacture of new and safe pharmaceutical products for patients.&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">The I-Corps training has changed the way in which we define research projects. We now realize that we must get out of the lab and have conversations with possible customers. We have been too focused on convincing about the importance of our research, without understanding the needs of possible customers. Graduate students are now encouraged to discuss projects with possible industrial sponsors and seek to understand their situations. Customer discovery is also essential in science. The customer discovery emphasized in I-Corps is a valuable form of active learning.&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/14/2018<br>      Modified by: Rodolfo&nbsp;J&nbsp;Romanach</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This project has investigated the need for developing a powder sampler for pharmaceutical powder mixtures. Federal regulations require pharmaceutical companies to obtain in-process samples of the powder mixtures that become the tablets and capsules that many patients take. This regulation is important because tablets and capsules are a mixture of particles of an active pharmaceutical ingredient and excipients. The excipients are added for various reasons such as improving powder flow, avoiding sticking of tablets to compressing machines, and many other reasons. Tablets and capsules often have four or five excipients, and these may constitute 50% of the tablet weight, but sometimes provide more than 99% of the tablet weight in potent drugs. The proper evaluation of pharmaceutical powder mixtures reduces the risk that a patient will receive an over or sub dose of a drug. The Food and Drug Administration does not currently have a guidance for industry on how to sample or establish specifications for powder mixtures. This project has been developed to address these needs.  The intellectual merits of the project are in the development of a new sampler where the entire powder mixture will have the same opportunity of being selected as a sample. This new approach is different from the current approach that obtains samples from pre-selected sampling locations. The new method also obtains samples as the powder mixture is flowing, while the current approach relies on inserting a spear into a static powder mixture. The new sampler is being developed for pharmaceutical processes, but future applications include detergent formulations and powdered infant milk. The broader impacts of the project lie in the possibility of improving quality control of pharmaceutical products. The researchers have identified pharmaceutical companies that are very interested in improving the quality of their products. The researchers found that powder sampling problems have delayed the approval of new pharmaceutical products. Thus, the new sampler could facilitate the approval and manufacture of new and safe pharmaceutical products for patients.  The I-Corps training has changed the way in which we define research projects. We now realize that we must get out of the lab and have conversations with possible customers. We have been too focused on convincing about the importance of our research, without understanding the needs of possible customers. Graduate students are now encouraged to discuss projects with possible industrial sponsors and seek to understand their situations. Customer discovery is also essential in science. The customer discovery emphasized in I-Corps is a valuable form of active learning.          Last Modified: 10/14/2018       Submitted by: Rodolfo J Romanach]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
