<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Extremal Graph Theory and Dynamical Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>287556.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>287556</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cesar Silva</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>csilva@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927522</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The NSF-REU Site in Extremal Graph Theory and Dynamical Systems at the Rochester Institute of Technology (RIT) will actively engage ten students in each of the summers 2017, 2018, and 2019 in a research experience in mathematics. Research projects will be in the areas of graph theory and dynamical systems, some of which are linked to mathematical biology. Projects will include both applied and theoretical topics. Applied projects will include development and analysis of functional connectivity models of the human brain, and modeling of cardiac arrhythmia. Projects with a theoretical focus will include problems from extremal and structural graph theory, graph labeling, and delay differential equations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;All students will work directly with RIT faculty for the entirety of the program and will receive mentoring in mathematical research practices, as well as in written and oral communication. Students will give presentations on their research findings at the end of each week. The program will have a heavy emphasis on networking with other mathematicians and will include "Researchers in Residence," where experts from outside of our university visit the program and work with the students. Results from research projects will be disseminated through publications in refereed journals, presentations at national and regional mathematical meetings, and at the students' home institutions. Students will be encouraged to pursue graduate studies and employment in the mathematical sciences. During the program students will participate in an Ethics in Science Workshop. The recruitment efforts will target students from universities, liberal arts colleges, and community colleges. Inclusion of women and minorities will be an important element of the program. We plan to have 50 percent of the students be female and aim to have 25 percent of the students be from underrepresented minority groups. We will also aim to have 80 percent of the participants from outside of the host institution, with an emphasis on drawing students from colleges without Ph.D. programs or have limited research opportunities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/18/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1659075</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Darren</FirstName>
<LastName>Narayan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Darren A Narayan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dansma@rit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5854752514</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000169128</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Cherry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth M Cherry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Elizabeth.cherry@gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048943889</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000217152</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/18/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rochester Institute of Tech</Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5854757987</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 LOMB MEMORIAL DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002223642</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ROCHESTER INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (INC)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002223642</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rochester Institute of Tech]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146235604</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[85 Lomb Memorial Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7335</Code>
<Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~287556</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The REU Site: Extremal Graph Theory and Dynamical Systems engaged 31 undergraduates in research during the summers of 2017, 2018, and 2019. </span></p> <p><span>Intellectual Merit:</span></p> <p><span>Working in teams guided by faculty undergraduate participants made research advances in the areas of extremal graph theory, algebraic graph theory, Graph Ramsey Theory, dynamical systems, modeling of the opiod epidemic, and modeling of heart arrhythmmia. The research resulted in six papers that have been accepted for publication in refereed scienfic journals in the mathematical sciences, with another under submission. All 31 students gave research presentations at the annual Joint Mathematics Meetings during January of the year following their summer research (San Diego, CA (2018), Baltimore, MD (2019), and Denver, CO (2020). In addition other students presented their research at other conferences including the Southeastern International Conference on Combinatorics, Graph Theory, and Computing at Florida Atlantic University, and the Young Mathematicians Conference at the Ohio State University.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Broader Impacts: </span></p> <p><span>Of the 31 students 15 were women and 11 identified as either American indian / Alaskan Native, Hispanic, or African American. As part of the program, All students participated in an Ethics in Science Workshop. Students in the second year gave presentations to RIT's Summer Mathematics Institute for high school mathematics teachers.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Darren&nbsp;A&nbsp;Narayan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The REU Site: Extremal Graph Theory and Dynamical Systems engaged 31 undergraduates in research during the summers of 2017, 2018, and 2019.   Intellectual Merit:  Working in teams guided by faculty undergraduate participants made research advances in the areas of extremal graph theory, algebraic graph theory, Graph Ramsey Theory, dynamical systems, modeling of the opiod epidemic, and modeling of heart arrhythmmia. The research resulted in six papers that have been accepted for publication in refereed scienfic journals in the mathematical sciences, with another under submission. All 31 students gave research presentations at the annual Joint Mathematics Meetings during January of the year following their summer research (San Diego, CA (2018), Baltimore, MD (2019), and Denver, CO (2020). In addition other students presented their research at other conferences including the Southeastern International Conference on Combinatorics, Graph Theory, and Computing at Florida Atlantic University, and the Young Mathematicians Conference at the Ohio State University.   Broader Impacts:   Of the 31 students 15 were women and 11 identified as either American indian / Alaskan Native, Hispanic, or African American. As part of the program, All students participated in an Ethics in Science Workshop. Students in the second year gave presentations to RIT's Summer Mathematics Institute for high school mathematics teachers.       Last Modified: 06/28/2021       Submitted by: Darren A Narayan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
