<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site:   Nevis Labs, Columbia University for Summers 2017-2019</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299905.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299905</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen McCloud</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmccloud@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928236</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the renewal of the Research Experience for Undergraduates  (REU) site in experimental high energy physics and astrophysics at Nevis Labs, Columbia University. The site will support undergraduate student participation in original, cutting-edge physics research, working with a faculty mentor. Two students per year will spend the summer conducting research at the European Organization for Nuclear Research in Switzerland at the Large Hadron Collider.  Key goals of the REU are increasing the knowledge and interest of students in physics research, increasing participation of traditionally under-represented populations, and motivating students to pursue graduate studies in science and engineering. Achieving these goals is critical for providing the Nation's future well-trained workforce required to continue to lead an increasingly technological world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The students spend 10 weeks during the summer participating in the broad Nevis high energy physics and particle astrophysics research program, which seeks to address the most pressing issues of these fields, including the origin of mass, the question of neutrino oscillations, and the search for Dark Matter. Answers to these questions will have profound implications for our understanding of the fundamental structure and evolution of the universe.  The strength of the Nevis research program, coupled with the Nevis infrastructure of world class electronics design and mechanical construction, forms a unique environment with opportunities for training of students. As the variety of experiments are at different stages in their development, Nevis provides the opportunity for students to gain experience in all aspects of the experiments, from initial detector design, hardware development and construction, to software development and data analysis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1659528</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Parsons</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Parsons</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>parsons@nevis.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128548127</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000184912</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Georgia</FirstName>
<LastName>Karagiorgi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Georgia Karagiorgi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>georgia@nevis.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128531615</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000727653</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University Nevis Labs]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvington</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>105330137</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[136 S. Broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9134</Code>
<Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~97000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~99950</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~102955</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During the 3-year period of this award, 30 undergraduate students from around the country have participated in cutting-edge scientific research at Nevis Labs, the high energy physics laboratory of Columbia University. The 30 participants include many individual from under-represented populations, including 22 women and 6 minority students, as well as 13 students from non-PhD granting institutions.</p> <p>The topics of research included data analysis looking for new physics discoveries at the Large Hadron Collider at CERN in Geneva, Switzerland, neutrino physics at Fermi National Laboratory, searching for Dark Matter with the XENON experiment in Gran Sasso Lab in Italy, and exploring the universe with gamma ray physics using data from the VERITAS telescope array. Each student made a final presentation summarizing the results of their summer's research, and also prepared a written paper. The presentations and papers are available online at our REU website at www.nevis.columbia.edu/reu/.</p> <p>A series of roughly biweekly seminars and lab visits was used to introduce the students to current outstanding research questions in a wide variety of subfields of physics. Other components included training in scientific ethics, a discussion about graduate school, and a day trip to visit the experimental facilities at Brookhaven National Lab.</p> <p>Over the life of the REU program at Nevis, about 80% of the REU participants have gone on to graduate school in STEM fields, providing strong support that the program is meeting its main goal of encouraging students to consider graduate training in STEM fields.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/31/2020<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;Parsons</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During the 3-year period of this award, 30 undergraduate students from around the country have participated in cutting-edge scientific research at Nevis Labs, the high energy physics laboratory of Columbia University. The 30 participants include many individual from under-represented populations, including 22 women and 6 minority students, as well as 13 students from non-PhD granting institutions.  The topics of research included data analysis looking for new physics discoveries at the Large Hadron Collider at CERN in Geneva, Switzerland, neutrino physics at Fermi National Laboratory, searching for Dark Matter with the XENON experiment in Gran Sasso Lab in Italy, and exploring the universe with gamma ray physics using data from the VERITAS telescope array. Each student made a final presentation summarizing the results of their summer's research, and also prepared a written paper. The presentations and papers are available online at our REU website at www.nevis.columbia.edu/reu/.  A series of roughly biweekly seminars and lab visits was used to introduce the students to current outstanding research questions in a wide variety of subfields of physics. Other components included training in scientific ethics, a discussion about graduate school, and a day trip to visit the experimental facilities at Brookhaven National Lab.  Over the life of the REU program at Nevis, about 80% of the REU participants have gone on to graduate school in STEM fields, providing strong support that the program is meeting its main goal of encouraging students to consider graduate training in STEM fields.       Last Modified: 05/31/2020       Submitted by: John Parsons]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
