<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SUNFEST: Summer Undergraduate Research in Sensor Technologies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>381244.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>381244</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amelia Greer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>agreer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922552</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This three year renewal Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site Program, SUNFEST: Summer Undergraduate Research in Sensor Technologies, at the University of Pennsylvania, will offer a diverse cohort of students from underrepresented groups who have limited opportunities for STEM-oriented research the opportunity to work on research projects involving sensor technologies with the goal to develop new materials and devices. Topics include sensor phenomena, modeling, materials, nano- and micro-technology, sensors for biomedical applications, sensory data processing and sensor systems for robotics. Sensor technology, which acts as a common intellectual focus and which addresses "real-life" applications, can have a huge scientific impact that can benefit society and the environment. The program will also serve as an intellectual hub for others' involvement, such as high school students from city high schools and their teachers.  The SUNFEST program will act as a catalyst for broader involvement and a supportive environment for meaningful participation in scientific communities.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Over 11 summer weeks, the University of Pennsylvania will host 10 undergraduate students who will be involved in high quality, cutting-edge research projects related to sensor technology. By working on a meaningful research project of their own in a dynamic and supportive environment, students will contribute to academically-based discovery that may lead to better devices and systems for medical, robotics, communications, environmental, energy and surveillance applications. To foster students' development as future researchers, they will participate in weekly group meetings and seminars in their labs.  In addition, the REU offers enhancement activities, include workshops on writing proposals and technical reports, responsible conduct of research, applying to graduate school, and effective oral presentations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/01/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1659190</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
<LastName>Van der Spiegel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jan Van der Spiegel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jan@ee.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158987116</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000222888</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3451 Walnut St, 5th Flr Franklin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3451 Walnut Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1360</Code>
<Text>EWFD-Eng Workforce Development</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~381244</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The outcomes of the SUNFEST REU Project can be summarized as follows.</p> <ol> <li>One of key goals and outcomes was <em>to provide undergraduate students with research opportunities, in particular those coming from underrepresented groups or small colleges.</em> Providing hands-on, engaging, and meaningful research experiences to students, allowed them to expand their knowledge in engineering and related STEM fields while contributing to cutting edge developments in sensor technologies. Students were able to develop specialized research skills and a high level of familiarity and confidence within the research setting.&nbsp;&nbsp;Several of the projects were published in archived journals or conference presentations.&nbsp;</li> <li>An equally important outcome was <em>to motivate the students to go on to graduate school and pursue careers in engineering</em>. This outcome was achieved with 63% of the students belonging to an underrepresented group while over 37% were female.&nbsp;&nbsp;Surveys of alumni indicated that&nbsp;72% have gone on to graduate school. What was equally encouraging is that the historical percentage of minority students going to graduate school was slightly above the average of all students going to graduate school A couple of quotes from students capture the experiences.&nbsp;&nbsp;One student commented, &ldquo;I realized that people are capable of much more than we think. I never thought about a PhD until now that I am done with my summer research. It gave me the opportunity to explore something I was entirely not even aware of.&rdquo; Another student remarked, &ldquo;I definitely am leaning more toward pursuing a PhD than I was before SUNFEST.&rdquo; A third student said, &ldquo;My experience at SUNFEST has helped me realize and confirm that I like engineering research, and now I am fully sure that I want to go to graduate school after I finish my bachelor's degree.&rdquo; More than 95% of students agreed that they felt prepared to succeed in future research project and were considering going on to graduate school.&nbsp;</li> <li>Another outcome was to&nbsp;<em>Engage Students in Professional Development Opportunities.&nbsp;&nbsp;</em>This was achieved by helping students to develop skills to succeed in the research field through a series of workshops. The workshops covered the following topics: how to do research, engineering research methods, collecting resources for scientific research, writing scientific abstracts and papers, developing and giving presentations, applying to graduate school, etc.</li> <li><em>Finally, the project also provided a strong</em>&nbsp;mentoring relationship between students and the other members for their laboratories, including principle investigators, post-doctoral students, and other graduate students. These relationships served to connect students to the scientific community, to excite them for graduate school, and further their careers and professional development.</li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/02/2020<br>      Modified by: Jan&nbsp;Van Der Spiegel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The outcomes of the SUNFEST REU Project can be summarized as follows.  One of key goals and outcomes was to provide undergraduate students with research opportunities, in particular those coming from underrepresented groups or small colleges. Providing hands-on, engaging, and meaningful research experiences to students, allowed them to expand their knowledge in engineering and related STEM fields while contributing to cutting edge developments in sensor technologies. Students were able to develop specialized research skills and a high level of familiarity and confidence within the research setting.  Several of the projects were published in archived journals or conference presentations.  An equally important outcome was to motivate the students to go on to graduate school and pursue careers in engineering. This outcome was achieved with 63% of the students belonging to an underrepresented group while over 37% were female.  Surveys of alumni indicated that 72% have gone on to graduate school. What was equally encouraging is that the historical percentage of minority students going to graduate school was slightly above the average of all students going to graduate school A couple of quotes from students capture the experiences.  One student commented, "I realized that people are capable of much more than we think. I never thought about a PhD until now that I am done with my summer research. It gave me the opportunity to explore something I was entirely not even aware of." Another student remarked, "I definitely am leaning more toward pursuing a PhD than I was before SUNFEST." A third student said, "My experience at SUNFEST has helped me realize and confirm that I like engineering research, and now I am fully sure that I want to go to graduate school after I finish my bachelor's degree." More than 95% of students agreed that they felt prepared to succeed in future research project and were considering going on to graduate school.  Another outcome was to Engage Students in Professional Development Opportunities.  This was achieved by helping students to develop skills to succeed in the research field through a series of workshops. The workshops covered the following topics: how to do research, engineering research methods, collecting resources for scientific research, writing scientific abstracts and papers, developing and giving presentations, applying to graduate school, etc. Finally, the project also provided a strong mentoring relationship between students and the other members for their laboratories, including principle investigators, post-doctoral students, and other graduate students. These relationships served to connect students to the scientific community, to excite them for graduate school, and further their careers and professional development.              Last Modified: 04/02/2020       Submitted by: Jan Van Der Spiegel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
