<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: A novel mechanism regulating leaf water transport: Reversible collapse of xylem conduits</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Irwin Forseth</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>iforseth@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927862</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project investigates how plants protect their vascular system from damage due to excessive evaporative loads. The significance of the work arises from the fact that photosynthesis is dependent upon a plant's capacity to transport water from the soil. Thus, understanding how plants protect their water transport system will illuminate constraints on the productivity of agricultural and natural ecosystems. A new finding shows that the terminal water transporting vessels, which are located in leaves and consist of non-living cells, function like a mechanical valve: closing off as the stresses in the system increase and re-opening as the system relaxes. The principle goal of this research is to determine if the valve-like behavior of terminal conduits prevents the stresses in the system from reaching levels that could cause lasting damage to upstream conduits. A second objective is to explore linkages between the rapid stress-induced closure of terminal conduits and the slower closure of stomatal pores in the leaf epidermis. The findings of this research will contribute to the development of crop varieties that are resilient to drought. The project will enhance research mentoring and training of students, as well as provide fundamental insights in plant biology that will be incorporated into teaching and disseminated to the general public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A fundamental issue in plant ecophysiology is how plants protect themselves from cavitation. Challenges to the plant vascular system associated with soil drying occur slowly, such that stomatal closure, root shrinkage, and leaf shedding are effective means of regulating xylem potentials. In contrast, excursions in transpiration rate have the potential to be fast relative to the ability of stomata to close, and thus to expose leaves to potentially damaging water potentials. This is especially the case for angiosperms in which stomatal aperture does not passively track leaf water potential and increases in transpiration lead initially to opening, rather than closing. A recent discovery shows that in the smallest leaf veins, which are the ones in closest contact to the sites of evaporation and thus experience the most negative pressures, the conduits deform (collapse) rather than cavitate and the change in shape is completely (and rapidly) reversible. The goals of this project are to investigate (1) whether the reduction in hydraulic conductivity due to terminal conduit collapse protects upstream xylem from experiencing water potentials that cause cavitation and (2) how collapse contributes to stomatal regulation of transpiration. The study provides a new perspective on the coordination of liquid and vapor phase transport, with implications for both plant productivity and drought response. Greater understanding of the role of xylem mechanical properties may provide new targets for phenotyping crop varieties and understanding plant diversity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/13/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1659918</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Noel</FirstName>
<LastName>Holbrook</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Noel M Holbrook</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>holbrook@oeb.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174960603</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000475979</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/13/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021382020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[16 Divinity Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7657</Code>
<Text>Integrtv Ecological Physiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The evolution of an internal water transport &lsquo;highway&rsquo; enabled vascular plants to deliver water from soils to the canopy efficiently over a long distance, allowing the rise of tall plants and development of forest ecosystems. Xylem is the name given to the vascular tissue responsible for moving water from soil to leaves. Xylem water transport is important for sustaining the hydration of photosynthetic tissues and loss of hydraulic capacity is a crucial determinant of tree mortality under drought.</p> <p>According to the cohesion-tension theory, water is pulled from the roots to the canopy because water loss from leaves (transpiration) decreases the pressure in xylem conduits, resulting in a pressure gradient that drives flow towards the leaves. Surprisingly, these pressures in the water column fall well below zero (a state often described as the water being under &ldquo;tension&rdquo;). When soils are dry and/or transpiration rates are high, the development of increasingly negative pressures can result in two types of failure. First, expansion of a gas nucleus can cause embolism, blocking water transport. Second, mechanical forces exerted by the water on the conduit walls can cause the conduit to implode (inward collapse). A major difference between these two failure modes is that embolism is not readily reversible, whereas conduits recover their original shape as soon as the tensions are relaxed.</p> <p>In stems, the xylem is generally conceived of as a rigid tubing system in which embolism (formation of air bubbles) is the major failure mode. However, in leaves the opposite appears to be true. When xylem tensions are large, the conduits collapse to the extent that their walls become appressed against themselves and the lumen space in which flow occurs is almost entirely occluded. The goal of this research project was to investigate whether this collapse might benefit the leaf, by protecting upstream (i.e., stem) xylem from experiencing negative pressures that could cause embolism to form.</p> <p>Leaves experience a dynamic environment with changes in wind speed driving high-frequency variations in incident solar radiation (due to leaf angle) and boundary layer thickness, both of which impact leaf temperature. For example, cloud-to-sun transitions can heat leaves by as much as 10<sup>o</sup>C, resulting in substantial increases in transpiration. Stomatal regulation functions to protect xylem from embolism. However, stomata close slowly, on the order of minutes, during which time damaging water potentials may develop. This mismatch in temporal scale motivated the hypothesis that reversible conduit deformation in vein endings enables plants to mitigate potential embolism hazards resulting from short-term increases in transpiration</p> <p>The principle finding of this research is that elastic conduits in vein endings are a general feature across diverse plant lineages and multiple life forms. Experiments to test the hypothesis that elastic xylem deformation/collapse protects upstream xylem from embolism when challenged with a rapid increase in transpiration provide strong support for conduit collapse having a functional role. The discovery that elastic conduits can serve as a protective mechanism for the xylem water transport system when confronted with rapid increases in evaporative demand needs to be considered when assessing the safety of the plant hydraulic system and tree mortality under a changing climate with increasing drought and climate variabilities. Additionally, this novel hydraulic design provides a biomimetic model for engineering passively and autonomously regulated flows in evaporation-driven microfluidic systems.</p> <p>This award supported the career and intellectual development of three students and three postdoctoral fellows. The results have been communicated through workshops and seminars to the broader plant biology &nbsp;and plant biomechanics community.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/15/2020<br>      Modified by: Noel&nbsp;M&nbsp;Holbrook</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The evolution of an internal water transport ‘highway’ enabled vascular plants to deliver water from soils to the canopy efficiently over a long distance, allowing the rise of tall plants and development of forest ecosystems. Xylem is the name given to the vascular tissue responsible for moving water from soil to leaves. Xylem water transport is important for sustaining the hydration of photosynthetic tissues and loss of hydraulic capacity is a crucial determinant of tree mortality under drought.  According to the cohesion-tension theory, water is pulled from the roots to the canopy because water loss from leaves (transpiration) decreases the pressure in xylem conduits, resulting in a pressure gradient that drives flow towards the leaves. Surprisingly, these pressures in the water column fall well below zero (a state often described as the water being under "tension"). When soils are dry and/or transpiration rates are high, the development of increasingly negative pressures can result in two types of failure. First, expansion of a gas nucleus can cause embolism, blocking water transport. Second, mechanical forces exerted by the water on the conduit walls can cause the conduit to implode (inward collapse). A major difference between these two failure modes is that embolism is not readily reversible, whereas conduits recover their original shape as soon as the tensions are relaxed.  In stems, the xylem is generally conceived of as a rigid tubing system in which embolism (formation of air bubbles) is the major failure mode. However, in leaves the opposite appears to be true. When xylem tensions are large, the conduits collapse to the extent that their walls become appressed against themselves and the lumen space in which flow occurs is almost entirely occluded. The goal of this research project was to investigate whether this collapse might benefit the leaf, by protecting upstream (i.e., stem) xylem from experiencing negative pressures that could cause embolism to form.  Leaves experience a dynamic environment with changes in wind speed driving high-frequency variations in incident solar radiation (due to leaf angle) and boundary layer thickness, both of which impact leaf temperature. For example, cloud-to-sun transitions can heat leaves by as much as 10oC, resulting in substantial increases in transpiration. Stomatal regulation functions to protect xylem from embolism. However, stomata close slowly, on the order of minutes, during which time damaging water potentials may develop. This mismatch in temporal scale motivated the hypothesis that reversible conduit deformation in vein endings enables plants to mitigate potential embolism hazards resulting from short-term increases in transpiration  The principle finding of this research is that elastic conduits in vein endings are a general feature across diverse plant lineages and multiple life forms. Experiments to test the hypothesis that elastic xylem deformation/collapse protects upstream xylem from embolism when challenged with a rapid increase in transpiration provide strong support for conduit collapse having a functional role. The discovery that elastic conduits can serve as a protective mechanism for the xylem water transport system when confronted with rapid increases in evaporative demand needs to be considered when assessing the safety of the plant hydraulic system and tree mortality under a changing climate with increasing drought and climate variabilities. Additionally, this novel hydraulic design provides a biomimetic model for engineering passively and autonomously regulated flows in evaporation-driven microfluidic systems.  This award supported the career and intellectual development of three students and three postdoctoral fellows. The results have been communicated through workshops and seminars to the broader plant biology  and plant biomechanics community.             Last Modified: 09/15/2020       Submitted by: Noel M Holbrook]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
