<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Meeting: 59th Annual Maize Genetics Conference St. Louis, Missouri March 9-12, 2017</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49620.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49620</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Clifford Weil</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cweil@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924668</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 59th Annual Maize Genetics Conference will be held March 9-12, 2017, at Union Station in St. Louis, Missouri. The meeting offers members of the scientific community the opportunity to present and discuss their most recent research relevant to maize genetics and plant biology. This conference grant will broaden the scope of the meeting by funding participants from under-represented groups to attend. These participants will also receive professional development training through presenting their research and interacting with invited speakers and scientist-mentors during the conference. The experience of attending a Maize Genetics Conference, the exposure to cutting-edge research, the scientific interactions, and the contacts established are vital catalysts for the careers of aspiring students and postdocs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 59th Annual meeting will feature talks by four invited plenary speakers: Rebecca Nelson (Cornell University), Nathan Springer (University of Minnesota), Philip Becraft (Iowa State University) and Jane Glazebrook (University of Minnesota). There will also be a plenary session to award the 4rd Barbara McClintock Prize for Plant Genetics and Genome Studies to recognize one of the most outstanding plant geneticists of the present era. The program will include approximately 35 18-minute talks by speakers selected from submitted abstracts, and two poster sessions. The Maize Genetics Conference provides outstanding opportunities for graduate students and postdoctoral scientists to meet and interact with an international gathering of scientists in the field, to discuss their research while presenting talks or posters, and to establish scientific networks that will be valuable as they embark on their careers. Funding from NSF will be used to broaden participation at the meeting through outreach and recruiting efforts that seek to support Conference attendance by students, postdocs and young faculty from under-represented groups with an interest in exploring research possibilities in maize genetics. Partnering these awardees with experienced maize researchers at similar career stages will facilitate their productive participation in the Conference. In addition, students who are minorities or first time attendees will be supported by defraying the cost of food and lodging at the Conference. The Maize Genetics Conference is unique compared to other meetings and is held up as a model for its efforts to support attendance of all graduate student attendees</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/28/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1659999</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erich</FirstName>
<LastName>Grotewold</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erich Grotewold</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>grotewol@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173551600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000122262</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/28/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432100012</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[012 Rightmire Hall, 1060 Carmack]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1329</Code>
<Text>Plant Genome Research Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~49620</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 59<span>th</span>&nbsp;Annual Maize Genetics Conference was held March 9-12, 2017, at Union Station, St. Louis, MO. The conference was attended by a record 678 scientists, including 209 graduate students and 32 undergraduate students. The 59<span>th</span>&nbsp;Annual meeting also featured talks by four invited plenary speakers: Rebecca Nelson (Cornell University), Nathan Springer (University of Minnesota), Philip Becraft (Iowa State University) and Jane Glazebrook (University of Minnesota). There was also a plenary session to award the 4<span>rd</span>&nbsp;Barbara McClintock Prize for Plant Genetics and Genome Studies, recognizing Mike Freeling, as one of the most outstanding plant geneticists of the present era. The program included 35 ~20-minute talks by speakers selected from submitted abstracts, and two poster sessions.</p> <p>Two types of broadening participation awards were offered for the 59<span>th</span>&nbsp;Annual Maize Genetics Conference: Maize Genetics Network Enhancement through Travel (MaGNET) travel awards and conference fee awards for undergraduate and graduate students from under-represented groups and/or first-time attendees of the conference. The MaGNET travel awards provided full travel funding plus all conference fees for 9 minority participants (4 African-American, 5 Latino/Hispanic) and two faculty mentors accompanying students from minority-serving institutions. Additionally, there were 50 broadening participation awards that funded minority participants, and first-time attendees.</p> <p>Participants for both types of awards were recruited by the Maize Genetics Conference Steering Committee using the conference website and targeted advertising. Additionally, an email was sent to the entire Maize Genetics Community asking for help identifying and encouraging qualified individuals to apply for the MaGNET awards. These advertisements resulted in 25 applications with 14 applicants qualifying for an award.</p> <p>At the conference MaGNET awardees were matched with colleagues from the maize genetics community (i.e., faculty, postdoc, or graduate student mentors). The mentors and MaGNET awardees exchanged emails and text messages before the meeting to acquaint themselves and answer any questions related to the meeting. The mentors and awardees met at a separate meeting immediately prior to the start of the conference for face-to-face introductions and a welcome orientation from Erich Grotewold explaining the history of the conference, the MaGNET program, what to expect during the conference, and to answer any questions. The mentors then took their mentees to the initial welcoming session, dinner, plenary talks, and reception as well as the poster sessions. In addition, the MaGNET awardees had a separate lunch with all of the invited, plenary speakers, NSF program officers, and an USDA-ARS National Program Leader. Additionally, several distinguished leaders in the maize genetics community also attended. The graduate student mentors also attended this lunch. The goal of the Awardee-Speaker lunch was to improve awareness of professional opportunities in plant biology and maize genetics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/09/2018<br>      Modified by: Erich&nbsp;Grotewold</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 59th Annual Maize Genetics Conference was held March 9-12, 2017, at Union Station, St. Louis, MO. The conference was attended by a record 678 scientists, including 209 graduate students and 32 undergraduate students. The 59th Annual meeting also featured talks by four invited plenary speakers: Rebecca Nelson (Cornell University), Nathan Springer (University of Minnesota), Philip Becraft (Iowa State University) and Jane Glazebrook (University of Minnesota). There was also a plenary session to award the 4rd Barbara McClintock Prize for Plant Genetics and Genome Studies, recognizing Mike Freeling, as one of the most outstanding plant geneticists of the present era. The program included 35 ~20-minute talks by speakers selected from submitted abstracts, and two poster sessions.  Two types of broadening participation awards were offered for the 59th Annual Maize Genetics Conference: Maize Genetics Network Enhancement through Travel (MaGNET) travel awards and conference fee awards for undergraduate and graduate students from under-represented groups and/or first-time attendees of the conference. The MaGNET travel awards provided full travel funding plus all conference fees for 9 minority participants (4 African-American, 5 Latino/Hispanic) and two faculty mentors accompanying students from minority-serving institutions. Additionally, there were 50 broadening participation awards that funded minority participants, and first-time attendees.  Participants for both types of awards were recruited by the Maize Genetics Conference Steering Committee using the conference website and targeted advertising. Additionally, an email was sent to the entire Maize Genetics Community asking for help identifying and encouraging qualified individuals to apply for the MaGNET awards. These advertisements resulted in 25 applications with 14 applicants qualifying for an award.  At the conference MaGNET awardees were matched with colleagues from the maize genetics community (i.e., faculty, postdoc, or graduate student mentors). The mentors and MaGNET awardees exchanged emails and text messages before the meeting to acquaint themselves and answer any questions related to the meeting. The mentors and awardees met at a separate meeting immediately prior to the start of the conference for face-to-face introductions and a welcome orientation from Erich Grotewold explaining the history of the conference, the MaGNET program, what to expect during the conference, and to answer any questions. The mentors then took their mentees to the initial welcoming session, dinner, plenary talks, and reception as well as the poster sessions. In addition, the MaGNET awardees had a separate lunch with all of the invited, plenary speakers, NSF program officers, and an USDA-ARS National Program Leader. Additionally, several distinguished leaders in the maize genetics community also attended. The graduate student mentors also attended this lunch. The goal of the Awardee-Speaker lunch was to improve awareness of professional opportunities in plant biology and maize genetics.          Last Modified: 03/09/2018       Submitted by: Erich Grotewold]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
