<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Enhancing Undergraduate Research Experiences in Networked Cyber-Physical Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>324000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>324000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Forbes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jforbes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925301</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award establishes a new Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site at Wichita State University.  The REU Site will host undergraduate students from across the nation to conduct research during the summer with faculty mentors on networked cyber-physical systems. Cyber-physical systems are engineered systems that are built from and depend on the seamless integration of computational algorithms and physical components.  Cyber-physical systems often present significant communications and networking challenges due to the complex, real-world environments in which the devices are expected to operate.  The environments are diverse and range from operating underwater to flying in the air. They could involve use in manufacturing facilities or simple use as personal devices. The project plans to recruit a diverse cohort of undergraduate students each summer, including students from groups traditionally under-represented in computing.   In addition to their research activities, the students will participate in other professional development activities that will prepare them for entering the computing workforce and for possible futures as researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The REU site is led by faculty mentors from the computer networking group within the Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science at Wichita State University. The affiliated research laboratories provide students with opportunities to use state-of-the-art equipment and facilities to explore topics that are current and timely with faculty mentors who have significant experience and expertise in the area of networked cyber-physical systems.  Realizing networked cyber-physical systems presents a rich set of research problems in areas such as indoor and outdoor positioning and localization, wireless communications and networking, security and privacy, cloud computing, mobile and wearable computing, and data analytics.  The goals of the project are to advance the technical field of networked cyber-physical systems while simultaneously preparing the next generation of graduate students and workforce participants. This project is jointly funded by the Directorate for Computer and Information Science and Engineering (CISE) and the Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/17/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/17/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1659396</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vinod</FirstName>
<LastName>Namboodiri</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vinod Namboodiri</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vinod.namboodiri@wichita.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3169783922</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000524543</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/17/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wichita State University</Name>
<CityName>Wichita</CityName>
<ZipCode>672600007</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3169783285</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1845 Fairmount</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Box 007]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KS04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053078127</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WICHITA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053078127</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wichita State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Wichita</CityName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>672600007</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KS04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~324000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) grant was awarded to Wichita State University (WSU) by the National Science Foundation in 2017.&nbsp; The purpose of the grant was to host a REU site at WSU to offer research opportunities to undergraduate (UG) students, especially those from underrepresented groups who are interested in <em>Networked Cyber-Physical Systems (CPS)</em>. Over the three-year duration of the proposed grant, 31 undergraduate students worked within research groups supervised by faculty with expertise in various aspects of Networked Cyber-Physical Systems (CPS). The WSU REU site was open to undergraduate students majoring in computer science, computer engineering, electrical engineering, information technology, and telecommunications engineering.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Thirty-one participants worked on a range of research projects within the Networked Cyber-Physical Systems theme; areas included assistive technologies for persons with disabilities, blockchain technology, secure manufacturing, privacy aspects of wearable computing, underwater sensor networks, among others. Participants came to the site from various parts of the country with only a total four students enrolled at the host institution. Over the course of the site, 8 different mentors were involved with participants along with their graduate students. All participants received training in conducting research, writing technical papers/reports and giving technical presentations. Furthermore, they were educated about research ethics and best practices in conducting research. All students were also provided information about applying to graduate school and fellowship opportunities in addition to other career mentoring.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Of the thirty-one participants of the site, 6 participants have reported to have begun a graduate program of study upon completion of their undergraduate studies with two more actively looking to commence such activities. Six different participants have authored/presented their work at national conferences (some of them as co-authors). &nbsp;Participants in all three summer programs responded positively (80% or higher) to exit survey questions related to gaining &ldquo;a better understanding of the nature of computer science/engineering research,&rdquo; to gaining &ldquo;a better understanding of the nature of graduate study in computer science/engineering,&rdquo; &ldquo;improved research skills,&rdquo; and &ldquo;awareness about NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program.&rdquo;&nbsp; In terms of recruitment of participants from underrepresented groups, the site was able to reach 42% from among the 31 participants. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/15/2021<br>      Modified by: Vinod&nbsp;Namboodiri</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) grant was awarded to Wichita State University (WSU) by the National Science Foundation in 2017.  The purpose of the grant was to host a REU site at WSU to offer research opportunities to undergraduate (UG) students, especially those from underrepresented groups who are interested in Networked Cyber-Physical Systems (CPS). Over the three-year duration of the proposed grant, 31 undergraduate students worked within research groups supervised by faculty with expertise in various aspects of Networked Cyber-Physical Systems (CPS). The WSU REU site was open to undergraduate students majoring in computer science, computer engineering, electrical engineering, information technology, and telecommunications engineering.     Thirty-one participants worked on a range of research projects within the Networked Cyber-Physical Systems theme; areas included assistive technologies for persons with disabilities, blockchain technology, secure manufacturing, privacy aspects of wearable computing, underwater sensor networks, among others. Participants came to the site from various parts of the country with only a total four students enrolled at the host institution. Over the course of the site, 8 different mentors were involved with participants along with their graduate students. All participants received training in conducting research, writing technical papers/reports and giving technical presentations. Furthermore, they were educated about research ethics and best practices in conducting research. All students were also provided information about applying to graduate school and fellowship opportunities in addition to other career mentoring.     Of the thirty-one participants of the site, 6 participants have reported to have begun a graduate program of study upon completion of their undergraduate studies with two more actively looking to commence such activities. Six different participants have authored/presented their work at national conferences (some of them as co-authors).  Participants in all three summer programs responded positively (80% or higher) to exit survey questions related to gaining "a better understanding of the nature of computer science/engineering research," to gaining "a better understanding of the nature of graduate study in computer science/engineering," "improved research skills," and "awareness about NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program."  In terms of recruitment of participants from underrepresented groups, the site was able to reach 42% from among the 31 participants.               Last Modified: 07/15/2021       Submitted by: Vinod Namboodiri]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
