<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Conference on Rock Magnetism</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>29000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robin Reichlin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rreichli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928556</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide partial support to hold a Conference on Rock Magnetism and its Applications in July, 2017 in Utrecht, the Netherlands, continuing a biennial series of such conferences. Previous gatherings in the series have mainly been held in Santa Fe, NM (ten meetings between 1992 and 2014), with two prior international editions: Erice, Sicily in 2002 and Cargese, Corsica in 2008, both of which were co-organized by the Institute for Rock Magnetism (IRM) and European colleagues and co-sponsored by funding agencies from several countries. These occasional forays outside the US promote more extensive interaction with international scientists and students, who are vital contributors to this field of research. The 2017 meeting will be organized in collaboration with the "Fort Hoofdijk" magnetics research group at Utrecht University. This award will provide partial coverage of participant travel expenses for US students, post-docs and early career faculty.  Broader impacts of this activity include: (1) transdisciplinary and interdisciplinary communications to foster new approaches to geoscience problems involving iron minerals and their use as paleomagnetic field recorders and as indicators of paleoenvironmental conditions and processes; and (2) the development of young scientists by providing the opportunity to meet and interact with leading international researchers, gaining deeper understanding and broader perspective, and  forming a basis for future cross-disciplinary collaborations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Rapid advances in research on magnetism and magnetic materials are occurring in geophysics, geochemistry, nanoscience, condensed-matter physics, and to a great extent, along the boundaries between these fields. An interdisciplinary discussion of critical developments in the geoscience applications of fine-particle magnetism, and their fundamental physical foundations, will help to advance our understanding of Earth?s surface environment, its lithospheric plates and its deep interior.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1660603</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dario</FirstName>
<LastName>Bilardello</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dario Bilardello</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dario@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126245599</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000643282</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Jackson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael J Jackson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jacks057@tc.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000382186</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Moskowitz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce M Moskowitz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bmosk@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126241547</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000174907</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Feinberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua M Feinberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>feinberg@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126245599</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000096871</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>Geobiology &amp; Low-Temp Geochem</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~29000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Organized by the faculty and staff of the University of Minnesota's Institute for Rock Magnetism (IRM) in collaboration with colleagues from the Netherlands, the 2017 International Conference on Rock Magnetism was held June 26-29, 2017 on the campus of Utrecht University in the Netherlands, and was attended by one hundred US and international scientists and graduate students. The broad goal of the IRM&rsquo;s biennial conference series is to bring together present and future leaders in rock magnetism, paleomagnetism and related fields for in-depth discussion of fundamental aspects of mineral magnetism, as well as applications in global geophysics, tectonics, extraterrestrial magnetism, and surficial environmental studies. These meetings are designed to allow collaborative exploration of the state of the art in magnetic geophysics and its applications throughout the natural sciences (including environmental science, geobiology, mineral physics and others), in an informal but intensive and sustained, interactive discussion-oriented mode. Ultimately the purpose is to advance our ability to understand the evolution of the Earth's deep interior and its surface environments, by analyzing the information stored in the magnetically-ordered Iron minerals contained in rocks and sediments.</p> <p>The IRM&rsquo;s biennial conferences are most frequently held in the US (in Santa Fe NM), but approximately once per decade they are moved to a foreign venue, as for this conference.&nbsp; The rationale for this is that the geomagnetism/rock magnetism/paleomagnetism (GP) research community in the US and elsewhere in North America is relatively small in number but broad in interests and diverse in specific areas of expertise, and the same is true of the European and Asian/Australian GP communities.&nbsp; The inevitable result is that there are specialized areas in which international researchers are more advanced than their US counterparts &ndash; and similarly, there are particular strengths in the US GP research community.&nbsp; The importance of exchange is clearly recognized on both sides, and the international conferences are particularly well attended and scientifically productive.</p> <p>Frontier research areas covered in the 2017 conference included: (1) the fundamental physics of rock and mineral magnetism; (2) the sources and significance of crustal anomalies detected in aeromagnetic or satellite magnetic surveys; (3) environmental magnetism, the effects of climate and environmental conditions on iron minerals that can be characterized by magnetic property measurements; (4) determination of paleomagnetic field strength from terrestrial and extraterrestrial materials; (5) records of past magnetic field variations stored in the magnetization of sediments; and (6) advanced experimental methods of rock magnetic characterization and data analysis.</p> <p>Each of these research areas is the subject of sustained and intensive study by research groups around the world. Naturally, the ultimate solutions to the problems outlined above still remain to be discovered, but focused interactive gatherings like this, with leading international and interdisciplinary researchers and students, constitute a very important part of the process of discovery. In this context, the IRM Conferences help to advance the state of the art in magnetic geophysics and its Earth-science applications.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/14/2019<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;J&nbsp;Jackson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Organized by the faculty and staff of the University of Minnesota's Institute for Rock Magnetism (IRM) in collaboration with colleagues from the Netherlands, the 2017 International Conference on Rock Magnetism was held June 26-29, 2017 on the campus of Utrecht University in the Netherlands, and was attended by one hundred US and international scientists and graduate students. The broad goal of the IRM?s biennial conference series is to bring together present and future leaders in rock magnetism, paleomagnetism and related fields for in-depth discussion of fundamental aspects of mineral magnetism, as well as applications in global geophysics, tectonics, extraterrestrial magnetism, and surficial environmental studies. These meetings are designed to allow collaborative exploration of the state of the art in magnetic geophysics and its applications throughout the natural sciences (including environmental science, geobiology, mineral physics and others), in an informal but intensive and sustained, interactive discussion-oriented mode. Ultimately the purpose is to advance our ability to understand the evolution of the Earth's deep interior and its surface environments, by analyzing the information stored in the magnetically-ordered Iron minerals contained in rocks and sediments.  The IRM?s biennial conferences are most frequently held in the US (in Santa Fe NM), but approximately once per decade they are moved to a foreign venue, as for this conference.  The rationale for this is that the geomagnetism/rock magnetism/paleomagnetism (GP) research community in the US and elsewhere in North America is relatively small in number but broad in interests and diverse in specific areas of expertise, and the same is true of the European and Asian/Australian GP communities.  The inevitable result is that there are specialized areas in which international researchers are more advanced than their US counterparts &ndash; and similarly, there are particular strengths in the US GP research community.  The importance of exchange is clearly recognized on both sides, and the international conferences are particularly well attended and scientifically productive.  Frontier research areas covered in the 2017 conference included: (1) the fundamental physics of rock and mineral magnetism; (2) the sources and significance of crustal anomalies detected in aeromagnetic or satellite magnetic surveys; (3) environmental magnetism, the effects of climate and environmental conditions on iron minerals that can be characterized by magnetic property measurements; (4) determination of paleomagnetic field strength from terrestrial and extraterrestrial materials; (5) records of past magnetic field variations stored in the magnetization of sediments; and (6) advanced experimental methods of rock magnetic characterization and data analysis.  Each of these research areas is the subject of sustained and intensive study by research groups around the world. Naturally, the ultimate solutions to the problems outlined above still remain to be discovered, but focused interactive gatherings like this, with leading international and interdisciplinary researchers and students, constitute a very important part of the process of discovery. In this context, the IRM Conferences help to advance the state of the art in magnetic geophysics and its Earth-science applications.       Last Modified: 02/14/2019       Submitted by: Michael J Jackson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
