<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WiFiUS: Collaborative Research: Sequential Inference and Learning for Agile Spectrum Use</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>85988.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>85988</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Monisha Ghosh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A key imperative to expanding future wireless services is to overcome the spectral crunch. At present, static allocation and rigid regulation lead to under utilization of available spectral resources. Flexible spectrum use aims at exploiting under-utilized spectrum. Available spectrum opportunities may be non-contiguous, scattered over a large bandwidth, and are available locally and for a limited period of time due to the highly dynamic nature of wireless transmissions. This fuels the need to understand how to discover, assess and utilize the time-frequency-location varying spectral resources efficiently and with minimal delay. Moreover, it is critical to access identified idle spectrum in an agile manner.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will design sequential inference and learning algorithms for agile spectrum access when the state of the spectrum varies rapidly. The key advantage of sequential algorithms, as compared to block-wise algorithms, is that they typically lead to significantly reduced decision delays. The overarching goal of this project is to design sequential inference and learning algorithms for agile spectrum utilization. In particular, this project will employ advanced sequential inference and learning methods for the following three interconnected yet increasingly sophisticated and demanding tasks: 1) to employ sequential reinforcement learning and sequential inference algorithms to design sensing policies for rapid spectrum opportunities discovery; 2) to design sequential algorithms for fast and accurate spectrum quality assessment; and 3) to build, maintain and exploit an interference map of the area where our network operates and represent it as a spatial potential field. The proposed research is expected to make substantial contributions to both applications and theory. On the application level, the proposed research has the potential to substantially improve spectral efficiency by introducing novel tools from sequential analysis, machine learning and statistical inference for the design of spectrum discovery, assessment and exploitation policies. On the theoretical level, the proposed project will advance the state of the art in sequential analysis and contribute new approaches to the general methodological base for optimal stopping, control and machine learning problems. Furthermore, new methods and theory of modeling and exploiting knowledge of interference using spatial potential fields, sequential statistics and advanced propagation modeling will be developed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1660128</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lifeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Lai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lifeng Lai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lflai@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307527978</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000541215</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>2878</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CCF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8229</Code>
<Text>WiFiUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~85988</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The goal of the project is to design sequential inference and learning algorithms for agile spectrum access when the state of the spectrum varies rapidly. The key advantage of sequential algorithms, as compared to block-wise algorithms, is that these sequential algorithms typically lead to significantly reduced decision delays. In the project, we investigated three main lines of research:</span></p> <p>1. Quickest transmission opportunity detection in a wideband system: In a typical wideband system with multiple channels, transmission opportunity may arise in a subset of channels. In our study, we propose several different approaches to quickly detect the presence of transmission opportunities. First,&nbsp;<span>we propose a novel two-stage mixed-observation sensing strategy. In the first stage, which is named as scanning stage, the sensor observes a linear combination of the signals from a pair of channels. The purpose of the scanning stage is to quickly identify a pair of channels such that at least one of them is highly likely to be unoccupied. In the second stage, which is called refinement stage, the sensor only observers the signal from one of those two channels identified from the first stage, and selects one of them as the unoccupied channel.</span>&nbsp; Second, we formulate this problem as a correlated components identification in Gaussian vectors problem. The sensor is capable of observing any subset of components in the underlying signal. We design an algorithm that enables&nbsp;the observer to select the most efficient sampling strategy to minimize the false identification probability. Third,&nbsp; we model the problem as a non-Bayesian multichannel quickest change-point detection problem, for which we propose a detection procedure with a channel switching rule and a detection stopping rule, based on the cumulative sum statistic.&nbsp;</p> <p>2. Transmission opportunity detection with model&nbsp;uncertainties: In this thrust, we focus on the scenarios with unknown parameters about the operating environment. We model the problem of quick transmission opportunity detection under this scenario as a Bayesian quickest change-point detection problem with incomplete post-change information. In particular, we consider a model in which the observer knows that the post-change distribution belongs to a parametric distribution family, but he does not know the true value of the post-change parameter. We study two problem formulations. In the first formulation, we assume no additional prior information about the post-change parameter. In this case, the observer aims to design a detection algorithm to minimize the average (over the change-point) detection delay for all possible post-change parameters simultaneously subject to a worst case false alarm constraint. In the second formulation, we assume that there is a prior distribution on the possible value of the unknown parameter. For this case, we propose another formulation that minimizes the average (over both the change-point and the post-change parameter) detection delay subject to an average false alarm constraint. We propose a novel algorithm, which is termed as M-Shiryaev procedure, and show that the proposed algorithm is first order asymptotically optimal for both formulations studied.</p> <p>3.&nbsp;Distributed spectrum sensing with optional observations at the fusion center: In this line of work, we consider distributed detection setup where multiple sensors are deployed to improve the detection performances. In a typical distributed detection setup,there are multiple peripheral sensors and a fusion center. In all existing work, the fusion center will make a final decision solely based on local decisions from the peripheral sensors. In our work, we propose a novel model that the fusion center, after receiving the alarms from peripheral sensors, has the option to make its own observations before raising a final alarm. This additional flexibility will be valuable when the quality of observations at peripheral sensors are low. Under a Bayesian setup, we consider the design of optimal policies at both the peripheral sensor and the coordinating sensor to minimize a cost function that is a linear combination of the false&nbsp;alarm probability and the expected detection delay. This problem can be formulated as an optimal multiple stopping time problem. Using tools from the ordered optimal multiple stopping theory, we show that, rather than the whole observation sequences, the optimal policies can depend only on the posterior probability information state. Building on this result, we derive optimal policies for the cases with and without strict deadlines.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/06/2018<br>      Modified by: Lifeng&nbsp;Lai</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of the project is to design sequential inference and learning algorithms for agile spectrum access when the state of the spectrum varies rapidly. The key advantage of sequential algorithms, as compared to block-wise algorithms, is that these sequential algorithms typically lead to significantly reduced decision delays. In the project, we investigated three main lines of research:  1. Quickest transmission opportunity detection in a wideband system: In a typical wideband system with multiple channels, transmission opportunity may arise in a subset of channels. In our study, we propose several different approaches to quickly detect the presence of transmission opportunities. First, we propose a novel two-stage mixed-observation sensing strategy. In the first stage, which is named as scanning stage, the sensor observes a linear combination of the signals from a pair of channels. The purpose of the scanning stage is to quickly identify a pair of channels such that at least one of them is highly likely to be unoccupied. In the second stage, which is called refinement stage, the sensor only observers the signal from one of those two channels identified from the first stage, and selects one of them as the unoccupied channel.  Second, we formulate this problem as a correlated components identification in Gaussian vectors problem. The sensor is capable of observing any subset of components in the underlying signal. We design an algorithm that enables the observer to select the most efficient sampling strategy to minimize the false identification probability. Third,  we model the problem as a non-Bayesian multichannel quickest change-point detection problem, for which we propose a detection procedure with a channel switching rule and a detection stopping rule, based on the cumulative sum statistic.   2. Transmission opportunity detection with model uncertainties: In this thrust, we focus on the scenarios with unknown parameters about the operating environment. We model the problem of quick transmission opportunity detection under this scenario as a Bayesian quickest change-point detection problem with incomplete post-change information. In particular, we consider a model in which the observer knows that the post-change distribution belongs to a parametric distribution family, but he does not know the true value of the post-change parameter. We study two problem formulations. In the first formulation, we assume no additional prior information about the post-change parameter. In this case, the observer aims to design a detection algorithm to minimize the average (over the change-point) detection delay for all possible post-change parameters simultaneously subject to a worst case false alarm constraint. In the second formulation, we assume that there is a prior distribution on the possible value of the unknown parameter. For this case, we propose another formulation that minimizes the average (over both the change-point and the post-change parameter) detection delay subject to an average false alarm constraint. We propose a novel algorithm, which is termed as M-Shiryaev procedure, and show that the proposed algorithm is first order asymptotically optimal for both formulations studied.  3. Distributed spectrum sensing with optional observations at the fusion center: In this line of work, we consider distributed detection setup where multiple sensors are deployed to improve the detection performances. In a typical distributed detection setup,there are multiple peripheral sensors and a fusion center. In all existing work, the fusion center will make a final decision solely based on local decisions from the peripheral sensors. In our work, we propose a novel model that the fusion center, after receiving the alarms from peripheral sensors, has the option to make its own observations before raising a final alarm. This additional flexibility will be valuable when the quality of observations at peripheral sensors are low. Under a Bayesian setup, we consider the design of optimal policies at both the peripheral sensor and the coordinating sensor to minimize a cost function that is a linear combination of the false alarm probability and the expected detection delay. This problem can be formulated as an optimal multiple stopping time problem. Using tools from the ordered optimal multiple stopping theory, we show that, rather than the whole observation sequences, the optimal policies can depend only on the posterior probability information state. Building on this result, we derive optimal policies for the cases with and without strict deadlines.       Last Modified: 05/06/2018       Submitted by: Lifeng Lai]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
