<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase II: Development and commercialization of a Wearable Long-term Monitor for Cardiac Arrhythmias</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>750000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>909999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase II project is far-reaching in terms of improving the quality of life and the cost/efficacy of healthcare for more than 20 Million people in the USA. We address the need for better methods for identifying and guiding the treatment of ambulatory patients with dangerous heart dysfunctions such as intermittent arrhythmias and heart failure. For example, atrial fibrillation arrhythmia afflicts nearly 8 Million patients in the USA, approximately 460,000 new patients every year, and the patient load is projected to grow to 12.1 million by 2050. The disease and its complications (stroke, congestive heart failure, seizures, death, etc.) add $26B to the nation's annual healthcare costs. Heart Failure currently afflicts nearly 5.7 Million people in the US growing to 8 Million by 2030. Their treatment and frequent hospitalization costs are already at 14B$ and will grow to 29B$ by 2030.  Together with reducing the economic impacts, it would be of an enormous benefit to human health to create a device that improves the diagnosis and guides effective therapy for these patients while they remain fully ambulatory and going about their normal activities outside the expensive confines of the hospital.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project has the following intellectual merits. In our Phase I STTR program we focused on developing a wearable Atrial Fibrillation monitor to assist physicians in the diagnosis of paroxysmal or episodic versions of that disorder. In Phase II we have pivoted towards the even more critical need of ambulatory monitoring of paroxysmal tachycardia and eventually heart failure patients. The current industry standard of ambulatory ECG does not provide enough sensitivity or specificity to determine if the patient has atypical or typical atrial flutter, paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardia as well as various forms of ventricular tachycardia. Accurately diagnosing and monitoring these disorders is critical to patient treatment and outcomes. Our device will be capable of ambulatory patient monitoring for any sort of arrhythmia, and we believe it can be the preferred choice for all portable monitoring if it provides in one device ECG, heart motion and breathing rate/pattern/volume. So, the overarching technical research goal of our Phase II work is to develop a full featured prototype cardiac motion sensor as described above that can be used for initial clinical tests. These features include: wearable, battery powered, signal storage, cardiac motion from radar, disposable antenna, onboard ECG, and breathing rate.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1660253</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoguang</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoguang Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lxgliu@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000614896</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
<LastName>Matthews</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dennis L Matthews</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dennis.matthews@cardiacmotion.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9167474209</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000672434</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cardiac Motion, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Truckee</CityName>
<ZipCode>961614835</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9167611667</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10121 Pine Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079410686</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARDIAC MOTION, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956165271</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Shield Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1591</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1591</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8240</Code>
<Text>SBIR/STTR CAP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~750000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~149999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcome Report &ndash; NSF STTR Phase II Grant #1660253</p> <p>Title: Wearable Long-term Monitor for Cardiac Arrythmias</p> <p>Recipient Organization: Cardiac Motion LLC</p> <p>Period: March 1, 2017 &ndash; Dec 31, 2019</p> <p>PI: Dennis Matthews, co-PI: Xiaoguang Liu</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase II project has developed a self-contained cardiac rhythm and motion monitor CardiaScan&trade;. The full prototype developed enables raw signal sensing and sampling of cardiac motion signal from radar, breathing rate and electrocardiogram. The CardiaScan&trade;&rsquo;s performance was tested in a wearable setting, which was compared with a number of different sensing modalities including electrocardiogram, ultrasonic imaging, and magnetic resonance imaging. Through both human and animal validation, it is shown that radar sensor developed is sensitive to movement of the heart wall, which has great potential in heart arrythmia, compromised cardiac output and heart failure detection.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition, this STTR Phase II project also provides a solution of application specific integrated circuit (ASIC) that realizes the sensing system on a chip design. This approach&nbsp;used a phase-locked loop-based system that is controlling a voltage-controlled oscillator to achieve self-injection locking (SIL) for vital sign detection.&nbsp;The system can potentially reduce areas and power consumption, offering simplicity to the wearable device realization.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impact/commercial potential of this STTR Phase II project is far-reaching in terms of improving the quality of life and the cost/efficacy of healthcare for more than 20 Million people in the USA. For example, atrial fibrillation arrhythmia afflicts nearly 8 Million patients in the USA, approximately 460,000 new patients every year, and the patient load is projected to grow to 12.1 million by 2050. The disease and its complications (stroke, congestive heart failure, seizures, death, etc.) add $26B to the nation's annual healthcare costs. Heart Failure currently afflicts nearly 5.7 Million people in the US growing to 8 Million by 2030. Their treatment and frequent hospitalization costs are already at 14B$ and will grow to 29B$ by 2030. Together with reducing the economic impacts, it addresses the need for better methods for identifying and guiding the treatment of ambulatory patients with dangerous heart dysfunctions such as intermittent arrhythmias and heart failure. It will make a dramatic change in how these medical conditions are discovered, treated and monitored by improving the diagnosis and guiding effective therapy for these patients while they remain fully ambulatory and going about their normal activities outside the expensive confines of the hospital.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project also led to employment of a summer graduate student intern and a part-time employee at the STTR funded company. Inherently, this project helps engage electrical engineering students, postdocs, professors, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) physicist and cardiologists in the field of medical device research, development and/or commercialization. This STTR project is done in full collaboration with a university partner, during which time skills, technologies, and infrastructure from the university in partnership with a private company were used to commercialize the novel medical device. The company will eventually be selling to large medical device companies thus creating new jobs as well as boosting local economy.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/27/2020<br>      Modified by: Dennis&nbsp;L&nbsp;Matthews</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcome Report &ndash; NSF STTR Phase II Grant #1660253  Title: Wearable Long-term Monitor for Cardiac Arrythmias  Recipient Organization: Cardiac Motion LLC  Period: March 1, 2017 &ndash; Dec 31, 2019  PI: Dennis Matthews, co-PI: Xiaoguang Liu     This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase II project has developed a self-contained cardiac rhythm and motion monitor CardiaScan&trade;. The full prototype developed enables raw signal sensing and sampling of cardiac motion signal from radar, breathing rate and electrocardiogram. The CardiaScan&trade;’s performance was tested in a wearable setting, which was compared with a number of different sensing modalities including electrocardiogram, ultrasonic imaging, and magnetic resonance imaging. Through both human and animal validation, it is shown that radar sensor developed is sensitive to movement of the heart wall, which has great potential in heart arrythmia, compromised cardiac output and heart failure detection.      In addition, this STTR Phase II project also provides a solution of application specific integrated circuit (ASIC) that realizes the sensing system on a chip design. This approach used a phase-locked loop-based system that is controlling a voltage-controlled oscillator to achieve self-injection locking (SIL) for vital sign detection. The system can potentially reduce areas and power consumption, offering simplicity to the wearable device realization.      The broader impact/commercial potential of this STTR Phase II project is far-reaching in terms of improving the quality of life and the cost/efficacy of healthcare for more than 20 Million people in the USA. For example, atrial fibrillation arrhythmia afflicts nearly 8 Million patients in the USA, approximately 460,000 new patients every year, and the patient load is projected to grow to 12.1 million by 2050. The disease and its complications (stroke, congestive heart failure, seizures, death, etc.) add $26B to the nation's annual healthcare costs. Heart Failure currently afflicts nearly 5.7 Million people in the US growing to 8 Million by 2030. Their treatment and frequent hospitalization costs are already at 14B$ and will grow to 29B$ by 2030. Together with reducing the economic impacts, it addresses the need for better methods for identifying and guiding the treatment of ambulatory patients with dangerous heart dysfunctions such as intermittent arrhythmias and heart failure. It will make a dramatic change in how these medical conditions are discovered, treated and monitored by improving the diagnosis and guiding effective therapy for these patients while they remain fully ambulatory and going about their normal activities outside the expensive confines of the hospital.   This project also led to employment of a summer graduate student intern and a part-time employee at the STTR funded company. Inherently, this project helps engage electrical engineering students, postdocs, professors, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) physicist and cardiologists in the field of medical device research, development and/or commercialization. This STTR project is done in full collaboration with a university partner, during which time skills, technologies, and infrastructure from the university in partnership with a private company were used to commercialize the novel medical device. The company will eventually be selling to large medical device companies thus creating new jobs as well as boosting local economy.           Last Modified: 02/27/2020       Submitted by: Dennis L Matthews]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
