<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Development of a radiometric receiver for 183 GHz.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>710802.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>720802</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is in the improvement of atmospheric state observations from various platforms. This compact, integrated and ?plug and play? receiver design will make the existing observations more available, more economical, and will also enable previously unattainable observations of water vapor distributions within the atmosphere. This environmental sensor?s small size and low power requirements enables its deployment on various airborne, spaceborne or ground-based platforms, such as unmanned aerial aircraft, nanosatellites, ocean buoys, and remotely located ground-based instruments. One promising commercial application is private weather observing satellite constellations. It has been estimated that around 400 remote sensing nano/microsatellites will be launched worldwide between the years of 2016-2018. Water vapor and cloud observations are among the most important observations promising further understanding of weather events and to better synoptic or mesoscale forecasts. Improved atmospheric observations are directly related to increasingly accurate and useful weather forecasts. The benefits are expected to extend widely across the economy. Meteorologists point to more accurate and rapidly refreshed atmospheric observations as one of the necessities for the continuous improvements in weather forecasting, understanding of the atmospheric physics and climate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 2 project will complete the design and build a fully functional prototype of a very compact, direct detection radiometer receiver, operating in the vicinity of the 183 GHz water vapor absorption line. All the receiver components will be designed and evaluated, including a noise source, detectors, filters, Monolithic Microwave Integrated circuits and others, first as individual parts and then within the assembly. A novel receiver architecture and integration of all components into one assembly allow for a drastic reduction in the receiver size and reduction of its power consumption, while improving its observational capabilities and stability. There are several aspects of the proposed effort that are unique and would provide profound advances in ultra-compact microwave radiometry. The receiver is expected to consume less than 0.5 Watt of power and weigh around 100 grams, with a continuous two-point calibration capability at its input.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/17/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1660250</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marian</FirstName>
<LastName>Klein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marian Klein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marian.klein@boulderest.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3035321198</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000084274</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/17/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boulder Environmental Sciences and Technology, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803039672</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3035321198</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5171 Eldorado Springs Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>623842619</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOULDER ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCES AND TECHNOLOGY, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boulder Environmental Sciences and Technology, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803039672</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5171 Eldorado Springs Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4096</Code>
<Text>COMMUNICATIONS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8240</Code>
<Text>SBIR/STTR CAP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~710802</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overall goal of this project was a development of an integrated microwave radiometer receiver operating in the vicinity of the 183.31&nbsp;GHz water vapor absorption line, from ~182 to ~199&nbsp;GHz. Such integrated and compact microwave radiometer will be used for environmental observation from various platforms, such as small satellites, unmanned and piloted aircraft, buoy based or ground based sensors.</p> <p>We were able to design and evaluate all of the receiver components to a certain level.</p> <p>The resulting design of the 183&nbsp;GHz 5&nbsp;channel, dual polarization receiver is shown in the enclosed image. Overall size of the receiver ~60 x 60 x 28&nbsp;mm. We originally estimated the receiver size to be comparable to a box of matches, which is 46 x 32 x 14&nbsp;mm. The dual polarization means the radiometer on the enclosed figure has two independent receivers and an integrated Ortho-Mode Transducer (OMT). Thus, its size is comparable to our initial estimate. The complete receiver power consumption is estimated to be just below 1&nbsp;W and its mass is ~103&nbsp;grams.</p> <p>We have developed and tested the following receiver components:</p> <ul> <li>Detectors</li> <li>Noise source</li> <li>Ambient load</li> <li>Hybrids (input and output)</li> <li>OMT</li> <li>Transitions (waveguide to microstrip to coplanar waveguide)</li> </ul> <p>We have designed and simulated performances of the following components:</p> <ul> <li>Low noise amplifiers and other MMICs</li> <li>Filters</li> </ul> <p>We have presented on conferences and meetings and other forums and talking to first adopters.</p> <p>Even though we did not achieve all of the project goals, it was a very important project for the integrated receivers&rsquo; technology development. We designed all of the receiver components, improved our understanding of the technological challenges involved and overcome many of them. We improved testing and assembly technologies for this frequency range.</p> <p>The project opened door to other business opportunities. We found a first customer for an airborne version of the radiometer. Our technology will support a NASA experiment. We are also in a process of designing a Microwave Weather Imaging CubeSat for another customer. The experience with this project and practices learned form the bases for this spacecraft development.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/04/2019<br>      Modified by: Marian&nbsp;Klein</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1660250/1660250_10477707_1564946277783_Receiver_image_183GHz--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1660250/1660250_10477707_1564946277783_Receiver_image_183GHz--rgov-800width.jpg" title="183 GHz radiometer receiver design"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1660250/1660250_10477707_1564946277783_Receiver_image_183GHz--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="183 GHz radiometer receiver design"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The 183 GHz integrated radiometer receiver</div> <div class="imageCredit">Boulder Environmental Sciences and Technology</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Marian&nbsp;Klein</div> <div class="imageTitle">183 GHz radiometer receiver design</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall goal of this project was a development of an integrated microwave radiometer receiver operating in the vicinity of the 183.31 GHz water vapor absorption line, from ~182 to ~199 GHz. Such integrated and compact microwave radiometer will be used for environmental observation from various platforms, such as small satellites, unmanned and piloted aircraft, buoy based or ground based sensors.  We were able to design and evaluate all of the receiver components to a certain level.  The resulting design of the 183 GHz 5 channel, dual polarization receiver is shown in the enclosed image. Overall size of the receiver ~60 x 60 x 28 mm. We originally estimated the receiver size to be comparable to a box of matches, which is 46 x 32 x 14 mm. The dual polarization means the radiometer on the enclosed figure has two independent receivers and an integrated Ortho-Mode Transducer (OMT). Thus, its size is comparable to our initial estimate. The complete receiver power consumption is estimated to be just below 1 W and its mass is ~103 grams.  We have developed and tested the following receiver components:  Detectors Noise source Ambient load Hybrids (input and output) OMT Transitions (waveguide to microstrip to coplanar waveguide)   We have designed and simulated performances of the following components:  Low noise amplifiers and other MMICs Filters   We have presented on conferences and meetings and other forums and talking to first adopters.  Even though we did not achieve all of the project goals, it was a very important project for the integrated receivers? technology development. We designed all of the receiver components, improved our understanding of the technological challenges involved and overcome many of them. We improved testing and assembly technologies for this frequency range.  The project opened door to other business opportunities. We found a first customer for an airborne version of the radiometer. Our technology will support a NASA experiment. We are also in a process of designing a Microwave Weather Imaging CubeSat for another customer. The experience with this project and practices learned form the bases for this spacecraft development.       Last Modified: 08/04/2019       Submitted by: Marian Klein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
