<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Mechanisms on Developable Surfaces</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>425001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>441001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathryn Jablokow</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kjabloko@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928360</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>There is an increasing demand for ultra-compact mechanical systems that are capable of complex tasks. Developable mechanisms are envisioned as next-generation mechanical systems to meet these needs. A developable surface can be thought of as a shape that can be made from a thin sheet of material without breaking or stretching. The term "developable mechanism" is coined to describe a mechanism that conforms to or is created from a developable surface. Developable mechanisms can be used in applications as diverse as spacecraft, automobiles, ships, architecture, furniture, clothing construction, and medical devices. They can also conform to or emerge from developable surfaces such as aircraft fuselages and wings, submarine hulls, rocket cones, and minimally invasive surgery tools. They make possible new mechanisms in highly constrained spaces (such as medical implants, next generation electronics equipment, and deployable aerospace components), and applications with limited manufacturing processes available (such as high-volume production and cost-sensitive applications). Results from this research will enable engineers to meet future and presently-unfulfilled needs for hyper-compact mechanisms in several important application areas. This will be demonstrated on industry applications. Although their motion is mathematically complex, developable mechanism fabrication is increasingly possible and accessible using 3-D printers and computer-controlled tools common to maker spaces. This accessibility, combined with plans to distribute open-source design materials, will make the research results useful to a broad community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives of this research are to advance understanding of developable mechanism fundamentals and use this knowledge to create methods for their analysis and design. This will include a thorough investigation of the properties, motion criteria and kinematics of developable mechanisms on fundamental developable surfaces, such as generalized cylinders, planes, cones, and tangent developable, and extensions to hybrid developable surfaces. Design guides and engineering models will be verified and demonstrated by designing and testing physical prototypes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1663345</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Spencer</FirstName>
<LastName>Magleby</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Spencer P Magleby</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>magleby@byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8014223151</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000413010</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Larry</FirstName>
<LastName>Howell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Larry L Howell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lhowell@byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8014228037</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000423514</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Denise</FirstName>
<LastName>Halverson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Denise Halverson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>halverson@math.byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8014221207</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000417626</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brigham Young University</Name>
<CityName>Provo</CityName>
<ZipCode>846021231</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8014223360</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>A-285 ASB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Campus Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009094012</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BRIGHAM YOUNG UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001940170</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brigham Young University]]></Name>
<CityName>Provo</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>846024201</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[435 CTB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT"</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>072Y</Code>
<Text>EDSE-Engineering Design and Sy</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1464</Code>
<Text>ESD-Eng &amp; Systems Design</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>067E</Code>
<Text>DESIGN TOOLS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068E</Code>
<Text>DESIGN THEORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~425001</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Developable mechanisms meet the demand for ultra-compact mechanical systems that are capable of complex tasks. The term "developable mechanism" was coined to describe a mechanism that conforms to a developable surface, such as a cylinder, cone, or tangent developed surface. Developable mechanisms are envisioned to be used in applications as diverse as spacecraft, automobiles, ships, architecture, furniture, clothing construction, and medical devices. They create desired motion in highly constrained spaces such as medical implants, next generation electronics equipment, and deployable aerospace components.</p> <p>The primary objective of the work was to create engineering models for analysis and synthesis of developable mechanisms, and to verify and demonstrate those models by designing and testing physical prototypes. Developable mechanism properties were defined, engineering models for their analysis and design were created and verified, design guides were demonstrated in hardware, the results were disseminated through peer-reviewed venues, and a broader community was engaged through industry applications, outreach videos, and providing resources to the maker community.</p> <p>Deliverables include documentation of engineering models; developable mechanisms prototypes; verification of analysis and design via hardware and applications; engineering student education; and open-source materials for the maker community.</p> <p>Four broader impact goals were also an important part of the work. 1. Education: Students were intimately involved in all aspects of the research and the largest budget item was dedicated to their support (ten graduate students completed theses or dissertations and many undergraduate students were involved). 2. Technical publications and presentations: Traditional academic venues were utilized for dissemination, including peer-reviewed journal publications (sixteen published so far) &nbsp;and conference presentations (thirteen papers published in conference proceedings to date). 3. Technology impact: Developable mechanisms' extraordinary compactness impacts diverse areas (six patent applications are pending and two option agreements negotiated). 4. Open access "maker" resources: Realizing sophisticated motions from easily manufactured topologies make developable mechanism designs ideal for engaging the maker community (approximately one hundred thousand downloads of files for 3D printing and millions of views of outreach videos).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/11/2021<br>      Modified by: Larry&nbsp;L&nbsp;Howell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722192886_1901-360385--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722192886_1901-360385--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cylindrical developable mechanism"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722192886_1901-360385--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cylindrical developable mechanism"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A cylindrical developable mechanism deployed from a cylindrical tube.</div> <div class="imageCredit">BYU Photo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Larry&nbsp;L&nbsp;Howell</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cylindrical developable mechanism</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722248169_3Devices--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722248169_3Devices--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Developable mechanism demontrators"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722248169_3Devices--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Developable mechanism demontrators"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3. Developable mechanism motion demonstrated on three fundamental developable surfaces: tangent developed (left), cone (center) and cylinder (right), with the conformed position (top) and deployed position (bottom).</div> <div class="imageCredit">BYU Photo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Larry&nbsp;L&nbsp;Howell</div> <div class="imageTitle">Developable mechanism demontrators</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722325396_1901-360005--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722325396_1901-360005--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Education of students"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722325396_1901-360005--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Education of students"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students were intimately involved in all aspects of the research and their education was a key objective of the work.</div> <div class="imageCredit">BYU Photo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Larry&nbsp;L&nbsp;Howell</div> <div class="imageTitle">Education of students</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722525203_1901-270329(2)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722525203_1901-270329(2)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Medical instrument through developable mechanisms"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722525203_1901-270329(2)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Medical instrument through developable mechanisms"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 4: An early prototype of a medical instrument that employs developable mechanism technology to embed features that deploy from the cylindrical cannula, while still allowing room for the surgical instrument. This was the focus of a related NSF I-Corps project focused on commercializing the res</div> <div class="imageCredit">BYU Photo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Larry&nbsp;L&nbsp;Howell</div> <div class="imageTitle">Medical instrument through developable mechanisms</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722673228_CylindricalDevelopable_landscape--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722673228_CylindricalDevelopable_landscape--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cylindrical developable mechanism"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628722673228_CylindricalDevelopable_landscape--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cylindrical developable mechanism"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A cylindrical developable mechanism deployed from a cylindrical tube. Left: looking down the cylinder. Right: isometric view.</div> <div class="imageCredit">BYU Photo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Larry&nbsp;L&nbsp;Howell</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cylindrical developable mechanism</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628723475983_1901-270382(2)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628723475983_1901-270382(2)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="A tangent developed mechanism."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1663345/1663345_10484525_1628723475983_1901-270382(2)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="A tangent developed mechanism."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A tangent developed mechanism.</div> <div class="imageCredit">BYU Photo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Larry&nbsp;L&nbsp;Howell</div> <div class="imageTitle">A tangent developed mechanism.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Developable mechanisms meet the demand for ultra-compact mechanical systems that are capable of complex tasks. The term "developable mechanism" was coined to describe a mechanism that conforms to a developable surface, such as a cylinder, cone, or tangent developed surface. Developable mechanisms are envisioned to be used in applications as diverse as spacecraft, automobiles, ships, architecture, furniture, clothing construction, and medical devices. They create desired motion in highly constrained spaces such as medical implants, next generation electronics equipment, and deployable aerospace components.  The primary objective of the work was to create engineering models for analysis and synthesis of developable mechanisms, and to verify and demonstrate those models by designing and testing physical prototypes. Developable mechanism properties were defined, engineering models for their analysis and design were created and verified, design guides were demonstrated in hardware, the results were disseminated through peer-reviewed venues, and a broader community was engaged through industry applications, outreach videos, and providing resources to the maker community.  Deliverables include documentation of engineering models; developable mechanisms prototypes; verification of analysis and design via hardware and applications; engineering student education; and open-source materials for the maker community.  Four broader impact goals were also an important part of the work. 1. Education: Students were intimately involved in all aspects of the research and the largest budget item was dedicated to their support (ten graduate students completed theses or dissertations and many undergraduate students were involved). 2. Technical publications and presentations: Traditional academic venues were utilized for dissemination, including peer-reviewed journal publications (sixteen published so far)  and conference presentations (thirteen papers published in conference proceedings to date). 3. Technology impact: Developable mechanisms' extraordinary compactness impacts diverse areas (six patent applications are pending and two option agreements negotiated). 4. Open access "maker" resources: Realizing sophisticated motions from easily manufactured topologies make developable mechanism designs ideal for engaging the maker community (approximately one hundred thousand downloads of files for 3D printing and millions of views of outreach videos).          Last Modified: 08/11/2021       Submitted by: Larry L Howell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
