<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Impact of the Human Genome Project on Scientific Discovery and Industry Evolution</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>21650.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>21650</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cassidy Sugimoto</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In March 2000, the Human Genome Project (HGP), the world's largest, publicly funded, collaborative biology project sequenced and released the first map of the human genome. This important development in human biology was aimed at revolutionizing our understanding of basic biological mechanisms, change how new drugs were discovered and improve medical care. The human genome is a digital map of 3 billion DNA base pairs revealing the location and identity of genes, which encode various proteins in cells and allow for a high level of specificity in the search for disease targets. The scientific approach was radically different from existing discovery paradigms. The attractiveness of a free genome map along with its predictive search capabilities lowered barriers to entry, leading to a sharp increase in new firm formation and entrepreneurship. The map, in effect, changed how firms searched for drugs and altered the competitive nature of the industry. Changes in the nature of discovery due to the Human Genome Project provide a unique opportunity to study the process of technological search under different informational and technological contexts and can inform the role of government-funded projects in providing economic and public health benefit.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study analyzes incumbent firms, new entrants and universities, and their R&amp;D projects in granular detail to shed light on how the human genome map impacted the exploration of new drugs and diseases, and trajectory of the biopharmaceutical industry. The project constructs an original and unique database of small molecule drug patents to trace the trajectories of search and evolution of R&amp;D projects before and after the HGP. The project links powerful computational techniques from text-mining and chemical/bio informatics with genomics and clinical trial databases to provide a rich, multi-level analysis of firm search behavior in the context of technological change.  The project demonstrates how the availability of predictive, large-scale search capabilities changed firm?s innovative behavior.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1664380</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michelle</FirstName>
<LastName>Gittelman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michelle Gittelman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>michelle.gittelman@business.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9733531538</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000692380</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sebastian</FirstName>
<LastName>Jayaraj</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sebastian Jayaraj</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sebastian.jayaraj@rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5103874886</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000731579</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University Newark</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>071021896</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9739720283</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Blumenthal Hall, Suite 206</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[249 University Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>130029205</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University Newark]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>071021896</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7009</Code>
<Text>SciSIP-DDRIG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~21650</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Scientific mapping projects like the ongoing US BRAIN initiative and Human Cell Atlas are data intensive endeavors that curate immense amounts of information. But their impact on innovation is not well understood. Innovation can be conceptualized as a spatial process, where firms and inventors search either locally or in distant, lesser explored, territories. In my PhD thesis, I asked whether scientific maps like the Human Genome Project influence the technological search process and impact innovation, and if so how. To test this empirically, I analyzed the impact of genomics on drug discovery processes and corporate R&amp;D strategy pre-and-post entry of genomics. I developed novel computational metrics using econometrics, machine learning, computational chemistry, patents and drug data.</p> <p>To summarize, in my dissertation research I found that the Human Genome map increased the rate of invention, novel compound production and altered technological search strategies in firms. Further, I found that prior firm knowledge, market competition and product market specialization are influential in adopting targeted strategies. Overall, targeted strategies lead to broad exploration compared to non-target based strategies.</p> <p>These results reveal an interesting finding: scientific maps not only increase the rate and intensity of technological search but also impact exploration. This study informs on mechanisms by which basic science driven scientific mapping projects influence industry innovation.</p> <p>These findings bear implications for public policy, R&amp;D management and firm strategy.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/23/2018<br>      Modified by: Sebastian&nbsp;Jayaraj</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Scientific mapping projects like the ongoing US BRAIN initiative and Human Cell Atlas are data intensive endeavors that curate immense amounts of information. But their impact on innovation is not well understood. Innovation can be conceptualized as a spatial process, where firms and inventors search either locally or in distant, lesser explored, territories. In my PhD thesis, I asked whether scientific maps like the Human Genome Project influence the technological search process and impact innovation, and if so how. To test this empirically, I analyzed the impact of genomics on drug discovery processes and corporate R&amp;D strategy pre-and-post entry of genomics. I developed novel computational metrics using econometrics, machine learning, computational chemistry, patents and drug data.  To summarize, in my dissertation research I found that the Human Genome map increased the rate of invention, novel compound production and altered technological search strategies in firms. Further, I found that prior firm knowledge, market competition and product market specialization are influential in adopting targeted strategies. Overall, targeted strategies lead to broad exploration compared to non-target based strategies.  These results reveal an interesting finding: scientific maps not only increase the rate and intensity of technological search but also impact exploration. This study informs on mechanisms by which basic science driven scientific mapping projects influence industry innovation.  These findings bear implications for public policy, R&amp;D management and firm strategy.       Last Modified: 10/23/2018       Submitted by: Sebastian Jayaraj]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
