<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FRG: Collaborative Research: Categorifying Quantum Three-Manifold Invariants</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>132594.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>132594</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Quantum topology is a branch of mathematics that provides a testing ground for the structures needed in a quantum theory of gravity. This field has brought about unprecedented interaction between mathematics and theoretical physics. It has been extremely successful and well studied in 3-dimensions. However, since we live in 4-dimensions (including time), a full theory of quantum gravity requires an extension of these tools to 4-dimensions. An emerging mathematical philosophy known as "categorification" provides an avenue to uncover a hidden layer in mathematical structures, revealing a richer and more robust theory capable of describing more complex phenomenon.  This project will use the perspective of categorification to enhance one of the most successful theories in 3-dimensions to a full 4-dimensional theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This collaboration will harness the interplay between low-dimensional geometry, representation theory, and higher-dimensional gauge theory. Through this coordinated effort the PIs will make substantial progress on the problem of categorifying 3-manifold invariants. The PIs will capitalize on recent breakthroughs in theoretical physics and higher representation theory that have created new possibilities for significant progress on this problem.  Among the techniques to be employed include:  fivebrane compactifications to provide a universal description of various old and new homological invariants of 3-manifolds, the use of infinity categories for defining tensor products of higher representations of quantum groups, and the theory of Hopfological algebra for categorifications at roots of unity, as well as recent work on odd link homology theory and categorifications of Habiro's universal invariant.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1664255</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mikhail</FirstName>
<LastName>Khovanov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mikhail G Khovanov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>khovanov@math.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128544186</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000116638</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2960 Broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1616</Code>
<Text>FOCUSED RESEARCH GROUPS IN MATH SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~132594</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project aims to bring together algebraic and topological structures directly related to quantum mathematics and physics. It builds&nbsp; on previous advances in physically motivated theories known as TQFTs (topological quantum field theories). One result of this project is the theory of foam evaluation. Foams, as considered here, are topological structures&nbsp; that are two-dimensional objects embedded&nbsp; in 3-space. Foams have singularities where three planes can meet together along a common edge, called a singular edge. Another type of singularity is a point where four singular edges meet&nbsp; together at a point. This&nbsp; singularity can be visualized by&nbsp; stacking a half-plane on top of a plane and stacking another half-plane below at a different angle.</p> <p>A foam of this sort has an evaluation in a suitable number system build on top of the field of residues modulo two (such systems are called commutative rings of characteristic two). This evaluation is a novel summation formula reminiscent of sums encountered in statistical mechanics and in graph and chromatic polynomial theory. Using this summation one is able to define so-called state spaces assigned to planar trivalent graphs. These state spaces are generalized vector spaces. Their dimension or rank is conjectured&nbsp; to coincide with the number of Tait colorings of the graph, which are colorings of edges into 3 colors such that at each vertex the three edges have different colorings. This construction lifts the classical theory of Tait colorings one dimension up, into vector spaces and their generalization. It connects a classical part of graph theory with gauge theory in three and four dimensions, as developed by Kronheimer and Mrowka. One expects further connections between gauge theory, topology, algebra and combinatorics as these structures are further understood, as well as developing a new viewpoint on the so-called Four-Color Theorem, which gives a simple criterion for a planar trivalent graph to admit a Tait coloring.</p> <p>In another work, the PI has started to develop a mathematical theory to answer the question: what is a vector space of fractional dimension? The notion of vector space and its dimension (the number of vectors in a basis) is fundamental for mathematics and its applications. It is a hard and poorly understood problem whether there exist a useful notion of a vector space of fractional dimension. Together, such vector spaces much constitute what is called a&nbsp; category with some rich structure, including tensor product and categorical analogue of substraction. The PI found an example of such structure than allows generalized vector spaces of fractional dimensions with denominators powers of two. It is likely to be a first step towards a theory of such structures, and it is a tantalizing open problem to find more examples and apply this theory to mathematical physics and to other parts of mathematics.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/10/2020<br>      Modified by: Mikhail&nbsp;G&nbsp;Khovanov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project aims to bring together algebraic and topological structures directly related to quantum mathematics and physics. It builds  on previous advances in physically motivated theories known as TQFTs (topological quantum field theories). One result of this project is the theory of foam evaluation. Foams, as considered here, are topological structures  that are two-dimensional objects embedded  in 3-space. Foams have singularities where three planes can meet together along a common edge, called a singular edge. Another type of singularity is a point where four singular edges meet  together at a point. This  singularity can be visualized by  stacking a half-plane on top of a plane and stacking another half-plane below at a different angle.  A foam of this sort has an evaluation in a suitable number system build on top of the field of residues modulo two (such systems are called commutative rings of characteristic two). This evaluation is a novel summation formula reminiscent of sums encountered in statistical mechanics and in graph and chromatic polynomial theory. Using this summation one is able to define so-called state spaces assigned to planar trivalent graphs. These state spaces are generalized vector spaces. Their dimension or rank is conjectured  to coincide with the number of Tait colorings of the graph, which are colorings of edges into 3 colors such that at each vertex the three edges have different colorings. This construction lifts the classical theory of Tait colorings one dimension up, into vector spaces and their generalization. It connects a classical part of graph theory with gauge theory in three and four dimensions, as developed by Kronheimer and Mrowka. One expects further connections between gauge theory, topology, algebra and combinatorics as these structures are further understood, as well as developing a new viewpoint on the so-called Four-Color Theorem, which gives a simple criterion for a planar trivalent graph to admit a Tait coloring.  In another work, the PI has started to develop a mathematical theory to answer the question: what is a vector space of fractional dimension? The notion of vector space and its dimension (the number of vectors in a basis) is fundamental for mathematics and its applications. It is a hard and poorly understood problem whether there exist a useful notion of a vector space of fractional dimension. Together, such vector spaces much constitute what is called a  category with some rich structure, including tensor product and categorical analogue of substraction. The PI found an example of such structure than allows generalized vector spaces of fractional dimensions with denominators powers of two. It is likely to be a first step towards a theory of such structures, and it is a tantalizing open problem to find more examples and apply this theory to mathematical physics and to other parts of mathematics.       Last Modified: 11/10/2020       Submitted by: Mikhail G Khovanov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
