<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Current Trends in Dynamical Systems and Bowen's Legacy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>34000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>34000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Holmer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for US participation in the conference "Current Trends in Dynamical Systems and Bowen's Legacy" that will be held from July 30- August 4, 2017 at the University of British Columbia.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference focuses on recent developments in Analysis, especially in the field of dynamical systems.   A number of distinguished mathematicians have agreed to attend and speak at this conference.  This award gives early career researchers, members of underrepresented groups, researchers not funded by NSF and the like an opportunity to attend and participate in this conference.   The organizing committee will strive to make this funding opportunity known to target groups through a number of different activities.   More information will be made available at:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;http://www.pims.math.ca/scientific-event/170730-ctdsmlrb-0</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/04/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/04/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1665537</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Lind</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas Lind</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lind@math.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065431176</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000242052</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981954350</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Department of Mathematics]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~34000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant supported the participation of 55 US scientists at a conference on the mathematical legacy of Berkeley mathematician Rufus Bowen. Since his untimely death in 1978 at age 31, the influence of Bowen's ideas and research has continued to have a profound impact on the development of dynamical systems and related areas. During his lifetime, he kept a notebook of research problems which was recently rediscovered, and this provided a basis for an important part of the meeting.</p> <p>The conference was very successful, with 190 partcipants from all over the world. They heard 20 survey lectures, which gave not only historical overviews but also provided up-to-the-minute descriptions of current research, most of which are directly outgrowths of Bowen's ideas. These lectures were recorded and are freely available.</p> <p>In addition, there were two poster sessions, which allowed 34 junior scientists to describe their work to all attendees.</p> <p>There were two problems sessions which gave participants a chance to brainstorm ideas and future directions, some giving more formal presentations and some inviting more informal discussions. The results of these sessions are available on the conference website.</p> <p>The organizers created a website for the Bowen Problem Notebook, which transcribed each of the 155 problems and invited comments and citations from participants. This website is now available to all to make further additions, and provides a living legacy that will continue into the future.</p> <p>Finally, there was a remembrance event to invoke the memories of Bowen's influence on those at the conference who worked directly with him. This was particularly important, since many attendees had not met him, and so provided these people with a more personal account that is otherwise impossible to obtain. Bowen's widow attended this event, and recounted Bowen's efforts to increase the number of women on the faculty at the Berkeley Mathematics Department (it was 0 when he joined it), and who gave an impassioned plea to continue these efforts throughout the mathematical community.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/20/2018<br>      Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;Lind</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant supported the participation of 55 US scientists at a conference on the mathematical legacy of Berkeley mathematician Rufus Bowen. Since his untimely death in 1978 at age 31, the influence of Bowen's ideas and research has continued to have a profound impact on the development of dynamical systems and related areas. During his lifetime, he kept a notebook of research problems which was recently rediscovered, and this provided a basis for an important part of the meeting.  The conference was very successful, with 190 partcipants from all over the world. They heard 20 survey lectures, which gave not only historical overviews but also provided up-to-the-minute descriptions of current research, most of which are directly outgrowths of Bowen's ideas. These lectures were recorded and are freely available.  In addition, there were two poster sessions, which allowed 34 junior scientists to describe their work to all attendees.  There were two problems sessions which gave participants a chance to brainstorm ideas and future directions, some giving more formal presentations and some inviting more informal discussions. The results of these sessions are available on the conference website.  The organizers created a website for the Bowen Problem Notebook, which transcribed each of the 155 problems and invited comments and citations from participants. This website is now available to all to make further additions, and provides a living legacy that will continue into the future.  Finally, there was a remembrance event to invoke the memories of Bowen's influence on those at the conference who worked directly with him. This was particularly important, since many attendees had not met him, and so provided these people with a more personal account that is otherwise impossible to obtain. Bowen's widow attended this event, and recounted Bowen's efforts to increase the number of women on the faculty at the Berkeley Mathematics Department (it was 0 when he joined it), and who gave an impassioned plea to continue these efforts throughout the mathematical community.       Last Modified: 10/20/2018       Submitted by: Douglas Lind]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
