<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Theory and Techniques for Controlling the Collective Behavior of Dynamical Systems under Stochastic Uncertainty</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>251285.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>251285</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Radhakisan Baheti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Physical systems such as micro-mechanical components experiencing thermal noise, particle beams, and laser-driven molecular reactions can all be modeled as dynamical system with stochastic excitation. The control of such processes requires that we steer the collective behavior of the individual constituents towards a specified terminal goal. Due to the stochastic uncertainty of their initial state as well as due to various stochastic effects (measurement noise, stochastic forcing, fluctuation-dissipation phenomena, etc.) one can only hope to be able to specify a target distribution for corresponding parameters and not their precise final values. Further, for such inherently stochastic systems, it is often the case that the performance of a control strategy can only be quantified in a statistical sense. Thus, the proposed research aims at developing theory and techniques that will allow steering such systems towards a desired end-point distribution for their parameters (position, velocity, temperature, etc.) while utilizing minimal amount of resources, typically energy. A wide range of physical systems and applications are envisioned and, accordingly, a range of mathematical models with linear, nonlinear, mean-field, etc. dynamics will be studied. The tools are expected to impact technology that relates to the aforementioned physical systems and applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A specific technical goal of the proposed research is to study the controllability and the optimal control of stochastic systems in the sense of being able to steer their state from a given initial probability density to a final target one. In effect, this is the problem to control the Fokker-Planck equation that specifies the flow of the state-probability density. Problems of optimal transport for mass and resources that obey nontrivial dynamics will also be considered; in these the stochastic uncertainty for the state remains while the stochastic excitation becomes negligible. Furthermore, problems of interacting particles and mean-field potentials will also be studied as will be the effect of observation noise and ensuing limits to performance. The development of theory and tools will make use of recent advances at the interface between Monge-Kantorovich optimal mass transport, Schroedinger bridges, and the contractive properties of stochastic maps in the geometry induced by the so-called Hilbert metric.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/17/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/17/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1665031</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tryphon</FirstName>
<LastName>Georgiou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tryphon T Georgiou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tryphon@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498249966</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000264261</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/17/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926973975</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Engineering Gatway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>092E</Code>
<Text>Control systems &amp; applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~251285</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Engineering design often needs to address random stochastic excitations that impact the state of physical processes. An important example is thermal noise that may degrade electronic measuring devices and information processing systems. At other times, thermal excitation can be tapped by man-made or biological systems to gain advantage as in thermal engines and stochastic resonance. Control engineering as a discipline is tasked with regulating man-made or physical processes (e.g., dealing with guidance and navigation, speed control, temperature regulation or, understanding the mechanisms of cell homeostasis in biology) often attempts to meet specifications indirectly, via tuning parameters to ensure a suitably small variance of error in specified objectives.</p> <p><br />The research completed in this project developed mathematical tools for shaping directly the response of systems subject to stochastic excitation. Specifically, physical or man-made processes evolve in time by tracing a path in an abstract space of internal states. Stochastically-driven dynamics, where noise plays an important role, trace a variety of alternative possible paths depending on the randomness of the noise, and collectively the flow of a cohort of possibly many processes may be thought as a fuzzy envelop that contain all typical trajectories. The displayed figure exemplifies the voltage-current state of an electrical oscillatory network subject to thermal noise. The purpose of control, embodied by a regulating voltage source, is to guide the voltage-current trajectories through an acceptable envelop, or to a specified terminal target distribution. That is, not only one needs to ensure proximity to a target-value at some (or all) points in time during operation, but one wants to know the statistics of deviating from such. Research in the project developed tools and theory on how to control and specify the statistics of deviating from a desired target value (or trajectory) for such processes.</p> <p><br />The mathematics underlying the problem to regulate stochastically driven dynamical systems apply to a much wider spectrum of engineering problems. Specifically, examples include the operation of thermodynamic systems (engines and biological processes), coping with disturbances in transporting resources in continuous or discrete space (e.g., networks), as well as dual problems where instead of specifying "how to control" one observes stochastic responses, and wants know "how to model." Estimating the trajectory of dynamical systems from observations (filtering) is such a problem.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />The theory and mathematical techniques that were developed under the project add to the toolbox of Stochastic Control Theory by advancing a new paradigm of directly specifying statistical constraints on admissible system response. At a technical level, a significant development in the project echoes earlier Stochastic Control methodologies where control design requires solving certain type of equations (e.g., Riccati equations, when the process dynamics are linear). The new theory explains how a more stringent adherence to probabilistic specifications on performance require solving a similar (nonlinearly coupled Riccati) set of equations, which however, in important cases, is shown to be solvable explicitly. Several generalizations ensued that pertain to a wider range of engineering problems, including regulating transportation and dynamical flows on networks.</p> <p><br />The intellectual merit of the endeavor was to prove viability of the concept of steering the stochastic response of general systems according to specifications and addressing questions as to when this is possible and when this is not. Broadly, the impact of the completed project is to provide specific tools that can now be used for the advancement of science and engineering, by designing regulation systems that can cope with uncertainty in desirable ways.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Tryphon&nbsp;T&nbsp;Georgiou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1665031/1665031_10371142_1569772206447_figure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1665031/1665031_10371142_1569772206447_figure--rgov-800width.jpg" title="resonant circuit"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1665031/1665031_10371142_1569772206447_figure--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="resonant circuit"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Control of a resonant circuit subject to Nyquist Johnson thermal noise</div> <div class="imageCredit">Y. Chen, T.T. Georgiou, M. Pavon</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tryphon&nbsp;T&nbsp;Georgiou</div> <div class="imageTitle">resonant circuit</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Engineering design often needs to address random stochastic excitations that impact the state of physical processes. An important example is thermal noise that may degrade electronic measuring devices and information processing systems. At other times, thermal excitation can be tapped by man-made or biological systems to gain advantage as in thermal engines and stochastic resonance. Control engineering as a discipline is tasked with regulating man-made or physical processes (e.g., dealing with guidance and navigation, speed control, temperature regulation or, understanding the mechanisms of cell homeostasis in biology) often attempts to meet specifications indirectly, via tuning parameters to ensure a suitably small variance of error in specified objectives.   The research completed in this project developed mathematical tools for shaping directly the response of systems subject to stochastic excitation. Specifically, physical or man-made processes evolve in time by tracing a path in an abstract space of internal states. Stochastically-driven dynamics, where noise plays an important role, trace a variety of alternative possible paths depending on the randomness of the noise, and collectively the flow of a cohort of possibly many processes may be thought as a fuzzy envelop that contain all typical trajectories. The displayed figure exemplifies the voltage-current state of an electrical oscillatory network subject to thermal noise. The purpose of control, embodied by a regulating voltage source, is to guide the voltage-current trajectories through an acceptable envelop, or to a specified terminal target distribution. That is, not only one needs to ensure proximity to a target-value at some (or all) points in time during operation, but one wants to know the statistics of deviating from such. Research in the project developed tools and theory on how to control and specify the statistics of deviating from a desired target value (or trajectory) for such processes.   The mathematics underlying the problem to regulate stochastically driven dynamical systems apply to a much wider spectrum of engineering problems. Specifically, examples include the operation of thermodynamic systems (engines and biological processes), coping with disturbances in transporting resources in continuous or discrete space (e.g., networks), as well as dual problems where instead of specifying "how to control" one observes stochastic responses, and wants know "how to model." Estimating the trajectory of dynamical systems from observations (filtering) is such a problem.    The theory and mathematical techniques that were developed under the project add to the toolbox of Stochastic Control Theory by advancing a new paradigm of directly specifying statistical constraints on admissible system response. At a technical level, a significant development in the project echoes earlier Stochastic Control methodologies where control design requires solving certain type of equations (e.g., Riccati equations, when the process dynamics are linear). The new theory explains how a more stringent adherence to probabilistic specifications on performance require solving a similar (nonlinearly coupled Riccati) set of equations, which however, in important cases, is shown to be solvable explicitly. Several generalizations ensued that pertain to a wider range of engineering problems, including regulating transportation and dynamical flows on networks.   The intellectual merit of the endeavor was to prove viability of the concept of steering the stochastic response of general systems according to specifications and addressing questions as to when this is possible and when this is not. Broadly, the impact of the completed project is to provide specific tools that can now be used for the advancement of science and engineering, by designing regulation systems that can cope with uncertainty in desirable ways.       Last Modified: 09/29/2019       Submitted by: Tryphon T Georgiou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
