<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development of a Competency-Based Education Program in CyberSecurity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>R. Corby Hovis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>chovis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924625</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>To address the demand for highly skilled workers who are prepared to protect the critical national cyber infrastructure as well as the call for greater student completion rates of a postsecondary degree or certificate, this project at Lincoln Land Community College (LLCC) in Illinois is designed to create a competency based education (CBE) program in cybersecurity. Working with industry and education partners, LLCC will plan, develop and implement this learner-focused CBE program that will increase completion rates while potentially reducing the time and the cost to students. The program will build upon the current knowledge base of each individual student and eliminate unnecessary time and effort on learning objectives already mastered. Because there is limited research for CBE programs developed within existing higher education structures, this project includes a comprehensive evaluation component. Because many institutions in postsecondary education and especially community colleges are looking for innovators who have paved the path in CBE and are seeking advice for best practices and program implementation to better serve their students, LLCC will be positioned to share best practices and data regarding participation and completion to both state and national organizations. Deployed military can use the CBE program to build upon their current knowledge and complete the program entirely off campus as a result of virtual technology. Since LLCC serves a large rural population, this competency-based program will address the barriers faced by rural students wishing to participate in opportunities related to this vital science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) field. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project objectives are to provide an alternative delivery model for attaining a cybersecurity certificate by: 1) developing curriculum based on competency driven assessments to deliver a CBE cybersecurity certificate program, 2) developing an effective student admission process for evaluating student skills and behaviors needed to be successful in a competency-based program, 3) developing support services for students including advising, financial aid, and coaching to ensure success and completion in the program, 4) implementing the CBE cybersecurity certificate, and 5) evaluating the process and outcomes of the CBE cybersecurity certificate program. LLCC will contribute course content to the ATE Center for Systems Security and Information Assurance (CCSIA) at Moraine Community College and the ATE National CyberWatch Center at Prince George's Community College as well as adapt many of their materials for a rural audience. Completion pathways for this program will include a certificate and upon completion of the certificate the student can enter the workforce or continue their educational endeavors. The certificate is a building block to receiving an associate degree, which the student can use to transfer to a four year institution to complete a baccalaureate degree. This program will provide promising opportunities for students (both local and rural), not only at the post-secondary level, but also at the secondary level through dual credit offerings or dual enrollment at the community college.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/12/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1700438</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Marsaglia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frank Marsaglia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>frank.marsaglia@llcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2177862871</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000733331</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/21/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeff</FirstName>
<LastName>Mehan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeff Mehan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jeff.mehan@llcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2177862755</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000733332</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/12/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carmen</FirstName>
<LastName>Allen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carmen R Allen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>carmen.allen@llcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2177862316</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000800695</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/21/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lincoln Land Community College</Name>
<CityName>Springfield</CityName>
<ZipCode>627949256</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2177862384</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5250 Shepherd Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071438204</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LINCOLN LAND COMMUNITY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071438204</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lincoln Land Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>Springfield</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>627949256</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5250 Shepherd Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0417</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~199999</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
