<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Algebraic Geometry of Knot Homology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A knot is a closed curve in three-dimensional space. More generally, a link is a collection of several such curves. Two links are equivalent if one can be transformed to another by a continuous deformation and/or stretching (without tearing). A link invariant is a quantity that does not change under the deformations of a link. Such invariants can be used to distinguish links and to study geometric properties of knots, and many powerful link invariants have been developed in recent decades. In another direction, the mathematical subject of algebraic geometry studies spaces described by polynomial equations and has applications in a wide range of fields, including statistics, control theory, and computer science. This project is focused on surprising interactions between the invariants of links and algebraic geometry that appear in two different mathematical frameworks. It is anticipated that the research will provide new perspectives on the relationships between low-dimensional topology, algebraic geometry, representation theory, and combinatorics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In more detail, the first framework is classical: given a complex plane curve singularity, its intersection with a small sphere is a link. Similarly, for a complex surface singularity its link is a three-manifold. The investigator will the study the interactions between the algebraic properties of these curves and surfaces, and the Heegaard-Floer homology of their links. The second framework is less direct. The investigator and collaborators have conjectured that the Khovanov-Rozansky homology of links can be computed by studying the algebraic and geometric properties of the Hilbert scheme of points (the configuration space of points in four-dimensional space). The Hilbert scheme is well studied in algebraic geometry, representation theory and combinatorics, so this interpretation would yield explicit computations of Khovanov-Rozansky homology that were previously out of reach. In this project the investigator will develop the connection between knots and the Hilbert scheme, with the goals of computing these invariants for various classes of links and proving the conjecture.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1700814</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Evgeny</FirstName>
<LastName>Gorskiy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Evgeny Gorskiy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>egorskiy@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307520827</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000653443</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956165270</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Shields Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The PI studied interactions between the invariants of links (such as Heegaard Floer and Khovanov-Rozansky homology) and algebraic geometry.</p> <p><br />Heegaard Floer homology was explored in a series of papers by PI, Lidman, Liu and Moore (and in several other papers by PI's graduate student Liu alone). One of the results of this work is that that Heegaard Floer homology detects Whitehead and Borromean links.</p> <p><br />Khovanov-Rozansky homology and related categorical invariants were explored in the series of papers of PI, Hogancamp, Mellit, Nakagane and Wedrich. Their connections to combinatorics were explored in papers of PI with Hawkes, Mazin, Schilling, Rainbolt and Vazirani, while their connections to Hilbert schemes were studied in a series of papers of PI, Carlsson, Mellit, Simental and Vazirani (and in several papers by PI's graduate student Kivinen alone). One of the results of this work is the explicit computation of Khovanov-Rozansky homology for the powers of the full twist braid.</p> <p><br />In addition to all this, the work of PI with Negut and Rasmussen spurred a lot of activity in link homology community. Several of the conjectures proposed in that paper were proved by the PI and his collaborators, and by other groups of researchers.</p> <p><br />The PI has mentored two graduate students (both graduated in 2019, now postdocs in University of Toronto and Max Planck Institute), two undergraduate students (both started graduate school) and one postdoc. The PI has also co-organized five workshops closely related to the topic of this project.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/11/2020<br>      Modified by: Evgeny&nbsp;Gorskiy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The PI studied interactions between the invariants of links (such as Heegaard Floer and Khovanov-Rozansky homology) and algebraic geometry.   Heegaard Floer homology was explored in a series of papers by PI, Lidman, Liu and Moore (and in several other papers by PI's graduate student Liu alone). One of the results of this work is that that Heegaard Floer homology detects Whitehead and Borromean links.   Khovanov-Rozansky homology and related categorical invariants were explored in the series of papers of PI, Hogancamp, Mellit, Nakagane and Wedrich. Their connections to combinatorics were explored in papers of PI with Hawkes, Mazin, Schilling, Rainbolt and Vazirani, while their connections to Hilbert schemes were studied in a series of papers of PI, Carlsson, Mellit, Simental and Vazirani (and in several papers by PI's graduate student Kivinen alone). One of the results of this work is the explicit computation of Khovanov-Rozansky homology for the powers of the full twist braid.   In addition to all this, the work of PI with Negut and Rasmussen spurred a lot of activity in link homology community. Several of the conjectures proposed in that paper were proved by the PI and his collaborators, and by other groups of researchers.   The PI has mentored two graduate students (both graduated in 2019, now postdocs in University of Toronto and Max Planck Institute), two undergraduate students (both started graduate school) and one postdoc. The PI has also co-organized five workshops closely related to the topic of this project.        Last Modified: 12/11/2020       Submitted by: Evgeny Gorskiy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
