<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The 2017 Spring Institute on Noncommutative Geometry and Operator Algebras</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>40000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Clancey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal requests funding to help defray the expenses of participants in the Annual Spring Institute in Noncommutative Geometry and Operator Algebras (NCGOA) to be held at Vanderbilt University in Nashville, Tennessee from May 5 to 11, 2017. Additional information about the institute can be found on the website http://math.vanderbilt.edu/ncgoa17&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The connections between operator algebras and logic have dramatically reemerged in the last 15 years. Advances in descriptive set theory have led to solutions to long standing problems in operator algebras and these have in turn spurred growth in descriptive set theory. Also, the emergence of continuous model theory in operator algebras has extraordinary potential to answer difficult problems in this area. The aim of this school and conference is to bring together world-class researchers and young workers from these areas to learn concepts and techniques from each other and to focus on recent developments.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1700457</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vaughan</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vaughan F Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vaughan.f.jones@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5103010589</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000470796</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dietmar</FirstName>
<LastName>Bisch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dietmar H Bisch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dietmar.bisch@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153221999</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000443633</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jesse</FirstName>
<LastName>Peterson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jesse Peterson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jesse.d.peterson@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153222631</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000511398</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PMB 407749 2301 Vanderbilt Place]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965717143</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004413456</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372400001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1326 Stevenson Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1268</Code>
<Text>FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award provided funding for the thirteenth annual spring institute on noncommutative geometry and operator algebras (NCGOA 2017). The topic of NCGOA 2017 was "Operator Algebras and Logic". Mini-courses were given by <span>Bradd Hart</span>, <span>Justin Moore</span>, <span>Roman Sasyk,&nbsp;<span>Simon Thomas,</span></span> and <span>Anush Tserunyan</span>, twenty one hour talks were presented, and two half-hour talks were presented. The speakers were carefully selected and featured a combination of senior researchers, postdoctoral fellows and graduate students. For several of them it was their first opportunity to present their work at a major conference in operator algebras. Mathematicians from different areas with interests in functional analytical interactions with logic attended the conference/schol. Many exciting discussions and interactions took place as ample time for these were provided in the schedule.</p> <p>72 mathematicians took part at NCGOA 2017, of which 32 were students and 14 were postdoctoral fellows. Thus, roughly 65% of the participants were students or postdocs. Furthermore, five of the participants came from underrepresented minority groups. Students and postdocs had plenty of opportunities to discuss topics on the research frontier of logic and operator algebras with senior mathematicians present at the conference/school.</p> <p>The conference website can be found at https://my.vanderbilt.edu/ncgoa17/. Program, abstracts of talks and some lecture notes can be found at the conference website.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Jesse&nbsp;Peterson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award provided funding for the thirteenth annual spring institute on noncommutative geometry and operator algebras (NCGOA 2017). The topic of NCGOA 2017 was "Operator Algebras and Logic". Mini-courses were given by Bradd Hart, Justin Moore, Roman Sasyk, Simon Thomas, and Anush Tserunyan, twenty one hour talks were presented, and two half-hour talks were presented. The speakers were carefully selected and featured a combination of senior researchers, postdoctoral fellows and graduate students. For several of them it was their first opportunity to present their work at a major conference in operator algebras. Mathematicians from different areas with interests in functional analytical interactions with logic attended the conference/schol. Many exciting discussions and interactions took place as ample time for these were provided in the schedule.  72 mathematicians took part at NCGOA 2017, of which 32 were students and 14 were postdoctoral fellows. Thus, roughly 65% of the participants were students or postdocs. Furthermore, five of the participants came from underrepresented minority groups. Students and postdocs had plenty of opportunities to discuss topics on the research frontier of logic and operator algebras with senior mathematicians present at the conference/school.  The conference website can be found at https://my.vanderbilt.edu/ncgoa17/. Program, abstracts of talks and some lecture notes can be found at the conference website.       Last Modified: 06/27/2018       Submitted by: Jesse Peterson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
