<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Birational Geometry and Bridgeland Stability Conditions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>154998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>65004</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Manes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmanes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924870</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The notion of stability conditions on derived categories emerged from high energy physics literature in the study of Dirichlet branes in string theory. Besides its original motivation, the theory of stability conditions has a much further reach, with connections to counting invariants, representation theory, homological mirror symmetry, and classical algebraic geometry. This project lies at the nexus of these areas; the theme is to apply Bridgeland stability condition techniques to solve questions arising from birational geometry and mathematical physics. A stability condition identifies a class of objects in the derived category, called stable objects, in an intrinsic way. Understanding if certain objects are stable or not gives important information on the geometry of algebraic varieties. A stability condition depends on the choice of certain parameters. Understanding how stable objects change by varying these parameters is the key to many applications of the theory and is the technical core of this project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are three main goals in the project. The first is to investigate the existence problem for Bridgeland stability conditions. A general framework for constructing Bridgeland stability conditions on threefolds was introduced by the investigator and collaborators, via certain conjectural inequalities. The new viewpoint is to look at fibrations in particular products, and to deduce such inequalities from the positivity of a certain divisor class on the base of the fibration. The second goal is to study stability conditions on non-commutative K3 surfaces and to use Bridgeland's theory to reinterpret and generalize geometric constructions, for example for cubic fourfolds, by using moduli spaces of Bridgeland stable objects. The third goal is to investigate whether such moduli spaces are "well-behaved" projective varieties in general and to study their local structure in the case of K3 surfaces. Applications include investigation of a conjecture on derived equivalences of birational irreducible holomorphic symplectic varieties.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/22/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1700751</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emanuele</FirstName>
<LastName>Macri</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emanuele Macri</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>e.macri@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173733893</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513314</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[177-500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~65003</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The broad goal of the project was to apply new techniques arising from mathematical physics to the study of classical problems in algebraic geometry.</p> <p>The main novelty of the approach is the notion of stability in derived category, introduced by Bridgeland about 15 years ago, &nbsp;and later perfectioned by Kontsevich and Soibelman and many others. This is based on the notion of Pi-stability in string theory studied by Douglas, Aspinwall, and many others.</p> <p>Open problems in algebaric geometry which can be tackled by using these techniques include understanding the birational geometry of cubic fourfolds and smooth projective threefolds.</p> <p>There are two main outcomes of the project. The PI and collaborators developed, in the course of a long project, the theory of stability conditions in families. This had immediate applications to cubic fourfolds, with the proof of conjectures by Huybrechts and Addington-Thomas, and more recently to further geometries. Yucheng Liu, one of the PI's PhD students supported by the grant, was able to show an existence result for stability conditions on product varieties, by proving a conjectural Bogomolov-type inequality, proposed by the PI and collaborators, for stable objects on such varieties.</p> <p>This is a rich area of study, which saw much progress recently; for example, many results are now known towards the general conjectural Bogomolov-type inequality, including the outstanding work by Chunyi Li on the quintic threefold, or work on the existence of moduli spaces, which now brought the theory of stability in derived category to an advanced stage to rival with more classical notions of stability for sheaves. The PI wrote a series of lecture notes summarizing some of these progresses aimed at advanced graduate students and postdocs. Training of graduate students and postdocs was an important part of the project: the PI involved younger mathematicians in parts of the project, he organized many activities, including workshops and conferences, and he&nbsp;gave lecture series and presentations during the years of funding, which will continue in the following years.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/28/2019<br>      Modified by: Emanuele&nbsp;Macri</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The broad goal of the project was to apply new techniques arising from mathematical physics to the study of classical problems in algebraic geometry.  The main novelty of the approach is the notion of stability in derived category, introduced by Bridgeland about 15 years ago,  and later perfectioned by Kontsevich and Soibelman and many others. This is based on the notion of Pi-stability in string theory studied by Douglas, Aspinwall, and many others.  Open problems in algebaric geometry which can be tackled by using these techniques include understanding the birational geometry of cubic fourfolds and smooth projective threefolds.  There are two main outcomes of the project. The PI and collaborators developed, in the course of a long project, the theory of stability conditions in families. This had immediate applications to cubic fourfolds, with the proof of conjectures by Huybrechts and Addington-Thomas, and more recently to further geometries. Yucheng Liu, one of the PI's PhD students supported by the grant, was able to show an existence result for stability conditions on product varieties, by proving a conjectural Bogomolov-type inequality, proposed by the PI and collaborators, for stable objects on such varieties.  This is a rich area of study, which saw much progress recently; for example, many results are now known towards the general conjectural Bogomolov-type inequality, including the outstanding work by Chunyi Li on the quintic threefold, or work on the existence of moduli spaces, which now brought the theory of stability in derived category to an advanced stage to rival with more classical notions of stability for sheaves. The PI wrote a series of lecture notes summarizing some of these progresses aimed at advanced graduate students and postdocs. Training of graduate students and postdocs was an important part of the project: the PI involved younger mathematicians in parts of the project, he organized many activities, including workshops and conferences, and he gave lecture series and presentations during the years of funding, which will continue in the following years.           Last Modified: 12/28/2019       Submitted by: Emanuele Macri]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
