<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Topics in Arithmetic Geometry:  Moduli Varieties, L-functions, Arakelov Theory and Their Interactions and Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>193185.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>193185</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Spiroff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspiroff@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project lies in a subfield of mathematics known as arithmetic geometry. Many of the questions in the project are motivated by the philosophy that information about algebraic equations over the integers can be obtained by geometric methods. Solution to the problems under study in this project will have substantial impact on research in cryptography, theoretical physics, and quantum computing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigator will study moduli varieties, L- functions, Arakelov theory and their interactions. This work will have applications to solution to the Birch and Swinnerton-Dyer conjecture, its generalization by Beilinson and Bloch, as well as related problems. . In particular, research will be done on 1) the arithmetic Gan-Gross-Prasad conjecture; 2) heights of Drinfeld-Heegner cycles with arbitrary length; 3) generalization of the Gross-Zagier formula to higher dimensions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1700883</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shou-wu</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shou-wu Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shouwu@math.princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092586455</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000180230</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Fine Hall, Washington Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~73185</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">This<span>&nbsp; </span>proposal is about arithmetic geometry, a subject about solution of polynomial equations with integer solutions which has important applications in science and technology.</p> <p class="p1">Interlectural Merit:</p> <p class="p1">In this proposal, the PI has written two papers and one book for some&nbsp; new constructoins&nbsp; of heights of solutions, including one for&nbsp; algebraic cycles and one for algebraic points. These constructions have applications to problems about special values of L-series and diophantine geometry.</p> <p class="p1">For heights of algebraic cycles, the PI found a new way to define harmonic forms using Lefschetz operators rather than Laplacian operators. This new height theory will have important application to Gross--Zagier type conjectures for Shimura varieties.&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">For heights of alebraic points, the PI and his collaborator X. Yuan have developed an intersection for adelic line bundles over quasi-projective varieties. This theory has been used already by Yuan for a uniform Bogomolov conjecture.</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">Broader impacts:</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;The PI has&nbsp;&nbsp;used some problems from this proposal or their&nbsp; derived forms for his current&nbsp; graduate and&nbsp; undergraduate students. In the comning semester, the PI will organize a workshop to study PI's book and its applications, especially the work on uniform Bogomolov conjecture and uniform Modell--Lang conjecture.&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">It is also very likely that new questions and speculations will arise in the course of studying questions raised by this proposal, and will stimulate future research programs in the field.</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/21/2021<br>      Modified by: Shou-Wu&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This  proposal is about arithmetic geometry, a subject about solution of polynomial equations with integer solutions which has important applications in science and technology. Interlectural Merit: In this proposal, the PI has written two papers and one book for some  new constructoins  of heights of solutions, including one for  algebraic cycles and one for algebraic points. These constructions have applications to problems about special values of L-series and diophantine geometry. For heights of algebraic cycles, the PI found a new way to define harmonic forms using Lefschetz operators rather than Laplacian operators. This new height theory will have important application to Gross--Zagier type conjectures for Shimura varieties.  For heights of alebraic points, the PI and his collaborator X. Yuan have developed an intersection for adelic line bundles over quasi-projective varieties. This theory has been used already by Yuan for a uniform Bogomolov conjecture.   Broader impacts:  The PI has  used some problems from this proposal or their  derived forms for his current  graduate and  undergraduate students. In the comning semester, the PI will organize a workshop to study PI's book and its applications, especially the work on uniform Bogomolov conjecture and uniform Modell--Lang conjecture.  It is also very likely that new questions and speculations will arise in the course of studying questions raised by this proposal, and will stimulate future research programs in the field.                  Last Modified: 08/21/2021       Submitted by: Shou-Wu Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
