<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research+Practice Collaboratory ECEP Symposium</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>45526.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>45526</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Janice Cuny</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of Washington, together with the Research+Practice Collaboratory, proposes a RAPID project to engage state teams from the Expanding Computer Education Pathways (ECEP) Alliance with education researchers. The project will test engagement strategies within an existing workshop to be held in conjunction with the upcoming ECEP Alliance Summit scheduled for October 28-29, 2016, to be held at the White House old executive building in Washington DC. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The proposed engagement will test strategies for working with Computer Science for All (CS4All) implementation teams and communities to build an understanding of the value of research-practice partnerships in supporting equity-oriented, sustainable CS education improvement efforts. Towards this end, workshop activities will include presentations by learning scientists with deep experience in research-practice partnerships that focus on equity in computer science, digital learning, and/or STEM learning. The ECEP state teams will then meet with researchers to identify research questions that address their concerns about supporting and scaling local initiatives, and the kinds of external research expertise and partnerships that would be needed to advance the specific ECEP state projects. The goal is to provide a broad model for building collaborations between CSforAll practitioners and the education research community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/18/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1700448</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Bell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philip L Bell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pbell@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065431139</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000415045</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bronwyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Bevan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bronwyn Bevan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bronwynb@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066168291</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000280008</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981051016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave. NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>005Y</Code>
<Text>STEM + Computing (STEM+C) Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>023Z</Code>
<Text>Computer Science for All (CS for All)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~45526</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Activities</strong></p> <p>On October 28, 2016, the Research+Practice Collaboratory hosted a half-&shy;day meeting in collaboration with Expanding Computing Education Pathways (ECEP) project. The goals of the meeting were to</p> <ol> <li>Introduce      the ECEP community to the potential of research-&shy;practice partnerships      (RPPs) for strengthening improvement efforts.</li> <li>Generate      ECEP research questions that could be addressed through an RPP.</li> <li>Provide      time for teams to consider if and how they could identify research      partners.</li> <li>Produce      a report summarizing research questions from the teams.</li> </ol> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>Traditionally in education, research is conducted <em>by</em> researchers <em>on</em> educators or students. Yet, studies find that a great deal of research results are not taken up or sustained in practice&mdash;studies are undertaken to improve the educational system or educational activities, but results usually fade away shortly after the studies are completed. To address this problem, there is a growing movement to expand the use of <em>research-practice partnerships</em> (RPPs).&nbsp; RPPs recognize and build on knowledge in both educators and researchers&nbsp;to ensure that research is relevant, timely, practical, and useful in practice. There is a body of work that defines what makes an RPP different from a "collaboration."</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>The ECEP program seeks to expand who engages in computer science education and careers.&nbsp; ThebBroader impacts of this half-day workshop, hosted by the Research+Practice Collaborartory for the ECEP community, included raising awareness among ECEP teams of the value of forming RPPs in order to produce research results that could inform and improve their projects' impacts.&nbsp; In this way, ECEP efforts to broaden participation in computer science would be strengthened through working in partnership with learning scientists who could study these efforts.</p> <p><strong>Project Impacts</strong></p> <p>Though only a half-day workshop, the RPP workshop, held at the White House in late October 2016, accomplished the following:</p> <ol> <li>It raised awareness, among the ECEP community, of the potential power and efficacy of RPPs for supporting implementation and improvement of CS for All initiatives. Participants from at least four of these projects (Alabama, Puerto Rico, and two from California) applied for and received awards from a subsequent NSF solicitation for a CS for All RPP program.</li> <li>It introduced 9 learning scientists to the CS for All community &shy;&shy; At least one of these individuals is leading a new CS for All RPP program, and at least one is advising on a CS for All RPP.</li> <li>It built understanding, for the Research + Practice Collaboratory leadership, of the CS for All community, which allowed us to refine and streamline our approach for subsequent workshops, held in January 2017, that we provided to help this community design RPPs in response to a new NSF program solicitation supporting CS for All RPPs.&nbsp;</li> </ol> <p>These January workshops, which were directly shaped and impacted by lessons learned from the October 2016 workshop, proved effective in that over 80% of the 20+ projects that were eventually funded by the NSF CS for All RPP solicitation attended the Collaboratory workshops.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/14/2017<br>      Modified by: Bronwyn&nbsp;Bevan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Activities  On October 28, 2016, the Research+Practice Collaboratory hosted a half-&shy;day meeting in collaboration with Expanding Computing Education Pathways (ECEP) project. The goals of the meeting were to  Introduce      the ECEP community to the potential of research-&shy;practice partnerships      (RPPs) for strengthening improvement efforts. Generate      ECEP research questions that could be addressed through an RPP. Provide      time for teams to consider if and how they could identify research      partners. Produce      a report summarizing research questions from the teams.   Intellectual Merit  Traditionally in education, research is conducted by researchers on educators or students. Yet, studies find that a great deal of research results are not taken up or sustained in practice&mdash;studies are undertaken to improve the educational system or educational activities, but results usually fade away shortly after the studies are completed. To address this problem, there is a growing movement to expand the use of research-practice partnerships (RPPs).  RPPs recognize and build on knowledge in both educators and researchers to ensure that research is relevant, timely, practical, and useful in practice. There is a body of work that defines what makes an RPP different from a "collaboration."  Broader Impacts  The ECEP program seeks to expand who engages in computer science education and careers.  ThebBroader impacts of this half-day workshop, hosted by the Research+Practice Collaborartory for the ECEP community, included raising awareness among ECEP teams of the value of forming RPPs in order to produce research results that could inform and improve their projects' impacts.  In this way, ECEP efforts to broaden participation in computer science would be strengthened through working in partnership with learning scientists who could study these efforts.  Project Impacts  Though only a half-day workshop, the RPP workshop, held at the White House in late October 2016, accomplished the following:  It raised awareness, among the ECEP community, of the potential power and efficacy of RPPs for supporting implementation and improvement of CS for All initiatives. Participants from at least four of these projects (Alabama, Puerto Rico, and two from California) applied for and received awards from a subsequent NSF solicitation for a CS for All RPP program. It introduced 9 learning scientists to the CS for All community &shy;&shy; At least one of these individuals is leading a new CS for All RPP program, and at least one is advising on a CS for All RPP. It built understanding, for the Research + Practice Collaboratory leadership, of the CS for All community, which allowed us to refine and streamline our approach for subsequent workshops, held in January 2017, that we provided to help this community design RPPs in response to a new NSF program solicitation supporting CS for All RPPs.    These January workshops, which were directly shaped and impacted by lessons learned from the October 2016 workshop, proved effective in that over 80% of the 20+ projects that were eventually funded by the NSF CS for All RPP solicitation attended the Collaboratory workshops.           Last Modified: 11/14/2017       Submitted by: Bronwyn Bevan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
