<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Evaluating the Influences of Aerosols on Low-level Cloud-precipitation Properties over Land and Ocean using Ground-based Observations and WRF Simulations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>90000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>90000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chungu Lu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>clu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927110</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Aerosol generation resulting from natural and anthropogenic activities is expected to have considerable, far-reaching effects on cloud development and the hydrologic cycle. Though the aerosol direct effect can simply be thought of as a reduction of incoming solar radiation reaching the Earth's surface, the aerosol indirect effect (AIE) involves a complex set of aerosol-cloud-precipitation interactions. These indirect effects include the alteration of cloud microphysical properties such as cloud lifetime, droplet size distribution, liquid water content and path, optical depth, and albedo. Precipitation processes will certainly be affected in numerous and at times, detrimental ways. Hence, there is a major impact to society as a whole due to a heavy dependence on the distribution of available water over a given region for public consumption, agriculture, and industrial purposes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;This research adopts a synergistic approach that uses the long-term ground-based observations and retrievals from the Southern Great Plains of the United States and Eastern North Atlantic Ocean regions to investigate the seasonal and diurnal variations of aerosol and clouds under the continental and maritime conditions, as well as compare their similarities and differences. Air parcel trajectory modeling will be conducted to identify the sources of air masses for the selected cases to investigate the AIEs over these two regions with additional WRF simulations. This study is important because it will aid to improve aerosol and cloud parameterizations as well as provide an in-depth understanding of aerosol-cloud-precipitation interactions in typical maritime and continental conditions. The following three scientific questions (SQs) will be investigated.&lt;br/&gt;SQ1: What are the similarities and differences of aerosol-cloud properties, as well as their interactions over ocean and land? &lt;br/&gt;SQ2: What are the indirect effects of aerosols on cloud microphysical properties? &lt;br/&gt;SQ3: How does wind shear enhance turbulent mixing and stimulate drizzle formation?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:&lt;br/&gt;This research will benefit society by helping to provide better support for the modeling of aerosol-cloud-precipitation interactions which will aid in researching the long-term distribution of available water by clouds and precipitation processes. The far-reaching goal of this project is to further reduce uncertainties in the climate modeling community by providing better constraints for seasonal and regional aerosol and cloud properties. Moreover, there will be plenty of opportunities to introduce aerosol-cloud interactions as "real world" examples in undergraduate and graduate geoscience courses where the students can not only investigate these examples as interdisciplinary class projects, but also improve upon current research techniques and develop their own theses and dissertation areas of focus.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1700727</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuk</FirstName>
<LastName>Yung</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yuk L Yung</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yly@gps.caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263956940</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000462600</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911252100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><h3>Summary of Work and Accomplishments</h3> <h3>Over the ocean, marine boundary layer (MBL) stratiform clouds dominate the lower troposphere. Meanwhiles, aerosols from natural sources or anthropogenic activities are expected to have considerable and &nbsp;far-reaching effects on MBL cloud development and the associated hydrologic cycle. The overarching goal of this collaborative project is to evaluate model performance on low clouds and to advance our understanding of aerosol-cloud-precipitation interactions for low clouds under different conditions. Four key scientific goals are set to obtain process-level understanding on: 1) How environmental conditions (e.g. wind shear) affect cloud-drizzle formation processes, 2) How aerosols transform and transport near the region of our interest 3) What are the indirect effects of aerosols on cloud microphysical properties, and 4) What are the similarities and differences of aerosol-cloud properties, as well as their interactions over ocean and land.&nbsp; Eventually, this proposal will aid to improve aerosol and cloud parameterizations as well as provide an in-depth understanding of aerosol-cloud-precipitation interactions in the typical maritime and continental conditions.</h3> <h3>In this project, we configured the Weather Research and Forecast (WRF) as an aerosol-aware large-eddy simulation (LES) tool to study MBL clouds and their interactions with aerosols from different sources. To accurately resolve the eddy and cloud structure, the spatial resolution was setup as 300 m with a 40 m vertical resolution in planetary boundary layer (PBL). The cloud microphysics advanced spectral bin microphysics with a full representation of CCN activation and re-suspension. The model has been well calibrated, and the simulation results have been extensively evaluated against the interpolated soundings as well as ground-based observations over the Azores during the ACE-ENA.</h3> <h3>A thorough analysis of cloud and atmospheric conditions in the model reveals that the banded regions of enhanced cloud optical thickness in the model are associated with narrow bands of enhanced upward vertical velocity. While the largest cloud optical thickness values coincide with the narrow band of upward vertical velocity, the band of enhanced cloud optical thickness extends laterally outward, indicating that drizzle formation extends laterally away from the updraft core. Regions of drizzle that extend laterally outward the from the updraft band are associated with relatively strong vertical wind directional shear which is favorable for the drizzle formation, as the drizzle drops experienced further growth by enhanced collision-coalescence process induced by the wind-shear associated turbulence.</h3> <h3>We combined the ACE-ENA aircraft measurements, CMAS aerosol reanalysis, and the WRF-LES model to characterize spatial variations of aerosols from long-range transport over the Azores islands and assess their possible influence on the marine boundary layer clouds. The reanalysis data show high frequency of long-range transport over this area, and our back-trajectory analyses confirm that those transported aerosols were mainly from the U.S. continent. Aircraft observations show distinctive aerosol vertical distribution scenarios on different days. WRF-LES simulations suggest the aerosol plume cannot affect underlying MBL cloud properties in the first scenario. Even when the aerosols are close to the cloud top in the second scenario, the deepening of cloud is critical to have significant aerosol-cloud interactions. For the noticeable long-range transport effect, the Re and LWC susceptibilities are &minus;0.11 and +0.14, respectively. Overall, the long-range transported aerosols are less efficient in altering MBL cloud properties than those originated from local sources.</h3> <p><strong>Peer-reviewed publications </strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Wang, Y.</strong>, X. Zheng, X. Dong, B. Xi, P. Wu, T. Logan, <strong>Y. L. Yung</strong>, ?Impacts of Long-range Transport of Aerosols on Marine Boundary Layer Clouds in the Eastern North Atlantic?,<em> Atmo. Chem. Phys</em><em>. Diss.</em> https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-2020-623, in review (2020)</p> <p>Ward, D., X. Dong, B. Xi, P. Wu, X. Zheng, <strong>Y. Wang</strong>, ?Organized Variations in MBL Cloud Microphysical Properties Observed by Aircraft and Satellite and Simulated by Model?, <em>Atmo. Chem. Phys</em><em>. Diss.</em> https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-2020-817, in review (2020)</p> <p><strong>Wang, Y.</strong>, T. Le, G. Chen, <strong>Y. Yung</strong>, H. Su, J. H. Seinfeld, J. H. Jiang, ?Reduced European aerosol emissions suppress winter extremes over northern Eurasia?,<em>&nbsp;Nature Climate Change<strong>&nbsp;</strong></em>10, 225-230&nbsp;(2020)&nbsp;</p> <p>Zhao, B.,&nbsp;<strong>Y. Wang</strong>, Y. Gu, K.-N. Liou, J. H. Jiang, J. Fan, X. Liu, L. Huang, <strong>Y. Yung</strong>, ?Ice nucleation by aerosols from anthropogenic pollution?,<em>&nbsp;Nature&nbsp;Geoscience<strong>&nbsp;</strong></em>12, 602-607 (2019)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Wang, Y.</strong>, J. Jiang,&nbsp;H. Su, S. Choi, L. Huang, J. Guo and <strong>Y. Yung</strong>, ?Elucidating the Role of Anthropogenic Aerosols in Arctic Sea Ice Variations?,&nbsp;<em>J. Climate</em>, 31(1), 99-114 (2018)</p> <p><strong>Wang, Y.</strong>, P.-L. Ma,&nbsp;J. Peng, R. Zhang, J. Jiang, R. Easter, and <strong>Y. Yung</strong>, ?Constraining Black Carbon Aging Process in the Community Atmosphere Model by Ambient Chamber Experiments?,&nbsp;<em>J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></em>10(10), 2514-2526 (2018)</p> <p><strong>Wang, Y.</strong>, J. M. Vogel, Y. Lin, B. Pan, J. Hu, Y. Liu, X. Dong, J. Jiang, <strong>Y. Yung</strong>, and R. Zhang, ?Aerosol Microphysical and Radiative Effects on Continental Cloud Ensembles?,&nbsp;<em>Adv. Atmo. Sci.</em>, 35(2), 234-247 (2018)</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition, we gave 8 presentations at national and international conferences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Yuk&nbsp;L&nbsp;Yung</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Summary of Work and Accomplishments Over the ocean, marine boundary layer (MBL) stratiform clouds dominate the lower troposphere. Meanwhiles, aerosols from natural sources or anthropogenic activities are expected to have considerable and  far-reaching effects on MBL cloud development and the associated hydrologic cycle. The overarching goal of this collaborative project is to evaluate model performance on low clouds and to advance our understanding of aerosol-cloud-precipitation interactions for low clouds under different conditions. Four key scientific goals are set to obtain process-level understanding on: 1) How environmental conditions (e.g. wind shear) affect cloud-drizzle formation processes, 2) How aerosols transform and transport near the region of our interest 3) What are the indirect effects of aerosols on cloud microphysical properties, and 4) What are the similarities and differences of aerosol-cloud properties, as well as their interactions over ocean and land.  Eventually, this proposal will aid to improve aerosol and cloud parameterizations as well as provide an in-depth understanding of aerosol-cloud-precipitation interactions in the typical maritime and continental conditions. In this project, we configured the Weather Research and Forecast (WRF) as an aerosol-aware large-eddy simulation (LES) tool to study MBL clouds and their interactions with aerosols from different sources. To accurately resolve the eddy and cloud structure, the spatial resolution was setup as 300 m with a 40 m vertical resolution in planetary boundary layer (PBL). The cloud microphysics advanced spectral bin microphysics with a full representation of CCN activation and re-suspension. The model has been well calibrated, and the simulation results have been extensively evaluated against the interpolated soundings as well as ground-based observations over the Azores during the ACE-ENA. A thorough analysis of cloud and atmospheric conditions in the model reveals that the banded regions of enhanced cloud optical thickness in the model are associated with narrow bands of enhanced upward vertical velocity. While the largest cloud optical thickness values coincide with the narrow band of upward vertical velocity, the band of enhanced cloud optical thickness extends laterally outward, indicating that drizzle formation extends laterally away from the updraft core. Regions of drizzle that extend laterally outward the from the updraft band are associated with relatively strong vertical wind directional shear which is favorable for the drizzle formation, as the drizzle drops experienced further growth by enhanced collision-coalescence process induced by the wind-shear associated turbulence. We combined the ACE-ENA aircraft measurements, CMAS aerosol reanalysis, and the WRF-LES model to characterize spatial variations of aerosols from long-range transport over the Azores islands and assess their possible influence on the marine boundary layer clouds. The reanalysis data show high frequency of long-range transport over this area, and our back-trajectory analyses confirm that those transported aerosols were mainly from the U.S. continent. Aircraft observations show distinctive aerosol vertical distribution scenarios on different days. WRF-LES simulations suggest the aerosol plume cannot affect underlying MBL cloud properties in the first scenario. Even when the aerosols are close to the cloud top in the second scenario, the deepening of cloud is critical to have significant aerosol-cloud interactions. For the noticeable long-range transport effect, the Re and LWC susceptibilities are &minus;0.11 and +0.14, respectively. Overall, the long-range transported aerosols are less efficient in altering MBL cloud properties than those originated from local sources.  Peer-reviewed publications      Wang, Y., X. Zheng, X. Dong, B. Xi, P. Wu, T. Logan, Y. L. Yung, ?Impacts of Long-range Transport of Aerosols on Marine Boundary Layer Clouds in the Eastern North Atlantic?, Atmo. Chem. Phys. Diss. https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-2020-623, in review (2020)  Ward, D., X. Dong, B. Xi, P. Wu, X. Zheng, Y. Wang, ?Organized Variations in MBL Cloud Microphysical Properties Observed by Aircraft and Satellite and Simulated by Model?, Atmo. Chem. Phys. Diss. https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-2020-817, in review (2020)  Wang, Y., T. Le, G. Chen, Y. Yung, H. Su, J. H. Seinfeld, J. H. Jiang, ?Reduced European aerosol emissions suppress winter extremes over northern Eurasia?, Nature Climate Change 10, 225-230 (2020)   Zhao, B., Y. Wang, Y. Gu, K.-N. Liou, J. H. Jiang, J. Fan, X. Liu, L. Huang, Y. Yung, ?Ice nucleation by aerosols from anthropogenic pollution?, Nature Geoscience 12, 602-607 (2019)     Wang, Y., J. Jiang, H. Su, S. Choi, L. Huang, J. Guo and Y. Yung, ?Elucidating the Role of Anthropogenic Aerosols in Arctic Sea Ice Variations?, J. Climate, 31(1), 99-114 (2018)  Wang, Y., P.-L. Ma, J. Peng, R. Zhang, J. Jiang, R. Easter, and Y. Yung, ?Constraining Black Carbon Aging Process in the Community Atmosphere Model by Ambient Chamber Experiments?, J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst. 10(10), 2514-2526 (2018)  Wang, Y., J. M. Vogel, Y. Lin, B. Pan, J. Hu, Y. Liu, X. Dong, J. Jiang, Y. Yung, and R. Zhang, ?Aerosol Microphysical and Radiative Effects on Continental Cloud Ensembles?, Adv. Atmo. Sci., 35(2), 234-247 (2018)     In addition, we gave 8 presentations at national and international conferences.          Last Modified: 09/30/2020       Submitted by: Yuk L Yung]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
