<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER/Collaborative Research: Center-of-Mass Control for Expressive and Effective Movement in Bipedal Robots</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>63476.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>63476</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Irina Dolinskaya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>idolinsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927078</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This EArly-concept Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER) collaborative project will apply insights from the study of human athletes and dancers to enable similarly effective and expressive movement in humanoid robots. The objective is to create the capability for such movement without duplicating the full complexity and articulation of the human torso. Specifically, the project will implement a novel mechanism for shifting a heavy mass that shifts the robot center of mass independently of limb movements using novel muscle-like actuators, and evaluate the results based on a formal system of movement analysis developed for dance, athletics, and physical therapy. In addition to improving the robot's effectiveness at accomplishing locomotion, i.e., a walking gait, these capabilities will provide new channels for communication between robots and humans, i.e., modulating the style of the walking gait. Humans make unconscious inferences about attitude and intent from observing movement. For example, a robot co-worker will be more effective if its movements communicate trustworthiness and competence to its human partners, and a robot first-responder will be more effective if its movements communicate confidence and leadership during an emergency situation. This project incorporates the interplay of art and technology into outreach activities, such as using dance movements to understand fundamentals of robot locomotion.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project takes a novel approach to generating dynamic walking in a humanoid robot, by exploiting the dynamics of a novel, core-located rolling ball-and-tray actuation mechanism arising from exploration of embodied movement theory. The impedance of the actuator is varied in real time, modulating the robot dynamics to produce qualitatively different excitations. The focus of the project is on controlling the expressive character of robot gait, with explicit comparison to human movement. The goals of the project are to explore the role of center-of-mass control in human walking and to demonstrate the feasibility of the approach for bipedal robotic walking through modeling, simulation, and an initial prototype. The work will model and validate the ball-and-tray actuator via a set of motion primitives designed in accordance with Bartenieff Fundamentals, a formal system of movement analysis. The research team brings together experts in movement science, dynamic walking, and muscle-like actuation. In addition to improving robot performance, this work has the potential to increase the bandwidth of robot-human communications. Expressive movement can convey many different emotional contexts, including urgency, calm, enthusiasm, confidence, et cetera. The ability to engineer these contexts into robot movement has many potential applications in human facing scenarios.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1701378</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Schultz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua A Schultz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>joshua-schultz@utulsa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9186313846</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000662434</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tulsa</Name>
<CityName>Tulsa</CityName>
<ZipCode>741049700</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9186312192</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 S. Tucker Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072420433</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TULSA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072420433</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tulsa]]></Name>
<CityName>Tulsa</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>741049700</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 S. Tucker Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>Dynamics, Control and System D</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8024</Code>
<Text>Complex Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~63476</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this EAGER project was to stimulate early-stage research on using an active core (used in the sense of ``core muscles'' as in exercise routines) to drive walking gaits that could be of various different characters. For instance, observers should be able to distinguish the difference between a ``spritely'' gait, and a ``trudge''. The research investigation proceeded from the idea that this character of the movement can be generated in a simple way, namely, by varying the characteristics of a moving system in the robot's ``core'', with the motions of the walker flowing from the core rather than precisely choreographed motions of the hips, knees and ankles. This one-year EAGER grant brought together a team from The University of Tulsa and The University of Illinois to examine whether a longer-term investigation was warranted.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />To study the effects of a moving ``core'', two instrumented trays were constructed at The University of Tulsa. It is shaped so that a heavy ball can roll within it when the tray is tilted about an axis by a motor. By varying the characteristics (e.g. shape, curvature) of the tray, the rolling motion of the ball will be affected. As the heavy ball changes direction due to tray shape, tray tilt, or impact with the ends of the tray, it imparts forces to base below as it rolls. If this tray is mounted atop a passive walker (such as those devices that have been demonstrated ``walk'' down a slope purely under the influence of gravity by careful tuning of the length of legs and joints), these forces at the base could potentially drive such a walker forward, or at least substantially influence the walking gait of a walking robot.<br />A computer simulation was conducted that shows the rolling motion of the ball in response to a tilt of the tray. This allowed the team to evaluate how trays of different characteristics would respond. This simulation is currently in the process of being validated using a motion capture system that can detect the location of the ball in non-contact fashion using the image from an RGBD camera. Experiments were conducted that measured the force and torque transmitted from the tray to the base. These measured forces and torques produced by the tray were compared against a series of forces and torques applied to the core of a two-legged walker in simulation at the University of Illinois.. A matrix of outputs of the University of Illinois simulation had been labeled by movement experts and members of the general public with terms corresponding to a particular gait style.<br />While the forces were not exactly equal in value at each instant in time, it was found that the two different trays produced noticeably different ``core forces'' and the amount of force and the speed with which the force is varied are equivalent to those in the walking simulation. This gives confidence that one could a walking gait that falls into each of the distinct categories identified by the human subjects tested by suitable tray designs and correctly timed tray tilts. These results were submitted to the proceedings of the International Conference on Robotics and Automation (under review at the time of this writing). The comparison between the physical tray-generated forces and torques and the simulation gives the investigators confidence and evidence that this research idea is worth pursuing further.<br />As a result of this project, strong professional relationships have been formed between graduate students at The University of Tulsa and The University of Illinois. The two who have yet to graduate remain in contact and speak regularly. The students (one US and the others international) are from very different backgrounds and it has promoted greater cross-cultural understanding. One activity that promoted this was a mid-year full team meeting at The University of Illinois, where the Tulsa team traveled to Champaign for the meeting. Since the two Universities are very different (One private, one public, and of different sizes), it has also enlarged the graduate students' perspective for considering future possible career options, should they opt for a career in academia.<br />The experiences and insights from this project have made their way into in-class discussions in undergraduate dynamics and control lecture and lab sections at The University of Tulsa, and will form the basis for at least one lecture in the upcoming graduate dynamics course, to be taught for the first time at The University of Tulsa in the spring of 2019. The PI is involved with continued discussion with the laboratory instructor about potential improvements to the system dynamics and controls lab during the semi-annual University of Tulsa Continuous Improvement Day, and concepts from this research project will enlighten those discussions and influence undergraduate student teaching laboratory exercises.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Joshua&nbsp;A&nbsp;Schultz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this EAGER project was to stimulate early-stage research on using an active core (used in the sense of ``core muscles'' as in exercise routines) to drive walking gaits that could be of various different characters. For instance, observers should be able to distinguish the difference between a ``spritely'' gait, and a ``trudge''. The research investigation proceeded from the idea that this character of the movement can be generated in a simple way, namely, by varying the characteristics of a moving system in the robot's ``core'', with the motions of the walker flowing from the core rather than precisely choreographed motions of the hips, knees and ankles. This one-year EAGER grant brought together a team from The University of Tulsa and The University of Illinois to examine whether a longer-term investigation was warranted.    To study the effects of a moving ``core'', two instrumented trays were constructed at The University of Tulsa. It is shaped so that a heavy ball can roll within it when the tray is tilted about an axis by a motor. By varying the characteristics (e.g. shape, curvature) of the tray, the rolling motion of the ball will be affected. As the heavy ball changes direction due to tray shape, tray tilt, or impact with the ends of the tray, it imparts forces to base below as it rolls. If this tray is mounted atop a passive walker (such as those devices that have been demonstrated ``walk'' down a slope purely under the influence of gravity by careful tuning of the length of legs and joints), these forces at the base could potentially drive such a walker forward, or at least substantially influence the walking gait of a walking robot. A computer simulation was conducted that shows the rolling motion of the ball in response to a tilt of the tray. This allowed the team to evaluate how trays of different characteristics would respond. This simulation is currently in the process of being validated using a motion capture system that can detect the location of the ball in non-contact fashion using the image from an RGBD camera. Experiments were conducted that measured the force and torque transmitted from the tray to the base. These measured forces and torques produced by the tray were compared against a series of forces and torques applied to the core of a two-legged walker in simulation at the University of Illinois.. A matrix of outputs of the University of Illinois simulation had been labeled by movement experts and members of the general public with terms corresponding to a particular gait style. While the forces were not exactly equal in value at each instant in time, it was found that the two different trays produced noticeably different ``core forces'' and the amount of force and the speed with which the force is varied are equivalent to those in the walking simulation. This gives confidence that one could a walking gait that falls into each of the distinct categories identified by the human subjects tested by suitable tray designs and correctly timed tray tilts. These results were submitted to the proceedings of the International Conference on Robotics and Automation (under review at the time of this writing). The comparison between the physical tray-generated forces and torques and the simulation gives the investigators confidence and evidence that this research idea is worth pursuing further. As a result of this project, strong professional relationships have been formed between graduate students at The University of Tulsa and The University of Illinois. The two who have yet to graduate remain in contact and speak regularly. The students (one US and the others international) are from very different backgrounds and it has promoted greater cross-cultural understanding. One activity that promoted this was a mid-year full team meeting at The University of Illinois, where the Tulsa team traveled to Champaign for the meeting. Since the two Universities are very different (One private, one public, and of different sizes), it has also enlarged the graduate students' perspective for considering future possible career options, should they opt for a career in academia. The experiences and insights from this project have made their way into in-class discussions in undergraduate dynamics and control lecture and lab sections at The University of Tulsa, and will form the basis for at least one lecture in the upcoming graduate dynamics course, to be taught for the first time at The University of Tulsa in the spring of 2019. The PI is involved with continued discussion with the laboratory instructor about potential improvements to the system dynamics and controls lab during the semi-annual University of Tulsa Continuous Improvement Day, and concepts from this research project will enlighten those discussions and influence undergraduate student teaching laboratory exercises.       Last Modified: 12/07/2018       Submitted by: Joshua A Schultz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
