<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT:  Smart Helmet Impact Sensing System</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>271000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating the research discovery of a printed and flexible pressure sensor into a smart helmet impact sensing system to fill the need for monitoring sports related traumatic brain injuries. The smart helmet impact sensing system is important because it will provide information needed to reliably detect head trauma and data for improved performance and training measures which can reduce head, spinal and neck trauma. The project will result in the development of a fully functional prototype of the smart helmet impact sensing system which will be able to monitor the intensity and location of head impacts sustained by athletes in the field. This smart helmet impact sensing system has unique features of being physically flexible, light weight and conformable. These features provide the advantage of being able to seamlessly integrate the system into existing helmets covering the entire helmet interior, thus enabling "point-of-impact mapping" of head trauma around the skull that no other system in the market provides. These features differentiate the impact sensing technology when compared to its competitors in this market space, who typically use traditional silicon based manufacturing processes that result in systems that are not flexible, non-conformal, bulky and relatively expensive.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the following technology gap(s) as it translates from research discovery toward commercial application: (a) developing an in-helmet sensor array for the characterization of impact forces as well as an integrated and miniaturized electronic readout circuit to enable it to fit within a helmet; (b) developing a communication system that can wirelessly send and store impact data; (c) confirming by field testing that the system is mechanically and operationally robust; (d) demonstrating that the system conforms to the Virginia Tech STAR Ratings standards; and (e) understanding the combined effects of the current accelerometer approach to that of impact alone as well as impact-accelerometer combinations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition, personnel involved in this project, a post-doctoral fellow and a graduate student, will receive technology and entrepreneurship translation experiences through: (a) participation in the system development project activities, (b) interactions with the Office of the Vice President of Research (OVPR) office at Western Michigan University for disclosures and patents, (c) developing pitch decks for participating in business pitch competitions, (d) developing a business plan for the commercialization of the smart helmet impact sensing system, (e) participation in developing follow-up grant proposals, and (f) further interactions with research scholars, business professionals, customers and entrepreneurs for licensing, technology transfer and commercialization activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1701157</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Massood</FirstName>
<LastName>Atashbar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Z</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Massood Z Atashbar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>massood.atashbar@wmich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2692763148</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000213687</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Western Michigan University</Name>
<CityName>Kalamazoo</CityName>
<ZipCode>490085200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2693878298</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1903 West Michigan Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>622364479</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WESTERN MICHIGAN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>062230560</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Western Michigan University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>490085200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PFI-Partnrships for Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>019Z</Code>
<Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Experience</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~55000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This PFI:AIR - TT project was performed by the research group of Prof. Massood Atashbar, at Western Michigan University, to develop an in-helmet sensor array for the characterization of impact forces. The main goals of this project were to: 1) model a capacitive pressure sensor array and electronic readout circuit, 2) fabricate a capacitive pressure sensor array, 3) fabricate a flexible electronic readout circuit, and 4) test the impact sensing system.</p> <p>Over the course of the project, an array of impact sensors and electronic circuit were fabricated and integrated into football helmets. In the laboratory, a drop-impact testing system that is compatible with the ASTM F429-10 standards was used for testing the performance of the system. Multiple tests performed on different locations (front, front boss, right side, rear boss, rear and top) demonstrated that the instrumented helmet could detect high, medium and low impacts in the sensors corresponding to the impact test locations.</p> <p>The helmets with the fully integrated system received the National Operating Committee on Standards for Athletic Equipment (NOCSAE) certification from the Safety Equipment Institute (SEI) test laboratory. Field testing was performed on 10 students in Michigan high schools during the 2017, 2018 and 2019 football practice season. The results and feedback during the field tests demonstrated the mechanical robustness, system performance and comfort fit of the system. The system was able to wirelessly transmit data, from the system to a computer, while the students were practicing on-field. The feedback provided by the students revealed that the students did not feel any difference in the performance of the helmet and did not have any discomfort.</p> <p>This PFI:AIR - TT project also leveraged NSF's INTERN and REU initiatives which provided one graduate student (INTERN) and two undergraduate students (REU) with additional diverse skills in addition to their laboratory experience. The INTERN received an industrial based training and experience that integrates electrical and computer engineering theory and methodology, with the practical and technical aspects of a research project that is focused on solving a real-world application problem. The REU provided a valuable opportunity for the graduate students to experience a complete product development cycle, by being exposed to different phases of a commercialization-based research project</p> <p>In summary, the results from this PFI:AIR - TT project is allowing the team to advance the technology from the laboratory to the market by understanding the customer needs. A core team that will develop a business plan and spin out this technology for commercialization is being formed.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/06/2020<br>      Modified by: Massood&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Atashbar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This PFI:AIR - TT project was performed by the research group of Prof. Massood Atashbar, at Western Michigan University, to develop an in-helmet sensor array for the characterization of impact forces. The main goals of this project were to: 1) model a capacitive pressure sensor array and electronic readout circuit, 2) fabricate a capacitive pressure sensor array, 3) fabricate a flexible electronic readout circuit, and 4) test the impact sensing system.  Over the course of the project, an array of impact sensors and electronic circuit were fabricated and integrated into football helmets. In the laboratory, a drop-impact testing system that is compatible with the ASTM F429-10 standards was used for testing the performance of the system. Multiple tests performed on different locations (front, front boss, right side, rear boss, rear and top) demonstrated that the instrumented helmet could detect high, medium and low impacts in the sensors corresponding to the impact test locations.  The helmets with the fully integrated system received the National Operating Committee on Standards for Athletic Equipment (NOCSAE) certification from the Safety Equipment Institute (SEI) test laboratory. Field testing was performed on 10 students in Michigan high schools during the 2017, 2018 and 2019 football practice season. The results and feedback during the field tests demonstrated the mechanical robustness, system performance and comfort fit of the system. The system was able to wirelessly transmit data, from the system to a computer, while the students were practicing on-field. The feedback provided by the students revealed that the students did not feel any difference in the performance of the helmet and did not have any discomfort.  This PFI:AIR - TT project also leveraged NSF's INTERN and REU initiatives which provided one graduate student (INTERN) and two undergraduate students (REU) with additional diverse skills in addition to their laboratory experience. The INTERN received an industrial based training and experience that integrates electrical and computer engineering theory and methodology, with the practical and technical aspects of a research project that is focused on solving a real-world application problem. The REU provided a valuable opportunity for the graduate students to experience a complete product development cycle, by being exposed to different phases of a commercialization-based research project  In summary, the results from this PFI:AIR - TT project is allowing the team to advance the technology from the laboratory to the market by understanding the customer needs. A core team that will develop a business plan and spin out this technology for commercialization is being formed.       Last Modified: 10/06/2020       Submitted by: Massood Z Atashbar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
