<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Costs and Benefits of Shelter-Building by Lepidopteran Caterpillars in a Tropical Dry Forest</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19307.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19307</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Betsy Von Holle</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mvonholl@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924974</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Tens of thousands of caterpillar species build shelters out of silk and leaves. Many are sufficiently abundant that they are important forest pests. However, little is known about how shelters affect the survival of the caterpillars and ultimately their egg production as adults. This project will provide information on the impact that shelters have on caterpillar survival and adult success. First, the project tests how much protection shelters provide from high temperatures and low humidity.  This information will help determine how sensitive the caterpillars are to their environment, clarifying how changes in local and global climate might influence the success of shelter-building species. Second, the project will test the protective effects of shelters against predatory insects and spiders, and against parasitic wasps and flies. Specifically, the experiments will determine whether caterpillars whose shelters provide better protection against predators are more vulnerable to parasitic insects. Both predators and parasitic insects are used to control pest insects, so testing this hypothesis could be applied to pest management. Because the research site is in Costa Rica, the researchers will also increase awareness of an under-studied tropical habitat (tropical dry forests) and foster international connections and training.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers will perform two sets of experiments using caterpillar species that cooperatively build group shelters, in which two to ten caterpillars can be found living together. Both sets of experiments will be conducted in the natural forest habitat of the caterpillars. The first experiment will measure the effects of shelters and the environment on caterpillar survival for four species. Caterpillars, along with temperature and humidity sensors, will be placed both inside and outside caterpillar shelters. Caterpillar survival will be monitored to determine whether the caterpillars are protected from the outside environment by their shelters. The second experiment will measure the costs and benefits of building and sharing group shelters for two caterpillar species. Caterpillars will be allowed to build shelters either alone or in groups, and the mortality caused by predators and parasitic insects will be measured. If some treatments are less likely to be killed by predators, the researchers will test whether the caterpillars are also more likely to be attacked by parasitic insects. The positive and negative effects of sharing a shelter with other caterpillars will also be measured by weighing the pupae of surviving caterpillars. Heavier pupae become adults who generally produce more offspring, so this measure will allow the researchers to determine whether sharing a shelter has a negative effect (due to competition with other caterpillars) or a positive one (due to sharing the costs of building and maintaining the shelter).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1701855</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Marquis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert J Marquis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robert_marquis@umsl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3145166213</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000328390</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christina</FirstName>
<LastName>Baer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christina S Baer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>baerc@umsl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3145166218</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000680486</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Missouri-Saint Louis</Name>
<CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>631214400</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3145165897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ONE UNIVERSITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804883825</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSOURI SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006326904</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Missouri-St. Louis]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631214400</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~19307</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this study was to understand the ecological factors influencing the success of leaf shelter building caterpillars in a tropical dry forest site in Costa Rica. Leaf shelter building is a common characteristic of many species of caterpillars at the study site. It is also common in caterpillar species that are forest pests throughout the world.</p> <p>Leaf shelter building caterpillars tie leaves together with silk produced by in their silk glands. The shelters might benefit the caterpillars because: 1) the provide a less stressful environment compared to feeding on single leaves, or 2) they protect the caterpillars from their enemies, including arthropod predators and parasites. Our environmental monitoring of the shelters showed that there is very little difference between the environments within a shelter and just outside the shelter. Thus the shelters do not seem to provide a less stressful environment. In contrast, shelters provide protection against both predators and parasitoids. In addition, when multiple caterpillars build a single shelter, predation decreases compared to caterpillars living alone. In one of the two caterpillar species studied, parasites preferentially attacked caterpillars in groups.&nbsp;</p> <p>Together these results contribute to our understanding of what controls populations of tree-feeding insects, in this case, in a little studied biome, tropical dry forest. The results confirm what is known from temperate North American forests, that is, forest insects that reach pest status often show a gregarious feeding style. In both caterpillar species studied, grerariousness resulted in reduced predation, and in one species, parasitism was also lower for individuals feeding together compared to those feeding alone. Knowledge of this basic biology is essential for understanding the factors that influence insect population growth and decline, and how we might control these populations when they reach outbreak proportions that cause economic damage.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/12/2019<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;J&nbsp;Marquis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1701855/1701855_10486052_1573536406745_Urbanusdorantes--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1701855/1701855_10486052_1573536406745_Urbanusdorantes--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Urbanus dorantes caterpillar"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1701855/1701855_10486052_1573536406745_Urbanusdorantes--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Urbanus dorantes caterpillar"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Late instar caterpillar</div> <div class="imageCredit">C. S. Baer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;J&nbsp;Marquis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Urbanus dorantes caterpillar</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1701855/1701855_10486052_1573536512337_shelterofEulepteconcordalis--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1701855/1701855_10486052_1573536512337_shelterofEulepteconcordalis--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Leaf shelter of Eulepte concordalis"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1701855/1701855_10486052_1573536512337_shelterofEulepteconcordalis--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Leaf shelter of Eulepte concordalis"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Typical leaf shelter from tropical dry forest at Palo Verde Costa Rica</div> <div class="imageCredit">C. S. Baer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;J&nbsp;Marquis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Leaf shelter of Eulepte concordalis</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this study was to understand the ecological factors influencing the success of leaf shelter building caterpillars in a tropical dry forest site in Costa Rica. Leaf shelter building is a common characteristic of many species of caterpillars at the study site. It is also common in caterpillar species that are forest pests throughout the world.  Leaf shelter building caterpillars tie leaves together with silk produced by in their silk glands. The shelters might benefit the caterpillars because: 1) the provide a less stressful environment compared to feeding on single leaves, or 2) they protect the caterpillars from their enemies, including arthropod predators and parasites. Our environmental monitoring of the shelters showed that there is very little difference between the environments within a shelter and just outside the shelter. Thus the shelters do not seem to provide a less stressful environment. In contrast, shelters provide protection against both predators and parasitoids. In addition, when multiple caterpillars build a single shelter, predation decreases compared to caterpillars living alone. In one of the two caterpillar species studied, parasites preferentially attacked caterpillars in groups.   Together these results contribute to our understanding of what controls populations of tree-feeding insects, in this case, in a little studied biome, tropical dry forest. The results confirm what is known from temperate North American forests, that is, forest insects that reach pest status often show a gregarious feeding style. In both caterpillar species studied, grerariousness resulted in reduced predation, and in one species, parasitism was also lower for individuals feeding together compared to those feeding alone. Knowledge of this basic biology is essential for understanding the factors that influence insect population growth and decline, and how we might control these populations when they reach outbreak proportions that cause economic damage.         Last Modified: 11/12/2019       Submitted by: Robert J Marquis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
