<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Mechanisms of asymmetrical ecosystem responses to precipitation extremes in xeric vs. mesic grasslands</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19316.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19316</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Blood</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eblood@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924349</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Native grasslands once covering millions of acres across the US have been reduced to a tiny fraction of their former distribution. These remaining grasslands play important roles in the cycling of carbon and nutrients, biodiversity, and as sources for restoration. The health and seasonal dynamics of the remaining native grasslands in the central US are controlled by the amount and timing of rainfall. Across the central US rainfall variability is predicted to increase, with greater frequencies of extreme wet and dry years expected. Grasslands are likely to be particularly sensitive to such changes, with evidence that these systems may be more sensitive to wet versus dry years. However, studies rarely include assessment of extreme years. This Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant (DDIG) award, will experimentally assess the sensitivity of the grassland composition, carbon cycle, and nutrient cycling to rainfall extremes within an intact semi-arid grassland system. The research results will be valuable to natural resource and land managers in managing or restoring native grasslands. Graduate and undergraduate students will be trained and participate in the research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project aims to advance a fundamental understanding of how ecosystems will respond to predicted increases in environmental variability and extremity. The grassland ecosystem's response to rainfall extremes is hypothesized to be non-linear and bi-modal. A novel experimental treatment is proposed to expose semi-arid grassland to a large gradient of growing season precipitation that will be able to detect nonlinearities in response variables that are otherwise not detectable in few-factor experimental design. The research will allow assessment of the comparative sensitivities of key carbon cycle components to dry versus wet years, and how this sensitivity may change when precipitation transitions from moderate to extreme deviations from mean levels.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/24/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/24/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1701966</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melinda</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melinda Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>melinda.smith@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704917155</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000419066</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Felton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Felton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>felton12392@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6122518554</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000732233</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>785979618</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>948905492</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805214593</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 W. Lake Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~19316</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The health and societal services of central US grasslands are largely controlled by the amount, timing, and variability of rainfall. Future weather patterns in the Central US are expected to be characterized by increasing rainfall variability and extreme events such as drought. Consequently, a need for mechanistic research studies to quantify the sensitivity of these systems to future changes in rainfall patterns has emerged. With funding from NSF, we conducted an experiment within an intact semi-arid grassland in northern Colorado during the summer (May &ndash; early September) of 2017. Our experiment simulated a gradient of growing season rainfall that gradually transitioned from the most extreme drought to the wettest year on record. In response to our experimental rainfall gradient, we quantified the sensitivity of forage production, plant biodiversity, and losses of carbon to the atmosphere within this grassland. We found forage production to increase linearly with precipitation, but that losses of carbon to the atmosphere tended to saturate, with both process most responsive to extreme wet versus dry conditions. We also find that under these wettest conditions, the growth and prevalence of exotic plant species undesirable to cattle as forage may be facilitated. This suggests that plant biodiversity and forage productivity within this grassland will be highly sensitive to future precipitation variability and in particular extreme wet years. These findings improve predictions of how semi-arid grasslands will respond to future changes in rainfall patterns. By better understanding the sensitivity of these ecosystem attributes to rainfall variability, land managers, ranchers, and policy makers will be better equipped to make informed decisions that maintain the health and services of central US grasslands and rangelands in light of a changing climate. Funding for this project has also had significantly positive implications for professional development. This research project supported the summer and fall employment of an undergraduate biology student, who gained comprehensive experience in ecological field research. Funding from this project also resulted in a dissertation chapter for a graduate student&rsquo;s PhD research, which facilitated the attainment of a PhD in ecology in 2018. This research project also has led to the production, submission, and acceptance of a scientific paper in a premier scientific journal of ecological research, which will be of a broad interest to the ecological research community. As a result, the outcomes of from the funding of this project are invaluable; extending from informing grassland ecosystem management, heightening professional development, to advancing the field of climate change and grassland ecology.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/16/2018<br>      Modified by: Melinda&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The health and societal services of central US grasslands are largely controlled by the amount, timing, and variability of rainfall. Future weather patterns in the Central US are expected to be characterized by increasing rainfall variability and extreme events such as drought. Consequently, a need for mechanistic research studies to quantify the sensitivity of these systems to future changes in rainfall patterns has emerged. With funding from NSF, we conducted an experiment within an intact semi-arid grassland in northern Colorado during the summer (May &ndash; early September) of 2017. Our experiment simulated a gradient of growing season rainfall that gradually transitioned from the most extreme drought to the wettest year on record. In response to our experimental rainfall gradient, we quantified the sensitivity of forage production, plant biodiversity, and losses of carbon to the atmosphere within this grassland. We found forage production to increase linearly with precipitation, but that losses of carbon to the atmosphere tended to saturate, with both process most responsive to extreme wet versus dry conditions. We also find that under these wettest conditions, the growth and prevalence of exotic plant species undesirable to cattle as forage may be facilitated. This suggests that plant biodiversity and forage productivity within this grassland will be highly sensitive to future precipitation variability and in particular extreme wet years. These findings improve predictions of how semi-arid grasslands will respond to future changes in rainfall patterns. By better understanding the sensitivity of these ecosystem attributes to rainfall variability, land managers, ranchers, and policy makers will be better equipped to make informed decisions that maintain the health and services of central US grasslands and rangelands in light of a changing climate. Funding for this project has also had significantly positive implications for professional development. This research project supported the summer and fall employment of an undergraduate biology student, who gained comprehensive experience in ecological field research. Funding from this project also resulted in a dissertation chapter for a graduate student?s PhD research, which facilitated the attainment of a PhD in ecology in 2018. This research project also has led to the production, submission, and acceptance of a scientific paper in a premier scientific journal of ecological research, which will be of a broad interest to the ecological research community. As a result, the outcomes of from the funding of this project are invaluable; extending from informing grassland ecosystem management, heightening professional development, to advancing the field of climate change and grassland ecology.       Last Modified: 11/16/2018       Submitted by: Melinda Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
