<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Hodge-Theoretic Generalizations of Multiplier Ideals</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research concerns several projects in algebraic geometry. Classically, algebraic geometry is the study of solutions of systems of polynomial equations, and it plays a key role in numerous fields of mathematics, both pure and applied. The solution space of a system of polynomial equations has a very rich structure that can be smooth (continuous) or singular (discontinuous). This project is concerned with a new approach to singularities that arises from transferring ideas from complex geometry to an algebraic setting. The main goal is to further develop the theory of "Hodge ideals," which are subtle invariants of singularities.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In more detail, several directions of research will be pursued: extending the current version of Hodge ideals associated to reduced hypersurfaces (one would like extensions to Q-divisors or to ideals defining a subscheme that is reduced in codimension one); extending the study of Hodge filtrations on localizations at one element (which is equivalent to the study of Hodge ideals) to the study of Hodge filtrations on local cohomology modules of a regular local ring along an arbitrary ideal; investigating a potential analogue of Hodge ideals in positive characteristic; exploiting the connection between Hodge ideals and the motivic Chern transformation of Brasselet-Schuermann-Yokura; and developing tools based on more classical methods to give new proofs of results on Hodge ideals whose current proofs rely on Saito's theory of Hodge modules.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1701622</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mircea</FirstName>
<LastName>Mustata</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mircea Mustata</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mmustata@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347646452</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000095275</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~112488</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~116585</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~130928</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Algebraic varieties are geometric shapes defined by algebraic objects (more precisely, as zeroes of polynomials). Some of these objects are smooth, while some have certain singularities. For a very long time, algebraic geometers have studied invariants that measure how complicated these singularities are. The invariants can be numbers or they can be themselves given by algebraic objects.</p> <p><br />The current project was motivated by previous joint work of the PI with Popa, in which they introduced some invariants of singularities (Hodge ideals) associated to singular varieties defined in a smooth variety by one reduced equation. While funded by this grant, they greatly extended this construction (to the setting of Q-divisors) and related the invariants they obtained to other invariants that have been previously studied (V-filtration and minimal exponents). In particular, this led to interesting applications to the study of minimal exponents, extending results obtained in the 80s for isolated singularities.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />Several side projects have been pursued by the PI. For example, together with Kien and Cluckers, the PI used results about a certain invariant of singularities (the log canonical threshold) to make progress on a decades-old conjecture due to Igusa. Another such project, joint with Elduque, settled an old conjecture of Teissier concerning the behavior of log canonical thresholds under a certain natural geometric operation (restriction to a hyperplane section). &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/24/2020<br>      Modified by: Mircea&nbsp;Mustata</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Algebraic varieties are geometric shapes defined by algebraic objects (more precisely, as zeroes of polynomials). Some of these objects are smooth, while some have certain singularities. For a very long time, algebraic geometers have studied invariants that measure how complicated these singularities are. The invariants can be numbers or they can be themselves given by algebraic objects.   The current project was motivated by previous joint work of the PI with Popa, in which they introduced some invariants of singularities (Hodge ideals) associated to singular varieties defined in a smooth variety by one reduced equation. While funded by this grant, they greatly extended this construction (to the setting of Q-divisors) and related the invariants they obtained to other invariants that have been previously studied (V-filtration and minimal exponents). In particular, this led to interesting applications to the study of minimal exponents, extending results obtained in the 80s for isolated singularities.    Several side projects have been pursued by the PI. For example, together with Kien and Cluckers, the PI used results about a certain invariant of singularities (the log canonical threshold) to make progress on a decades-old conjecture due to Igusa. Another such project, joint with Elduque, settled an old conjecture of Teissier concerning the behavior of log canonical thresholds under a certain natural geometric operation (restriction to a hyperplane section).         Last Modified: 10/24/2020       Submitted by: Mircea Mustata]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
