<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Moduli of Galois Representations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>189854.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>189854</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Number theory is one of the oldest branches of mathematics. At its most fundamental, number theory is the study of whole number solutions to polynomial equations, and especially to equations motivated by geometry. For example, the lengths of the three sides of a right triangle are related by the Pythagorean theorem. While it is straightforward to find all right triangles whose side lengths are rational numbers, it perhaps surprisingly remains an unsolved problem to determine which whole numbers can be the area of a right triangle with rational sides. Number theory has many important practical applications. For instance, most cellular telephone calls are protected by a code based on elliptic curves, one of the primary objects of study in the Langlands program, the principal investigator's area of research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Significant progress has been made in recent decades towards understanding Langlands's conjectural reciprocity between automorphic forms and Galois representations. Techniques for proving reciprocity laws generally require the consideration of p-adic families of Galois representations. Three projects to investigate p-adic families of Galois representations will be undertaken. The first project will produce moduli stacks of certain Galois representations in which the residual representation is allowed to vary. This will open up the possibility of proving results in the Langlands program by establishing them generically on these spaces. The second project, on Breuil's local-global compatibility conjecture for types in the p-adic Langlands program, will be a demonstration of this technique. A third project is to study the weight part of Serre's conjecture for GL(n), for n larger than 2, in non-generic cases.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1702161</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Savitt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David L Savitt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>savitt@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5202473818</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000186675</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/28/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212182686</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439971898</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1101 E 33rd St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite B001]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001910777</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001910777</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Johns Hopkins University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3400 N CHARLES ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~189854</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Number theory is one of the oldest branches of mathematics. At its most fundamental, number theory is the study of whole number solutions to polynomial equations, and especially to equations motivated by geometry. For example, the lengths of the three sides of a right triangle are related by the Pythagorean theorem. While it is straightforward to find all right triangles whose side lengths are rational numbers, it perhaps surprisingly remains an unsolved problem to determine which whole numbers can be the area of a right triangle with rational sides. Number theory has many important practical applications. For instance, most cellular telephone calls are protected by a code based on elliptic curves, one of the primary objects of study in the Langlands program, the principal investigator's area of research.</p> <p>Significant progress has been made in recent decades towards understanding Langlands's conjectural reciprocity between automorphic forms and Galois representations. Techniques for proving reciprocity laws generally require the consideration of p-adic families of Galois representations, or in other words of a "p-adic Langlands correspondence". During the course of this award the PI made major contributions to the study of the p-adic Langlands correspondence.</p> <p>Most notably, the PI (in joint work with Ana Caraiani, Matthew Emerton, and Toby Gee) proved the geometric Breuil-Mezard conjecture for two-dimensional potentially Barsotti-Tate Galois representations.For each p-adic local field we construct a moduli stack of 2-dimensional mod p representations of its Galois group, and prove a geometrization of the weight part of Serre's conjecture and the Breuil-Mezard conjecture. Namely, the irreducible components of the moduli stack are in bijection with Serre weights, and a representation lies on precisely the components corresponding to the Serre weights for that representation. These results are expected to be a key ingredient in future investigations of the p-adic Langlands correspondence for GL(2).</p> <p>During the course of this award the PI made important contributions to the development of human resources. He is supervising five PhD students, has co-organized multiple conferences (including the "Junior Number Theory Days" conference which is now hosted at the PI's institution), and continues to serve on the board of directors for the Canada/USA Mathcamp high school summer program. He is also chair of his department.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/21/2020<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;L&nbsp;Savitt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Number theory is one of the oldest branches of mathematics. At its most fundamental, number theory is the study of whole number solutions to polynomial equations, and especially to equations motivated by geometry. For example, the lengths of the three sides of a right triangle are related by the Pythagorean theorem. While it is straightforward to find all right triangles whose side lengths are rational numbers, it perhaps surprisingly remains an unsolved problem to determine which whole numbers can be the area of a right triangle with rational sides. Number theory has many important practical applications. For instance, most cellular telephone calls are protected by a code based on elliptic curves, one of the primary objects of study in the Langlands program, the principal investigator's area of research.  Significant progress has been made in recent decades towards understanding Langlands's conjectural reciprocity between automorphic forms and Galois representations. Techniques for proving reciprocity laws generally require the consideration of p-adic families of Galois representations, or in other words of a "p-adic Langlands correspondence". During the course of this award the PI made major contributions to the study of the p-adic Langlands correspondence.  Most notably, the PI (in joint work with Ana Caraiani, Matthew Emerton, and Toby Gee) proved the geometric Breuil-Mezard conjecture for two-dimensional potentially Barsotti-Tate Galois representations.For each p-adic local field we construct a moduli stack of 2-dimensional mod p representations of its Galois group, and prove a geometrization of the weight part of Serre's conjecture and the Breuil-Mezard conjecture. Namely, the irreducible components of the moduli stack are in bijection with Serre weights, and a representation lies on precisely the components corresponding to the Serre weights for that representation. These results are expected to be a key ingredient in future investigations of the p-adic Langlands correspondence for GL(2).  During the course of this award the PI made important contributions to the development of human resources. He is supervising five PhD students, has co-organized multiple conferences (including the "Junior Number Theory Days" conference which is now hosted at the PI's institution), and continues to serve on the board of directors for the Canada/USA Mathcamp high school summer program. He is also chair of his department.       Last Modified: 12/21/2020       Submitted by: David L Savitt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
