<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WiFiUS: IoCT-CARE: Internet of Cognitive Things for Personalized Healthcare</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Sprintson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asprints@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922170</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Recent advances in Internet-of-Things (IoT) and cognitive computing promise new modalities for delivering and improving healthcare solutions, both for in-hospital and everyday settings. The ubiquitous computing nature of IoT enables continuous monitoring and management of all healthcare vitals. However, these real-time mission-critical IoT applications demand both a consistent Quality of Experience (QoE), as well as personalization for individual health care contexts. Additionally, there is a need for long-lasting battery-powered wireless sensors, reliable network connectivity, and cloud services. This project aims to solve these challenges via personalization and holistic coupling of the IoT infrastructure and the services provided to end users. The approach utilizes a novel self-aware cognitive architecture that delivers efficient and customized services by learning from end user behavior and adapting the IoT infrastructure to a person's current state, daily life routine, and environment. The project's exemplar application - efficient early detection of life-threatening signs - can potentially save lives through better quality of care, and timely delivery of critical/urgent health indicators. While the project will be validated in the healthcare domain, the project's framework and services are applicable to a broad range of other IoT application domains. The international collaborative nature of this project will enrich the learning experience of students and researchers by exposing them to the challenges of developing IoT services for delivering life-critical services in the healthcare domain.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Quality of Experience (QoE) is a key metric for successful delivery of end-user services for IoT-enabled applications. Achieving consistent end-user QoE poses tremendous challenges in the face of resource constraints and dynamic variations at multiple scales of the IoT system stack: at the application, network, resource, and device levels. Personalization - through holistic coupling of both the IoT infrastructure, as well as end-user services - provides a key opportunity to manage and exploit these variations and deliver customized QoE under resource constraints. This proposal outlines a self-aware Internet of Cognitive Things (IoCT) architecture that leverages edge (i.e., Fog) computing architectures to introduce intelligence and adaptability in integrated multi-scale IoT systems. The objective is to efficiently manage information acquisition, communication and processing across different scales of the IoT systems, while synergistically coupling learning of end-user behaviors to deliver efficient and customized services. The compelling use case of personalized healthcare will be used as an exemplar for a large class of IoT-enabled applications that can exploit and benefit from personalization empowered by a multi-layered, self-aware IoCT architecture.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1702950</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nikil</FirstName>
<LastName>Dutt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nikil D Dutt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dutt@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498247219</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000207740</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marco</FirstName>
<LastName>Levorato</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marco Levorato</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>levorato@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498242175</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000658096</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926970001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3091 Bren Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8229</Code>
<Text>WiFiUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The IoCT (Internet of Cognitive Things) project explored novel approaches for delivering and improving healthcare solutions, both for in-hospital and everyday settings.&nbsp; The IoCT approach uses the Internet of Things (IoT) for continuous monitoring and management of healthcare vitals,&nbsp; enhanced by cognitive mechanisms to personalize and customize the Quality of Experience (QoE) for individual health care contexts, enabling effective decision making and delivery of feedback to individuals by healthcare workers.&nbsp; Additionally, IoT frameworks face challenges in energy efficiency to make&nbsp; battery-powered wireless sensors last longer, and deal with unreliable network connectivity and cloud services. his project addressed these challenges via cognitive solutions to achieve personalization and holistic coupling of the IoT infrastructure and the services provided to end users. The IoCT project was conducted jointly by US (UC Irvine) and Finnish (University of Turku and VTT) partners, under the auspices of the US (NSF) and Finnish (Academy of Finland) WiFiUS program, enabling tight integration of research, education and training activities across both the US and Finnish institutions.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>Quality of Experience (QoE) is a key metric for successful delivery of end-user services for IoT-enabled applications. Achieving consistent end-user QoE poses tremendous challenges in the face of resource constraints and dynamic variations at multiple scales of the IoT system stack: at the application, network, resource, and device levels. This project developed a self-aware cognitive architecture &ndash; the Internet of Cognitive Things (IoCT) &ndash; that delivers acceptable QoE by adapting to dynamic variations in infrastructural compute, communication and resource needs, while also synergistically learning and adapting to end user behavior. The IoCT approach leverages edge (i.e., Fog) computing architectures to introduce intelligence and adaptability in integrated multi-scale IoT systems,&nbsp; and efficiently manages information acquisition, communication and processing across different scales of the IoT systems, while synergistically coupling learning of end-user behaviors to deliver efficient and customized services. The IoCT system architecture was designed to enable a network of algorithms communicate and collaborate synergistically to achieve a system-wide objective for desired QoE. Cognition and edge computing architectures were leveraged to introduce intelligence and adaptability in integrated multi-scale IoT systems, through a Personal Holistic Cognitive Optimization (PHCO) framework. The project leveraged an on-going collaboration with the Turku University Hospital to demonstrate a personalized ubiquitous healthcare framework using the Early Warning Score (EWS) system for human health monitoring.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong><br /><br />This research project investigated Internet-of-Things (IoT) health monitoring systems, by which individuals' health and well-being can be monitored remotely and continuously. These systems collect data from various energy-efficient sensors (e.g., wearables) and thereby facilitate home-based health monitoring. Such services enable health providers to track the users' conditions remotely and to intervene in case of emergencies. Therefore, they can decrease hospital stays and subsequently healthcare costs for both the patients and healthcare systems. Moreover, these services can tackle some of the challenges of basic nursing care, such as heavy workload and hospital staff shortage, providing automated health data collection and analysis. Additionally, the ability to generate an Early Warning Score (EWS) for chronic diseases in everyday home settings (rather than in-hospital settings) can potentially save lives through better quality of care, and timely delivery of critical/urgent health indicators.</p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-c7424509-7fff-2729-208c-c290f8082ddb"><span>Finally, the project has contributed to education and training, as well as broadening of participation across the US (at UC Irvine) and Finland (at University of Turku, and VTT).&nbsp; A female PhD student was mentored at UC Irvine and completed a high-quality dissertation. The female PhD student served as a role model for several underrepresented undergraduate students at UC Irvine, and also participated in multiple workshops that aim to increase interest and participation in STEM fields, particularly in science and engineering. Several other PhD and undergraduate students received research training through the project.&nbsp; The NSF WiFiUS program facilitated extensive interactions between the US and Finnish partners, including student and researcher exchanges,&nbsp; multiple joint publications, keynotes and joint tutorial presentations at leading conferences.&nbsp; These trans-Atlantic activities enabled the students and researchers to gain a broadened perspective of research conducted in different cultural settings, and also exposed them to different models of remote and in-person team communication and collaboration.</span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/01/2020<br>      Modified by: Nikil&nbsp;D&nbsp;Dutt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The IoCT (Internet of Cognitive Things) project explored novel approaches for delivering and improving healthcare solutions, both for in-hospital and everyday settings.  The IoCT approach uses the Internet of Things (IoT) for continuous monitoring and management of healthcare vitals,  enhanced by cognitive mechanisms to personalize and customize the Quality of Experience (QoE) for individual health care contexts, enabling effective decision making and delivery of feedback to individuals by healthcare workers.  Additionally, IoT frameworks face challenges in energy efficiency to make  battery-powered wireless sensors last longer, and deal with unreliable network connectivity and cloud services. his project addressed these challenges via cognitive solutions to achieve personalization and holistic coupling of the IoT infrastructure and the services provided to end users. The IoCT project was conducted jointly by US (UC Irvine) and Finnish (University of Turku and VTT) partners, under the auspices of the US (NSF) and Finnish (Academy of Finland) WiFiUS program, enabling tight integration of research, education and training activities across both the US and Finnish institutions.  Intellectual Merit:  Quality of Experience (QoE) is a key metric for successful delivery of end-user services for IoT-enabled applications. Achieving consistent end-user QoE poses tremendous challenges in the face of resource constraints and dynamic variations at multiple scales of the IoT system stack: at the application, network, resource, and device levels. This project developed a self-aware cognitive architecture &ndash; the Internet of Cognitive Things (IoCT) &ndash; that delivers acceptable QoE by adapting to dynamic variations in infrastructural compute, communication and resource needs, while also synergistically learning and adapting to end user behavior. The IoCT approach leverages edge (i.e., Fog) computing architectures to introduce intelligence and adaptability in integrated multi-scale IoT systems,  and efficiently manages information acquisition, communication and processing across different scales of the IoT systems, while synergistically coupling learning of end-user behaviors to deliver efficient and customized services. The IoCT system architecture was designed to enable a network of algorithms communicate and collaborate synergistically to achieve a system-wide objective for desired QoE. Cognition and edge computing architectures were leveraged to introduce intelligence and adaptability in integrated multi-scale IoT systems, through a Personal Holistic Cognitive Optimization (PHCO) framework. The project leveraged an on-going collaboration with the Turku University Hospital to demonstrate a personalized ubiquitous healthcare framework using the Early Warning Score (EWS) system for human health monitoring.  Broader Impacts:  This research project investigated Internet-of-Things (IoT) health monitoring systems, by which individuals' health and well-being can be monitored remotely and continuously. These systems collect data from various energy-efficient sensors (e.g., wearables) and thereby facilitate home-based health monitoring. Such services enable health providers to track the users' conditions remotely and to intervene in case of emergencies. Therefore, they can decrease hospital stays and subsequently healthcare costs for both the patients and healthcare systems. Moreover, these services can tackle some of the challenges of basic nursing care, such as heavy workload and hospital staff shortage, providing automated health data collection and analysis. Additionally, the ability to generate an Early Warning Score (EWS) for chronic diseases in everyday home settings (rather than in-hospital settings) can potentially save lives through better quality of care, and timely delivery of critical/urgent health indicators.  Finally, the project has contributed to education and training, as well as broadening of participation across the US (at UC Irvine) and Finland (at University of Turku, and VTT).  A female PhD student was mentored at UC Irvine and completed a high-quality dissertation. The female PhD student served as a role model for several underrepresented undergraduate students at UC Irvine, and also participated in multiple workshops that aim to increase interest and participation in STEM fields, particularly in science and engineering. Several other PhD and undergraduate students received research training through the project.  The NSF WiFiUS program facilitated extensive interactions between the US and Finnish partners, including student and researcher exchanges,  multiple joint publications, keynotes and joint tutorial presentations at leading conferences.  These trans-Atlantic activities enabled the students and researchers to gain a broadened perspective of research conducted in different cultural settings, and also exposed them to different models of remote and in-person team communication and collaboration.       Last Modified: 07/01/2020       Submitted by: Nikil D Dutt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
