<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Organizational, Community, and State Regulatory Characteristics Influence on Venting and Flaring Rates of Texas Gas Wells.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11954.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11954</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project examines why some gas wells and operating companies vent and flare at a higher rate than others by testing hypotheses developed using the organizational political economy framework. Specifically, it analyzes how community, business, and state regulatory organizational characteristics at the branch plant (i.e., gas well) and central headquarters (i.e., operating company) level relate to Texas gas well flaring and venting rates in 2012. This project advances basic understandings of the way social organization influences industrial environmental pollution and waste of natural resources. The primary aim of this project is to assist business practitioners, state managers, and communities to better combat climate change, economic waste, and community health hazards by identifying the social structural factors related to venting and flaring practices in the natural gas production industry and making this information publicly available by publishing high-quality, mobile-friendly maps, presentations, and scientific and technical papers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Venting and flaring in the gas production industry are processes by which natural gas is extracted from a well and purposefully burned (i.e., flaring) or released or leaked into the air (i.e., venting), sometimes after first collecting the crude petroleum oil and associated gas extracted along with the natural gas. There is currently no systematic explanation for why some organizations in the natural gas production industry vent and flare natural gas at a higher rate than others. There is an urgent need to identify the social organizational structures associated with pollution and waste, so that organizations and public policies can be reorganized to better achieve environmental sustainability. This project will fill this need by testing several hypotheses developed using the organizational political economy of the environment framework. Hypotheses are tested by quantifying the relationship between Texas gas well venting and flaring rates in 2012, and organizational characteristics at the gas well and operating company level using multilevel statistical modeling.  Statistical analysis will be conducted on a created dataset using Texas Railroad Commission, National Center for Charitable Statistics, United States Energy Information Administration, and United States Census Bureau data. Using the created dataset, this project will examine the characteristics of affected communities surrounding gas wells and develop high-quality, mobile-friendly maps of gas well venting and flaring rates and overlying business, community, and state regulatory organizational characteristics. By producing high quality maps, presentations, and papers, this project will increase public understanding of scientific knowledge regarding the relationship between social organizational structures and venting and flaring rates.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1702683</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Theresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Morris</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Theresa Morris</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>theresa.morris@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798623193</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000387279</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katherine Ann</FirstName>
<LastName>Willyard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katherine Ann Willyard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kate.willyard@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2108448312</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000733799</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020271826</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778434351</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4351 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~11954</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Goals</p> <p>The overall goal of this project is to quantify the relationship between oil and gase extraction facility venting and flaring volumes and organizational, community, and state regulatory characteristics. The resources developed as part of this project will provide information about which types of facilities and operators are responsible for industry venting and flaring practices so that corporate leaders and state managers can develop more effective organizations and public policies by targeting ecologically inefficient facilities and operators for the use of green technologies.</p> <p>Major Activities</p> <p>This project resulted in the completion of a doctoral dissertation, maps of oil and gas venting and flaring volumes, multiple conference presentations and peer reviewed journal publication to show the types of facilities and operators most responsible for venting and flaring.</p> <p>Specific Objectives</p> <p>This project resulted in regression model results quantifying the relationship between oil and gas extraction facility venting and flaring volumes and organizational, community, and state regulatory characteristics.</p> <p>Significant results</p> <p>This project found subsidiary organizations vent and flare more than non subsidiary organizations</p> <p>Training opportunities</p> <p>This project provided data science training for a PhD student and research training for an undergraduate</p> <p>Dissemination</p> <p>Results of this project have been published in peer reviewed journals and discussed on local NPR stations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/01/2020<br>      Modified by: Katherine Ann&nbsp;Willyard</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Goals  The overall goal of this project is to quantify the relationship between oil and gase extraction facility venting and flaring volumes and organizational, community, and state regulatory characteristics. The resources developed as part of this project will provide information about which types of facilities and operators are responsible for industry venting and flaring practices so that corporate leaders and state managers can develop more effective organizations and public policies by targeting ecologically inefficient facilities and operators for the use of green technologies.  Major Activities  This project resulted in the completion of a doctoral dissertation, maps of oil and gas venting and flaring volumes, multiple conference presentations and peer reviewed journal publication to show the types of facilities and operators most responsible for venting and flaring.  Specific Objectives  This project resulted in regression model results quantifying the relationship between oil and gas extraction facility venting and flaring volumes and organizational, community, and state regulatory characteristics.  Significant results  This project found subsidiary organizations vent and flare more than non subsidiary organizations  Training opportunities  This project provided data science training for a PhD student and research training for an undergraduate  Dissemination  Results of this project have been published in peer reviewed journals and discussed on local NPR stations.          Last Modified: 05/01/2020       Submitted by: Katherine Ann Willyard]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
