<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: The Emergence of Disciplinary Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11334.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11334</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Title: The Emergence of Disciplinary Networks&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project uses the emergence of neurology in France to investigate how social networks form around emerging areas of inquiries, ultimately transitioning them from idea to institution. What leads to the alignment of a dense community of relationships among medical researchers with a novel set of ideas, and how might this coupling process differ among relationship types? The case of French neurology is an ideal one with which to answer these questions because the structure of relationships among its practitioners well represents that of other nascent disciplines in 19th century France and emerging fields more generally. The project aims to reconstruct apprenticeship, colleagueship, co-authorship, and communication networks among French medical scientists between 1840 and 1900 and to identify the mechanisms that generated the structure of relationships among those individuals who would become neurologists. Data are collected from archives located in Paris, France, and statistical network and text analyses are used in order to address the research questions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to explain why researchers collectively orient themselves toward institutionalizing particular groundbreaking ideas.  Most current work on social networks in science only examines co-publication or co-citation networks, which leaves one unable to explain disciplinary emergence. The disciplinary network theoretical framework of this research advances sociology of science in a key way.&lt;br/&gt;At the same time, it advances two central areas in social network analysis. Foci serve as critical organizers of networks, and this research illuminates the process through which emerging foci come to affect social networks. Further, while much research in&lt;br/&gt;network science of science investigates the structure of scientific communities, it neglects how ideas, and other attributes of researchers, as well as the multitude of relationships that usually exist between them cohere into the foundations of a new discipline.&lt;br/&gt;The ability to detect social groups from relationship data constitutes one of the most active areas being developed by network scientists, but no models exist that accurately capture how traits of individuals within networks generate community structure. This research will uncover the mechanisms that produce community structure. The results of my projectwill also shed light on the mechanisms that generate relationships among distinct social networks.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1702667</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Omar</FirstName>
<LastName>Lizardo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Omar Lizardo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>olizardo@soc.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3102675438</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000501196</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brandon</FirstName>
<LastName>Sepulvado</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brandon Sepulvado</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sepulvado-brandon@norc.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3016345435</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000707633</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>824910376</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048994727</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName>Notre Dame</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~11334</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project sought at the most general level to understand how new scientific fields emerge, focusing in particular on two questions: what leads to the alignment of a dense community of relationships among researchers with a novel set of ideas and how might this coupling process differ among the types of relationships that researchers can have with one another. It took as a case of study the emergence of French neurology between 1840 and 1900. Data were collected from archival records which were then digitized to extract information on four types of relationship: which medical researchers worked together, which researchers communicated informally with one another, which individuals co-authored publications together, and which researchers mentored which students. Text and social network analyses uncovered that the student-mentor relationships were among the most influential for the emergence of neurology in France and that, for a stable relationship to form between a mentor and student, both individuals had to value each other.</p> <p>In the course of this research, a novel theoretical framework was created in order to understand how social and cultural factors combine to produce new research fields: that of disciplinary networks. The disciplinary networks framework fuses two distinct bodies of social theory by connecting examinations of the invention process with investigations of the professional reorganizations that new ideas can bring forth. Submission of findings to peer-reviewed journals and the data generated from the archival records are forthcoming. Throughout this project, multiple undergraduate students were mentored in research design and computational methods (e.g., text and social network analysis) and a computational social science workshop was held.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Brandon&nbsp;Sepulvado</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project sought at the most general level to understand how new scientific fields emerge, focusing in particular on two questions: what leads to the alignment of a dense community of relationships among researchers with a novel set of ideas and how might this coupling process differ among the types of relationships that researchers can have with one another. It took as a case of study the emergence of French neurology between 1840 and 1900. Data were collected from archival records which were then digitized to extract information on four types of relationship: which medical researchers worked together, which researchers communicated informally with one another, which individuals co-authored publications together, and which researchers mentored which students. Text and social network analyses uncovered that the student-mentor relationships were among the most influential for the emergence of neurology in France and that, for a stable relationship to form between a mentor and student, both individuals had to value each other.  In the course of this research, a novel theoretical framework was created in order to understand how social and cultural factors combine to produce new research fields: that of disciplinary networks. The disciplinary networks framework fuses two distinct bodies of social theory by connecting examinations of the invention process with investigations of the professional reorganizations that new ideas can bring forth. Submission of findings to peer-reviewed journals and the data generated from the archival records are forthcoming. Throughout this project, multiple undergraduate students were mentored in research design and computational methods (e.g., text and social network analysis) and a computational social science workshop was held.          Last Modified: 08/30/2019       Submitted by: Brandon Sepulvado]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
