<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A High Degree-of-Freedom Body-Machine Interface for Children with Severe Motor Impairments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>379925.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>379925</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Grace Hwang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ghwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924271</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Children with severe movement impairments often depend on assistive devices such as wheelchairs, robotic arms, or communication aids for activities of their daily lives. However, learning to control these complex devices can be challenging for children. In this project, the investigators explore the development of a general purpose body-machine interface that allows children to control several devices using movements of the body. A key advantage of this type of interface is that it is non-invasive, easy to wear, and can "grow" with the child. The project will enhance basic understanding of how body movements can be exploited to control external devices, especially in children. The project will have an impact on the independence and quality of life for children with severe movement impairments.  A key challenge of this research is to translate the body movements of the user into commands that can control the robotic arm for performing an intended task.  The traditional approach to this translation problem has been based on principal components analysis (PCA); however, this is not well suited for complex tasks requiring the control of many degrees of freedom.  In this project, the investigators will develop alternative, novel methods that can take full advantage of the movement repertoire of the user and can also yield intuitive control. In addition to the significant impact of this research on the quality of life of individuals with disabilities, the project includes outreach to K12 students and teachers to interest them in STEM and improve their understanding of disabilities and motor development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The current work will be carried out through three aims. These are: 1) utilize a principal component analysis-based approach for control of high degree of freedom movements within the robot; 2) develop a virtual body model approach; and 3) determine learning characteristics of high-degree of freedom body machine interfaces in children. Each aspect of the research will be assessed through rigorous performance metrics. Specifically, the objectives of this project are to: capture a wide range of motion patterns using sensors on the head and upper body; and to map anatomically distinct motion patterns to commands for controlling the robot arm using a virtual model of the user's body. Based on the sensor data from the user, algorithms will be used to calculate how the virtual model bends, twists, and turns; and these deformations will then be translated into commands that control the robotic arm. In addition to developing these methods, the investigators will also evaluate the intuitiveness of these new methods by testing how quickly children can learn to control a robotic arm using these methods.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1703735</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rajiv</FirstName>
<LastName>Ranganathan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rajiv Ranganathan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rrangana@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173555040</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000706520</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Florian</FirstName>
<LastName>Kagerer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Florian A Kagerer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fkagerer@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5174329907</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485807</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mei-Hua</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mei-Hua Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mhlee@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173555040</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000700679</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ranjan</FirstName>
<LastName>Mukherjee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ranjan Mukherjee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mukherji@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173551834</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486665</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488244403</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[428 south shaw lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5342</Code>
<Text>Disability &amp; Rehab Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~379925</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
