<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PostDoctoral Research Fellowship</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vroytbur@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928584</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is made as part of the FY 2017 Mathematical Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships Program. Each of the fellowships supports a research and training project at a host institution in the mathematical sciences, including applications to other disciplines, under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist. The title of the project for this fellowship to Theodore Drivas is "Turbulent Anomalous Dissipation and Spontaneous Stochasticity." The host institution for the fellowship is Princeton University, and the sponsoring scientist is Peter Constantin.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1703997</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Theodore</FirstName>
<LastName>Drivas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Theodore D Drivas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>9148065146</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000728966</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Drivas                  Theodore       D</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212313318</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Johns Hopkins University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>060Y</Code>
<Text>Workforce (MSPRF) MathSciPDFel</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9219</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS IN MATH SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The proposed topic of the grant was two-fold; the study of anomalous dissipation in hydrodynamic models (Onsager's conjecture) and of non-uniqueness of orbits in non-smooth dynamical systems (spontaneous stochasticity).</p> <p>In the first direction, the PI established sharp (as demonstrated by exact shock solutions) criteria for anomalous entropy production in the fully compressible Euler/Navier-Stokes system. The PI then extended the framework used to study Onsager's conjecture in order to allow for weak dependence of the dissipation on Reynolds number and accommodate the effects of physical boundaries.&nbsp; Finally, in an effort to understand drag reduction by polymers, the PI derived a model which incorporated the effect of polymeric interaction at the wall and rigorously showed how it can mollify strong dissipation events.&nbsp;</p> <p>In the second direction, at the intersection of both themes, the PI established novel Lagrangian representation formulae for the dissipation anomaly involving relative tracer particle dispersion forward and backward in time. The PI also introduced a set of singular ODE models in arbitrary dimensions for which non-uniqueness can be studied in-depth and connected to "hidden" chaotic properties of the system.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to this work, the PI collaborated with other researchers at Princeton in a research program on plasma confinement fusion.&nbsp; In this direction, the PI worked towards the understanding flexibility and rigidity properties of equilibrium configurations in ideal hydrodynamic models. Additional work was performed towards understanding stochastic fluid models, Arnold's geometric picture of fluid dynamics, and the dynamics of one-dimensional compressible fluid systems.</p> <p>The work conducted during the tenure of this grant resulted in sixteen publications in top journals. Additionally, the work was disseminated at twenty-four seminars and colloquia talks, and fifteen conference talks. Additional broader impacts included: (1) Designed and taught a graduate course&nbsp; "Introduction to Stochastic Differential Equations with Applications to Fluid Dynamics" for Brazilian summer school short course (Jan. 2019) on the second theme of the proposal, (2) co-organized the "Analysis of Fluids and Related Topics", a weekly seminar series at Princeton University (2017&ndash;2020) and (3) co-organized the special session "Regularity, Singularity and Turbulence in Fluids", SIAM Conference on Analysis of Partial Differential Equations, La Quinta, CA (Dec. 2019).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/12/2021<br>      Modified by: Theodore&nbsp;D&nbsp;Drivas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The proposed topic of the grant was two-fold; the study of anomalous dissipation in hydrodynamic models (Onsager's conjecture) and of non-uniqueness of orbits in non-smooth dynamical systems (spontaneous stochasticity).  In the first direction, the PI established sharp (as demonstrated by exact shock solutions) criteria for anomalous entropy production in the fully compressible Euler/Navier-Stokes system. The PI then extended the framework used to study Onsager's conjecture in order to allow for weak dependence of the dissipation on Reynolds number and accommodate the effects of physical boundaries.  Finally, in an effort to understand drag reduction by polymers, the PI derived a model which incorporated the effect of polymeric interaction at the wall and rigorously showed how it can mollify strong dissipation events.   In the second direction, at the intersection of both themes, the PI established novel Lagrangian representation formulae for the dissipation anomaly involving relative tracer particle dispersion forward and backward in time. The PI also introduced a set of singular ODE models in arbitrary dimensions for which non-uniqueness can be studied in-depth and connected to "hidden" chaotic properties of the system.   In addition to this work, the PI collaborated with other researchers at Princeton in a research program on plasma confinement fusion.  In this direction, the PI worked towards the understanding flexibility and rigidity properties of equilibrium configurations in ideal hydrodynamic models. Additional work was performed towards understanding stochastic fluid models, Arnold's geometric picture of fluid dynamics, and the dynamics of one-dimensional compressible fluid systems.  The work conducted during the tenure of this grant resulted in sixteen publications in top journals. Additionally, the work was disseminated at twenty-four seminars and colloquia talks, and fifteen conference talks. Additional broader impacts included: (1) Designed and taught a graduate course  "Introduction to Stochastic Differential Equations with Applications to Fluid Dynamics" for Brazilian summer school short course (Jan. 2019) on the second theme of the proposal, (2) co-organized the "Analysis of Fluids and Related Topics", a weekly seminar series at Princeton University (2017&ndash;2020) and (3) co-organized the special session "Regularity, Singularity and Turbulence in Fluids", SIAM Conference on Analysis of Partial Differential Equations, La Quinta, CA (Dec. 2019).       Last Modified: 08/12/2021       Submitted by: Theodore D Drivas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
