<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>AF: Medium: Collaborative Research: Sequential and Parallel Algorithms for Approximate Sequence Matching with Applications to Computational Biology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>290000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>346000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mitra Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928649</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Sequence matching problems are central to the field of genomics, both in analyzing naturally occurring sequences such as genomes and in analyzing data from sequencing instruments. Often, methods that can accommodate a small number of differences within the matching regions suffice in practice. Such methods, described as alignment-free or approximate sequence matching methods, have typically relied on heuristics. This project work is advancing the field by creating a mathematical framework and solving multiple approximate sequence matching problems with provably efficient run-time guarantees. Project work is also supporting the development of practical heuristics inspired and supported by the mathematical framework, development of parallel methods for solving large-scale problems on high performance parallel computers, and studying the impact of these methods on important applications. Project results are made available through open source software for use by practitioners. Results from this research will be incorporated into courses taught by the PIs, and disseminated more broadly through book chapters and tutorials and accompanying slides. The project will support research scientist and Ph.D. students in interdisciplinary training for launching them into productive careers focused on important problems of current relevance. Undergraduate participation is planned through course projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project work builds upon recent progress in alignment-free genome comparison methods, and exploits the controlled error characteristics of data generated by high-throughput sequencers, and the many bioinformatics applications enabled by them. Project objectives include developing a robust algorithmic framework for designing newer alignment-free methods based on approximate substring composition, and developing sequential and parallel algorithms for pairwise approximate sequence matching among large sequence data sets. The goal is to develop algorithms that are asymptotically superior to quadratic alignment-based approaches, and achieve good practical performance either directly or through further development of practical heuristic that rely on the underlying theory. The developed techniques will be further investigated in the context of important applications such as read error correction, genome mapping, and assembly. Though conducted in the context of computational biology, some of the methods are potentially applicable to other areas such as text processing and information retrieval. Broader research community will be impacted through release of software modules and project work in important application areas.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1703489</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharma</FirstName>
<LastName>Thankachan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharma Thankachan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sharma.thankachan@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2252506999</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000711084</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees</Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>150805653</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CENTRAL FLORIDA BOARD OF TRUSTEES, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Central Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>089Y</Code>
<Text>FET-Fndtns of Emerging Tech</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7931</Code>
<Text>Computational Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7924</Code>
<Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7931</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~290000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~24000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This Project Outcomes Report for the General Public is displayed verbatim as submitted by the Principal Investigator (PI) for this award. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions, or recommendations expressed in this Report are those of the PI and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation; NSF has not approved or endorsed its content.</span></p> <p><span> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>The goal of this project was to develop algorithms for various approximate string matching problems in Computational Biology. Approaches based on standard heuristics are prevalent in practice; however, our primary focus was to create provably efficient algorithms. To that end, we achieved several new results, as summarized below.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> </span></p> <p><span>We developed a novel and versatile algorithmic framework for solving approximate sequence matching problems that permit a bounded number of mismatches, insertions, and deletions as part of a matching. We obtained novel algorithms for several problems using this unified framework: the k-edit longest/average common substring, read mapping, all-pair maximal k-edit common substrings, and all-pair maximal k-edit suffix/prefix overlaps, 1-mappability, k-mismatch shortest unique substring, etc. We also developed efficient heuristics for alignment-free sequence matching; implementations are available at&nbsp;</span><a rel="noreferrer" href="https://alurulab.cc.gatech.edu/phylo" target="_blank">https://alurulab.cc.gatech.edu/phylo</a>. We studied the median string problem (closely related to the multiple sequence alignment problem) and proved that the existing solutions are almost optimal (via fine-grained complexity techniques). We also studied several aspects of the more complex string-to-graph matching problems and provided improved lower bounds. We obtained hardness (NP-completeness) for problems related to indexed string matching: (i) checking if a given graph is a Wheeler graph (a class of efficiently indexable graphs), and (ii) finding the optimal order of alphabets for minimizing the number of runs in the Burrows-Wheeler Transform (BWT).&nbsp;</p> <div> <div> <div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>The work performed under this project has a broad impact beyond computational biology due to the generality of the developed algorithmic techniques. The results were disseminated via top conferences and journals in computer science such as RECOMB, Super Computing, ESA, TCBB, etc. Several students were supported (including women and minorities) and trained in theoretical and practical aspects of string algorithms and computational biology.</span></p> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/11/2021<br>      Modified by: Sharma&nbsp;Thankachan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Project Outcomes Report for the General Public is displayed verbatim as submitted by the Principal Investigator (PI) for this award. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions, or recommendations expressed in this Report are those of the PI and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation; NSF has not approved or endorsed its content.       The goal of this project was to develop algorithms for various approximate string matching problems in Computational Biology. Approaches based on standard heuristics are prevalent in practice; however, our primary focus was to create provably efficient algorithms. To that end, we achieved several new results, as summarized below.       We developed a novel and versatile algorithmic framework for solving approximate sequence matching problems that permit a bounded number of mismatches, insertions, and deletions as part of a matching. We obtained novel algorithms for several problems using this unified framework: the k-edit longest/average common substring, read mapping, all-pair maximal k-edit common substrings, and all-pair maximal k-edit suffix/prefix overlaps, 1-mappability, k-mismatch shortest unique substring, etc. We also developed efficient heuristics for alignment-free sequence matching; implementations are available at https://alurulab.cc.gatech.edu/phylo. We studied the median string problem (closely related to the multiple sequence alignment problem) and proved that the existing solutions are almost optimal (via fine-grained complexity techniques). We also studied several aspects of the more complex string-to-graph matching problems and provided improved lower bounds. We obtained hardness (NP-completeness) for problems related to indexed string matching: (i) checking if a given graph is a Wheeler graph (a class of efficiently indexable graphs), and (ii) finding the optimal order of alphabets for minimizing the number of runs in the Burrows-Wheeler Transform (BWT).         The work performed under this project has a broad impact beyond computational biology due to the generality of the developed algorithmic techniques. The results were disseminated via top conferences and journals in computer science such as RECOMB, Super Computing, ESA, TCBB, etc. Several students were supported (including women and minorities) and trained in theoretical and practical aspects of string algorithms and computational biology.             Last Modified: 08/11/2021       Submitted by: Sharma Thankachan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
