<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Spectroscopic Study of New, Effective Up-Conversion Charging Process in Persistent Phosphors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>387724.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>387724</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Lane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>plane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922453</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical Description: Afterglow (i.e. persistent luminescence) is a self-sustained luminescence phenomenon whereby a material (i.e. persistent phosphor) glows in the dark for hours after the excitation light source has been switched off. Nowadays persistent phosphors emitting in the visible and near-infrared spectral ranges are being used in daily life, e.g., security signs, emergency route signs, traffic signage, dials and displays, and medical research. However, the widespread use of persistent phosphors is greatly hindered because of the need of high-energy excitation light, mostly ultraviolet light, to charge the materials. Therefore, solutions to achieving effective excitation with low-energy light, particularly the visible light, are in demand. This project investigates a new charging process that enables low-energy visible-light sources (e.g. laser diodes) to be as effective as the commonly used high-energy ultraviolet light sources (e.g. ultraviolet lamps) in charging persistent phosphors. The outcomes of this research have a potential to open new strategies for studying and utilizing persistent phosphors. The project provides an interdisciplinary training experience to graduate, undergraduate and K-12 students in luminescent materials research and applications. The undergraduate and K-12 education is implemented through the existing programs at University of Georgia, such as the NSF-sponsored Peach State-Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation program, NSF-sponsored Research Experiences for Undergraduates sites, and Young Dawgs program (for K-12 education).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description: It is a general knowledge in persistent luminescence that high-energy ultraviolet light is usually necessary in order to effectively charge a persistent phosphor. However, the need of high-energy excitation compromises some applications where the ultraviolet light is unavailable or unsuitable. This project aims to tackle this limitation by investigating a new, two-photon up-conversion charging (UCC) process where low-energy visible-light sources (e.g. laser diodes) are as effective as the commonly used high-energy ultraviolet light sources (e.g. ultraviolet lamps) in charging persistent phosphors. In the UCC concept, two visible photons from a visible-light laser diode are successively absorbed by a UCC enabling ion (e.g. trivalent chromium ion) so that the high-energy delocalization state of the ion is reached and the electron traps in the phosphor are filled. The UCC enabling ions include trivalent chromium, divalent manganese, quadrivalent manganese, trivalent praseodymium, and trivalent neodymium. Several power-tunable visible-light laser diodes with wavelengths in the range of 400-700 nm are used as the excitation sources. New optical measurement techniques for UCC, such as UCC excitation spectroscopy, are under development in order to acquire spectral data that are essential for understanding the energy absorption, electron transfer, electron trapping and de-trapping processes involved in the UCC.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1705707</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Kner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Kner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kner@engr.uga.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7065425939</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526443</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhengwei</FirstName>
<LastName>Pan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhengwei Pan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zhengwei.pan@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7065424657</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000076613</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/19/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Tucker Hall Room 409]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004315578</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 East Campus Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8611</Code>
<Text>Energy Efficiency and End Use</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~137593</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~124231</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~125900</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In the work supported by this proposal, we have extended the emission wavelengths of persistent luminescence research to the ultraviolet (UV) spectral region, including ultraviolet-C (UVC; 200?280 nm) and ultraviolet-B (UVB; 280?315 nm). Based on the unique merits of UVC and UVB radiation, we expect potential applications from the persistent phosphors emitting in these two spectral regions.</p> <p>We have identified highly coordinated silicates as the suitable hosts for Pr<sup>3+</sup> UVC persistent luminescence and synthesized five types, more than ten kinds, of Pr<sup>3+</sup>-activated silicate-based UVC persistent phosphors, including melilite-based aluminosilicates M<sub>2</sub>Al<sub>2</sub>SiO<sub>7</sub> (M = Ca, Sr), e.g., Ca<sub>2</sub>Al<sub>2</sub>SiO<sub>7</sub>:Pr<sup>3+</sup>; alkaline-earth lanthanide cyclosilicates M<sub>3</sub>Y<sub>2</sub>Si<sub>6</sub>O<sub>18</sub> (M = Ca, Sr, or Sr + Ca), e.g., Sr<sub>3</sub>Y<sub>2</sub>Si<sub>6</sub>O<sub>18</sub>:Pr<sup>3+</sup>; lanthanide oxyorthosilicates R<sub>2</sub>Si<sub>x</sub>O<sub>3+2x</sub> (R = Lu, Y; x = 1 or 2), e.g., Lu<sub>2</sub>SiO<sub>5</sub>:Pr<sup>3+</sup>; alkali-earth lanthanide orthosilicates LiRSiO<sub>4</sub> (R = Y, Lu), e.g., LiYSiO<sub>4</sub>:Pr<sup>3+</sup>; and silicate garnets M<sub>3</sub>X<sub>2</sub>Si<sub>3</sub>O<sub>12</sub> (M = Ca, Sr; X = Al, Al + Ga, or Al + Y), e.g., Ca<sub>3</sub>Al<sub>2</sub>Si<sub>3</sub>O<sub>12</sub>:Pr<sup>3+</sup>. These Pr<sup>3+</sup>-activated silicate-based UVC persistent phosphors can be conveniently and effectively charged by a standard 254 nm lamp and emit intense, long-lasting (~10 h) afterglow with emission bands peaking at 265?270 nm.</p> <p>We demonstrated the use of UVC persistent phosphors as glowing tags in bright environments. Benefitting from the zero solar UVC background on the Earth?s surface, the solar-blind UVC afterglow from these Pr<sup>3+</sup>-activated silicates can be clearly monitored and imaged by a corona camera in all ambient lighting conditions including in sunlight and room light. Such a unique spectral feature enables exciting applications of UVC persistent phosphors such as self-sustained, solar-blind glowing tags in bright environments, a capability that is not possible for visible and infrared persistent phosphors.</p> <p>The UVC persistent phosphors also produce efficient photostimulated persistent luminescence ? when they are excited with a low-energy light source (e.g. a white LED, iPhone flashlight, room light, or sunlight), they can stimulate the release of higher energy UVC phosphorescence. This photostimulated persistent luminescence in the UVC rejuvenates the output of the UVC signal without the need for a UV light source.</p> <p>The results on UVC persistent phosphors were published in <em>Nature Communications</em> (Vol. 11, p. 2040, 2020; https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-020-16015-z)</p> <p>UV light in the natural solar spectrum has been known and used for centuries in the treatment of skin disorders such as psoriasis, vitiligo, and atopic eczema. However, the broad high-energy UV emission causes side effects such as accelerated skin aging (age spots and freckles) and intense sunburns. In the 1970s, narrow-band UVB (NB-UVB; 309?313 nm) was found to be the most effective wavelength of light for skin phototherapy especially for psoriasis treatment without producing significant erythema (i.e., skin burns).</p> <p>We have designed and fabricated the first ever Gd<sup>3+</sup>-activated, Pr<sup>3+</sup>-sensitized NB-UVB persistent phosphor Sr<sub>3</sub>Gd<sub>2</sub>Si<sub>6</sub>O<sub>18</sub>:Pr<sup>3+</sup> based on persistent energy transfer from Pr<sup>3+</sup> to Gd<sup>3+</sup> and upon a Pr<sup>3+</sup>-activated UVC persistent phosphor Sr<sub>3</sub>Y<sub>2</sub>Si<sub>6</sub>O<sub>18</sub>:Pr<sup>3+</sup>. Based on other available Pr<sup>3+</sup>- activated UVC persistent phosphors, we have also developed another four Gd<sup>3+</sup>-activated NB-UVB persistent phosphors including Ca<sub>1.8</sub>Gd<sub>0.2</sub>Al<sub>2</sub>SiO<sub>7</sub>:Pr<sup>3+</sup>, Lu<sub>1.8</sub>Gd<sub>0.2</sub>SiO<sub>5</sub>:Pr<sup>3+</sup>, Ca<sub>2.8</sub>Gd<sub>0.2</sub>Al<sub>2</sub>Si<sub>3</sub>O<sub>12</sub>:Pr<sup>3+</sup> and LiY<sub>0.8</sub>Gd<sub>0.2</sub>SiO<sub>4</sub>:Pr<sup>3+</sup>. The strong Gd<sup>3+</sup> NB-UVB emission in the therapeutic region and the absence of Pr<sup>3+</sup> UVC emission in the non-therapeutic, erythemal action region (~280 - 300 nm) from these NB-UVB persistent phosphors suggests that they are good phosphors for dermatological therapy applications. The strategy of designing Gd<sup>3+</sup>-activated NB-UVB persistent phosphor based on Pr<sup>3+</sup>-activated UVC persistent phosphors proposed in this study is expected to lead to the discovery of more NB-UVB persistent phosphors.</p> <p>The results on NB-UVB persistent phosphors were published in <em>Dalton Transactions</em> (Vol. 50, pp. 3499 - 3505, 2021; https://doi.org/10.1039/D1DT00120E).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/05/2021<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;Kner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1705707/1705707_10484074_1625532017179_outcomesfigure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1705707/1705707_10484074_1625532017179_outcomesfigure--rgov-800width.jpg" title="UVC Tagging"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1705707/1705707_10484074_1625532017179_outcomesfigure--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="UVC Tagging"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">UVC radiation images of 50 mm diameter Ca2Al2SiO7:Pr3+ discs placed in various outdoor locations in direct sunlight. (a, c, e, g) Images of discs. (b, d, f, h) UVC luminescence imaged 2 minutes after irradiation by 254nm lamp. UVC is represented by red or yellow.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Zhengwei Pan, Xianli Wang, Yafei Chen, Feng Liu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peter&nbsp;Kner</div> <div class="imageTitle">UVC Tagging</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the work supported by this proposal, we have extended the emission wavelengths of persistent luminescence research to the ultraviolet (UV) spectral region, including ultraviolet-C (UVC; 200?280 nm) and ultraviolet-B (UVB; 280?315 nm). Based on the unique merits of UVC and UVB radiation, we expect potential applications from the persistent phosphors emitting in these two spectral regions.  We have identified highly coordinated silicates as the suitable hosts for Pr3+ UVC persistent luminescence and synthesized five types, more than ten kinds, of Pr3+-activated silicate-based UVC persistent phosphors, including melilite-based aluminosilicates M2Al2SiO7 (M = Ca, Sr), e.g., Ca2Al2SiO7:Pr3+; alkaline-earth lanthanide cyclosilicates M3Y2Si6O18 (M = Ca, Sr, or Sr + Ca), e.g., Sr3Y2Si6O18:Pr3+; lanthanide oxyorthosilicates R2SixO3+2x (R = Lu, Y; x = 1 or 2), e.g., Lu2SiO5:Pr3+; alkali-earth lanthanide orthosilicates LiRSiO4 (R = Y, Lu), e.g., LiYSiO4:Pr3+; and silicate garnets M3X2Si3O12 (M = Ca, Sr; X = Al, Al + Ga, or Al + Y), e.g., Ca3Al2Si3O12:Pr3+. These Pr3+-activated silicate-based UVC persistent phosphors can be conveniently and effectively charged by a standard 254 nm lamp and emit intense, long-lasting (~10 h) afterglow with emission bands peaking at 265?270 nm.  We demonstrated the use of UVC persistent phosphors as glowing tags in bright environments. Benefitting from the zero solar UVC background on the Earth?s surface, the solar-blind UVC afterglow from these Pr3+-activated silicates can be clearly monitored and imaged by a corona camera in all ambient lighting conditions including in sunlight and room light. Such a unique spectral feature enables exciting applications of UVC persistent phosphors such as self-sustained, solar-blind glowing tags in bright environments, a capability that is not possible for visible and infrared persistent phosphors.  The UVC persistent phosphors also produce efficient photostimulated persistent luminescence ? when they are excited with a low-energy light source (e.g. a white LED, iPhone flashlight, room light, or sunlight), they can stimulate the release of higher energy UVC phosphorescence. This photostimulated persistent luminescence in the UVC rejuvenates the output of the UVC signal without the need for a UV light source.  The results on UVC persistent phosphors were published in Nature Communications (Vol. 11, p. 2040, 2020; https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-020-16015-z)  UV light in the natural solar spectrum has been known and used for centuries in the treatment of skin disorders such as psoriasis, vitiligo, and atopic eczema. However, the broad high-energy UV emission causes side effects such as accelerated skin aging (age spots and freckles) and intense sunburns. In the 1970s, narrow-band UVB (NB-UVB; 309?313 nm) was found to be the most effective wavelength of light for skin phototherapy especially for psoriasis treatment without producing significant erythema (i.e., skin burns).  We have designed and fabricated the first ever Gd3+-activated, Pr3+-sensitized NB-UVB persistent phosphor Sr3Gd2Si6O18:Pr3+ based on persistent energy transfer from Pr3+ to Gd3+ and upon a Pr3+-activated UVC persistent phosphor Sr3Y2Si6O18:Pr3+. Based on other available Pr3+- activated UVC persistent phosphors, we have also developed another four Gd3+-activated NB-UVB persistent phosphors including Ca1.8Gd0.2Al2SiO7:Pr3+, Lu1.8Gd0.2SiO5:Pr3+, Ca2.8Gd0.2Al2Si3O12:Pr3+ and LiY0.8Gd0.2SiO4:Pr3+. The strong Gd3+ NB-UVB emission in the therapeutic region and the absence of Pr3+ UVC emission in the non-therapeutic, erythemal action region (~280 - 300 nm) from these NB-UVB persistent phosphors suggests that they are good phosphors for dermatological therapy applications. The strategy of designing Gd3+-activated NB-UVB persistent phosphor based on Pr3+-activated UVC persistent phosphors proposed in this study is expected to lead to the discovery of more NB-UVB persistent phosphors.  The results on NB-UVB persistent phosphors were published in Dalton Transactions (Vol. 50, pp. 3499 - 3505, 2021; https://doi.org/10.1039/D1DT00120E).          Last Modified: 07/05/2021       Submitted by: Peter Kner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
