<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Nanostructure Synthesis at the Liquid-Substrate Interface: A New Strategy for Obtaining Plasmonic and Chemically Active Surfaces</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>329325.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>329325</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Catherine Oertel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;The key enablers for transformative nanotechnologies are breakthroughs in both the synthesis of nanomaterials and an understanding of the chemistry and physics which guides their formation. Applications typically require that the nanomaterials be suspended in liquids or immobilized on planar substrates such as glass or silicon. While substrate-based nanostructure synthesis techniques have undeniably given rise to an impressive list of technologically relevant nanomaterials, the scope and scale of this success is dwarfed by the many accomplishments of liquid-based syntheses. With financial support from both the Solid State and Materials Chemistry program and the Electronic and Photonic Materials program in the Division of Materials Research, the research project aims to remedy this disparity through a new synthetic strategy reliant on forming nanostructures on substrates while immersed in a liquid medium. If proven successful, the approach will allow the solution-based chemistry which has proved so successful to be practiced directly on substrates and, in doing so, establish the science needed to support applications in sensing, photovoltaics and catalysis. Research activities are being integrated with undergraduate education through the supervision of summer undergraduate research internships. Outreach initiatives are being directed toward the matriculation of women into the Engineering profession.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;This research project seeks to determine whether synthetic protocols reliant on seed-mediated colloidal chemistry are adaptable to a substrate-based platform reliant on substrate-immobilized templates. The overriding goal is to define the chemical controls and mechanistic framework needed to form organized surfaces of noble metal nanostructures and then establish their technological relevance by demonstrating the functionalities of the plasmonic and chemically active surfaces formed. Three thrust areas advancing additive, subtractive and multistage template-assisted growth modes, which are reliant on heterogeneous nucleation and/or galvanic replacement processes, are being used to isolate the exact roles played by the substrate, reaction kinetics, pH, template material and template surface modifications in determining the reaction product. Being targeted are synthetic protocols able to define periodic arrays of: (i) core-shell structures with advanced functionalities derived from the integration of materials with dissimilar physical and chemical properties into a single nanostructure architecture, (ii) caged nanostructures offering intense plasmonic near-fields and tunable spacings between the nanostructure and its cage and (iii) substrate-based nanoframes written into patterns with predetermined layouts. These synthetic trials, combined with simulations and the use of characterization techniques which are unique to the substrate-based platform, are providing the means to form intricate nanostructures whose shape and composition are engineered to realize a desired response.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/07/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1707593</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Svetlana</FirstName>
<LastName>Neretina</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Svetlana Neretina</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sneretina@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746316127</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000539836</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/07/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>824910376</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048994727</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1762</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~329325</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><em>Intellectual Merit:</em> </strong>The DMR-1707593 Award aimed to define the chemical controls and mechanistic framework needed to obtain ordered arrays of noble metal nanostructures with plasmonic and catalytically active surfaces. The project not only succeeded in its goal, but also spawned a successful side-project that provided a fundamental understanding of an important model reaction for heterogeneous catalysis. The award has resulted in 12 publications,<sup> </sup>with a total of 4 undergraduate coauthors, 2 completed Ph.D. degrees, and 4 summer research internships. The PI and 3 of her group members have collectively attended 6 American Chemical Society (ACS) and Materials Research Society (MRS) meetings where 8 oral presentations have been given, including 4 invited talks by the PI. Research has been published in high impact journals (<em>ACS Nano,</em> IF 13.7; <em>Nano Lett., </em>IF 12.1; <em>ACS Catalysis,</em> IF 11.38; <em>Small</em>, IF 9.6), where the PI has received further recognition for her work in the form of an invited Account (<em>Acc. Chem. Res., </em>IF 20.9) and an invited Topical Review (<em>Nanotechnology</em>, IF 3.4). Specific research accomplishments include: (i) the first galvanic replacement reactions carried out on substrate-based core-shell structures, a synthetic strategy yielding an entire class of new nanostructures consisting of a plasmonic core separated from a nanocage by a well-defined and adjustable nanogap, (ii) the first synthetic protocol yielding periodic arrays of core-shell nanocubes that are epitaxially aligned with the substrate surface, a robust two-reagent water-based synthesis that is currently the simplest growth mode capable of generating nanocubes, (iii) resolving a longstanding controversy regarding the origin of the induction period in the catalytic reduction of 4-NP, and (iv) the demonstration of a spectroscopically monitored split test that allows for a simple, inexpensive, and unambiguous determination of whether leached species are the true catalyst.</p> <p><strong><em>Broader Impacts:</em></strong> The nanofabrication scheme devised by the PI is arguably the most successful route for defining periodic arrays of complex metal nanostructures. It could, hence, assume an important place in enabling on-chip plasmonic devices. By adapting synthetic protocols from colloid chemistry to the substrate platform, the work also opened a new window through which complex reactions occurring in liquid media can be examined and from which an understanding of growth modes, structure-property relationships, and physicochemical properties can be obtained. Examples include: (i) work that challenges the well-accepted role that citrate plays as a capping agent, and (ii) studies that show potential pitfalls in the benchmarking of catalysts using the reduction of 4-NP. The PI has also had an impact as a (i) 2017 MRS Spring Meeting symposium organizer (ii) guest editor for a special issue of Particle &amp; Particle Systems Characterization, (iii) Scientific Advisor for the 2018 AEMC congress, and (iv) session chair at MRS, E-MRS, and ACS meetings. Highlights in terms of student training and outreach include: (i) 4 undergraduate research internships, (ii) community engagement through the <em>Science Alive</em> event and Penn High School's <em>Technology Student Association</em>, (iii) a 2<sup>nd</sup> place award by former graduate student Maryam Hajfathalian at a SWE-sponsored research competition, and (iv) the mentorship and judging of high school science fair projects. The PI is especially proud of her mentorship of Nathanial and William Watkins, who for three consecutive years carried out science fair projects in her laboratory, garnering 23 awards at local, regional, and state competitions. It has been truly gratifying to see these two extraordinary individuals enter the prestigious Vagelos Scholars Program in Molecular Life Science at the University of Pennsylvania.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/06/2019<br>      Modified by: Svetlana&nbsp;Neretina</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: The DMR-1707593 Award aimed to define the chemical controls and mechanistic framework needed to obtain ordered arrays of noble metal nanostructures with plasmonic and catalytically active surfaces. The project not only succeeded in its goal, but also spawned a successful side-project that provided a fundamental understanding of an important model reaction for heterogeneous catalysis. The award has resulted in 12 publications, with a total of 4 undergraduate coauthors, 2 completed Ph.D. degrees, and 4 summer research internships. The PI and 3 of her group members have collectively attended 6 American Chemical Society (ACS) and Materials Research Society (MRS) meetings where 8 oral presentations have been given, including 4 invited talks by the PI. Research has been published in high impact journals (ACS Nano, IF 13.7; Nano Lett., IF 12.1; ACS Catalysis, IF 11.38; Small, IF 9.6), where the PI has received further recognition for her work in the form of an invited Account (Acc. Chem. Res., IF 20.9) and an invited Topical Review (Nanotechnology, IF 3.4). Specific research accomplishments include: (i) the first galvanic replacement reactions carried out on substrate-based core-shell structures, a synthetic strategy yielding an entire class of new nanostructures consisting of a plasmonic core separated from a nanocage by a well-defined and adjustable nanogap, (ii) the first synthetic protocol yielding periodic arrays of core-shell nanocubes that are epitaxially aligned with the substrate surface, a robust two-reagent water-based synthesis that is currently the simplest growth mode capable of generating nanocubes, (iii) resolving a longstanding controversy regarding the origin of the induction period in the catalytic reduction of 4-NP, and (iv) the demonstration of a spectroscopically monitored split test that allows for a simple, inexpensive, and unambiguous determination of whether leached species are the true catalyst.  Broader Impacts: The nanofabrication scheme devised by the PI is arguably the most successful route for defining periodic arrays of complex metal nanostructures. It could, hence, assume an important place in enabling on-chip plasmonic devices. By adapting synthetic protocols from colloid chemistry to the substrate platform, the work also opened a new window through which complex reactions occurring in liquid media can be examined and from which an understanding of growth modes, structure-property relationships, and physicochemical properties can be obtained. Examples include: (i) work that challenges the well-accepted role that citrate plays as a capping agent, and (ii) studies that show potential pitfalls in the benchmarking of catalysts using the reduction of 4-NP. The PI has also had an impact as a (i) 2017 MRS Spring Meeting symposium organizer (ii) guest editor for a special issue of Particle &amp; Particle Systems Characterization, (iii) Scientific Advisor for the 2018 AEMC congress, and (iv) session chair at MRS, E-MRS, and ACS meetings. Highlights in terms of student training and outreach include: (i) 4 undergraduate research internships, (ii) community engagement through the Science Alive event and Penn High School's Technology Student Association, (iii) a 2nd place award by former graduate student Maryam Hajfathalian at a SWE-sponsored research competition, and (iv) the mentorship and judging of high school science fair projects. The PI is especially proud of her mentorship of Nathanial and William Watkins, who for three consecutive years carried out science fair projects in her laboratory, garnering 23 awards at local, regional, and state competitions. It has been truly gratifying to see these two extraordinary individuals enter the prestigious Vagelos Scholars Program in Molecular Life Science at the University of Pennsylvania.          Last Modified: 09/06/2019       Submitted by: Svetlana Neretina]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
