<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: LSC Center for Coatings Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>107738.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>107738</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mark Coles</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mcoles@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924432</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The LIGO Scientific Collaboration (LSC) Center for Coatings Research (CCR), funded by the NSF and with planned co-funding by the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation, seeks to extend the reach of the next generation of gravitational wave detectors by addressing the dominant noise source limiting their performance, thermal noise in the interferometer mirrors. This noise reduces the number of observable gravitational wave signals from astronomical sources. It arises from thermal excitation of the vibrational modes of the mirrors in the LIGO detector optics. The effect of these excitations is reduced as the mechanical quality factor (Q) of the mirrors is increased. Since the Q of the mirrors is limited by the reflective coatings deposited on their surfaces, lower noise requires development of better coatings. The CCR combines groups from 10 institutions in the US working on computational modeling of amorphous materials, deposition of coatings, and characterization of their atomic structure and macroscopic properties. These components are often performed by three diverse communities that work in relative isolation from each other. The strength of the CCR and its promise of accelerating discoveries arises from close integration of these three communities focused on a unified research goal. Coating thermal noise is also a limiting factor in the fields of precision timing, quantum information, low noise interferometry, and precision measurements like the search for deviations in the gravitational inverse-square law. Coatings improving on the state of the art in mechanical and optical properties developed under this program would be applicable to these communities as well. On broader impacts in education, the mixture of undergraduate institutions with elite graduate programs provides research opportunities at all education levels and establishes clear avenues of advancement for students who wish to pursue a career within the physical sciences. In addition, the CCR has a strong commitment to the advancement of women and underrepresented minorities; and will also continue its participants' activities in issues of education and public outreach through all major channels of public and social media.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The A+ LIGO detector, planned for 2021, will reduce quantum noise with squeezed light injection, leaving thermal noise dominant in the mid-band of the detector.  Reducing this noise source requires reducing the mechanical dissipation in the mirror coatings on the test masses. The goal of this project is to develop mirror coatings consistent with A+ LIGO's mechanical and optical requirements. Meeting this goal requires solution of a longstanding problem in the physics of amorphous materials: the nature and control of the low-energy excitations in amorphous oxides. On a longer time scale, developing mirror coatings for the cryogenic LIGO Voyager detector broadens the possibilities to include amorphous or crystalline semiconductors. The primary research focus is to find conditions under which amorphous metal-oxide coatings can be deposited as "ultrastable glasses", which have a low density of the structural motifs that form two-level systems, the source of elastic dissipation. A second research track seeks methods to stabilize coatings against crystallization during high temperature annealing, another method known to reduce room temperature elastic losses. For the longer term research towards LIGO Voyager applications, the group will investigate non-oxide coatings such as single-crystal semiconductors AlGaAs and AlGaP, which have shown low mechanical loss for small geometries but whose scale up to the size of LIGO optics is challenging; and also amorphous silicon and silicon nitride, which have attractive mechanical properties but whose optical properties must be improved.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1707863</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Penn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven D Penn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>penn@hws.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3153830069</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000143718</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hobart and William Smith Colleges</Name>
<CityName>Geneva</CityName>
<ZipCode>144563397</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3157813754</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>337 Pulteney Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079680203</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HOBART AND WILLIAM SMITH COLLEGES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079680203</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hobart and William Smith Colleges]]></Name>
<CityName>Geneva</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>144563397</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 Pulteney Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~107738</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Gravitational wave astronomy has opened up an exciting new window on our universe with its ability to "see" the extremely energetic, and previously unseen, inspiral and coalescence of compact objects, like black holes and neutron stars.&nbsp; As the catalogue of these events grows, we will continue to gain more insight in to the formation and evolution of our universe.&nbsp; But the primary limit to the development of this field is the sensitivity of the detectors.</p> <p>The LIGO Scientific Collaboration's Center for Coating Research (CCR) was founded in order to understand and minimize mirror coating thermal noise, which, along with quantum noise, limits the interferometer in its most sensitive frequency band of 40-4000 Hz. &nbsp;</p> <p>Binary compact objects, such as black holes and neutron stars, strongly curve spacetime.&nbsp; As they orbit each other, the oscillations in spacetime curvature --gravitational waves -- &nbsp;radiate out and carry away the system's energy.&nbsp; As a result, the orbit decays, causing the pair to draw closer, increase their velocity, and radiate more strongly. This vicious cycle of inspiral and ultimately coalesce is the canonical event observed in gravitational wave detectors.&nbsp; These interferometers observe the oscillations in spacetime curvature by measuring the relative stretching and contraction in orthogonal directions.&nbsp; The detectors send laser light along the X and Y arms of the interferometer.&nbsp; The relative arm length is determined by the change in phase of the two beams as they return to the origin.&nbsp; For LIGO, the interferometer arms are 4 km long and the relative length sensitivity is 10<sup>-19</sup>&nbsp; m. &nbsp; For a sense of scale, note that the laser wavelength is&nbsp;10<sup>-6</sup>&nbsp;m, the size of an atom is 10<sup>-10</sup>&nbsp; m, and the size of a proton is 10<sup>-15</sup>&nbsp; m. Therefore, the interaction of the light with the atoms of the mirror coatings as it reflects from that surface are critical to the sensitivity of these measurements.&nbsp; At 300 K, these mirror coating atoms have a great deal of thermal energy and the amplitude of their motion is approximately 1 million times larger than the length sensitivity required for gravitational wave detection.&nbsp; The motion of the mirror surface resulting from this thermal energy is known as coating thermal noise.</p> <p>The strategy for minimizing coating thermal noise is to design the mirrors such that the resonant frequencies are outside of the desired detection band.&nbsp; In addition, the mirror materials must be of very high quality such that the resonant motion is narrowly concentrated around the resonant frequencies and does not spread into the detection band.&nbsp; Thus our goal is to design mirror coatings with very high mechanical <span>Q</span>, or alternatively with very low elastic loss.</p> <p>During this most recent round of research funding, the PI and collaborators produced the best mirror coating yet measured for gravitational wave detectors.&nbsp; These coatings are thermo-optically optimized, crystalline, GaAs/AlGaAs coatings.&nbsp; The coating thermal noise was so low that it was difficult to measure, but the results are 5 --10 times lower than the noise in the current coatings being used for Advanced LIGO.&nbsp; In addition the optical quality of the high-reflectivity mirror coating is excellent.&nbsp; Overall, the characteristics for this coating meet or exceed the specification for any upgrades to LIGO currently being considered.&nbsp; However, currently these coatings cannot yet be made at sizes large enough to cover the LIGO mirrors.&nbsp; One could say that we have met or exceeded the scientific goals of this project.&nbsp; Now we must solve the engineering challenges required to boost production of these coatings from the current 20-cm sizes to 30-cm and ultimately 45-cm.</p> <p>Our experience with crystalline coatings is less extensive than is our experience with amorphous coatings, and there remain some open research questions about crystalline coatings that we will continue to explore.&nbsp; But at this juncture, crystalline GaAs/AlGaAs coatings appear to be the most significant advance in low thermal noise mirror coatings in the past 20 years.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/03/2021<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;D&nbsp;Penn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Gravitational wave astronomy has opened up an exciting new window on our universe with its ability to "see" the extremely energetic, and previously unseen, inspiral and coalescence of compact objects, like black holes and neutron stars.  As the catalogue of these events grows, we will continue to gain more insight in to the formation and evolution of our universe.  But the primary limit to the development of this field is the sensitivity of the detectors.  The LIGO Scientific Collaboration's Center for Coating Research (CCR) was founded in order to understand and minimize mirror coating thermal noise, which, along with quantum noise, limits the interferometer in its most sensitive frequency band of 40-4000 Hz.    Binary compact objects, such as black holes and neutron stars, strongly curve spacetime.  As they orbit each other, the oscillations in spacetime curvature --gravitational waves --  radiate out and carry away the system's energy.  As a result, the orbit decays, causing the pair to draw closer, increase their velocity, and radiate more strongly. This vicious cycle of inspiral and ultimately coalesce is the canonical event observed in gravitational wave detectors.  These interferometers observe the oscillations in spacetime curvature by measuring the relative stretching and contraction in orthogonal directions.  The detectors send laser light along the X and Y arms of the interferometer.  The relative arm length is determined by the change in phase of the two beams as they return to the origin.  For LIGO, the interferometer arms are 4 km long and the relative length sensitivity is 10-19  m.   For a sense of scale, note that the laser wavelength is 10-6 m, the size of an atom is 10-10  m, and the size of a proton is 10-15  m. Therefore, the interaction of the light with the atoms of the mirror coatings as it reflects from that surface are critical to the sensitivity of these measurements.  At 300 K, these mirror coating atoms have a great deal of thermal energy and the amplitude of their motion is approximately 1 million times larger than the length sensitivity required for gravitational wave detection.  The motion of the mirror surface resulting from this thermal energy is known as coating thermal noise.  The strategy for minimizing coating thermal noise is to design the mirrors such that the resonant frequencies are outside of the desired detection band.  In addition, the mirror materials must be of very high quality such that the resonant motion is narrowly concentrated around the resonant frequencies and does not spread into the detection band.  Thus our goal is to design mirror coatings with very high mechanical Q, or alternatively with very low elastic loss.  During this most recent round of research funding, the PI and collaborators produced the best mirror coating yet measured for gravitational wave detectors.  These coatings are thermo-optically optimized, crystalline, GaAs/AlGaAs coatings.  The coating thermal noise was so low that it was difficult to measure, but the results are 5 --10 times lower than the noise in the current coatings being used for Advanced LIGO.  In addition the optical quality of the high-reflectivity mirror coating is excellent.  Overall, the characteristics for this coating meet or exceed the specification for any upgrades to LIGO currently being considered.  However, currently these coatings cannot yet be made at sizes large enough to cover the LIGO mirrors.  One could say that we have met or exceeded the scientific goals of this project.  Now we must solve the engineering challenges required to boost production of these coatings from the current 20-cm sizes to 30-cm and ultimately 45-cm.  Our experience with crystalline coatings is less extensive than is our experience with amorphous coatings, and there remain some open research questions about crystalline coatings that we will continue to explore.  But at this juncture, crystalline GaAs/AlGaAs coatings appear to be the most significant advance in low thermal noise mirror coatings in the past 20 years.          Last Modified: 06/03/2021       Submitted by: Steven D Penn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
