<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Isotope labeling for quantitative determination of defect sink strength and fundamentals studies on defect-sink interactions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>385003.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>385003</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Judith Yang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>juyang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927086</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical  Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nuclear power is one solution to meet the ever-increasing demand for energy. One key issue in the so called "nuclear renaissance" is materials development towards longer life time under harsh environments. In order to withstand neutron damage at high temperatures, various nanostructured materials have been developed by introducing defect sinks to absorb/remove defects. However, quantitative determination of defect sink strength is still a technological bottleneck.  This project uses an isotope labeling technique to quantitatively measure the sink strength in ion irradiated stainless steels as a key approach for a full scope investigation on defect-sink interactions.  Such capability is critical to develop radiation tolerant materials. Even for the same type of defect sinks, fine tuning of their microstructures to maximize sink strength requires knowledge of one-to-one correlation between structures and sink strength.  The study  will contribute to the general understanding of defects in metals.  The project offers students unique opportunities to combine training and research in nuclear engineering, nanomaterials, atomic scale characterization and atomic scale modeling, for solving issues of real-world importance.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For Fe based stainless steels of nature Fe abundance, implantation of 57Fe isotope atoms will introduce 57Fe interstitials. Upon annealing, the amount of 57Fe enrichments at defect sinks directly reflects the sink strength for defect trapping. Hence the defect sink strength under different irradiation/annealing/stress conditions can be systematically studied. Three-dimensional atom probe tomography (APT) will be used to map 57Fe isotope distributions. APT is coupled with transmission electron microscopy (TEM) and 3-D TEM tomography to establish one-to-one correlation between defect sink structure and sink strength.  The project will study two defect sink types: (1) grain boundaries in grain-engineered stainless steels in order to understand effects of boundary misorientation angles on sink strength and (2) oxide particles in oxide-dispersion-strengthened alloys (ODS) in order to understand the effects of oxide-matrix interfaces on sink strength. The project further integrates molecular dynamics simulations to shed light onto fundamentals. The defect sink strength will be used as inputs in kinetic Monte Carlo simulations for obtaining structural evolutions which can be linked to and compared with experimental observations. In conjunction with materials synthesis, modeling, and atomic scale characterization, the project will obtain the fundamental understanding needed to maximize radiation tolerance of reactor core components. The project offers students unique opportunities to combine training and research in nuclear engineering, nanomaterials, atomic scale characterization and atomic scale modeling, for solving issues of real-world importance.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1708788</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lin</FirstName>
<LastName>Shao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lin Shao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lshao@ne.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798454107</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491873</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>847205572</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433133</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[205E AIEN, Department of Nuclear]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8608</Code>
<Text>Nuclear Energy</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~385003</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project used ion irradiation to simulate neutron damage in reactors and used atomic-scale characterization to understand responses of materials having various microstructures that were intentionally introduced. Such understating is critical to predict and slow down materials failures such as swelling, cracking, and embrittlement in reactors. The understanding is essential to guide materials developments, towards longer lifetime and better accident tolerance. The project led to one material design, which will impact the fusion reactor application by using vertically-grained W to reduce gas retention on the first wall of a fusion reactor. Such grain structures significantly reduce blistering and cracking of W wall under plasma and neutron bombardment. The project led to the development of first-passage kinetic Monte Carlo simulations, which impacted multiscale modeling in radiation materials science. The project obtained fundamental understandings of various defect clustering and defect-boundary interactions in various metals and alloys. One such alloy system was oxide-dispersion-strengthened alloys that were designed for high-temperature applications. The project advanced the understanding of the effects of dispersion morphology on structural evolution. Another important system studied was grain-engineered alloys. The project advanced the knowledge about grain boundaries, high angle vs. low angle, for defect trapping, and removal. The project advanced the understanding of the effects of coating interface on defect developments. The coating concept has been proposed to improve accident tolerance of fuel cladding to avoid the hydrogen explosion encountered in the Fukushima Daiichi nuclear disaster. The project gained an understanding of the complexity of the coating interface in structural integrity under irradiation. The project has led to two invited presentations in international conferences (International conference of ion beam irradiation of materials, IBMM 2018, San Antonio, TX, and International conference of radiation effects in matters, REM10, Galveston, TX). The project has led to two PhDs and one MS. The project had led to eight journal publications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/03/2020<br>      Modified by: Lin&nbsp;Shao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project used ion irradiation to simulate neutron damage in reactors and used atomic-scale characterization to understand responses of materials having various microstructures that were intentionally introduced. Such understating is critical to predict and slow down materials failures such as swelling, cracking, and embrittlement in reactors. The understanding is essential to guide materials developments, towards longer lifetime and better accident tolerance. The project led to one material design, which will impact the fusion reactor application by using vertically-grained W to reduce gas retention on the first wall of a fusion reactor. Such grain structures significantly reduce blistering and cracking of W wall under plasma and neutron bombardment. The project led to the development of first-passage kinetic Monte Carlo simulations, which impacted multiscale modeling in radiation materials science. The project obtained fundamental understandings of various defect clustering and defect-boundary interactions in various metals and alloys. One such alloy system was oxide-dispersion-strengthened alloys that were designed for high-temperature applications. The project advanced the understanding of the effects of dispersion morphology on structural evolution. Another important system studied was grain-engineered alloys. The project advanced the knowledge about grain boundaries, high angle vs. low angle, for defect trapping, and removal. The project advanced the understanding of the effects of coating interface on defect developments. The coating concept has been proposed to improve accident tolerance of fuel cladding to avoid the hydrogen explosion encountered in the Fukushima Daiichi nuclear disaster. The project gained an understanding of the complexity of the coating interface in structural integrity under irradiation. The project has led to two invited presentations in international conferences (International conference of ion beam irradiation of materials, IBMM 2018, San Antonio, TX, and International conference of radiation effects in matters, REM10, Galveston, TX). The project has led to two PhDs and one MS. The project had led to eight journal publications.          Last Modified: 08/03/2020       Submitted by: Lin Shao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
