<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development of unimolecular antibacterial nanomaterials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>390000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steve Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sjsmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928158</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical:&lt;br/&gt;This award by the Division of Materials Research to University of South Florida is to develop novel antibacterial nanomaterials. Due to the emerging resistance in the treatment of microbial diseases, development of new antimicrobial materials is of vital importance. Low-cost polymer-based  materials are attractive. However, antimicrobial activity of currently available polymers is at best moderate. This project is to design a new class of unimolecular antibacterial nanomaterials with improved broad-spectrum activity. Through novel design, synthesis and mechanistic studies, more potent antimicrobial agents are expected with the proposed studies. These novel materials can be used for a variety of antimicrobial applications under different conditions. This project is highly interdisciplinary, and embraces cutting-edge chemistry, microbiology, and biomaterials. Both graduate and undergraduate students working in this research are expected to gain diverse expertise and experience. The successful outcome of this project is expected to advance the national interest because it will promote the scientific progress, advance the health and welfare of the U.S. citizens, and potentially improve the national biodefense.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical:&lt;br/&gt;Due to the emerging antibiotic resistance among patients with different diseases, development of novel, potent and broad-spectrum, and low-cost antimicrobial biomaterials with less probability to develop drug-resistance is critical. To this end, this award will design dendrimer-based cationic nanomaterials with diverse functional groups, and controlled charge densities and distributions. The aims of this project are: 1) design and synthesis of nano-micelles with diverse functional groups, and controlled charge densities and distributions; 2) evaluation of the antibacterial activity and selectivity of the nanomaterials being developed against a panel of significant Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria; and 3) investigation of the mechanism for antimicrobial activity of these novel materials being developed with a focus on bacterial membrane disruption and bactericidal properties of the novel nano-micelles being studied. The project is highly interdisciplinary and embraces cutting-edge synthetic chemistry, microbiology, biomaterials, biophysics, and biochemistry. Both graduate and undergraduate students, with diverse scientific interests and backgrounds, will gain excellent learning experience with the studies carried out with this award.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1708500</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jianfeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Cai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jianfeng Cai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jianfengcai@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8139749506</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000570101</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Florida</Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<ZipCode>336172008</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4019 E. Fowler Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 100]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069687242</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069687242</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>336209951</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4202 E. Fowler Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1711</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS EDUCATION AND RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~260000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> <span>The resistance of bacterial infections is currently a big concern. Therefore there is an urgent need to develop antimicrobial biomaterials.&nbsp;</span>In this grant period, we aim to 1) Design and synthesize unimolecular nanomicelles with diverse functional groups, controlled charge densities and distributions. (2) Test the antibacterial activity and selectivity of unimolecular nanomicelles against a panel of significant Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria. Those that are active against both Gram-positive (MIC &le; 1 &micro;g/mL) and Gram-negative (MIC &le; 5 &micro;g/mL) bacteria will be used in objective 3 for the assessment of their ability to disrupt bacteria membranes. (3) Investigate if bacterial membrane disruption is the general bactericidal mechanism of unimolecular nanomicelles.&nbsp;&nbsp;The result of this project will guide the development of potent and broad-spectrum antimicrobial unimolecular nanomicelles as the new generation of antibiotic materials in the long term. Such antimicrobial biomaterials mimic the mechanisms of action of HDPs but with significantly easier synthesis and lower production cost, higher potency, and enhanced selectivity.&nbsp; Meanwhile, these unimolecular nanomicelles will provide excellent tools to gain insight into the mechanisms of action of HDPs, which are still controversial and elusive. Furthermore,&nbsp; the knowledge obtained from this project will also inspire the design and development of other classes of antimicrobial polymer biomaterials, which allows the generation of novel antibiotic agents.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact:</strong> <span>The project led to 10 publications which have been published and available to public. The data has also been presented in conferences. The project provided great training opportunity for graduate and undergraduate students to acquire interdisciplinary training in organic synthesis, chemical biology and microbiology. This project also integrated teaching, research and outreach activities to broaden exposure to science and research for the local youth population in the Tampa community, as the PI gave lectures to K12 students and also accepted high school students to do research in his lab.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <div><span style="font-family: Verdana; font-size: 11.2px;"><br /></span></div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/10/2021<br>      Modified by: Jianfeng&nbsp;Cai</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: The resistance of bacterial infections is currently a big concern. Therefore there is an urgent need to develop antimicrobial biomaterials. In this grant period, we aim to 1) Design and synthesize unimolecular nanomicelles with diverse functional groups, controlled charge densities and distributions. (2) Test the antibacterial activity and selectivity of unimolecular nanomicelles against a panel of significant Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria. Those that are active against both Gram-positive (MIC &le; 1 &micro;g/mL) and Gram-negative (MIC &le; 5 &micro;g/mL) bacteria will be used in objective 3 for the assessment of their ability to disrupt bacteria membranes. (3) Investigate if bacterial membrane disruption is the general bactericidal mechanism of unimolecular nanomicelles.  The result of this project will guide the development of potent and broad-spectrum antimicrobial unimolecular nanomicelles as the new generation of antibiotic materials in the long term. Such antimicrobial biomaterials mimic the mechanisms of action of HDPs but with significantly easier synthesis and lower production cost, higher potency, and enhanced selectivity.  Meanwhile, these unimolecular nanomicelles will provide excellent tools to gain insight into the mechanisms of action of HDPs, which are still controversial and elusive. Furthermore,  the knowledge obtained from this project will also inspire the design and development of other classes of antimicrobial polymer biomaterials, which allows the generation of novel antibiotic agents.   Broader Impact: The project led to 10 publications which have been published and available to public. The data has also been presented in conferences. The project provided great training opportunity for graduate and undergraduate students to acquire interdisciplinary training in organic synthesis, chemical biology and microbiology. This project also integrated teaching, research and outreach activities to broaden exposure to science and research for the local youth population in the Tampa community, as the PI gave lectures to K12 students and also accepted high school students to do research in his lab.               Last Modified: 08/10/2021       Submitted by: Jianfeng Cai]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
