<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Crack Growth During Fatigue in Ni Superalloys: Physical Origin of Stochastic Jumps and Their Predictive Role Using Statistical Approaches</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>423277.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>423277</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Judith Yang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>juyang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927086</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Strong, durable materials are an integral part of our society. One such class of materials found in turbine engines, used in the aerospace and marine industries, are known as superalloys. Superalloys exhibit excellent mechanical properties (strength, creep resistance, corrosion resistance). However, there is a catch in that these materials involve a large degree of structural disorder as a result of the required material manufacturing process. The effects of such disorder become even more pronounced at the high temperatures of turbines, due to sustained loading conditions, leading to microscopic damage and cracks in the material. These cracks are exacerbated over the lifetime of the machinery. Therefore, it is crucial to understand the behavior of these cracks and prevent catastrophic mechanical failure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Crack initiation and growth in very heterogeneous materials not only can be detrimental but also very unpredictable, thus it requires statistical methods and protocols for assessing the reliability of components at various stages of fatigue loading. This project will advance the science of stochastic crack growth jumps during cyclic loading (fatigue) of metallic heterogeneous materials, with a particular focus on Ni superalloys. The usefulness of the mechanical noise produced by such little cracks is that it might contain distinctive statistical features that can identify the damage level in a turbine component. A team of engineers and scientists will combine multi-scale modeling approaches, statistical methods, and experiments to ultimately develop combined experiment and theory protocols for characterizing the fatigue-induced "cracking noise" and assessing the damage levels of mechanical components. Beyond superalloys, the very outcome of this research is to promote the progress of the fundamental understanding of fatigue damage and develop non-invasive structural prognosis methods. An educational outreach program is also  planned that involves graduate, undergraduate, and high-school students, as well as the general public, in the under-represented EPSCoR state of West Virginia.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will advance the understanding of stochastic jumps during fatigue loading of Ni superalloys. A multi-scale modeling approach will be employed that will combine density functional theory (DFT) predictions with phase-field modeling. Machine-learning methods will be incorporated into the phase field model, which will be trained based on conducted experiments. The outcome of this research will be the fundamental understanding of fatigue damage that may be used to predict catastrophic failures, especially when there is limited statistical sampling.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A team of engineers and scientists will develop a novel pathway to predictive modeling of crack growth during fatigue loading in metallic superalloys: By statistically sampling the noise correlations at various stages of fatigue under the assumption of constant-stress short-time tests, we will build a predictive machine-learning framework using a direct multi-step forecasting strategy. In doing so, we will investigate the fundamental origin of stochastic crack growth jumps and will develop a probabilistic model that will incorporate a first-principles relationship of the cohesive energy, generated by density functional theory predictions and phase-field modeling. To validate our models, we will conduct a series of well-controlled experiments using in-situ SEM and we will track crack growth using DC resistance drop measurements. The statistical properties of crack growth noise at various stages as a function of temperature and environmental pressure will be compared to the multi-scale model predictions. The validated multi-scale model will then be used to investigate the probability distributions of crack growth events (classified in terms of crack-length changes) during the first few cycles to predict crack growth at late stages. The outcome will be a trained model that can predict failure based on early fatigue events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project has a societal impact based on the fundamental physical origin of crack growth jumps during fatigue loading of metallic superalloys, which are commonly used on aircraft turbines and other hardware. The aim is to develop general protocols to promote early, safe prediction of crack growth in metallic alloys. In addition to societal impact, an educational outreach program is planned that involve training graduate, undergraduate, and high-school students, as well as the general public, in the under-represented EPSCoR state of West Virginia. The focus of training will be on the use of computational modeling materials science as well as the deep understanding of basic physical properties of crack growth, fracture, and non-equilibrium rare events. The PI will design a course that will introduce the fundamentals of non-equilibrium statistical mechanics and fracture to multidisciplinary, undergraduate engineering environments.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/17/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1709568</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xingbo</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xingbo Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Xingbo.Liu@mail.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3042933998</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000247463</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/30/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terence</FirstName>
<LastName>Musho</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terence D Musho</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Terence.musho@mail.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3042933998</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000632614</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terence</FirstName>
<LastName>Musho</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terence D Musho</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Terence.musho@mail.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3042933998</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000632614</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/23/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stefanos</FirstName>
<LastName>Papanikolaou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stefanos Papanikolaou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Stefanos.Papanikolaou@mail.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3042933998</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000727626</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/23/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>West Virginia University Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Morgantown</CityName>
<ZipCode>265066845</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3042933998</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 6845</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>WV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>191510239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WEST VIRGINIA UNIVERSITY RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[West Virginia University]]></Name>
<CityName>MORGANTOWN</CityName>
<StateCode>WV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>265066106</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[395 Evansdale Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~423277</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Durable, strong materials form a key structural component of technological progress. In turbine engines, used in the aerospace and marine industries, superalloys are widely used due to their excellent thermo-mechanical properties (strength, creep resistance, corrosion resistance). These These materials develop damage and cracks due to repeated loading conditions many times,&nbsp; but the initiation and overall behavior of these cracks is highly dependent on the particular sample used. In this project, novel methods have been developed to promote predictive ability of individual samples, based on practical engineering observations and efficient superalloy modeling assumptions. The basis of the investigations in this work has been the mechanical noise produced by little cracks that contain distinctive statistical features that can identify the damage level in a turbine component. This fatigue-induced ?cracking noise? is characteristic of the damage levels of mechanical components, and is connected to the fundamental understanding of fatigue damage and can lead to non-invasive structural prognosis methods.<br /><br />In a sequence of peer-reviewed publications in high-impact journals [1-10], the PI and his collaborators advanced the understanding of stochastic jumps in crystal plasticity [1-4] and damage [5-6], developed novel approaches for predictive machine learning in crystal plasticity and damage [3,5,7,8,9], and applied these methods and understanding during fatigue loading of Ni superalloys [10]. A benchmark study was performed in various model superalloy samples [6], modeled in phase-field modeling, that allowed the development of a ground-breaking machine learning approach that allowed for the contruction of fundamental principles in machine learning, based on the understanding of solids' elasticity and plasticity [7].&nbsp; A variety of methods, including the novel ones, were used to investigate a large collection of experimental samples of Ni-based superalloys that had undergone fatigue loading [10]. The outcome of this research is the fundamental understanding of fatigue damage that may be used to predict catastrophic failures, especially when there is limited statistical sampling.<br /><br />The societal impact of the project was based on the understanding of the fundamental physical origin of crack growth jumps during fatigue loading of metallic superalloys, which are commonly used on aircraft turbines and other hardware. General protocols have been advanced to promote early, safe prediction of crack growth in metallic alloys. An educational outreach program was also implemented that involved training graduate, undergraduate, and high-school students, as well as the general public, in the under-represented EPSCoR state of West Virginia. The focus of training was on the use of computational modeling materials science as well as the deep understanding of basic physical properties of crack growth, fracture, and non-equilibrium rare events. Finally, the PI designed a course that introduces the fundamentals of non-equilibrium statistical mechanics and fracture to multidisciplinary, undergraduate engineering environments.<br /><br />1.&nbsp;&nbsp; P. Ispanovity, S. Papanikolaou, I. Groma, The emergence of Dipolar Dislocation Walls in Discrete and Continuum Theory Formulations, Phys. Rev. B 101, 024105 (2019).<br />2. R. Bolin, H. Yavas, H. Song , K. J. Hemker&nbsp; and S. Papanikolaou , Bending Nanoindentation and Plasticity Noise in FCC Single and Polycrystals, Crystals 2019, 9(12), 652; https://doi.org/10.3390/cryst9120652.<br />3. S. Papanikolaou, M. Tzimas, Effects of Rate, Size and Prior Deformation in Microcrystal Plasticity, (book chapter in ICACM Proceedings, ISBN: 978-1-786-30531-2, edited by I. Ionescu, S. Patinet, U. Salman, Wiley-ISTE, published (2019).<br />4. H. Song, S. Papanikolaou, From statistical correlations to stochasticity and size effects in submicron crystal plasticity, Metals, 9(8), 835 (2019).<br />5. S. Papanikolaou, Learning local, quenched disorder distributions in plasticity and other crackling-noise phenomena, , NPJ Computational Materials 4, 1-7, (2018).<br />6. S. Papanikolaou, P. Shanthraj, J. Thibault, C. Woodward, F. Roters, Brittle to Quasi-Brittle Transition and Crack Initiation Precursors in Disordered Crystals, Materials Theory, 3, 5 (2019). <br />7. S. Papanikolaou, Microstructural Inelastic Fingerprints And Data-Rich Predictions of Plasticity and Damage in Solids, Computational Mechanics 1-14 (2020) doi: 10. 1007/ s00466-020-01845-x.<br />8. Z. Yang, S. Papanikolaou, A. C. Reid, W. K. Liao, A. N. Choudhary, C. Campbell, and A. Agrawal, Learning to Predict Crystal Plasticity at the Nanoscale: Deep Residual Networks and Size Effects in Uniaxial Compression Discrete Dislocation Simulations, Scientific Reports, 10(1), pp.1-14. (2020).<br />9. S. Papanikolaou, G. Po, &Lambda;-invariant and topological pathways to influence the strength of submicron crystals, Phys. Rev. Lett. 124, 205502 (2020).<br />10. J. Lindsay, S. Papanikolaou, T. Musho, Experimental investigation of stochastic jumps during Crack Initiation and Growth in IN718, (Under Review) (2020)</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/04/2020<br>      Modified by: Stefanos&nbsp;Papanikolaou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709568/1709568_10488347_1591286842394_Fig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709568/1709568_10488347_1591286842394_Fig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709568/1709568_10488347_1591286842394_Fig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Optical micrograph of crack initiation near notch during mode-I fatigue in an Inconel 718 sample.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. Lindsay, S. Papanikolaou, T. Musho, Experimental investigation of stochastic jumps during Crack Initiation and Growth in IN718, (Under Review) (2020)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stefanos&nbsp;Papanikolaou</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709568/1709568_10488347_1591286927534_Fig2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709568/1709568_10488347_1591286927534_Fig2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709568/1709568_10488347_1591286927534_Fig2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Control of Crystal Plasticity through Dislocation Microstructure Design(a) Axial mechanical response of compressed metallic nanopillars with commonly designed microstructures (inset showing strength size effect),(b) Axial mechanical response of compres</div> <div class="imageCredit">Phys. Rev. Letters, 124, 205502 (2020)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stefanos&nbsp;Papanikolaou</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709568/1709568_10488347_1591287070304_Fig3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709568/1709568_10488347_1591287070304_Fig3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709568/1709568_10488347_1591287070304_Fig3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Process diagram of main steps towards equation-free prediction for plasticity and damage. The field &#966; typically is a strain field, invariant under frame rotations, that can be accurately measured through image correlation techniques. The applied strain &#491; corresponds to the  loading steps.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Computational Mechanics 1-14 (2020) doi: 10. 1007/ s00466-020-01845-x</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stefanos&nbsp;Papanikolaou</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709568/1709568_10488347_1591287160706_Fig4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709568/1709568_10488347_1591287160706_Fig4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709568/1709568_10488347_1591287160706_Fig4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Prediction vs. Observation in a model binary alloy crystalline sample using equation-free prediction for plasticity and damage. The strain field is accurately measured through image correlation techniques. The applied strain corresponds to the externally-controlled loading steps.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Computational Mechanics 1-14 (2020) doi: 10. 1007/ s00466-020-01845-x</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stefanos&nbsp;Papanikolaou</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig4</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Durable, strong materials form a key structural component of technological progress. In turbine engines, used in the aerospace and marine industries, superalloys are widely used due to their excellent thermo-mechanical properties (strength, creep resistance, corrosion resistance). These These materials develop damage and cracks due to repeated loading conditions many times,  but the initiation and overall behavior of these cracks is highly dependent on the particular sample used. In this project, novel methods have been developed to promote predictive ability of individual samples, based on practical engineering observations and efficient superalloy modeling assumptions. The basis of the investigations in this work has been the mechanical noise produced by little cracks that contain distinctive statistical features that can identify the damage level in a turbine component. This fatigue-induced ?cracking noise? is characteristic of the damage levels of mechanical components, and is connected to the fundamental understanding of fatigue damage and can lead to non-invasive structural prognosis methods.  In a sequence of peer-reviewed publications in high-impact journals [1-10], the PI and his collaborators advanced the understanding of stochastic jumps in crystal plasticity [1-4] and damage [5-6], developed novel approaches for predictive machine learning in crystal plasticity and damage [3,5,7,8,9], and applied these methods and understanding during fatigue loading of Ni superalloys [10]. A benchmark study was performed in various model superalloy samples [6], modeled in phase-field modeling, that allowed the development of a ground-breaking machine learning approach that allowed for the contruction of fundamental principles in machine learning, based on the understanding of solids' elasticity and plasticity [7].  A variety of methods, including the novel ones, were used to investigate a large collection of experimental samples of Ni-based superalloys that had undergone fatigue loading [10]. The outcome of this research is the fundamental understanding of fatigue damage that may be used to predict catastrophic failures, especially when there is limited statistical sampling.  The societal impact of the project was based on the understanding of the fundamental physical origin of crack growth jumps during fatigue loading of metallic superalloys, which are commonly used on aircraft turbines and other hardware. General protocols have been advanced to promote early, safe prediction of crack growth in metallic alloys. An educational outreach program was also implemented that involved training graduate, undergraduate, and high-school students, as well as the general public, in the under-represented EPSCoR state of West Virginia. The focus of training was on the use of computational modeling materials science as well as the deep understanding of basic physical properties of crack growth, fracture, and non-equilibrium rare events. Finally, the PI designed a course that introduces the fundamentals of non-equilibrium statistical mechanics and fracture to multidisciplinary, undergraduate engineering environments.  1.   P. Ispanovity, S. Papanikolaou, I. Groma, The emergence of Dipolar Dislocation Walls in Discrete and Continuum Theory Formulations, Phys. Rev. B 101, 024105 (2019). 2. R. Bolin, H. Yavas, H. Song , K. J. Hemker  and S. Papanikolaou , Bending Nanoindentation and Plasticity Noise in FCC Single and Polycrystals, Crystals 2019, 9(12), 652; https://doi.org/10.3390/cryst9120652. 3. S. Papanikolaou, M. Tzimas, Effects of Rate, Size and Prior Deformation in Microcrystal Plasticity, (book chapter in ICACM Proceedings, ISBN: 978-1-786-30531-2, edited by I. Ionescu, S. Patinet, U. Salman, Wiley-ISTE, published (2019). 4. H. Song, S. Papanikolaou, From statistical correlations to stochasticity and size effects in submicron crystal plasticity, Metals, 9(8), 835 (2019). 5. S. Papanikolaou, Learning local, quenched disorder distributions in plasticity and other crackling-noise phenomena, , NPJ Computational Materials 4, 1-7, (2018). 6. S. Papanikolaou, P. Shanthraj, J. Thibault, C. Woodward, F. Roters, Brittle to Quasi-Brittle Transition and Crack Initiation Precursors in Disordered Crystals, Materials Theory, 3, 5 (2019).  7. S. Papanikolaou, Microstructural Inelastic Fingerprints And Data-Rich Predictions of Plasticity and Damage in Solids, Computational Mechanics 1-14 (2020) doi: 10. 1007/ s00466-020-01845-x. 8. Z. Yang, S. Papanikolaou, A. C. Reid, W. K. Liao, A. N. Choudhary, C. Campbell, and A. Agrawal, Learning to Predict Crystal Plasticity at the Nanoscale: Deep Residual Networks and Size Effects in Uniaxial Compression Discrete Dislocation Simulations, Scientific Reports, 10(1), pp.1-14. (2020). 9. S. Papanikolaou, G. Po, &Lambda;-invariant and topological pathways to influence the strength of submicron crystals, Phys. Rev. Lett. 124, 205502 (2020). 10. J. Lindsay, S. Papanikolaou, T. Musho, Experimental investigation of stochastic jumps during Crack Initiation and Growth in IN718, (Under Review) (2020)       Last Modified: 06/04/2020       Submitted by: Stefanos Papanikolaou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
