<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Singularities in General Relativity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>120000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>120000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marian Bocea</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbocea@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922595</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project studies spacetime singularities in the solutions to the Einstein vacuum equations, a system of nonlinear partial differential equations that describes gravity in locations devoid of matter. Solutions to this system of equations can develop singularities from regular initial data; some such singularities are inside a black hole event horizon. A fundamental mathematical question concerns understanding how such singularities arise from generic initial data. In particular, this project explores questions that include: What does the boundary of the interior of black holes look like? Are they always singular? Are there singularities that are not in the black hole regions? These are questions that the strong and weak cosmic censorship conjectures in general relativity seek to address -- study of those conjectures is the central motivation for this project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A particular focus of the project is to understand the singular boundary of the interior of black holes and also to understand sharp criteria under which trapped surfaces (structures closely related to black holes) may form. Recent work of the investigator and collaborators provides a resolution of the strong cosmic censorship conjecture for the Einstein-Maxwell (real) scalar field in spherical symmetry, showing that solutions arising from generic data have singular black hole interiors, in the sense that the spacetime metric cannot be extended in a suitably regular manner. This project aims to extend these results to settings without symmetry assumptions, in particular to give a complete description of the boundary of black holes that arise from perturbations of the explicit Kerr solutions. In a different direction, this project also aims to establish criteria that guarantee that trapped surfaces form, as a step towards understanding the weak cosmic censorship conjecture in general relativity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/18/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1709458</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Luk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan W Luk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jluk@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507232209</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000602195</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052125</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main purpose of this project is to understand singularities in solutions to the Einstein equations, which according to the theory of general relativity governs the evolution of spacetimes. Of particular interest is the nature of singularities in the interior of gneric dynamical black holes. In a joint work "The interior of dynamical vacuum black holes I: The C0 stability of the Kerr Cauchy horizon" with M. Dafermos, we showed that the Cauchy horizon of the rotating subextremal Kerr black holes persists for any black hole spacetime whose exterior region converges to Kerr. Assuming that the exterior region of the Kerr black hole is stable, as is widely expected, we moreover show that the interior of the black hole has a bifurcate Cauchy horizon. This disproves the original formulation of Penrose's strong cosmic censorship conjecture, and provides new insights on the structure of the singularity in the interior of generic dynamical black holes.</p> <p>In a different direction, we study spacelike singularities that arise in general relativity. A basic example here is the Kasner singularity. In a joint work with G. Fournodavlos, "Asymptotically Kasner-like singularities", we constructed a large class of spacelike singularities which are similar to Kasner in a certain sense. This is the first such general construction which does not rely on any symmetry or analyticity assumptions.</p> <p>Another work supported by the award is the joint paper with D. Gajic "The interior of dynamical extremal black holes in spherical symmetry", in which we give the first description of the interior of an extermal black hole in a nonlinear setting. The extremal interior also features a Cauchy horizon, but we showed that it is less singular than its subextremal counterpart. We also studied high-frequency gravitational waves in the context of general relativity in&nbsp;a joint paper with C. Huneau, "Trilinear compensated compactness and Burnett's conjecture in general relativity".</p> <p>Beyond the results themselves, the project develops mathematical techniques more generally to handle solutions to hyperbolic partial differential equations featuring singularities. The research is written up in research articles, submitted to peer-reviewed journals, as well as presented in seminars and conferences to both the mathematics and physics communities. Some of the results have been presented to a more general audience for instance consisting mostly of undergraduate students. The research concerning the stability of the Kerr Cauchy horizon was also featured in the science magazine Quanta.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;W&nbsp;Luk</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main purpose of this project is to understand singularities in solutions to the Einstein equations, which according to the theory of general relativity governs the evolution of spacetimes. Of particular interest is the nature of singularities in the interior of gneric dynamical black holes. In a joint work "The interior of dynamical vacuum black holes I: The C0 stability of the Kerr Cauchy horizon" with M. Dafermos, we showed that the Cauchy horizon of the rotating subextremal Kerr black holes persists for any black hole spacetime whose exterior region converges to Kerr. Assuming that the exterior region of the Kerr black hole is stable, as is widely expected, we moreover show that the interior of the black hole has a bifurcate Cauchy horizon. This disproves the original formulation of Penrose's strong cosmic censorship conjecture, and provides new insights on the structure of the singularity in the interior of generic dynamical black holes.  In a different direction, we study spacelike singularities that arise in general relativity. A basic example here is the Kasner singularity. In a joint work with G. Fournodavlos, "Asymptotically Kasner-like singularities", we constructed a large class of spacelike singularities which are similar to Kasner in a certain sense. This is the first such general construction which does not rely on any symmetry or analyticity assumptions.  Another work supported by the award is the joint paper with D. Gajic "The interior of dynamical extremal black holes in spherical symmetry", in which we give the first description of the interior of an extermal black hole in a nonlinear setting. The extremal interior also features a Cauchy horizon, but we showed that it is less singular than its subextremal counterpart. We also studied high-frequency gravitational waves in the context of general relativity in a joint paper with C. Huneau, "Trilinear compensated compactness and Burnett's conjecture in general relativity".  Beyond the results themselves, the project develops mathematical techniques more generally to handle solutions to hyperbolic partial differential equations featuring singularities. The research is written up in research articles, submitted to peer-reviewed journals, as well as presented in seminars and conferences to both the mathematics and physics communities. Some of the results have been presented to a more general audience for instance consisting mostly of undergraduate students. The research concerning the stability of the Kerr Cauchy horizon was also featured in the science magazine Quanta.       Last Modified: 09/29/2020       Submitted by: Jonathan W Luk]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
