<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Coherent X-ray Studies of Surface Growth and Patterning Processes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>271104.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>271104</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James H. Edgar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jedgar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922053</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical description: Controlling the growth and nanometer-scale patterning of materials surfaces is critical to many applications in energy, communication and information technologies.  However, a major impediment to developing more useful materials is the difficulty of measuring the evolution of surface structure during such processes.  This research meets that challenge by using very intense x-rays to measure the nanometer-scale dynamics on surfaces during growth and patterning.  These experiments are made possible by the use of the latest x-ray sources, which have been rapidly developing increasing brightness.  The experimental measurements are compared with predictions of theory and computer simulations, leading to increased understanding and predictive power.  Such knowledge can help scientists and engineers better control surface processes on materials, enhancing their technological capabilities.  In addition, the project trains graduate, undergraduate and high school students in this very important and rapidly developing part of materials research, leading to future careers in materials innovation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical description: This research is developing x-ray photon correlation spectroscopy as a powerful new approach to investigating the nanoscale dynamics of surfaces during growth and ion beam patterning.  Given the technique?s early stage of application to such challenging problems, it is important to examine the range of its capabilities.  This project is therefore investigating a carefully chosen set of systems and behaviors.  First, it is being used to carefully probe the fundamental processes in kinetic roughening during amorphous film growth, an issue of long-standing interest and controversy.  Second, the applicability of the technique to investigating epitaxial growth processes is being examined within the context of vapor deposition of organic semiconductor films and plasma-assisted atomic layer epitaxial growth of III-V nitride epitaxial films. Finally, the dynamics of semiconductor ion beam nanopatterning, an issue generating unusually close interaction between experiment and theory, is being studied.  In all cases, simulations of continuum and atomistic models are being performed to relate observations to underlying mechanisms.  Graduate, undergraduate and high school students involved have an outstanding opportunity to work in an area that bridges basic research and application.  Participating students learn a wide range of characterization and computational tools that can translate well to future careers in industry or academia.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1709380</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
<LastName>Ludwig</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karl F Ludwig</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ludwig@buphy.bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173539346</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000246467</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022152521</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~271104</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Controlling the growth and nanometer-scale patterning of materials surfaces is critical to many applications in energy, communication and information technologies.&nbsp; However, a major impediment to developing a robust understanding of surface evolution during growth and patterning is the difficulty of measuring surface dynamics -- i.e. how things move at the nanoscale on the surface -- during such processes.&nbsp; This research meets that challenge by using the very intense coherent x-rays made available by recent synchrotron x-ray sources to measure the nanometer-scale dynamics of surface evolution.&nbsp; Coherent x-ray scattering does this by being able to examine fluctuations around the average system behavior, revealing dynamics information not accessible through more conventional experiments.&nbsp; Key intellectual goals of the project have been to: 1) Develop the experimental capability to perform these challenging experiments; 2) Develop techniques for the analysis of this new kind of data. 3) Use these new capabilities to gain new insights into the processes of thin film growth and of spontaneous nano-structure formation by ion beams.</p> <p>Our work has been performed in close collaboration with a group from the University of Vermont and with scientists from Argonne National Lab, Brookhaven National Lab and the Naval Research Laboratory.&nbsp; Results have already been published in four papers in leading journals and another four papers have been submitted at this time.</p> <p>We believe that the techniques developed here will find application to better understanding surface growth and patterning phenomena in a wide range of materials.&nbsp; The fundamental knowledge gained from such studies can help scientists and engineers better control surface processes on materials, enhancing their technological capabilities for meeting societal needs in energy conversion, computing, and communications.</p> <p>Students working on the project have benefited from a multidisciplinary environment involving national and international collaborations with scientists at other universities and at national laboratories. During the course of the project, two graduate students, have, or will soon (Fall 2020), graduate with their PhD in Physics or Materials Science and Engineering (MSE). A third Physics PhD student has also worked recently on the project. Three MSE Masters students who worked on the project have graduated and a fourth is expected to graduate in Spring 2021.&nbsp; Two Physics undergraduates have also worked on the project.</p> <p>During each of the summers of 2018 and 2019, we mentored two high school students in our lab for six-week internships through the Boston University Research in Science &amp; Engineering (RISE) and Greater Boston Research Opportunities for Young Women (GROW) programs.&nbsp; The RISE program recruits top students nationally while the GROW program provides paid research internship opportunities to talented local rising senior high school women interested in STEM fields.&nbsp; Because of University closure due to COVID-19, we were not able to take on any high school interns during summer 2020.&nbsp; Participating high school students have had an excellent opportunity to observe materials research first hand.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/18/2020<br>      Modified by: Karl&nbsp;F&nbsp;Ludwig</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Controlling the growth and nanometer-scale patterning of materials surfaces is critical to many applications in energy, communication and information technologies.  However, a major impediment to developing a robust understanding of surface evolution during growth and patterning is the difficulty of measuring surface dynamics -- i.e. how things move at the nanoscale on the surface -- during such processes.  This research meets that challenge by using the very intense coherent x-rays made available by recent synchrotron x-ray sources to measure the nanometer-scale dynamics of surface evolution.  Coherent x-ray scattering does this by being able to examine fluctuations around the average system behavior, revealing dynamics information not accessible through more conventional experiments.  Key intellectual goals of the project have been to: 1) Develop the experimental capability to perform these challenging experiments; 2) Develop techniques for the analysis of this new kind of data. 3) Use these new capabilities to gain new insights into the processes of thin film growth and of spontaneous nano-structure formation by ion beams.  Our work has been performed in close collaboration with a group from the University of Vermont and with scientists from Argonne National Lab, Brookhaven National Lab and the Naval Research Laboratory.  Results have already been published in four papers in leading journals and another four papers have been submitted at this time.  We believe that the techniques developed here will find application to better understanding surface growth and patterning phenomena in a wide range of materials.  The fundamental knowledge gained from such studies can help scientists and engineers better control surface processes on materials, enhancing their technological capabilities for meeting societal needs in energy conversion, computing, and communications.  Students working on the project have benefited from a multidisciplinary environment involving national and international collaborations with scientists at other universities and at national laboratories. During the course of the project, two graduate students, have, or will soon (Fall 2020), graduate with their PhD in Physics or Materials Science and Engineering (MSE). A third Physics PhD student has also worked recently on the project. Three MSE Masters students who worked on the project have graduated and a fourth is expected to graduate in Spring 2021.  Two Physics undergraduates have also worked on the project.  During each of the summers of 2018 and 2019, we mentored two high school students in our lab for six-week internships through the Boston University Research in Science &amp; Engineering (RISE) and Greater Boston Research Opportunities for Young Women (GROW) programs.  The RISE program recruits top students nationally while the GROW program provides paid research internship opportunities to talented local rising senior high school women interested in STEM fields.  Because of University closure due to COVID-19, we were not able to take on any high school interns during summer 2020.  Participating high school students have had an excellent opportunity to observe materials research first hand.       Last Modified: 08/18/2020       Submitted by: Karl F Ludwig]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
