<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Electrically Pumped Full-Color and White-Color InGaN/GaN Surface-Emitting Lasers Monolithically Integrated on a Single Chip</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruyan Guo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rguo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927718</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract title: Full-Color and White-Color Surface-Emitting Lasers for Lighting and Display Applications&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Nontechnical: This project is related to the demonstration of white-color and full-color surface-emitting lasers, which have the potential to revolutionize next-generation lighting, display, sensing, and communication technologies. To date, there are no efficient semiconductor lasers operating in the deep visible (green and yellow) spectral range, which has been limited by the presence of large densities of defects in gallium nitride based materials. Consequently, the current commercial green lasers generally rely on the use of nonlinear optical conversion. Such devices, however, are bulky, heavy and expensive, and are not suitable for on-chip integration. Moreover, there has been no established manufacturable technology to spatially vary alloy compositions to achieve multi-color emission on the same substrate. As a result, the current solid-state lamps rely on the use of rare earth doped phosphors to down-convert the blue emission of a gallium nitride based light emitting diode (LED) to generate white-light, which limits the flexibility to tune the spectral power distribution and to achieve color-tunable emission. In this project, by using gallium nitride based nanostructures, the applicant will address these fundamental challenges and demonstrate small size, high efficiency multi-color lasers. This project will address the "green gap" in semiconductor light emitters and will enable phosphor-free solid-state lighting, thereby significantly enhancing the efficiency, reducing the manufacturing cost, and improving the light quality. The broader impacts of this research also include the highly interdisciplinary nature of the proposed research and the outreach to undergraduate, underrepresented minorities, and K-12. This project also provides the opportunity to educate the students involved in the research and to involve high school students on the science and technology of nanostructured materials, LED lighting, and photonics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical: The applicant proposes to demonstrate white-color and full-color surface-emitting lasers through innovations in epitaxy, quantum-confined nanostructures, nanophotonics, and device engineering. Full-color emission will be achieved on a single chip by varying the nanowire diameters through selective area epitaxy, which was not previously possible for gallium nitride based quantum wells. Moreover, nonradiative surface recombination, one of the primary limiting factors for nanowire devices, will be addressed by using dot-in-nanowire core-shell heterostructures. In this project, surface-emitting lasers will be achieved by exploiting the two-dimensional band-edge resonant effect of a nanowire photonic crystal, instead of using conventional thick and resistive distributed Bragg reflectors. The unique approach will also enable the monolithic integration of red, green and blue emitters on a single chip, thereby leading to full-color and white-color laser diodes that were not previously possible. The device characteristics, including threshold, wall-plug efficiency, near and far-field profile, and modulation characteristics will be investigated.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1709207</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zetian</FirstName>
<LastName>Mi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zetian Mi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ztmi@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347636438</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000726602</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092122</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1301 Beal Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project is related to the development of surface-emitting laser diodes using InGaN nanocrystal arrays. Prior to this work, there has been no demonstration of GaN-based all epitaxial surface emitting laser diodes operating in the green wavelength region, to which human eyes are most sensitive. In this project, we have studied InGaN/AlGaN dot-in-nanowire core-shell heterostructures, which can suppress nonradiative surface recombination and lead to significantly enhanced luminescence emission, compared to conventional nanowire structures. We have performed detailed characterization of InGaN/AlGaN dot-in-nanowire heterostructures and observed the presence of extensive atomic ordering, instead of dislocations and indium phase separation commonly seen in InGaN quantum wells. &nbsp;We have experimentally observed the formation of a stable coherent optical mode in InGaN nanowire photonic crystal structures, which is in excellent agreement with our theoretical calculations. We have demonstrated that the size, spacing and shape of InGaN/AlGaN nanowire heterostructures can be well controlled using the technique of selective area epitaxy, which makes it possible to fabricate nanowire photonic crystal surface emitting lasers. We have demonstrated, for the first time, InGaN surface emitting laser diodes operating in the green wavelength without using conventional distributed Bragg reflectors (DBRs), which exhibit low threshold at room temperature. The presence of a clear threshold, sharp linewidth reduction, distinct far field emission pattern, and polarized light emission provides unambiguous evidence for the achievement of coherent lasing oscillation. Significantly, compared to the conventional GaN VCSELs, lasing and surface emission is achieved without using thick, resistive, and often heavily dislocated DBRs. This unique laser concept can be further extended to achieve all-epitaxial, DBR-free surface-emitting laser diodes operating across the entire visible, as well as mid and deep UV wavelengths, and to realize such lasers on low cost, large area Si wafers. Our studies therefore open a new paradigm in the design and development of surface-emitting laser diodes, wherein the performance is no longer limited by the availability of DBRs, lattice mismatch, and substrate availability. The development of electrically pumped deep visible lasers has the potential to address the &ldquo;green gap&rdquo; in semiconductor LEDs and lasers and to revolutionize next-generation lighting and display technologies. This interdisciplinary project covers important topics in materials science, physics and electrical engineering, and has contributed the multi-disciplinary student training on the science and technology of nanostructured materials, LED lighting, and photonics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/19/2020<br>      Modified by: Zetian&nbsp;Mi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709207/1709207_10480002_1602956512557_Nanowire--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709207/1709207_10480002_1602956512557_Nanowire--rgov-800width.jpg" title="InGaN nanowire photonic crystal"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1709207/1709207_10480002_1602956512557_Nanowire--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="InGaN nanowire photonic crystal"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Scanning electron microscopy image of InGaN nanowire photonic crystal array</div> <div class="imageCredit">Yong-Ho Ra</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Zetian&nbsp;Mi</div> <div class="imageTitle">InGaN nanowire photonic crystal</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project is related to the development of surface-emitting laser diodes using InGaN nanocrystal arrays. Prior to this work, there has been no demonstration of GaN-based all epitaxial surface emitting laser diodes operating in the green wavelength region, to which human eyes are most sensitive. In this project, we have studied InGaN/AlGaN dot-in-nanowire core-shell heterostructures, which can suppress nonradiative surface recombination and lead to significantly enhanced luminescence emission, compared to conventional nanowire structures. We have performed detailed characterization of InGaN/AlGaN dot-in-nanowire heterostructures and observed the presence of extensive atomic ordering, instead of dislocations and indium phase separation commonly seen in InGaN quantum wells.  We have experimentally observed the formation of a stable coherent optical mode in InGaN nanowire photonic crystal structures, which is in excellent agreement with our theoretical calculations. We have demonstrated that the size, spacing and shape of InGaN/AlGaN nanowire heterostructures can be well controlled using the technique of selective area epitaxy, which makes it possible to fabricate nanowire photonic crystal surface emitting lasers. We have demonstrated, for the first time, InGaN surface emitting laser diodes operating in the green wavelength without using conventional distributed Bragg reflectors (DBRs), which exhibit low threshold at room temperature. The presence of a clear threshold, sharp linewidth reduction, distinct far field emission pattern, and polarized light emission provides unambiguous evidence for the achievement of coherent lasing oscillation. Significantly, compared to the conventional GaN VCSELs, lasing and surface emission is achieved without using thick, resistive, and often heavily dislocated DBRs. This unique laser concept can be further extended to achieve all-epitaxial, DBR-free surface-emitting laser diodes operating across the entire visible, as well as mid and deep UV wavelengths, and to realize such lasers on low cost, large area Si wafers. Our studies therefore open a new paradigm in the design and development of surface-emitting laser diodes, wherein the performance is no longer limited by the availability of DBRs, lattice mismatch, and substrate availability. The development of electrically pumped deep visible lasers has the potential to address the "green gap" in semiconductor LEDs and lasers and to revolutionize next-generation lighting and display technologies. This interdisciplinary project covers important topics in materials science, physics and electrical engineering, and has contributed the multi-disciplinary student training on the science and technology of nanostructured materials, LED lighting, and photonics.          Last Modified: 10/19/2020       Submitted by: Zetian Mi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
