<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop:   Addressing data management challenges within integrative biodiversity projects; Spring/Summer; University of Florida</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>16783.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>16783</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The ability to identify common mechanisms regulating the diversification, maintenance and/or loss of biodiversity in diverse ecosystems depends on having relatable data across habitats, time-scales, levels of biological organization and geographical regions. This workshop will bring together participants from six Dimensions of Biodiversity projects spanning terrestrial to marine systems, past and present time-scales, cellular to ecosystem levels of biological organization, and diverse geographical regions to discuss the challenges in making biodiversity data more comparable across projects. The ability to analyze comparable biodiversity data across disciplines will offer new opportunities to identify common themes across diverse ecosystems and enhance current and future management practices for diverse habitats. Fifteen people will attend the workshop including Full, Associate, and Assistant Professors, as well as postdoctoral fellows and graduate students. Participation by early-career scientists and groups under-represented in science will be prioritized. Four of the six Dimensions of Biodiversity projects participating will be represented by women researchers, and two of these six projects are based at Hispanic-serving institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will enhance interdisciplinary work within diversity-focused projects and facilitate joint data analyses across research teams. Dimensions of Biodiversity projects are fundamentally transdisciplinary, integrating across genetic, phylogenetic and functional aspects of biodiversity. Each of these core dimensions generates many different types of data, including locality and abundance, genomic sequence, environmental, paleoclimatic, and phenotypic information. Multiple projects also gather these data across a range of geographic scales (local to continental) and time periods (present day to thousands or millions of years in the past). However, the volume and heterogeneous nature of the shared datasets strain the current capacity to integratively address some of the most fundamental questions about biodiversity. This workshop will provide participants an opportunity to share challenges, findings, data management approaches, as well as discuss potential solutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1710560</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ana</FirstName>
<LastName>Carnaval</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ana C Carnaval</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>acarnaval@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126505099</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000560277</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City College</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>603503991</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY City College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Convent Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7374</Code>
<Text>Systematics &amp; Biodiversity Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~16783</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We organized a workshop to discuss and brainstorm solutions to the great challenge of data management of NSF-funded projects that integrate multiple sources of information about biodiversity. At this two-day event, which happened at the University of Florida in November of 2017, we 1) reviewed current data management strategies within seven large NSF biodiversity projects, highlighting specific data types generated, and strengths and weaknesses of current data management strategies; 2) synthesized input from the multiple project teams and identified a general set of common requirements shared by large-scale projects; 3) identified currently available data management platforms/strategies, and 4) discussed how to&nbsp;address the central question of whether to build a new system from scratch (laborious) or make connections across databases that already exist (less clean, but perhaps faster). The group decided to aim for a flexible, yet simple and user-friendly set of relatable databases that will allow scientists to combine data across projects. To exemplify how this data organization scheme would work, the gorup jointly designed a data management strategy for the newest project represented at the meeting. Yet it became clear, at the end of the event, that a truly novel approach to integrate biodiversity data and enable convergence across research groups will require additional funding and time. The group decided, then, to collaboratively write grant proposals to specifically develop this framework, to make it available to the scientific community, and thus to make possible to combine heterogeneous data collected by several ongoing projects while addressing transformative questions about the drivers of biodiversity patterns.&nbsp;From 2017 to 2019, subsets of the group, with the addition of new collaborators, met on multiple occasions in person and via the web to work three grant proposals. One of them (DBI-&nbsp;1927319:&nbsp;IIBR RoL: Collaborative Research: A Rules Of Life Engine (RoLE) Model to Uncover Fundamental Processes Governing Biodiversity) was recently recommended for funding through the Rules of Life program. Another proposal is still in review.</p> <p>Fulfilling its proposed intellectual impact, this working group enhanced interdisciplinarity within multiple diversity-focused projects, facilitated joint data analyses across research teams, and created new opportunities of data integration via new grant proposals. Although various isolated repositories do exist for warehousing biodiversity data and are widely used by biodiversity scientists to date, they each have internal missions that are divergent from the needs of the community for data sharing and access. To better understand the nature of biodiversity, research teams should be able to ask questions about the multivariate forces that influence it - and thus make these datasets talk to each other. Answering integrated questions such as species responses to environmental shifts at multiple time scales, the impacts and mechanisms of species interactions, and other relevant topics addressed by a biodiversity-focused program will require that we develop a forward-looking, intentional strategy for data sharing and management. This broader impact of this workshop is now carried over to the new Rules of Life grant.</p> <p>This working group was composed by scientists supported by NSF&rsquo;s Dimensions of Biodiversity (DoB) program, and who are pursuing integrative questions across a diversity of realms (terrestrial and marine), time scales (past, present, future), levels of biological organization (cellular to ecosystems), and geographical regions. The group of participants included representatives of senior, mid-term and newly funded projects, allowing for a wide variety of needs and perspectives, as well as teams co-funded by NSF-China and FAPESP in Brazil. Teams were represented by PIs, postdocs, technical staff, or graduate students directly involved with data management and integration. We ensured gender balance in the final group and included Full, Associate, and Assistant Professors, as well as postdoctoral fellows and graduate students, to bring together scientists at various stages of career development. A subset of the participating junior scientists was directly mentored by the senior faculty during the process of proposal writing and submission, and one postdoc participant will be the lead PI of the follow-up NSF Rules of Life grant</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Ana&nbsp;C&nbsp;Carnaval</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We organized a workshop to discuss and brainstorm solutions to the great challenge of data management of NSF-funded projects that integrate multiple sources of information about biodiversity. At this two-day event, which happened at the University of Florida in November of 2017, we 1) reviewed current data management strategies within seven large NSF biodiversity projects, highlighting specific data types generated, and strengths and weaknesses of current data management strategies; 2) synthesized input from the multiple project teams and identified a general set of common requirements shared by large-scale projects; 3) identified currently available data management platforms/strategies, and 4) discussed how to address the central question of whether to build a new system from scratch (laborious) or make connections across databases that already exist (less clean, but perhaps faster). The group decided to aim for a flexible, yet simple and user-friendly set of relatable databases that will allow scientists to combine data across projects. To exemplify how this data organization scheme would work, the gorup jointly designed a data management strategy for the newest project represented at the meeting. Yet it became clear, at the end of the event, that a truly novel approach to integrate biodiversity data and enable convergence across research groups will require additional funding and time. The group decided, then, to collaboratively write grant proposals to specifically develop this framework, to make it available to the scientific community, and thus to make possible to combine heterogeneous data collected by several ongoing projects while addressing transformative questions about the drivers of biodiversity patterns. From 2017 to 2019, subsets of the group, with the addition of new collaborators, met on multiple occasions in person and via the web to work three grant proposals. One of them (DBI- 1927319: IIBR RoL: Collaborative Research: A Rules Of Life Engine (RoLE) Model to Uncover Fundamental Processes Governing Biodiversity) was recently recommended for funding through the Rules of Life program. Another proposal is still in review.  Fulfilling its proposed intellectual impact, this working group enhanced interdisciplinarity within multiple diversity-focused projects, facilitated joint data analyses across research teams, and created new opportunities of data integration via new grant proposals. Although various isolated repositories do exist for warehousing biodiversity data and are widely used by biodiversity scientists to date, they each have internal missions that are divergent from the needs of the community for data sharing and access. To better understand the nature of biodiversity, research teams should be able to ask questions about the multivariate forces that influence it - and thus make these datasets talk to each other. Answering integrated questions such as species responses to environmental shifts at multiple time scales, the impacts and mechanisms of species interactions, and other relevant topics addressed by a biodiversity-focused program will require that we develop a forward-looking, intentional strategy for data sharing and management. This broader impact of this workshop is now carried over to the new Rules of Life grant.  This working group was composed by scientists supported by NSF?s Dimensions of Biodiversity (DoB) program, and who are pursuing integrative questions across a diversity of realms (terrestrial and marine), time scales (past, present, future), levels of biological organization (cellular to ecosystems), and geographical regions. The group of participants included representatives of senior, mid-term and newly funded projects, allowing for a wide variety of needs and perspectives, as well as teams co-funded by NSF-China and FAPESP in Brazil. Teams were represented by PIs, postdocs, technical staff, or graduate students directly involved with data management and integration. We ensured gender balance in the final group and included Full, Associate, and Assistant Professors, as well as postdoctoral fellows and graduate students, to bring together scientists at various stages of career development. A subset of the participating junior scientists was directly mentored by the senior faculty during the process of proposal writing and submission, and one postdoc participant will be the lead PI of the follow-up NSF Rules of Life grant          Last Modified: 07/03/2019       Submitted by: Ana C Carnaval]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
