<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Quantum Interference and Coherence Effects on Charge Transport in Organic Semiconductors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>337454.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>337454</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James H. Edgar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jedgar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922053</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical description: This project addresses preparation and investigation of new materials made of organic molecules possessing electronic properties that enhance the performance of semiconductors. These electronic properties determine how electrons flow along multiple possible pathways in the semiconductor, and therefore are anticipated to affect the material's behavior. Optical probe techniques utilizing ultra-fast lasers are implemented to understand the details of electronic charge transport in semiconductors comprising these new organic molecules. Such semiconductors may be utilized to significantly enhance the performance of ultra-fast optical or electronic devices that are at the core of communications and information technologies. These inexpensive materials, while attractive for implementing improvements to device performance, may therefore also have major impact on the economy. This project encompasses a wide variety of disciplines in materials science, offering training opportunities to scientists at all academic levels. Outreach plans further include ongoing efforts at Northwestern University to integrate students in grades K-12 in educational activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical description: Photo-initiated charge transfer events in organic semiconductors can occur over a very large range of timescales. However, the uniquely quantum mechanical aspect of electronic coherence generally persists for only 10s to 100s of femtoseconds (fs). This project designs and synthesizes new organic semiconductors to more easily detect and exploit these electronic coherences, and to investigate how the consequences of coherent charge transfer can be used to enhance charge generation and transport in organic semiconductors. Femtosecond time-resolved spectroscopies are used to study the charge transport dynamics at the earliest stages, where the influence of electronic coherences is manifest. More specifically, this project is investigating how coherent charge transfer from a donor to two or more electron acceptors occurs within molecular building blocks of organic semiconductors. Separately, the project investigates coherent charge transfer in thin solid films of organic semiconductors. Additionally, the influence of quantum interference in multi-path charge transfer processes on the rate and efficiency of electron-hole pair production in organic semiconductors is addressed. The ability to tailor the design and performance of organic semiconductors via quantum coherence effects is anticipated to enhance semiconductor device performance, therefore impacting electronic and photonic devices commonly used in modern communications and information technologies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1710104</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Wasielewski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael R Wasielewski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>m-wasielewski@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474671423</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000308132</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Young</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan M Young</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ryan.young@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474913003</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000735926</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602080834</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2145 Sheridan Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>053Z</Code>
<Text>Quantum Leap Materials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~337454</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Organic semiconductors suitable for photonic device applications require ultrafast photo-driven electron-hole pair formation and subsequent rapid charge transport over long distances. Many such materials are based on electron donor-bridge-acceptor (D-B-A) molecular components, such that optimizing the performance of organic semiconductors requires a fundamental understanding of charge transfer in D-B-A systems. While charge transfer is inherently quantum mechanical in nature, many of the salient features of electron transfer processes can be modelled classically. However, these treatments largely ignore the role of quantum mechanical effects, such as coherences between electronic states, as they are typically very short lived (~10-100 femtoseconds) and as such are assumed to have decayed prior to most electron transfer events relevant to devices. However, with increasingly advanced spectroscopic techniques and improvements in time resolution, it is now possible to probe processes on these timescales and directly observe these coherences and their effects on the charge transfer processes that are critical to high-performance devices.</p> <p>Work accomplished in this project demonstrated that coherent charge transfer can occur from an electron donor to two or more electron acceptors within molecular building blocks that comprise organic semiconductors. Moreover, this project has established that coherent charge transfer from a donor to two or more electron acceptors can occur in thin solid films of organic semiconductors. Finally, this project extensively investigated quantum interference in multi-path charge transfer processes and has determined that these quantum effects can influence the rate and efficiency of electron-hole pair production in organic semiconductors.</p> <p>The students who engaged in this project were taught to prepare complex molecules and materials, while at the same time learning the physical techniques necessary to answer the questions addressed in their research. Moreover, they were strongly encouraged to develop an understanding and practical skills in whatever technique is necessary to solve their research problems. In this project, we also actively recruited and mentored women scientists. This has been one of our long-term, ongoing goals. Women scientists from our research group co-founded and remain very active in the organization Women in Science and Engineering Research (WISER) that seeks to support women in STEM fields as they advance through graduate school and pursue fulfilling professional careers. In addition, we participate in STEM education programs to develop and execute novel, impactful science programs in K-12 education including teacher professional development. Our outreach efforts in the K-12 teacher-training program and after-school program promote broad advocacy for scientific research to solve real-world problems and attract the widest talent base. This program continues to be a major means through which we disseminate our research broadly, while promoting teaching, training, and learning.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/04/2021<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;R&nbsp;Wasielewski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Organic semiconductors suitable for photonic device applications require ultrafast photo-driven electron-hole pair formation and subsequent rapid charge transport over long distances. Many such materials are based on electron donor-bridge-acceptor (D-B-A) molecular components, such that optimizing the performance of organic semiconductors requires a fundamental understanding of charge transfer in D-B-A systems. While charge transfer is inherently quantum mechanical in nature, many of the salient features of electron transfer processes can be modelled classically. However, these treatments largely ignore the role of quantum mechanical effects, such as coherences between electronic states, as they are typically very short lived (~10-100 femtoseconds) and as such are assumed to have decayed prior to most electron transfer events relevant to devices. However, with increasingly advanced spectroscopic techniques and improvements in time resolution, it is now possible to probe processes on these timescales and directly observe these coherences and their effects on the charge transfer processes that are critical to high-performance devices.  Work accomplished in this project demonstrated that coherent charge transfer can occur from an electron donor to two or more electron acceptors within molecular building blocks that comprise organic semiconductors. Moreover, this project has established that coherent charge transfer from a donor to two or more electron acceptors can occur in thin solid films of organic semiconductors. Finally, this project extensively investigated quantum interference in multi-path charge transfer processes and has determined that these quantum effects can influence the rate and efficiency of electron-hole pair production in organic semiconductors.  The students who engaged in this project were taught to prepare complex molecules and materials, while at the same time learning the physical techniques necessary to answer the questions addressed in their research. Moreover, they were strongly encouraged to develop an understanding and practical skills in whatever technique is necessary to solve their research problems. In this project, we also actively recruited and mentored women scientists. This has been one of our long-term, ongoing goals. Women scientists from our research group co-founded and remain very active in the organization Women in Science and Engineering Research (WISER) that seeks to support women in STEM fields as they advance through graduate school and pursue fulfilling professional careers. In addition, we participate in STEM education programs to develop and execute novel, impactful science programs in K-12 education including teacher professional development. Our outreach efforts in the K-12 teacher-training program and after-school program promote broad advocacy for scientific research to solve real-world problems and attract the widest talent base. This program continues to be a major means through which we disseminate our research broadly, while promoting teaching, training, and learning.          Last Modified: 01/04/2021       Submitted by: Michael R Wasielewski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
