<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Topology of Real Algebraic Varieties: Deterministic and Random Aspects</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Shanks workshop on  "The Topology of Real Algebraic Varieties: Deterministic and Random Aspects"  will take place on March 10-11, 2017, at Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN. The workshop brings together leading researchers with different backgrounds, but common research  interests in the area of real algebraic geometry. The emphasis is on enumerative and random aspects in the topology of real algebraic varieties. The main goal of the meeting is to facilitate discussions and collaborations in a focused setting, between researchers mostly in Northern America but also in France. The small size of the workshop provides an ideal environment for graduate students and young researchers to interact with experts in the field. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The field of real algebraic geometry, and in particular the study of the topology of real algebraic varieties, employs a wide variety of techniques, ranging from symplectic geometry, tropical geometry, as well as more traditional tools such as complex algebraic geometry, topology of manifolds and transformation groups. In the recent years we have witnessed spectacular developments stemming from symplectic geometry, complex analysis and probability. This workshop brings together researchers from many of these areas, assuring that the vast amount of techniques available in the field are shared among its participants. In particular, the presentations will be devoted to the recent progress in the enumerative geometry of real algebraic varieties (Georgieva, Niu, Tukachinsky), a probabilistic approach to real enumerative geometry (Basu, Lundberg) and to new directions in the study of real algebraic manifolds (Gabrielov, Sottile).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For more details, see the webpage of the workshop:  https://my.vanderbilt.edu/ragworkshop/ .</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1711567</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ioana</FirstName>
<LastName>Suvaina</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ioana Suvaina</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ioana.suvaina@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153222631</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000543618</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rares</FirstName>
<LastName>Rasdeaconu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rares Rasdeaconu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rares.rasdeaconu@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153223619</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000577777</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PMB 407749 2301 Vanderbilt Place]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965717143</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004413456</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372400001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1326 Stevenson Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The workshop: "The Topology of Real Algebraic Varieties: Deterministic and Random Aspects" took place at Vanderbilt University from March 10 to March 11, 2017. It was organized in conjunction with the visit of Prof. Viatcheslav Kharlamov (University of Strasbourg), one of the leading experts in the field of real algebraic geometry.</p> <p>The understanding of the topology of real algebraic varieties is a long-lasting challenge. New achievements were obtained in the last decade by means of emerging new tools coming from symplectic geometry, tropical geometry, complex analysis and probability combined with more traditional tools such as complex algebraic geometry, topology of manifolds and transformation groups. The workshop addressed enumerative and random aspects in the topology of real algebraic varieties.</p> <p>The conference featured 6 speakers from leading institutions in USA and France. The talks were all of high quality and there were stimulating discussions and exchange of ideas. Many mathematical ideas were exchanged during the workshop and new research collaborations were established.&nbsp;Four of the invited speakers were junior mathematicians, and their participation in this major conference promoted their professional development. The conference brought together twenty one mathematicians from institutions from USA and France. The NSF funds were used, among other, to support the participation of 6 graduate students, 3 recent PhD's and 3 female researchers, with some overlap in a few cases.</p> <p>The event was advertised on the conference website available on the mathematics department of Vanderbilt University server</p> <p>https://my.vanderbilt.edu/ragworkshop/</p> <p>as well as the American Mathematical Society calendar, on posters distributed across mathematics departments in US and email lists. NSF was acknowledged in all the advertisements. The conference website will remain available indefinitely and contains the list of speakers, the titles and abstracts of the talks, as well as the slides of the presentations, when available.&nbsp;</p> <p>During the second year of the award, the PI organized several research meetings to follow up on the work presented during the workshop. Two such meetings were centered around presentations given by Professor Viatcheslav Kharlamov (IRMA, Strasbourg, France). The rest of the meetings were organized on separate occasions, at Vanderbilt University, as well. They wereeach two-days long research sessions with the participation of Professor Jesse Leo Kass (University of South Carolina), Professor Scott Wilson (CUNY, Queens College), Professor Gueo Grantcharov (Florida International University) and Professor Laurentiu Maxim (University of Wisconsin-Madison). These yielded new research projects on the enumerative geometry of real algebraic varieties, and introduced the graduate students at Vanderbilt University to recent advances in the field of real algebraic geometry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/13/2019<br>      Modified by: Rares&nbsp;Rasdeaconu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The workshop: "The Topology of Real Algebraic Varieties: Deterministic and Random Aspects" took place at Vanderbilt University from March 10 to March 11, 2017. It was organized in conjunction with the visit of Prof. Viatcheslav Kharlamov (University of Strasbourg), one of the leading experts in the field of real algebraic geometry.  The understanding of the topology of real algebraic varieties is a long-lasting challenge. New achievements were obtained in the last decade by means of emerging new tools coming from symplectic geometry, tropical geometry, complex analysis and probability combined with more traditional tools such as complex algebraic geometry, topology of manifolds and transformation groups. The workshop addressed enumerative and random aspects in the topology of real algebraic varieties.  The conference featured 6 speakers from leading institutions in USA and France. The talks were all of high quality and there were stimulating discussions and exchange of ideas. Many mathematical ideas were exchanged during the workshop and new research collaborations were established. Four of the invited speakers were junior mathematicians, and their participation in this major conference promoted their professional development. The conference brought together twenty one mathematicians from institutions from USA and France. The NSF funds were used, among other, to support the participation of 6 graduate students, 3 recent PhD's and 3 female researchers, with some overlap in a few cases.  The event was advertised on the conference website available on the mathematics department of Vanderbilt University server  https://my.vanderbilt.edu/ragworkshop/  as well as the American Mathematical Society calendar, on posters distributed across mathematics departments in US and email lists. NSF was acknowledged in all the advertisements. The conference website will remain available indefinitely and contains the list of speakers, the titles and abstracts of the talks, as well as the slides of the presentations, when available.   During the second year of the award, the PI organized several research meetings to follow up on the work presented during the workshop. Two such meetings were centered around presentations given by Professor Viatcheslav Kharlamov (IRMA, Strasbourg, France). The rest of the meetings were organized on separate occasions, at Vanderbilt University, as well. They wereeach two-days long research sessions with the participation of Professor Jesse Leo Kass (University of South Carolina), Professor Scott Wilson (CUNY, Queens College), Professor Gueo Grantcharov (Florida International University) and Professor Laurentiu Maxim (University of Wisconsin-Madison). These yielded new research projects on the enumerative geometry of real algebraic varieties, and introduced the graduate students at Vanderbilt University to recent advances in the field of real algebraic geometry.             Last Modified: 08/13/2019       Submitted by: Rares Rasdeaconu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
