<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2017: Evolution of Defensive Traits and Diversification in Catfishes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel Marenda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dmarenda@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922157</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2017, Research Using Biological Collections. The fellowship supports research and training of the fellow that will utilize biological collections in innovative ways. There are over 3000 species of catfish, making up roughly one in twenty species of vertebrates. Catfishes are able to lock their fin spines outwards, providing a defense mechanism against predators, and this has been hypothesized to be a key innovation that allowed catfishes to escape predation and radiate. Furthermore, it was recently discovered that in roughly half of all catfishes, these fin spines also deliver venom, and catfishes comprise almost all venomous freshwater vertebrates. Venom has been poorly studied for fishes, including catfishes.  Understanding catfish diversity, evolution and co-evolution of traits (spines and venom) and the role that such adaptations play in species diversification has broad relevance for all vertebrate biology.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project will integrate various types of data, including a new catfish Tree of Life inferred based on phylogenomic data, venom transcriptomic data, computed tomography (CT) scans and photographic data that will derive from biological collections and efforts from the All Catfishes Species Inventory. These data will be integrated using comparative phylogenetics methods to test for shifts in the rates of diversification across catfish phylogeny that were associated with defensive traits and their evolution. The fellow will gain training in generation and analysis of next-generation genomic, transcriptomic, phenomic, and phylogenomic data types. In addition, the fellow will instruct undergraduate level classes and mentor students in research. Broader impacts of this research include collaboration with the Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History to interact with the public and develop education materials to inform the public about ichthyology, and particularly catfishes. The fellow will also engage in online outreach, including making data and results available to the public.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1711854</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Milton</FirstName>
<LastName>Tan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Milton Tan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>2173000987</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000734794</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tan                     Milton</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303221119</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>001Y</Code>
<Text>Collections Postdocs</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Catfishes are an important component of animal diversity as they comprise roughly 5% of all vertebrate species. They are also important globally as sources of protein, commercial and sport fisheries, aquaculture, and even as pets. In addition, they are dominant components of freshwater ecological communities on most continents. However, the origins of the diversity of catfishes and what has led to their dominance has not been studied, leaving a gap in our knowledge of vertebrate diversity.</p> <p>Catfish diversification may relate to origins of fin spines and multiple origins of venoms in catfishes. These provide a formidable defense against predation. This escape from predation may have allowed catfishes to better succeed at surviving, reproducing, and diversifying. To explore this, we aimed to document the diversity of defenses and reconstruct the origin of traits and whether they may have contributed to catfish diversification.</p> <p>To accomplish this, we aimed to combine data from extensive catfish specimens that have been historically collected and preserved in museum collections with cutting-edge genomic data on new specimens. The award resulted in the collection of new specimens that were added to museum collections, as well as diverse data types for catfishes including photographs and CT scans to study catfish anatomy, as well as genetic data to explore the relationships among catfish species with the aim to identify venoms. We also performed analyses to test for the association of defensive traits with diversification.</p> <p>In addition, multiple undergraduates were trained in the scientific method, data collection, and statistical analysis during the work for this proposal.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/28/2020<br>      Modified by: Milton&nbsp;Tan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Catfishes are an important component of animal diversity as they comprise roughly 5% of all vertebrate species. They are also important globally as sources of protein, commercial and sport fisheries, aquaculture, and even as pets. In addition, they are dominant components of freshwater ecological communities on most continents. However, the origins of the diversity of catfishes and what has led to their dominance has not been studied, leaving a gap in our knowledge of vertebrate diversity.  Catfish diversification may relate to origins of fin spines and multiple origins of venoms in catfishes. These provide a formidable defense against predation. This escape from predation may have allowed catfishes to better succeed at surviving, reproducing, and diversifying. To explore this, we aimed to document the diversity of defenses and reconstruct the origin of traits and whether they may have contributed to catfish diversification.  To accomplish this, we aimed to combine data from extensive catfish specimens that have been historically collected and preserved in museum collections with cutting-edge genomic data on new specimens. The award resulted in the collection of new specimens that were added to museum collections, as well as diverse data types for catfishes including photographs and CT scans to study catfish anatomy, as well as genetic data to explore the relationships among catfish species with the aim to identify venoms. We also performed analyses to test for the association of defensive traits with diversification.  In addition, multiple undergraduates were trained in the scientific method, data collection, and statistical analysis during the work for this proposal.          Last Modified: 04/28/2020       Submitted by: Milton Tan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
