<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Underrepresented Students In Topology and Algebra Research Symposium (USTARS)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/02/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5590.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5590</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>snaik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The sixth annual meeting of the Underrepresented Students in Topology and Algebra Research Symposium (USTARS) is to be held at Sam Houston State University on April 15-17, 2016.  Speakers will give 30-minute research talks in various subfields of topology and algebra; these subfields include algebraic combinatorics, enumerative geometry, knot theory, and representation theory.  Two distinguished graduate students will give hour-long presentations and one invited faculty member, Dr. Abakuse Mbrika of the University of Wisconsin at Eau Claire, will give a one-hour keynote address.  Invited undergraduate researchers will participate in a poster session. USTARS promotes diversity within the mathematical community by providing a platform for collaboration and professional development.  Participants are exposed to a variety of current research, ideas, and results, and meet underrepresented professors and students who will become future collaborators or colleagues. The conference also promotes diversity by encouraging women and minorities to attend and give talks. Indeed, the conference organizing committee is diverse in gender, ethnicity, and educational background, and hence is well-positioned to encourage participation from a diverse group of students. The participants of the conference will continue to influence the next generation of students by serving as much needed mentors and encouraging students in the mathematical sciences to advance themselves and participate in research and conference events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary goal of the symposium is to showcase the mathematical research being conducted by underrepresented graduate students. This is done by structuring the meeting so that speakers will give 30-minute parallel research talks focusing on research leading to their graduate theses. Graduate students will give at least 75% of these presentations. Topics of prior years' presentations include: combinatorics, braid groups, graph theory, knot theory, representation theory, number theory, and algebraic geometry. In addition to the parallel sessions, two distinguished graduate students and one invited faculty member are chosen to give 1-hour lectures and a poster session featuring invited undergraduates is also planned. Given the high quality and diversity of talks and participants "The Underrepresented Students in Topology and Algebra Research Symposium (USTARS) Invited Volume" was created in 2014. This is a new series aimed specifically at disseminating the research of USTARS participants. The intention of this Invited Volume is to provide graduate students with an opportunity to publish their results in order to further their development as mathematical researchers. In light of this, a yearly online volume will be published at the conclusion of each annual research symposium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;http://www.ustars.org</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/18/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1711937</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Candice</FirstName>
<LastName>Price</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Candice Price</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cprice@smith.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135853590</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000568088</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of San Diego</Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<ZipCode>921102476</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6192606825</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5998 Alcala Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>52</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA52</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064467962</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>064467962</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921102492</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5998 Alcala Park]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>52</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA52</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~5588</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span><br />This award funded participant travel to USTARS 2017 at Amherst College.&nbsp;&nbsp;The primary mission of the Underrepresented Students in Topology and Algebra Research Symposium (</span>USTARS<span>) is to showcase the excellent research conducted by underrepresented students studying topology and algebra. Dedicated to furthering the success of underrepresented students, USTARS seeks to broaden the participation in the mathematical sciences by cultivating research and mentoring networks. USTARS is open to all people interested in the topological and algebraic fields.</span></p> <p>USTARS 2017 welcomed over 84 participants and showcased the excellent research being conducted by underrepresented graduate students by including 15 half-hour oral presentations in three parallel-sessions and 22 poster presentations in research areas including, but not limited to, algebra, topology, combinatorics, and number theory. All 15 of the talks were presented by graduate students and all 22 posters were presented by undergraduate and graduate students.</p> <p>USTARS 2017 opened with a one-day early career faculty development workshop on "Writing Through Your Career."&nbsp; Through a series of panels and discussions, participants were provided with information and advice on grant writing, forming writing groups to create accountability, and compiling and writing tenure and promotion portfolios.&nbsp; The conference also included two 1-hour presentations delivered by Distinguished Graduate Students whose abstracts were selected by an external committee of reviewers. &nbsp;Robert Walker, a graduate student at the University of Michigan, lectured on the "Uniform Asymptotic Growth on Symbolic Powers of Ideals," and Bahar Acu, a graduate student at the University of Southern California, talked about "Symplectic mapping class group relations generalizing the chain relation." The Invited Faculty Mentor was Dr. Chelsea Walton, Selma Lee Bloch Brown Assistant Professor at Temple University. She gave an inspiring address on "Math in the Age of Trump."</p> <p>This event featured professional development panels where participants were invited to ask for advice on how to apply to graduate schools, find jobs, give great presentations, and become active in research opportunities.&nbsp; The professional development panels consisted of groups of&nbsp;faculty and students of diverse backgrounds, career stages, and academic experiences.&nbsp;</p> <p>One of the most important outcomes of each USTARS event is that participants are encouraged to develop a network of mentors and peers that will serve as a vital resource for collaboration and professional development throughout their careers.&nbsp; The networks of new connections made at USTARS 2017 are included as supporting images to this report.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Candice&nbsp;Price</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1711937/1711937_10406143_1522396800865_USTARS2017--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1711937/1711937_10406143_1522396800865_USTARS2017--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Conference Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1711937/1711937_10406143_1522396800865_USTARS2017--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Conference Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conference Photo</div> <div class="imageCredit">USTARS Media Group</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Candice&nbsp;Price</div> <div class="imageTitle">Conference Photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1711937/1711937_10406143_1522396717866_USTARS2017_Network--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1711937/1711937_10406143_1522396717866_USTARS2017_Network--rgov-800width.jpg" title="USTARS 2017 Network"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1711937/1711937_10406143_1522396717866_USTARS2017_Network--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="USTARS 2017 Network"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">USTARS 2017 Network</div> <div class="imageCredit">USTARS Media Group</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Candice&nbsp;Price</div> <div class="imageTitle">USTARS 2017 Network</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This award funded participant travel to USTARS 2017 at Amherst College.  The primary mission of the Underrepresented Students in Topology and Algebra Research Symposium (USTARS) is to showcase the excellent research conducted by underrepresented students studying topology and algebra. Dedicated to furthering the success of underrepresented students, USTARS seeks to broaden the participation in the mathematical sciences by cultivating research and mentoring networks. USTARS is open to all people interested in the topological and algebraic fields.  USTARS 2017 welcomed over 84 participants and showcased the excellent research being conducted by underrepresented graduate students by including 15 half-hour oral presentations in three parallel-sessions and 22 poster presentations in research areas including, but not limited to, algebra, topology, combinatorics, and number theory. All 15 of the talks were presented by graduate students and all 22 posters were presented by undergraduate and graduate students.  USTARS 2017 opened with a one-day early career faculty development workshop on "Writing Through Your Career."  Through a series of panels and discussions, participants were provided with information and advice on grant writing, forming writing groups to create accountability, and compiling and writing tenure and promotion portfolios.  The conference also included two 1-hour presentations delivered by Distinguished Graduate Students whose abstracts were selected by an external committee of reviewers.  Robert Walker, a graduate student at the University of Michigan, lectured on the "Uniform Asymptotic Growth on Symbolic Powers of Ideals," and Bahar Acu, a graduate student at the University of Southern California, talked about "Symplectic mapping class group relations generalizing the chain relation." The Invited Faculty Mentor was Dr. Chelsea Walton, Selma Lee Bloch Brown Assistant Professor at Temple University. She gave an inspiring address on "Math in the Age of Trump."  This event featured professional development panels where participants were invited to ask for advice on how to apply to graduate schools, find jobs, give great presentations, and become active in research opportunities.  The professional development panels consisted of groups of faculty and students of diverse backgrounds, career stages, and academic experiences.   One of the most important outcomes of each USTARS event is that participants are encouraged to develop a network of mentors and peers that will serve as a vital resource for collaboration and professional development throughout their careers.  The networks of new connections made at USTARS 2017 are included as supporting images to this report.          Last Modified: 03/30/2018       Submitted by: Candice Price]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
