<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Technology-Rich Units for Future Secondary Teachers: Forging Dynamic Connections Between Geometry and Functions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299989.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>314816</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Richardson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>srichard@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924657</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will address the documented need for undergraduate prospective secondary mathematics teachers to possess strong content knowledge in order to develop in their future students the rich mathematical understandings necessary to pursue STEM careers. While preservice teachers often take twelve or more undergraduate mathematics courses, they typically fail to see the deep mathematical interrelationships between the courses and their relevance to the mathematics they will teach. Prospective teachers need experiences in thinking about and knitting together these big mathematical ideas as well as making clear their applicability to school mathematics. This project will create and test five web-based units for preservice teachers that address these goals by promoting an interactive, geometry-based approach to middle school and high school mathematics through the use of web-based technology.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will build on the foundations of cognitive science, technology, and pedagogy to advance the goal of strengthening the mathematical background of future mathematics teachers. It will employ a geometric approach to functions as an overarching framework for technology-rich investigations of geometric transformations, analytic geometry, trigonometry, complex numbers, and relative rates of change with connections to calculus. Additionally, the project will capitalize on the ability of Web Sketchpad, a new web-based software, to design mathematical tools tailored to the needs of each particular activity. The project will construct measures aligned with each unit to assess what preservice teachers learn, pilot test each unit and make revisions based on data collection, and design teacher support materials for implementation. Project curriculum materials and project findings from the research will be shared with mathematics teacher educators to inform their preparation of secondary mathematics teachers. The Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship program will provide co-funding for this project in recognition of its alignment with the broader teacher preparation goals of the Noyce effort.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1712280</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Hollebrands</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen Hollebrands</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>karen_hollebrands@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195130505</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000160356</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allison</FirstName>
<LastName>McCulloch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allison W McCulloch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amccul11@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000332073</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Steketee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott Steketee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ssteketee@21pstem.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2156067787</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000660890</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Scher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Scher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dscher@21pstem.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2123170321</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000660892</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957801</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Stinson Drive; Poe Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0417</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~299989</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~14827</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>Intellectual Merit:</em> This current project focused on the development and implementation of six curriculum units (over 80 technology-based activties) built on the foundations of cognitive science, technology, and pedagogy to achieve the following goals: strengthen the mathematical background of future mathematics teachers, using a geometric approach to functions as an overarching framework for technology-rich investigations of geometric transformations, analytic geometry, trigonometry, complex numbers, and relative rates of change with connections to calculus; lead with geometry rather than algebra, grounding teachers? understanding in a visual, sensorimotor, and embodied approach to mathematics throughout the units; capitalize on the ability of Web Sketchpad, a new web-based software funded in part by a prior DRK?12 NSF grant, to design one-of-a-kind mathematical tools tailored to the needs of each particular lesson; and focus on student thinking and pedagogy through discussions of student interview videos and modeling the pedagogy that teachers will bring to their classroom.</p> <p><em>Broader Impacts:</em> Strong preparation of middle and high school mathematics teachers is needed to support future generations of students prepared to enter STEM fields. By assuring that teachers are prepared to teach the rigorous mathematics content in middle and high school, we can better prepare students to pursue STEM careers. The project materials have been used with 49 preservice mathematics teachers at NC State over four semesters. Many of these students are now working as teachers or student teachers. Their middle and high scholl students benefit from having well-prepared teachers of mathematics who can capitalize on connections between geometry and function and the use of technology to help turn sensorimotor experiences into conceptual understanding in their instruction. The materials are freely available at geometricfunctions.org/fc. Findings from our research are being shared with other mathematics educators to inform their preparation of teachers. To date our project team has made 16 presentations (or has been accepted to present) for mathematics teacher educators, mathematics teachers, and researchers. Four manuscripts have been published and two manuscripts are currently under review. We also hosted an online interactive workshop in the summer of 2020. Close to one hundred mathematics teacher educators registered to attend the workshop.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/16/2021<br>      Modified by: Karen&nbsp;Hollebrands</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: This current project focused on the development and implementation of six curriculum units (over 80 technology-based activties) built on the foundations of cognitive science, technology, and pedagogy to achieve the following goals: strengthen the mathematical background of future mathematics teachers, using a geometric approach to functions as an overarching framework for technology-rich investigations of geometric transformations, analytic geometry, trigonometry, complex numbers, and relative rates of change with connections to calculus; lead with geometry rather than algebra, grounding teachers? understanding in a visual, sensorimotor, and embodied approach to mathematics throughout the units; capitalize on the ability of Web Sketchpad, a new web-based software funded in part by a prior DRK?12 NSF grant, to design one-of-a-kind mathematical tools tailored to the needs of each particular lesson; and focus on student thinking and pedagogy through discussions of student interview videos and modeling the pedagogy that teachers will bring to their classroom.  Broader Impacts: Strong preparation of middle and high school mathematics teachers is needed to support future generations of students prepared to enter STEM fields. By assuring that teachers are prepared to teach the rigorous mathematics content in middle and high school, we can better prepare students to pursue STEM careers. The project materials have been used with 49 preservice mathematics teachers at NC State over four semesters. Many of these students are now working as teachers or student teachers. Their middle and high scholl students benefit from having well-prepared teachers of mathematics who can capitalize on connections between geometry and function and the use of technology to help turn sensorimotor experiences into conceptual understanding in their instruction. The materials are freely available at geometricfunctions.org/fc. Findings from our research are being shared with other mathematics educators to inform their preparation of teachers. To date our project team has made 16 presentations (or has been accepted to present) for mathematics teacher educators, mathematics teachers, and researchers. Four manuscripts have been published and two manuscripts are currently under review. We also hosted an online interactive workshop in the summer of 2020. Close to one hundred mathematics teacher educators registered to attend the workshop.          Last Modified: 04/16/2021       Submitted by: Karen Hollebrands]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
