<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Determining the Response of Migratory Fish to Environmental and Climatic Variability</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research will be completed in collaboration with leading fish migration expert, Dr. Gerard Closs at the University of Otago, and will identify factors and conditions influential to the success of migration in fishes. The implications of this study can be drawn broadly to understand the factors that influence migratory species under rapidly changing environmental and climatic conditions which will be foundational in determining future population dynamics of, often threatened, migratory fishes and will provide information for conservation and management of these threatened populations. Climate variability can influence the nutrients available in freshwater and marine aquatic systems which can subsequently affect the success of migratory organisms to move between those two environments, called diadromy. Additionally, stream flow can be influenced by climatic/environmental variability directly influencing the success of migratory individuals. In this study, we will evaluate how climatic processes, like El Niño, affect stream flow and marine and freshwater nutrient availability to determine if migration success is influenced in two migratory fish species, Gobiomorphus cotidianus and Galaxias argentius. This study will evaluate samples collected from streams representative of varying stream flow and nutrient productivity and will use MODIS satellite images to determine how changes in nutrient availability in the marine environment might influence migration success. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Climate variability can affect the productivity of freshwater and marine systems influencing the success of aquatic migrants between those systems (i.e., diadromy). Migratory success can fluctuate in response to variable environmental conditions such as stream flow or productivity. The primary hypothesis of this study is that climate variation (i.e., El Niño) alters the success of migrants and residents by affecting stream flow regimes and marine and freshwater productivity by sampling two diadromous species, Gobiomorphus cotidianus and Galaxias argentius along stream flow and productivity gradients. Otolith microstructure and microchemistry analysis will be used to determine the rate at which individuals migrate from freshwater streams to marine environments under different climatic conditions (ENSO index). MODIS satellite images will be used to analyze the influence of coastal productivity on migration propensity across a nutrient/productivity gradient while land use/land change satellite imagery will be used as proxy for stream productivity to determine migration rate dynamics across a terrestrial nutrient gradient.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award, under the East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes program, supports summer research by a U.S. graduate student and is jointly funded by NSF and the Royal Society of New Zealand.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1713617</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heidi</FirstName>
<LastName>Ballew</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Heidi E Ballew</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>3617281775</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000708756</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ballew                  Heidi          E</Name>
<CityName>Rockport</CityName>
<ZipCode>78412</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ballew                  Heidi          E]]></Name>
<CityName>Rockport</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>78412</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5941</Code>
<Text>NEW ZEALAND</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~5400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Little is known about how access to resources affects flexible migratory species, especially on remote island systems. This research sought to better understand how access to productive sites, both freshwater and marine, influences the recruitment of migratory fish into freshwater systems and the proportion of individuals that are non-migrant residents. Establishing a baseline understanding of residency/marine recruitment across an environmental gradient can provide insight for changing aquatic systems with changing climate. We found that marine recruitment of fish into freshwater systems occurs across productivity gradients but freshwater systems with a lack of freshwater productive sites (i.e. lakes) might have a higher prevalence of individuals that require a marine phase versus freshwater systems with large productive sites. That is, flexible migratory species closest to large lakes may utilize these naturally productive sites during the larval stage for development rather than risking a downstream migration into the pelagic marine environment. Alternatively, more individuals of flexible species farthest from productive lakes and closer to marine access may complete a larval marine phase and recruit back to downstream locations to complete the adult life stage. The outcomes of this research suggest that productivity plays a significant role in the &ldquo;decision&rdquo; to remain resident or complete marine migrations during the larval stage depending on the environment best suited for larval development and survival. The findings of this research are important for understanding how changing productivity in terrestrial and marine environments might influence remote island population dynamics of aquatic species.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/16/2018<br>      Modified by: Heidi&nbsp;E&nbsp;Ballew</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Little is known about how access to resources affects flexible migratory species, especially on remote island systems. This research sought to better understand how access to productive sites, both freshwater and marine, influences the recruitment of migratory fish into freshwater systems and the proportion of individuals that are non-migrant residents. Establishing a baseline understanding of residency/marine recruitment across an environmental gradient can provide insight for changing aquatic systems with changing climate. We found that marine recruitment of fish into freshwater systems occurs across productivity gradients but freshwater systems with a lack of freshwater productive sites (i.e. lakes) might have a higher prevalence of individuals that require a marine phase versus freshwater systems with large productive sites. That is, flexible migratory species closest to large lakes may utilize these naturally productive sites during the larval stage for development rather than risking a downstream migration into the pelagic marine environment. Alternatively, more individuals of flexible species farthest from productive lakes and closer to marine access may complete a larval marine phase and recruit back to downstream locations to complete the adult life stage. The outcomes of this research suggest that productivity plays a significant role in the "decision" to remain resident or complete marine migrations during the larval stage depending on the environment best suited for larval development and survival. The findings of this research are important for understanding how changing productivity in terrestrial and marine environments might influence remote island population dynamics of aquatic species.        Last Modified: 03/16/2018       Submitted by: Heidi E Ballew]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
