<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: A Common Sensor and Software Approach For Humanoid Material-Handling Missions in Disaster Scenarios</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Major disasters like Hurricane Katrina and the Fukushima nuclear accident strike quickly but leave regions devastated for years afterwards. Even a fractional reduction in cleanup time can drastically reduce economic opportunity costs and low social morale while more quickly returning these communities to pre-disaster quality of life. One possibility for reducing cleanup time is the deployment of humanoid robots. In the 2015 DARPA challenge, teams from around the world demonstrated that humanoid robots have the ability to navigate and interact with their world with unprecedented complexity: driving, using tools, opening doors, and manipulating facility controls. The biggest obstacle to overcome before humanoids can be deployed for cleanup is developing better material-handling capabilities like lifting, pushing, pulling, and stacking. As roboticists develop these capabilities, their humanoid robots are evolving different software and sensor approaches. This project will compare the software and sensors of an American and a Korean humanoid being developed for disaster cleanup, identify disparities in configuration, and determine optimum configuration for material-handling missions. The project will be conducted at Korea Advanced Institute for Science and Technology under the mentorship of Dr. Jun Ho Oh, whose team placed first in the 2015 DARPA Robotics Challenge.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The humanoids being compared in this study are DRC Hubo 2 platforms. The American and Korean Hubos use many of the same scripts and hardware, but differences have evolved as both groups continue to develop the platform independently. In cases that these differences significantly affect performance, the researcher will use a combination of simulated and real material-handling trials to determine which software and sensor approach produces superior success rates and completion times.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award, under the East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes program, supports summer research by a U.S. graduate student and is jointly funded by NSF and the National Research Foundation of Korea.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/04/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1713972</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Blake</FirstName>
<LastName>Hament</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Blake Hament</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>3216935294</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000731719</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hament                  Blake</Name>
<CityName>Las Vegas</CityName>
<ZipCode>891223536</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hament                  Blake]]></Name>
<CityName>Las Vegas</CityName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>891223536</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5942</Code>
<Text>KOREA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~5400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-40e0a0e2-f412-00ba-2747-795533f4470b"><span>In the event of a major disaster, communities are left devastated by physical damage, low social morale, and losses due to economic inactivity. This devastation can continue for years, as has been the case in Fukushima and New Orleans after the nuclear accident and Hurricane Katrina, respectively. If disaster cleanup could be completed more quickly, communities would be able to rebuild and resume normal activities sooner. One way to decrease cleanup time is to use robots for disaster cleanup. Robots can work around the clock in extreme environments that would be too hazardous for human laborers. Humanoid robots specifically are very versatile in that they can navigate spaces designed for humans, they can be adapted for a wide variety of applications, and their capabilities such as strength and stamina far exceed those of humans. Before humanoid robots can be deployed in a disaster situation, robust footstep planning must be developed so that the robots can safely navigate debris riddled environments.</span></span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-40e0a0e2-f411-6f82-3f31-dfbe95299c5d"><span>This EAPSI project presents progress towards a new pipeline for footstep planning with the DRC Hubo. The proposed approach more quickly captures and updates point clouds, allowing for continuous footstep planning and execution. Contributions include a new modality of point cloud capture, the addition of registration in the pipeline using RTAB-Map, new methods of processing point clouds using Point Cloud Library functions, and adaptation of the DRC Hubo Gazebo simulator for future testing of new footstep planning algorithms.</span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/04/2018<br>      Modified by: Blake&nbsp;Hament</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1713972/1713972_10485437_1520218769020_CopyofScreenshotfrom2017-08-0716-24-03--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1713972/1713972_10485437_1520218769020_CopyofScreenshotfrom2017-08-0716-24-03--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Footstep Planning"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1713972/1713972_10485437_1520218769020_CopyofScreenshotfrom2017-08-0716-24-03--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Footstep Planning"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">DRC Hubo scans debris riddled terrain in simulation</div> <div class="imageCredit">B. Hament</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Blake&nbsp;Hament</div> <div class="imageTitle">Footstep Planning</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the event of a major disaster, communities are left devastated by physical damage, low social morale, and losses due to economic inactivity. This devastation can continue for years, as has been the case in Fukushima and New Orleans after the nuclear accident and Hurricane Katrina, respectively. If disaster cleanup could be completed more quickly, communities would be able to rebuild and resume normal activities sooner. One way to decrease cleanup time is to use robots for disaster cleanup. Robots can work around the clock in extreme environments that would be too hazardous for human laborers. Humanoid robots specifically are very versatile in that they can navigate spaces designed for humans, they can be adapted for a wide variety of applications, and their capabilities such as strength and stamina far exceed those of humans. Before humanoid robots can be deployed in a disaster situation, robust footstep planning must be developed so that the robots can safely navigate debris riddled environments.  This EAPSI project presents progress towards a new pipeline for footstep planning with the DRC Hubo. The proposed approach more quickly captures and updates point clouds, allowing for continuous footstep planning and execution. Contributions include a new modality of point cloud capture, the addition of registration in the pipeline using RTAB-Map, new methods of processing point clouds using Point Cloud Library functions, and adaptation of the DRC Hubo Gazebo simulator for future testing of new footstep planning algorithms.       Last Modified: 03/04/2018       Submitted by: Blake Hament]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
