<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Analysis of SLOCC Convertibility and Quantum Transformations on Higher Order N-Partite Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger States</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Computers and information systems are built on bits, which can be anything that represents a binary value such as off/on, or 0/1. We may use quantum objects as bits, such as photons, because two possible states of polarization can be measured. However, quantum objects are especially unique because they can be in a superposition of both states, and they can also be entangled in a way such that the measurement of one system affects the other, which cannot be done with non-quantum (classical) bits. So quantum computing systems allow for calculations that cannot be done classically, and it is useful to know of systems that perform computations that classical computers cannot. One particularly interesting quantum state is the Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger (GHZ) state because of its non-classical properties, and the focus of this project is to do extensive research on this state and its properties. This project will be done in collaboration with Dr. Kae Nemoto, the leading professor in the Quantum Information Sciences research group at the National Institute of Informatics in Tokyo, Japan.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;GHZ states are non-biseparable states even for the simplest GHZ state. Therefore, it is useful to study its entanglement in terms of Stochastic Local Operations and Classical Communication (SLOCC) convertibility to apply those states in quantum information systems. It is also useful to study quantum operations on the state that do not result in simply entangled (Bell) states. This project will study both those properties in the n-partite GHZ state for few qubits and work its way up to make general statements for n-partite states for large number of qubits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award, under the East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes program, supports summer research by a U.S. graduate student and is jointly funded by NSF and the Japanese Society for the Promotion of Science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1713796</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrian</FirstName>
<LastName>Rivera-Torres</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrian A Rivera-Torres</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>7874750266</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000731670</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rivera-Torres           Adrian         A</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606164392</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Illinois Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606164392</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5921</Code>
<Text>JAPAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~5400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Classical information and computation systems are built on electronic circuits and devices that use what we commonly know as bits. By using quantum particles such as photons and taking advantage of their quantum properties not found in classical particles (such as entanglement and superposition of states,) we can create quantum systems that may be used to compute, transmit, and encode information. These quantum systems use new entities known as quantum bits, or "qubits", which are fundamentally different to bits and have the potential for far more powerful information devices and computing systems. Quantum information science is the field that studies the capabilities and development for these systems with two main objectives: to apply concepts from information theory for use in quantum systems, and to devise ways to create information and computation devices that may be used and scaled up.</p> <p>The original goal of the project is to investigate the capabilities of the<br />Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger (GHZ) quantum state, which is a special type of entangled quantum state, in terms of quantum computation, cryptography and information science. What first began as an overview of the capabilities of the GHZ state in quantum computation, ended as a survey of the capabilities of the GHZ state in quantum secret sharing schemes, which are methods of distributing a secret (classified or private information) among a group of participants in a way that they need to work together to decode the secret. So the main objective was applying Shamir&rsquo;s secret sharing scheme, a well-known algorithm in classic cryptography, into quantum cryptography schemes, using the GHZ state as the quantum channel.</p> <p>My first and second research objectives were learning how Shamir's scheme generally works in classical cryptography and learning of error correction methods through factorization. Then I needed to find a "quantum version" of that classical method, so my third and fourth research objectives were studying the geometry of the GHZ state as our channel and learning of a reliable quantum teleportation method, a unique quantum property shown to be extremely useful in information transmission. Once I had all the pieces of the puzzle, I developed a quantum secret sharing scheme that applied Shamir's scheme.</p> <p>Unfortunately I learned later on by reading articles and dissertations on quantum secret sharing schemes that the scheme I devised was inefficient and, in some cases, impractical <span class="ILfuVd">&mdash; my research project turned out to be a dead end. However, science is built on failures and dead theories, so by learning from these mistakes and hitting multiple dead ends we are able to find a theory that works successfully and efficiently. A reliable quantum secret sharing scheme may be used in governments, large corporations, and any entity that works with highly-encrypted data, meaning this line of research may prove to be highly valuable.<br /></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/21/2018<br>      Modified by: Adrian&nbsp;A&nbsp;Rivera-Torres</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Classical information and computation systems are built on electronic circuits and devices that use what we commonly know as bits. By using quantum particles such as photons and taking advantage of their quantum properties not found in classical particles (such as entanglement and superposition of states,) we can create quantum systems that may be used to compute, transmit, and encode information. These quantum systems use new entities known as quantum bits, or "qubits", which are fundamentally different to bits and have the potential for far more powerful information devices and computing systems. Quantum information science is the field that studies the capabilities and development for these systems with two main objectives: to apply concepts from information theory for use in quantum systems, and to devise ways to create information and computation devices that may be used and scaled up.  The original goal of the project is to investigate the capabilities of the Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger (GHZ) quantum state, which is a special type of entangled quantum state, in terms of quantum computation, cryptography and information science. What first began as an overview of the capabilities of the GHZ state in quantum computation, ended as a survey of the capabilities of the GHZ state in quantum secret sharing schemes, which are methods of distributing a secret (classified or private information) among a group of participants in a way that they need to work together to decode the secret. So the main objective was applying Shamir?s secret sharing scheme, a well-known algorithm in classic cryptography, into quantum cryptography schemes, using the GHZ state as the quantum channel.  My first and second research objectives were learning how Shamir's scheme generally works in classical cryptography and learning of error correction methods through factorization. Then I needed to find a "quantum version" of that classical method, so my third and fourth research objectives were studying the geometry of the GHZ state as our channel and learning of a reliable quantum teleportation method, a unique quantum property shown to be extremely useful in information transmission. Once I had all the pieces of the puzzle, I developed a quantum secret sharing scheme that applied Shamir's scheme.  Unfortunately I learned later on by reading articles and dissertations on quantum secret sharing schemes that the scheme I devised was inefficient and, in some cases, impractical &mdash; my research project turned out to be a dead end. However, science is built on failures and dead theories, so by learning from these mistakes and hitting multiple dead ends we are able to find a theory that works successfully and efficiently. A reliable quantum secret sharing scheme may be used in governments, large corporations, and any entity that works with highly-encrypted data, meaning this line of research may prove to be highly valuable.        Last Modified: 09/21/2018       Submitted by: Adrian A Rivera-Torres]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
