<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Examining the Innate Immune Responses of the Pacific Coral Pocillopora Damicornis from Thermally Variable Reefs</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Coral reefs provide important benefits to coastal communities and are in worldwide decline due to rapid environmental change. Stony corals that build reefs are comprised of the cnidarian host, symbiotic algae and additional bacteria, fungi and viruses that are collectively termed the "coral holobiont". Disruptions that affect the healthy holobiont, such as high temperature stress due to climate change, are hypothesized to increase the incidence of coral bleaching and disease via immune suppression of the coral host. However, coral innate immunity research has been limited, and there is a poor understanding of in vivo host-microbe regulatory mechanisms. Nanwan Bay in southern Taiwan has unique oceanographic and bathymetric features that cause deepwater upwelling during spring tides, leading to temperature fluctuations as great as 10ºC over the course of a few hours. This highly variable temperature regime experienced by corals on reefs near upwelling regions in Nanwan Bay may contribute to increased resilience to thermal stress, although the physiological basis for enhanced tolerance is undetermined. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;During this EAPSI fellowship, recirculating aquarium experiments will use antibiotics, heat stress and immune stimulation to perturb the holobiont of the model coral species Pocillopora damicornis before gene expression, protein expression, and flow cytometry analyses are applied to assess the capacity for coral immune adaptation in variable temperature settings. The primary hypothesis is that temperature fluctuations caused by tidal upwelling in Nanwan Bay select for Pocillopora corals with a broader immune capacity to modulate microbial community shifts due to temperature variability. This research will be completed under the supervision of Dr. Pi-Jen Liu from National Dong-Hwa University in Kaohsiung, Taiwan, and will make use of the marine operations and aquarium facilities at the National Museum of Marine Biology and Aquarium in Kending.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award, under the East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes program, supports summer research by a U.S. graduate student and is jointly funded by NSF and the Ministry of Science and Technology of Taiwan.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1713962</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Connelly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael T Connelly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>8564954785</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000737708</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Connelly                Michael        T</Name>
<CityName>MIAMI</CityName>
<ZipCode>331491031</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Connelly                Michael        T]]></Name>
<CityName>MIAMI</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331491031</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5924</Code>
<Text>TAIWAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~5400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>NSF EAPSI Public Outcomes Report</p> <p>Michael Connelly</p> <p>5/31/2018&nbsp;</p> <p>Corals establish diverse symbioses with dinoflagellate algae, bacteria, and micro-eukaryotes that benefit the health of the coral holobiont. Climate change is causing a global collapse of coral reefs, as rising temperatures disturb coral symbioses resulting in coral bleaching, disease and death. Activation of innate immunity has been observed during coral stress responses, and heat tolerance may be influenced by coral bacteria communities.</p> <p>To clarify patterns of immune gene expression in response to heat stress and bacterial community disruption, <em>Pocillopora damicornis</em> corals from Kenting National Park in Taiwan were subjected to treatments with antibiotics (ampicillin and streptomycin), heat stress, and bacterial lipopolysaccharide (LPS), an immune stimulant.</p> <p>After RNA extraction, cDNA library preparation and sequencing at the University of Miami, bioinformatics analyses revealed that genes involved in microbial recognition, immune signaling and defense were upregulated in LPS and antibiotics treatments relative to control fragments, suggesting that antibiotics cause a dysbiotic bacterial community that drives immune inflammation. Antioxidants such as superoxide dismutase and peroxidase were downregulated in these treatments, suggesting trade-offs between immunity and antioxidant capacity. Additionally, immune genes were downregulated during heat stress, and activation of apoptotic pathways was observed in combined antibiotics and heat treatments. These results suggest that stability within the coral bacterial community is essential for maintaining coral immune function and holobiont health in a changing climate.</p> <p>The facilities at the National Museum of Marine Biology and Aquarium (NMMBA) in southern Taiwan were ideal for conducting aquarium-based coral stress experiments and extensive fieldwork on nearby reefs in Kenting National Park. The research buildings were also well equipped and the staff at the NMMBA as well as the primary mentor, Dr. Pi-Jen Liu, were very responsive and helpful throughout the duration of the summer research. Altoghether, the EAPSI Taiwan program is a well-organized and highly impactful program for U.S. graduate students to develop international collaborations, and I would highly recommend the program to future students seeking to build these connections.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;T&nbsp;Connelly</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF EAPSI Public Outcomes Report  Michael Connelly  5/31/2018   Corals establish diverse symbioses with dinoflagellate algae, bacteria, and micro-eukaryotes that benefit the health of the coral holobiont. Climate change is causing a global collapse of coral reefs, as rising temperatures disturb coral symbioses resulting in coral bleaching, disease and death. Activation of innate immunity has been observed during coral stress responses, and heat tolerance may be influenced by coral bacteria communities.  To clarify patterns of immune gene expression in response to heat stress and bacterial community disruption, Pocillopora damicornis corals from Kenting National Park in Taiwan were subjected to treatments with antibiotics (ampicillin and streptomycin), heat stress, and bacterial lipopolysaccharide (LPS), an immune stimulant.  After RNA extraction, cDNA library preparation and sequencing at the University of Miami, bioinformatics analyses revealed that genes involved in microbial recognition, immune signaling and defense were upregulated in LPS and antibiotics treatments relative to control fragments, suggesting that antibiotics cause a dysbiotic bacterial community that drives immune inflammation. Antioxidants such as superoxide dismutase and peroxidase were downregulated in these treatments, suggesting trade-offs between immunity and antioxidant capacity. Additionally, immune genes were downregulated during heat stress, and activation of apoptotic pathways was observed in combined antibiotics and heat treatments. These results suggest that stability within the coral bacterial community is essential for maintaining coral immune function and holobiont health in a changing climate.  The facilities at the National Museum of Marine Biology and Aquarium (NMMBA) in southern Taiwan were ideal for conducting aquarium-based coral stress experiments and extensive fieldwork on nearby reefs in Kenting National Park. The research buildings were also well equipped and the staff at the NMMBA as well as the primary mentor, Dr. Pi-Jen Liu, were very responsive and helpful throughout the duration of the summer research. Altoghether, the EAPSI Taiwan program is a well-organized and highly impactful program for U.S. graduate students to develop international collaborations, and I would highly recommend the program to future students seeking to build these connections.          Last Modified: 06/01/2018       Submitted by: Michael T Connelly]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
