<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Remake Making: Understanding Adoption and Adaptation of Facilitated Making in Libraries</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299495.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299495</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Russell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rlrussel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922995</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>As part of its overall strategy to enhance learning in informal environments, the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program funds innovative research, approaches and resources for use in a variety of settings. The project plans to deliver and improve a constructivist professional development (PD) program called Remake Making for library staff that work with youth in maker spaces. The proposed project will be led by a partnership of the University of Pittsburgh and the Children's Museum of Pittsburgh and builds on a pilot facilitation framework developed in an earlier project by this team. The PD program responds to the rapid growth of makerspaces with a constructivist PD program focused on facilitation. Maker spaces are a new service model in many public libraries, part of a broader shift in general library services. Effective facilitation for learning, like that required in makerspaces, is a relatively new facet of librarianship that is not a consistent part of librarian education or PD. The project will work with two local library systems with libraries that have makerspaces but little to no PD opportunities around facilitation.  The project plans to iteratively design and investigate the Remake Making program, its impact on library maker facilitators and their interactions with child and youth learners. This will provide a setting for preliminary research about constructivist PD and the experiences and struggles of staff who facilitate making in libraries within the context of shifting library norms. This project will produce an efficient, maker-friendly PD system for facilitation in makerspaces, applicable to a broad range of informal and formal educators who wish to incorporate facilitated making.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project plans to conduct an iterative development process involving several cohorts of participants and using multiple data sources which include embedded PD workshop data, participant pre-post surveys, observation of library makerspaces, and interviews/focus groups. A participatory approach will be employed by involving participants in creating and refining research questions within the scope of the project. This approach is designed around inquiry-based improvement, which is experienced by participants as reflective practice or continuous improvement. The proposed project aims to advance knowledge and PD strategies for facilitation in library makerspaces. The research will build knowledge about the efficacy of an innovative constructivist PD program with adaptation as a key feature. The data collected in the context of the development of this innovation will provide opportunities for applied research about informal STEM learning in the context of library maker spaces, and the role that library staff play in facilitating this type of learning.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1713299</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Crowley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin J Crowley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>crowleyk+@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126248116</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000317741</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leanne</FirstName>
<LastName>Bowler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leanne J Bowler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lbowler@pratt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126477703</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000596628</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Akiva</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas M Akiva</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tomakiva@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126487320</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000648943</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Wardrip</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Wardrip</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wardrip@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4127708766</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000674550</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0417</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~299495</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this NSF pilot, we iteratively developed the <a href="https://www.simpleinteractions.org">Simple Interactions</a> (SI) Leadership program across three cohorts of 39 total participants over two years. The majority of participants were library staff in settings with makerspaces. The SI Leadership Program is a constructivist professional learning workshop that focuses on relational practice. It features (a) strengths-based discussion around short video clips of participants interacting with children and youth and (b) Try-It-Out projects in which participants to identify a growth area and &ldquo;try out&rdquo; small changes in their practice to address their improvement goals.&nbsp;We partnered with <a href="https://www.afterschoolpgh.org">our local afterschool intermediary</a> to develop and deliver this professional development program, and they are now equipped to deliver it in the future.</p> <p>In interviews with 16 participants across three cohorts, all participants found the program to be positive, productive, and useful.&nbsp; Participants especially valued connecting with other professionals, making time to reflect on their practices, and the SI Tool itself. Responses from surveys and participant journals were also overwhelmingly positive. Participants felt that the workshops affirmed their work and gave them confidence that they could productively change things in their program. The pilot also involved studies of the professional identities of child &amp; teen library staff as well as afterschool workers.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:&nbsp;</strong>This project advanced&nbsp;professional development strategies for facilitation in library makerspaces and establisehd the efficacy of our constructivist profesionall learning program that targets relational practice. The project also led to learning about professional identity in what we refer to as the Allied Youth Fields.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts:&nbsp;</strong>Educational and facilitated making continue to be in a period of expansion, with makerspaces appearing across a diverse range of formal and informal education settings including libraries. This project produced an efficient, maker-friendly PD system for facilitation in makerspaces, that is now ready for scaling.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/07/2020<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;M&nbsp;Akiva</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this NSF pilot, we iteratively developed the Simple Interactions (SI) Leadership program across three cohorts of 39 total participants over two years. The majority of participants were library staff in settings with makerspaces. The SI Leadership Program is a constructivist professional learning workshop that focuses on relational practice. It features (a) strengths-based discussion around short video clips of participants interacting with children and youth and (b) Try-It-Out projects in which participants to identify a growth area and "try out" small changes in their practice to address their improvement goals. We partnered with our local afterschool intermediary to develop and deliver this professional development program, and they are now equipped to deliver it in the future.  In interviews with 16 participants across three cohorts, all participants found the program to be positive, productive, and useful.  Participants especially valued connecting with other professionals, making time to reflect on their practices, and the SI Tool itself. Responses from surveys and participant journals were also overwhelmingly positive. Participants felt that the workshops affirmed their work and gave them confidence that they could productively change things in their program. The pilot also involved studies of the professional identities of child &amp; teen library staff as well as afterschool workers.   Intellectual Merit: This project advanced professional development strategies for facilitation in library makerspaces and establisehd the efficacy of our constructivist profesionall learning program that targets relational practice. The project also led to learning about professional identity in what we refer to as the Allied Youth Fields.   Broader impacts: Educational and facilitated making continue to be in a period of expansion, with makerspaces appearing across a diverse range of formal and informal education settings including libraries. This project produced an efficient, maker-friendly PD system for facilitation in makerspaces, that is now ready for scaling.           Last Modified: 10/07/2020       Submitted by: Thomas M Akiva]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
