<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative EAGER project: Early Career Seismic Chief Scientist Training Cruise</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>68102.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>68102</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rose Dufour</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rdufour@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928811</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Results of the recent UNOLS Marine Seismic Questionnaire (MSQ) demonstrate the value of an early &lt;br/&gt;career scientist Multi-Channel Seismic (MCS) chief scientist training cruise. Proposed, and awarded, are funds to carry out &lt;br/&gt;a MCS training program that includes 4 days of seismic data acquisition to increase the number of early career scientists &lt;br/&gt;experienced in marine seismology and to demonstrate the value of the Scripps Institution of &lt;br/&gt;Oceanography portable MCS system, a UNOLS facility. The training program consists of three parts: (i) &lt;br/&gt;Webinars prior to the cruise to expose the participants to the fundamentals of active source marine &lt;br/&gt;seismology, to provide the scientific background needed to plan the upcoming survey effectively, and to &lt;br/&gt;introduce the participants to open source processing and interpretation tools. The Webinars will include &lt;br/&gt;Proposal Writing and Data Management training. Applications will be solicited, including a maximum 2- &lt;br/&gt;page science proposal, after the webinar series. Once selected, participants will discuss their cruise plans &lt;br/&gt;with the PI team prior to the pre-cruise workshop via several telepresence meetings; then, during a 2-day &lt;br/&gt;workshop immediately before the cruise, the participants will finalize the cruise plan under the PI team's &lt;br/&gt;guidance; (ii) A training cruise. Each participant will contribute to the entire team walking off the ship &lt;br/&gt;with post-stack time migrated data, as well as writing a cruise report collaboratively; and (iii) a 2-day data &lt;br/&gt;interpretation workshop with computer-based visualization software. &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;The proposed survey regions are on the active continental margin of the west coast of the United States, &lt;br/&gt;where a variety of sedimentary and tectonic settings are available, providing targets of interest to a wide &lt;br/&gt;range of participants. At the extended continental margin off the coast of Oregon, the seismic reflection &lt;br/&gt;profiles acquired, processed, and archived from this cruise can be used to image the subducting plate and &lt;br/&gt;the Astoria Fan, as well as accretionary ridges hosting gas hydrate and pockets of hemipelagic sediment &lt;br/&gt;containing paleo-oceanographic information. Targets have implications for addressing important &lt;br/&gt;societally relevant questions, such as earthquake hazards and paleoclimate records in basins. There will &lt;br/&gt;also be potential for using seismic techniques to reveal real-time, fine-scale within the water column &lt;br/&gt;around upwelling regions of the northeastern Pacific Ocean boundaries. Open access data from this cruise &lt;br/&gt;can augment on-going and near-future science conducted by a broader community. &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;For this novel, transformative project, early-career scientists will be selected from a wide applicant pool. &lt;br/&gt;This science mission will be advertised on the MSQ and other geoscience listservs, and encouraged participations &lt;br/&gt;of underrepresented minorities and women by promoting the opportunity via organizations such as &lt;br/&gt;Society for Advancement of Chicanos/Hispanics and Native Americans in Scienceand Earth Science &lt;br/&gt;Women's Network. Participants will gain not only first-hand seismic cruise experience but also &lt;br/&gt;experience communicating their research to non-scientists. The proposed activities will be used to inform &lt;br/&gt;the public about the unique and essential contributions of seismic research toward solving a variety of &lt;br/&gt;important societal challenges. Results will be shared on the AGU's GeoSpace blog and Instagram &lt;br/&gt;account. Important deliverables from the pre-cruise and onboard activities to the community are to &lt;br/&gt;establish and provide "cookbook" of the open source software used during this cruise; and make the data &lt;br/&gt;acquired from the cruise open immediately as soon as they are archived at the publically accessible &lt;br/&gt;archives. A post-cruise survey will be conducted in collaboration with the UNOLS office to obtain &lt;br/&gt;feedback from the participants and encourage the participants to write NSF proposals, the number of &lt;br/&gt;which will be the direct and ultimate measurement of the success of this ECS.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/03/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/03/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1714413</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mitchell</FirstName>
<LastName>Lyle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mitchell W Lyle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mlyle@coas.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417373427</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000318186</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Trehu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne M Trehu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>trehu@coas.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417372655</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000238365</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973315503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[104 CEOAS Admin Bldg]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5411</Code>
<Text>SHIP OPERATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5411</Code>
<Text>SHIP OPERATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~68102</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project supported&nbsp;a cruise on the research vessel Revelle to acquire multichannel seismic (MCS) data from the continental margin offshore Oregon.&nbsp; Objectives of the cruise were to:&nbsp;(1) train early career geoscientists in marine seismology; (2) increase the visibility of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography (SIO) portable MCS system and demonstrate its value as a UNOLS national asset; and (3) fill important gaps in coverage of the Cascadia continental margin, where the Juan de Fuca tectonic plate is being thrust under the North American plate, resulting in significant seismic and tsunami risk.&nbsp;A 15-day training program was conducted that consisted of: (1) multiple on-line lectures and discussion prior over the course of several months prior to the cruise; (2) a 2-day workshop Newport, OR immediately before the cruise; (3) a 7-day long research cruise; and (4) a 1-day long post-cruise data processing and interpretation workshop. Surveys were sent to cruise participants soon after the cruise and again a year later to evaluate the impact of the program.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Pre-cruise:</p> <p>In April 2017, the principle investigators presented a series of webinars covering background information about the project for prospective participants. These webinars reached nearly 100 registrants each session and covered a wide variety of topics. Topics covered included: (1) science questions related to&nbsp;the Cascadia continental margin; (2) an overview of the U.S. Academic Research Fleet systems; (3) an introduction to the National Science Foundation&nbsp;proposal submission process; and (4) an introduction to the principles of MCS data acquisition. The principle investigator (PI) team then selected 19 early career scientists (10 male, 9 female) including MS and PhD students, postdoctoral associates, and university faculty at the assistant professor level. The participants were divided into 4 groups based on their scientific interests as outlined in their application. The PIs (2 male; 2 female) each served as a faculty mentor for one of the groups, and were available to answer questions as the groups developed a cruise plan to address their scientific questions.&nbsp; After several virtual meetings for each group, the groups each assigned one member to participate in a conference call to integrate the different science plans.&nbsp;</p> <p>The PIs, early career&nbsp;scientists selected to participate in the program, and 2 postdoc mentors who had prior seismic acquisition and processing experience&nbsp;(1 male; 1female) participated in a 1.5-day long pre-cruise&nbsp;workshop led by a professional science writer. This workshop was held at the Hatfield Marine Science Center in Newport, OR immediately before the cruise.&nbsp; The objective was to learn how to engage the public through science through writing and social media. We were introduced to the COMPASS message box model and discussed various ways to address NSF&rsquo;s Broader Impact criteria.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During the cruise:</p> <p>During the 7-day long MCs data acquisition cruise, the 19 early career scientists were grouped into 3 different 8-hr long shifts.&nbsp; Data acquisition continues around the clock to maximize science data acquisition. Each shift had a designated &ldquo;chief scientist&rdquo;, &ldquo;co-chief scientist,&rdquo; &ldquo;event logger,&rdquo; &ldquo;seismic processor,&rdquo; &rdquo;seismic watchstander,&rdquo; and &rdquo;underway data processor,&rdquo; and participates rotated through these positions over the course of the cruise to optimize opportunities for active learning&nbsp;to allow each participant to experience a leadership position during our research expedition. The designated chief scientist for a shift made operational decisions in close communication with officers in the pilot house, the science support service group, and other participants. We appreciate the patience of the ship&rsquo;s crew with this somewhat unconventional leadership format. By the end of expedition, we had acquired approximately 770km of seismic data and shipboard underway geophysics data from previously poorly mapped segments of the Cascadia seismogenic margin.&nbsp;</p> <p>During the cruise, all the early career participants were required to provide an entry for the cruise blog post to engage the public with the science. A total of 20 entries (including 1 by a PI) &nbsp;were posted (<a href="http://csw.unols.org/scientist-posts/">http://csw.unols.org/scientist-posts/</a>). Some of the entries were translated into Spanish by one of the participants (also posted on the American Geophysical Union Blogosphere): <a href="https://blogs.agu.org/thefield/2017/10/13/de-estudiante-de-geofisica-jefe-cientifico-por-un-dia/">https://blogs.agu.org/thefield/2017/10/13/de-estudiante-de-geofisica-jefe-cientifico-por-un-dia/</a>).&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Post-cruise:</p> <p>All the data became open to public access after an initial assessment of data quality (<a href="http://www-udc.ig.utexas.edu/sdc/DOI/datasetDOI.php?datasetuID=500194">doi: 10.1594/IEDA/500194</a>). In addition to a cruise evaluation prepared by participants soon after the cruise, we queried participants one year later to determine how many of the participants had used data from their cruise for their research. As of October 15, 2018, 15 out of 19 early career participants had answered the follow-up query; 67% of the participants have used the data from this expedition for&nbsp;their thesis research, classroom presentation, teaching materials, conference papers, and department seminars. In addition, 60% are planning to use the data for publications or proposals in 2018-2020 timeframe, including two pre-proposals for scientific drilling efforts to better understand past climate and the earthquake and tsunami risk associated with the Cascadia Margin.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/17/2018<br>      Modified by: Anne&nbsp;M&nbsp;Trehu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project supported a cruise on the research vessel Revelle to acquire multichannel seismic (MCS) data from the continental margin offshore Oregon.  Objectives of the cruise were to: (1) train early career geoscientists in marine seismology; (2) increase the visibility of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography (SIO) portable MCS system and demonstrate its value as a UNOLS national asset; and (3) fill important gaps in coverage of the Cascadia continental margin, where the Juan de Fuca tectonic plate is being thrust under the North American plate, resulting in significant seismic and tsunami risk. A 15-day training program was conducted that consisted of: (1) multiple on-line lectures and discussion prior over the course of several months prior to the cruise; (2) a 2-day workshop Newport, OR immediately before the cruise; (3) a 7-day long research cruise; and (4) a 1-day long post-cruise data processing and interpretation workshop. Surveys were sent to cruise participants soon after the cruise and again a year later to evaluate the impact of the program.     Pre-cruise:  In April 2017, the principle investigators presented a series of webinars covering background information about the project for prospective participants. These webinars reached nearly 100 registrants each session and covered a wide variety of topics. Topics covered included: (1) science questions related to the Cascadia continental margin; (2) an overview of the U.S. Academic Research Fleet systems; (3) an introduction to the National Science Foundation proposal submission process; and (4) an introduction to the principles of MCS data acquisition. The principle investigator (PI) team then selected 19 early career scientists (10 male, 9 female) including MS and PhD students, postdoctoral associates, and university faculty at the assistant professor level. The participants were divided into 4 groups based on their scientific interests as outlined in their application. The PIs (2 male; 2 female) each served as a faculty mentor for one of the groups, and were available to answer questions as the groups developed a cruise plan to address their scientific questions.  After several virtual meetings for each group, the groups each assigned one member to participate in a conference call to integrate the different science plans.   The PIs, early career scientists selected to participate in the program, and 2 postdoc mentors who had prior seismic acquisition and processing experience (1 male; 1female) participated in a 1.5-day long pre-cruise workshop led by a professional science writer. This workshop was held at the Hatfield Marine Science Center in Newport, OR immediately before the cruise.  The objective was to learn how to engage the public through science through writing and social media. We were introduced to the COMPASS message box model and discussed various ways to address NSF?s Broader Impact criteria.      During the cruise:  During the 7-day long MCs data acquisition cruise, the 19 early career scientists were grouped into 3 different 8-hr long shifts.  Data acquisition continues around the clock to maximize science data acquisition. Each shift had a designated "chief scientist", "co-chief scientist," "event logger," "seismic processor," "seismic watchstander," and "underway data processor," and participates rotated through these positions over the course of the cruise to optimize opportunities for active learning to allow each participant to experience a leadership position during our research expedition. The designated chief scientist for a shift made operational decisions in close communication with officers in the pilot house, the science support service group, and other participants. We appreciate the patience of the ship?s crew with this somewhat unconventional leadership format. By the end of expedition, we had acquired approximately 770km of seismic data and shipboard underway geophysics data from previously poorly mapped segments of the Cascadia seismogenic margin.   During the cruise, all the early career participants were required to provide an entry for the cruise blog post to engage the public with the science. A total of 20 entries (including 1 by a PI)  were posted (http://csw.unols.org/scientist-posts/). Some of the entries were translated into Spanish by one of the participants (also posted on the American Geophysical Union Blogosphere): https://blogs.agu.org/thefield/2017/10/13/de-estudiante-de-geofisica-jefe-cientifico-por-un-dia/).      Post-cruise:  All the data became open to public access after an initial assessment of data quality (doi: 10.1594/IEDA/500194). In addition to a cruise evaluation prepared by participants soon after the cruise, we queried participants one year later to determine how many of the participants had used data from their cruise for their research. As of October 15, 2018, 15 out of 19 early career participants had answered the follow-up query; 67% of the participants have used the data from this expedition for their thesis research, classroom presentation, teaching materials, conference papers, and department seminars. In addition, 60% are planning to use the data for publications or proposals in 2018-2020 timeframe, including two pre-proposals for scientific drilling efforts to better understand past climate and the earthquake and tsunami risk associated with the Cascadia Margin.             Last Modified: 10/17/2018       Submitted by: Anne M Trehu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
