<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Predicting the Observational Signatures of Accreting Black Holes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>408418.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>408418</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hans Krimm</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hkrimm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922761</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Since black holes (BH) are by definition invisible, the only way that astronomers can detect them is by observing material accreting onto (or falling into) the black hole.   Given the strong gravity, intense radiation and powerful magnetic fields near black holes, it is not surprising that such accretion is complex and can only be understood by running sophisticated numerical models on supercomputers.  A research collaboration between the University of Illinois, Princeton University and the University of California-Berkeley will model the behavior of BH accretion in the realm intermediate between strong and weak accretion, when interesting effects such as jets of outflowing material and unusual oscillations in the accretion are known to take place.  This work will help to unravel mysteries related to black holes, such as how the jets form and how the structure of the accretion flow changes over time.  The team will communicate the excitement of black-hole astrophysics to the public through lectures and visualizations, and to future generations of students through a black hole summer school.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theory of black-hole (BH) accretion and outflows is central to many areas of modern astrophysics and gravitational physics. The collaboration team has developed numerical techniques that permit nearly ab initio modeling of black-hole accretion in both the high- and low-accretion-rate limits. The team plans to develop new numerical techniques and codes suitable for studying the difficult, intermediate-accretion-rate regime, which is associated with jets, quasi-periodic oscillations, and state transitions around stellar-mass black holes. Additions to the models include radiation forces, pair production and transport, nonthermal particle production and transport, and collisionless plasma effects, all of which are critical for making progress on long-standing problems in black-hole astrophysics, such as the structure and observational appearance (spectrum, time variability, polarization) of accretion at intermediate accretion rates, as well as questions about the origin and maintenance of large-scale magnetic fields believed to power relativistic jets from such systems.   The group will make their new codes available for others to use through public releases.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1715277</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Stone</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James M Stone</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jstone@astro.princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092583815</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000300597</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Kunz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew W Kunz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mkunz@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092583090</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000711776</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085441001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4 Ivy Lane, Peyton Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~121641</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~286777</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>When black holes accrete matter from their surroundings, they produce<br />powerful relativistic outflows of matter and in some cases become<br />some of the most luminous objects in the known Universe. In turn,<br />the outflow and radiation can strongly affect the surroundng matter,<br />by a process termed feedback.&nbsp; Recently, the Event Horizon Telescope<br />(EHT) reported the first-ever image of matter accreting into the<br />black hole at the center of the galaxy M87.&nbsp; Thus, developing a<br />better understanding of how matter accretes in to black holes is<br />central to many areas of modern astrophysics.&nbsp; This project was a<br />continuing collaboration between researchers at Princeton University,<br />the University of Illinois, and the University of California Berkeley<br />to predict the observational signature of accreting black holes.<br />It builds upon previous collaborative work between the same<br />participants that was also funded by the NSF.<br />&nbsp;<br />Significant advances were made in a variety of areas.&nbsp; Most of the<br />theoretical effort requires sophisticated and state-of-the-art <br />numerical algorithms for modeling the plasma dynamics, and for<br />capturing radiation transport through the flow in order to predict<br />the emergent radiation field for comparison to observations.&nbsp; As<br />part of this effort we developed powerful new numerical methods for<br />studying radiation-dominated magnetized plasmas.&nbsp; We used some of<br />the nations largest supercomputers to study radiation-dominated<br />black hole accretion flows.&nbsp; We discovered new phenomena, for example<br />the emergence of very hot gas above the surface in the disk which<br />is analagous to the very hot gas in the corona of the Sun. Such<br />"accretion disk corona" might help exlplain the high-energy spectrum <br />of many accreting black holes in active galactic nuclei.&nbsp; We also<br />studied how plasma is fed inwards into the central regions of a<br />galaxy in order to evntually accrete in to the black hole.&nbsp; In<br />particular, for the case of our own Milky Way galaxy, our work has<br />shown that colliding winds from stars orbiting very close to the<br />center can explain the rate at which matter flows into the central<br />black hole.&nbsp; This work helps us understand the environment and<br />dynamics of the closest supermassive black hole known, and will be<br />useful for interpreting upcoming observations from the EHT.<br /><br />In addition, we were able to use advanced numerical methods to<br />compute the dynamics of collisionless plasmas and study angular<br />momentum transport and magnetically-driven turbulence in this regime.<br />These results are relevant to understadning very low luminosity<br />black hole accretion flows.<br /><br />Our work has advanced our understanding of these important astrophysical<br />systems.&nbsp; We developed and have made publically available new<br />numerical codes that can be used to study a variety of problems in<br />plasma physics, these codes have already been downloaded hundreds<br />of times by research groups around the world.&nbsp; Nearly half a dozen<br />postdoctoral research associates participated in this collaboration,<br />many of whom have gone on to research positions at universities and<br />the national labs.&nbsp; This project was a major part of the PhD thesis<br />of two graduate students at Princeton.&nbsp; Finally, we published<br />numerous refereed papers, gave dozens of research talks and seminars,<br />and to desseminate our resulat more widely to the public, we created<br />animations, visualizations, and wrote several popular-level reviews<br />on our results.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2020<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;M&nbsp;Stone</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ When black holes accrete matter from their surroundings, they produce powerful relativistic outflows of matter and in some cases become some of the most luminous objects in the known Universe. In turn, the outflow and radiation can strongly affect the surroundng matter, by a process termed feedback.  Recently, the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) reported the first-ever image of matter accreting into the black hole at the center of the galaxy M87.  Thus, developing a better understanding of how matter accretes in to black holes is central to many areas of modern astrophysics.  This project was a continuing collaboration between researchers at Princeton University, the University of Illinois, and the University of California Berkeley to predict the observational signature of accreting black holes. It builds upon previous collaborative work between the same participants that was also funded by the NSF.   Significant advances were made in a variety of areas.  Most of the theoretical effort requires sophisticated and state-of-the-art  numerical algorithms for modeling the plasma dynamics, and for capturing radiation transport through the flow in order to predict the emergent radiation field for comparison to observations.  As part of this effort we developed powerful new numerical methods for studying radiation-dominated magnetized plasmas.  We used some of the nations largest supercomputers to study radiation-dominated black hole accretion flows.  We discovered new phenomena, for example the emergence of very hot gas above the surface in the disk which is analagous to the very hot gas in the corona of the Sun. Such "accretion disk corona" might help exlplain the high-energy spectrum  of many accreting black holes in active galactic nuclei.  We also studied how plasma is fed inwards into the central regions of a galaxy in order to evntually accrete in to the black hole.  In particular, for the case of our own Milky Way galaxy, our work has shown that colliding winds from stars orbiting very close to the center can explain the rate at which matter flows into the central black hole.  This work helps us understand the environment and dynamics of the closest supermassive black hole known, and will be useful for interpreting upcoming observations from the EHT.  In addition, we were able to use advanced numerical methods to compute the dynamics of collisionless plasmas and study angular momentum transport and magnetically-driven turbulence in this regime. These results are relevant to understadning very low luminosity black hole accretion flows.  Our work has advanced our understanding of these important astrophysical systems.  We developed and have made publically available new numerical codes that can be used to study a variety of problems in plasma physics, these codes have already been downloaded hundreds of times by research groups around the world.  Nearly half a dozen postdoctoral research associates participated in this collaboration, many of whom have gone on to research positions at universities and the national labs.  This project was a major part of the PhD thesis of two graduate students at Princeton.  Finally, we published numerous refereed papers, gave dozens of research talks and seminars, and to desseminate our resulat more widely to the public, we created animations, visualizations, and wrote several popular-level reviews on our results.       Last Modified: 10/29/2020       Submitted by: James M Stone]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
