<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Linear and Nonlinear Data Assimilation in Turbulent Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>140067.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>140067</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Embid</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pembid@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924859</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Turbulent flows play a fundamental role in weather and climate dynamics, which are major factors impacting environmental stability, agricultural production, civil infrastructure, and other important areas.  Turbulence is highly chaotic, and therefore modern approaches to predicting its behavior are based on simulations.  A major difficulty in accurately simulating turbulent flows is the problem of determining the initial state of the flow.  For example, weather prediction models typically require the present state of the weather as input.  However, the state of the weather is only measured at certain points, such as at the locations of weather stations or weather satellites.  Data assimilation makes up for the lack of complete knowledge of the initial state.  It incorporates incoming data into the equations, driving the simulation to the correct solution.  The objective of this project is to develop innovative computational and mathematical methods to test, improve, and extend a promising new class of algorithms for data assimilation in turbulent flows.  Results of this work increase predictive capabilities of scientists, produce new mathematical and computational tools, and help educate students in challenging new areas with real-world impacts.  A student participates in the work of the project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project focuses on major areas of research aimed at making a new data assimilation tool as useful as possible to researchers in fluid dynamics and geophysics.  Firstly, an in-depth analytical and computational study of new nonlinear versions of the data assimilation algorithm is carried out, and its convergence rates are carefully estimated.  Secondly, the investigator carries out the first 3D simulations using the new algorithm in the context of the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations of fluids, and makes a detailed comparison of the method with cutting-edge data assimilation methods.  Finally, the method is extended to multi-physics settings to include fluids driven by heat convection and fluids with magnetic properties.  A student participates in the work of the project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1716801</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Larios</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adam Larios</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alarios@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9497489532</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000629113</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2200 Vine St]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555456995</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068662618</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska-Lincoln]]></Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>685880130</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[203 Avery Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~140067</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project produced major advances in the theory of continuous data assimilation; a subject of major importance in many branches of science, including weather prediction, aerospace technology, agriculture, solar storm monitoring, and ocean dynamics.&nbsp; In particular, this project produced new algorithms with order-of-magnitude improvements over previous algorithms, in terms of both time to convergence, and number of observation points required, which will likely lead to significant decreases in cost and significant increases in accuracy for prediction.&nbsp; This was done by exploring new non-linear approaches to data assimilation proposed by the PI and coauthors, as well as new algorithms that exploit&nbsp; observers that move in time.&nbsp; On the mathematical side, new proof techniques were developed to handle these algorithms, and proofs of the super-exponential convergence of the non-linear algorithm were discovered.<br /><br />Thanks to the collaboration facilitated by the NSF's funding of this project, discussions between the PI and coauthors led to an unexpected new branch of research, which pushed far beyond the original goals.&nbsp; Namely, by investigating the sensitivity of the data assimilation algorithm with respect to parameters in the system (which are often unknown, or difficult to measure accurately), we realized that we could build a new algorithm on top of the data assimilation algorithm to drive the system to the correct set of parameters on-the-fly, using only sparse measurement information.&nbsp; Moreover, in our tests, this new on-the-fly parameter recovery algorithm converged exponentially fast to both the correct parameter and the correct solution!&nbsp; This kind of algorithm is brand new, and has opened the doorway for many new lines of research, including multiple-parameter recovery, model reconstruction, and model validation.&nbsp; To delve into these new ideas and to push them to their fullest potential, the PI and coauthor Prof. Jared Whitehead formed a new research group called ``Applied Data Assimilation and Parameter Tuning'' (ADAPT), which involves graduate students and senior researchers in tackling several lines of research in this direction.&nbsp; The future potential applications for parameter estimation via continuous data assimilation are enormous, and are likely to be a game-changer for several areas of pure and applied research.<br /><br />This project also served to build a bridge between academic research and applied research being done at national labs.&nbsp; Indeed, this project produced the first implementation and tests of the new data assimilation algorithm in large-scale real-world simulations at Los Alamos National Lab (LANL) as part of the MPAS-Ocean code, a major project being developed for use within the Department of Energy's Energy Exascale Earth System Model (E3SM).&nbsp; It also facilitated new collaborations between the PI and researchers at LANL that are likely to be fruitful for many years to come.&nbsp; As part of this collaboration, the PI was able to send his graduate students to work at LANL with the scientists there, further strengthening this collaboration, and providing opportunities for graduate students to gain hands-on experience working with leading scientists on practical applications.&nbsp; This collaboration is part of the long-term goal of the PI to develop tools that will be useful to scientists and engineers working on real-world problems, with the larger aim of leveraging academic advancements for the advantage the general public.<br /><br />Funding for this project facilitated the dissemination of knowledge, the scientific exchange of ideas, and opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students to speak about their research.&nbsp; In particular, the PI gave 25 research talks at national and international academic conferences.&nbsp; His graduate students gave a combined 17 talks, and his undergraduate students gave several talks and poster presentations.&nbsp; Travel to these conferences also contributed to new collaborations, the formation of new ideas, and a synergy with other research groups.&nbsp; In particular, this project produced 14 papers that have been submitted or accepted to high quality academic journals.&nbsp; These papers involved a total of 15 coauthors of the PI.<br /><br />In summary, this project was a major success, and went far beyond its original goals.&nbsp; It has contributed to new knowledge in both pure and applied settings, and has opened up new branches of research.&nbsp; It has built new research connections and strengthened existing ones.&nbsp;&nbsp; It has facilitated the professional development of undergraduate and graduate students.&nbsp; Moreover, it has made tangible impacts in areas of interest to the general public via collaboration with researchers at LANL to enhance the speed and accuracy of simulations of Earth systems, such as the ocean and atmosphere.&nbsp; The impact of the NSF's support of this research will be felt for many years to come, as the work it made possible will generate a rich wealth of future research, education, and collaboration.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Adam&nbsp;Larios</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project produced major advances in the theory of continuous data assimilation; a subject of major importance in many branches of science, including weather prediction, aerospace technology, agriculture, solar storm monitoring, and ocean dynamics.  In particular, this project produced new algorithms with order-of-magnitude improvements over previous algorithms, in terms of both time to convergence, and number of observation points required, which will likely lead to significant decreases in cost and significant increases in accuracy for prediction.  This was done by exploring new non-linear approaches to data assimilation proposed by the PI and coauthors, as well as new algorithms that exploit  observers that move in time.  On the mathematical side, new proof techniques were developed to handle these algorithms, and proofs of the super-exponential convergence of the non-linear algorithm were discovered.  Thanks to the collaboration facilitated by the NSF's funding of this project, discussions between the PI and coauthors led to an unexpected new branch of research, which pushed far beyond the original goals.  Namely, by investigating the sensitivity of the data assimilation algorithm with respect to parameters in the system (which are often unknown, or difficult to measure accurately), we realized that we could build a new algorithm on top of the data assimilation algorithm to drive the system to the correct set of parameters on-the-fly, using only sparse measurement information.  Moreover, in our tests, this new on-the-fly parameter recovery algorithm converged exponentially fast to both the correct parameter and the correct solution!  This kind of algorithm is brand new, and has opened the doorway for many new lines of research, including multiple-parameter recovery, model reconstruction, and model validation.  To delve into these new ideas and to push them to their fullest potential, the PI and coauthor Prof. Jared Whitehead formed a new research group called ``Applied Data Assimilation and Parameter Tuning'' (ADAPT), which involves graduate students and senior researchers in tackling several lines of research in this direction.  The future potential applications for parameter estimation via continuous data assimilation are enormous, and are likely to be a game-changer for several areas of pure and applied research.  This project also served to build a bridge between academic research and applied research being done at national labs.  Indeed, this project produced the first implementation and tests of the new data assimilation algorithm in large-scale real-world simulations at Los Alamos National Lab (LANL) as part of the MPAS-Ocean code, a major project being developed for use within the Department of Energy's Energy Exascale Earth System Model (E3SM).  It also facilitated new collaborations between the PI and researchers at LANL that are likely to be fruitful for many years to come.  As part of this collaboration, the PI was able to send his graduate students to work at LANL with the scientists there, further strengthening this collaboration, and providing opportunities for graduate students to gain hands-on experience working with leading scientists on practical applications.  This collaboration is part of the long-term goal of the PI to develop tools that will be useful to scientists and engineers working on real-world problems, with the larger aim of leveraging academic advancements for the advantage the general public.  Funding for this project facilitated the dissemination of knowledge, the scientific exchange of ideas, and opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students to speak about their research.  In particular, the PI gave 25 research talks at national and international academic conferences.  His graduate students gave a combined 17 talks, and his undergraduate students gave several talks and poster presentations.  Travel to these conferences also contributed to new collaborations, the formation of new ideas, and a synergy with other research groups.  In particular, this project produced 14 papers that have been submitted or accepted to high quality academic journals.  These papers involved a total of 15 coauthors of the PI.  In summary, this project was a major success, and went far beyond its original goals.  It has contributed to new knowledge in both pure and applied settings, and has opened up new branches of research.  It has built new research connections and strengthened existing ones.   It has facilitated the professional development of undergraduate and graduate students.  Moreover, it has made tangible impacts in areas of interest to the general public via collaboration with researchers at LANL to enhance the speed and accuracy of simulations of Earth systems, such as the ocean and atmosphere.  The impact of the NSF's support of this research will be felt for many years to come, as the work it made possible will generate a rich wealth of future research, education, and collaboration.       Last Modified: 11/30/2020       Submitted by: Adam Larios]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
