<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CSR: Small: Collaborative Research: Easily Adapting Apps to Diverse Wearable Form Factors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>284497.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>284497</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Brunvand</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ebrunvan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922767</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the advent of many small, inter-connected devices - from appliances to wearable computers - the vision of ubiquitous computing appears increasingly tractable. The key obstacle is software development effort. Currently, a programmer must write a substantial amount of code for each different device form factor, such as smart phones, smart watches, and smart glasses.  The research objective of this proposal is to demonstrate that a combination of techniques from Operating Systems, Human Computer Interaction, and Programming Languages can significantly reduce the programmer effort in adapting applications to different form factors. The developer writes an application for one form factor, and then specifies a simple metaprogram to extend the application to additional form factors. The UIWear system proposed in this project compiles the metaprogram to effectively and efficiently extend the smart phone application to different form factors. UIWear has the potential to transform the wearable application market by: (a) reducing the barrier for development and (b) intelligently offloading computation between the smart phone and the wearable device.  Ubiquitous computing has the potential to dramatically improve many aspects of life, including healthcare, commerce, and education.  Unfortunately, the widening range of different devices also introduces an equally large range of different and complex programming models' creating an obstacle between good ideas and end users. This proposal, if successful, will significantly simplify development of ubiquitous apps, making these platforms available to a wide range of developers. The work on augmenting accessibility services is independently useful to design new applications for the visually impaired.  The software designed as part of this project will be released on a public site: https://github.com/sbunetsys. Electronic data will be archived internally. All data will be kept for at least 5 years after publication; likely longer, depending on its size and outside interest. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will advance the state-of-the-art in three key areas. First, it will explore new models for abstracting and refactoring graphical user interfaces (GUIs) for a wide range of form factors. The research approach is to identify an intermediate, lowest-common-denominator-style representation of the GUI that has enough details to allow the GUI to be repositioned, transformed, and scaled, but is simple enough that it can be rendered natively on any device display. Second, the UIWear framework will design new constraint optimization strategies to find the optimal UI that satisfies the limitations of the new form factor while leveraging the unique capabilities of the form factor. Third, the UIWear framework will use new language-level analysis techniques to guide programmers in placing computation across multiple devices.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1717973</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aruna</FirstName>
<LastName>Balasubramanian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aruna Balasubramanian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>arunab@cs.stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316329949</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000600655</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roy</FirstName>
<LastName>Shilkrot</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roy Shilkrot</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>roys@cs.stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316329949</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000738194</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804878247</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>CCRI-CISE Cmnty Rsrch Infrstrc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~284497</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project is to investigate the efficacy of virtualizing User Interfaces (UI) to easy extend smartphone applications to wearable devices. The project combined research in systems and HCI and resulted in three projects---UIWear, ULPM, DarkReader, and one study characterizing Smartphone-Smartwatch UI transformations. Together, the projects add knowledge to the state-of-the-art in terms of how UI virtualization can be used to improve usability, energy, and accessibility. The results of the project was published as papers at ACM MobiCom, ACM ASSETS, ACM UIST, and ACM MobileHCI.<br />Intellectual Merit: The UIWear project show that with only a few lines of code, a designer can extend a smartphone applications to wearable devices to create ``companion apps". UIWear is a first step towards a write-once-extend-to-many programming paradigm that allows developers to write one application, and then easily extend them to heterogenous devices. UIWear uses an intermediate representation of the UI elements as a logical model and uses this abstraction to re-tailor and render the UI on a wearable device.&nbsp;<br />The ULPM project extends the UI abstraction model created in UIWear to design an Ultra-low power mode on smartphones that significantly reduces power consumption. The display is one of the main power hog in a smartphone. ULPM allows users to type on the keyboard and perform other actions without the display switched on. To do this, ULPM relies on the ``muscle memory" of the users to remember the placement of the keyboard. Rather than update the UI elements, that requires building the UI components, ULPM updates the intermediate representation of the UI. Not building the UI elements provide considerable power savings, while updating the intermediate representation allows the application to function even with a disabled display. The DarkReader work showed how this Ultra-low power mode can be used by blind users. The DarkReader work started with a survey that showed that that blind users are anxious about their battery lifetime. DarkReader is a ultra-low power screenreader that switches off the display to reduce power but continues to provide application functionality to blind users.<br />The final piece of the project is a taxonomy and a set of best practices on transforming smartphone UIs to smartwatches. The taxonomy, generated with UI layouts for the top 100 apps from the AndroidWear Market, identifies common trends in adapting a smartphone UI to a much smaller wearable display.&nbsp;<br />Broader Impact: Ubiquitous computing has the potential to dramatically improve many aspects of life, including healthcare, commerce, and education; yet, a range of different devices introduces a range of different and complex programming models---creating a barrier to entry for good ideas. This proposal shows that UI virtualization ideas can be used to significantly simplify development of ubiquitous apps, making these platforms available to a wide range of developers. The work on improving energy consumption for blind users is independently useful to improve the user experience&nbsp; for the visually impaired. The project funded the research of three (3) graduate students.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/13/2021<br>      Modified by: Aruna&nbsp;Balasubramanian</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project is to investigate the efficacy of virtualizing User Interfaces (UI) to easy extend smartphone applications to wearable devices. The project combined research in systems and HCI and resulted in three projects---UIWear, ULPM, DarkReader, and one study characterizing Smartphone-Smartwatch UI transformations. Together, the projects add knowledge to the state-of-the-art in terms of how UI virtualization can be used to improve usability, energy, and accessibility. The results of the project was published as papers at ACM MobiCom, ACM ASSETS, ACM UIST, and ACM MobileHCI. Intellectual Merit: The UIWear project show that with only a few lines of code, a designer can extend a smartphone applications to wearable devices to create ``companion apps". UIWear is a first step towards a write-once-extend-to-many programming paradigm that allows developers to write one application, and then easily extend them to heterogenous devices. UIWear uses an intermediate representation of the UI elements as a logical model and uses this abstraction to re-tailor and render the UI on a wearable device.  The ULPM project extends the UI abstraction model created in UIWear to design an Ultra-low power mode on smartphones that significantly reduces power consumption. The display is one of the main power hog in a smartphone. ULPM allows users to type on the keyboard and perform other actions without the display switched on. To do this, ULPM relies on the ``muscle memory" of the users to remember the placement of the keyboard. Rather than update the UI elements, that requires building the UI components, ULPM updates the intermediate representation of the UI. Not building the UI elements provide considerable power savings, while updating the intermediate representation allows the application to function even with a disabled display. The DarkReader work showed how this Ultra-low power mode can be used by blind users. The DarkReader work started with a survey that showed that that blind users are anxious about their battery lifetime. DarkReader is a ultra-low power screenreader that switches off the display to reduce power but continues to provide application functionality to blind users. The final piece of the project is a taxonomy and a set of best practices on transforming smartphone UIs to smartwatches. The taxonomy, generated with UI layouts for the top 100 apps from the AndroidWear Market, identifies common trends in adapting a smartphone UI to a much smaller wearable display.  Broader Impact: Ubiquitous computing has the potential to dramatically improve many aspects of life, including healthcare, commerce, and education; yet, a range of different devices introduces a range of different and complex programming models---creating a barrier to entry for good ideas. This proposal shows that UI virtualization ideas can be used to significantly simplify development of ubiquitous apps, making these platforms available to a wide range of developers. The work on improving energy consumption for blind users is independently useful to improve the user experience  for the visually impaired. The project funded the research of three (3) graduate students.        Last Modified: 01/13/2021       Submitted by: Aruna Balasubramanian]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
