<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Vikings Enhancing STEM Innovation and Collaboration (VESTEMic) Model</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>350000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Implementation projects provide support to Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) to design, implement, and assess strategies that can lead to comprehensive institutional efforts to increase the number of students receiving undergraduate degrees in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) and enhance the quality of their preparation by strengthening STEM education and research. The project at Elizabeth City State University seeks to further strengthen programs for building STEM student success. The goal of the project is to design pathways to increase the numbers of students pursuing STEM majors and the quality of their preparation into graduate programs and careers.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Activities that are part of this project are: a pre-college summer program that includes incoming freshmen, K-12 teachers and parents; a sophomore bridge program to address the critical transition from the freshman to the sophomore year; a STEM innovation lab to develop creative approaches to teaching STEM undergraduate courses;  and hierarchical mentoring for undergraduate students. The activities and strategies are evidence-based and what is learned through this project can serve as a model for other small liberal arts institutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1719479</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ali</FirstName>
<LastName>Khan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ali A Khan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aakhan@mail.ecsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2523353242</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000179042</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gloria</FirstName>
<LastName>Payne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gloria Payne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gepayne@ecsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2523353250</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000651230</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Elizabeth City State University</Name>
<CityName>Elizabeth City</CityName>
<ZipCode>279097806</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2523353222</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1704 Weeksville Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066024357</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ELIZABETH CITY STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Elizabeth City State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Elizabeth City</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>279099913</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1704 Weeksville Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0417</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~350000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>There are numerous challenges associated with the recruitment, retention, and graduation of underrepresented students majoring in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) disciplines.<span>&nbsp; </span>During the one year of this project, four activities were initiated to gain further knowledge and understanding of this challenge that addresses our nation.</span></p> <p><span>The first activity, a Pre-Viking STEM program, was implemented to provide academic and social support activities for incoming freshmen to enhance retention and persistence in the major.<span>&nbsp; </span>This program was conducted during the fall and spring semesters and included seminars and workshops focused on time management, study skills, test-taking strategies, overcoming barriers, and building pathways to success.<span>&nbsp; </span>The second activity conducted during the grant period was the Sophomore Bridge Program which was held during the summer of 2017 for five intensive weeks of </span><span>classroom instruction in physics, organic chemistry, statistics, and computational skills.<span>&nbsp; </span>Students attended seminars and workshops in test-taking strategies, self-efficacy building, essay writing and reading sessions for a total of 200 contact hours. The third activity targeted the redesign of the General Physics course and consisted of a collaborative team of six students, four physics/engineering professors, and one physical science high school teacher.<span>&nbsp; </span>This team met throughout the one-year period to discuss challenges encountered in physics and to review evidence-based practices that could be modified and adapted for the VESTEMic Program participants. The fourth activity, hierarchical mentoring, was implemented throughout all activities.<span>&nbsp; </span>A structured mentoring program provided students contact with two or three individuals who were trained and experienced.</span><span> Each participant was paired with a faculty member, graduate student, and senior-level undergraduate STEM major.<span>&nbsp; </span>Mentors met on a weekly basis with the assigned mentee.</span></p> <p><span>Overall, the project provided direct support to 23 freshmen and sophomore students majoring in biology, chemistry, computer science, engineering technology, and mathematics.<span>&nbsp; </span>The redesign of the physics course impacted a total of 54 students enrolled in Spring 2018. Four graduate students, eight undergraduate senior-level majors, and three faculty members were provided mentoring training.</span></p> <p><span>In summary, the general findings from this one-year project indicated that participants in the Pre-Viking STEM and Sophomore Bridge programs were retained in the major at higher rates than non-participants.<span>&nbsp; </span>This suggests that early interventions at both the freshman and sophomore levels are important to persistence and retention within the major for the targeted population of underrepresented students.<span>&nbsp; </span>Findings from the redesigned physics course showed a 10% decrease in the number of students who received grades of &ldquo;D&rdquo;, &ldquo;F&rdquo;, or &ldquo;W&rdquo; (withdrew from the course).<span>&nbsp; </span>These initial findings during the one-year period strongly suggest that the VESTEMic Model has the potential to increase the number of students who are retained in STEM disciplines and who eventually enter graduate programs or the workforce.<span>&nbsp; </span>Relationships established through the collaborative physics redesign team provided a foundation for sharing and mentoring among professional colleagues.<span>&nbsp; </span>This has enormous promise for providing a collaborative platform for addressing challenging problems confronted by teachers and students in the STEM field.</span></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Gloria&nbsp;Payne</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ There are numerous challenges associated with the recruitment, retention, and graduation of underrepresented students majoring in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) disciplines.  During the one year of this project, four activities were initiated to gain further knowledge and understanding of this challenge that addresses our nation.  The first activity, a Pre-Viking STEM program, was implemented to provide academic and social support activities for incoming freshmen to enhance retention and persistence in the major.  This program was conducted during the fall and spring semesters and included seminars and workshops focused on time management, study skills, test-taking strategies, overcoming barriers, and building pathways to success.  The second activity conducted during the grant period was the Sophomore Bridge Program which was held during the summer of 2017 for five intensive weeks of classroom instruction in physics, organic chemistry, statistics, and computational skills.  Students attended seminars and workshops in test-taking strategies, self-efficacy building, essay writing and reading sessions for a total of 200 contact hours. The third activity targeted the redesign of the General Physics course and consisted of a collaborative team of six students, four physics/engineering professors, and one physical science high school teacher.  This team met throughout the one-year period to discuss challenges encountered in physics and to review evidence-based practices that could be modified and adapted for the VESTEMic Program participants. The fourth activity, hierarchical mentoring, was implemented throughout all activities.  A structured mentoring program provided students contact with two or three individuals who were trained and experienced. Each participant was paired with a faculty member, graduate student, and senior-level undergraduate STEM major.  Mentors met on a weekly basis with the assigned mentee.  Overall, the project provided direct support to 23 freshmen and sophomore students majoring in biology, chemistry, computer science, engineering technology, and mathematics.  The redesign of the physics course impacted a total of 54 students enrolled in Spring 2018. Four graduate students, eight undergraduate senior-level majors, and three faculty members were provided mentoring training.  In summary, the general findings from this one-year project indicated that participants in the Pre-Viking STEM and Sophomore Bridge programs were retained in the major at higher rates than non-participants.  This suggests that early interventions at both the freshman and sophomore levels are important to persistence and retention within the major for the targeted population of underrepresented students.  Findings from the redesigned physics course showed a 10% decrease in the number of students who received grades of "D", "F", or "W" (withdrew from the course).  These initial findings during the one-year period strongly suggest that the VESTEMic Model has the potential to increase the number of students who are retained in STEM disciplines and who eventually enter graduate programs or the workforce.  Relationships established through the collaborative physics redesign team provided a foundation for sharing and mentoring among professional colleagues.  This has enormous promise for providing a collaborative platform for addressing challenging problems confronted by teachers and students in the STEM field.              Last Modified: 09/01/2018       Submitted by: Gloria Payne]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
