<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Arctic Observing Network: Continuing the Beaufort Gyre Observing System in 2018-2021 to Document and Enhance Understanding of Arctic Freshwater Transformations and Fate</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1579287.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1579287</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Roberto Delgado</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>robdelga@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922397</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The western part of the Arctic Ocean contains a large amount of freshwater (more than 23,000 cubic kilometers which is comparable with the volume of fresh water stored in all the Great Lakes). Our project uses samples from ships and moored instruments to study the mechanisms controlling the amount of freshwater and other ocean properties in the western Arctic Ocean under different climate conditions. Changes in the western Arctic system are driven by changes in the Arctic and global climate systems while at the same time they are strong enough to influence both the weather and climate in the Northern Hemisphere. What we learn on this project will allow us to predict changes in the Arctic Ocean and is important for oil and gas exploration, shipping, navigation, tourism, and military operations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Arctic Observing Network project will continue for 2018-2019 the Beaufort Gyre Observing System operations begun in 2003 designed to document the unprecedented changes in sea ice and ocean parameters that are presently occurring in the region. We will continue measuring time series of temperature, salinity, currents, geochemical tracers, sea ice draft, and sea level using bottom-anchored moorings and shipboard measurements. Ship-based synoptic sampling covering the Beaufort Gyre will take place during the summer of 2018 in collaboration with scientists from Canada and Japan, with shared logistic expenses, to augment the year-round mooring measurements. Temperature, salinity, oxygen, nutrients, barium, and 18O will continue to be measured at standard locations along sections at 140째W and 150째W longitudes, and ~75째N and ~78째N latitudes using a shipboard CTD/rosette to continue the long-term time series started in 2003. Samples that provide information on longer time-scales, such as CFCs and carbon tetrachloride, alkalinity, total CO2, dissolved inorganic carbon, and tritium/3He, will be collected less frequently. Expendable CTDs that profile to 1100 m depth will be used between CTD/rosette casts to increase spatial resolution of the temperature and salinity fields. The project will be coordinated with other elements of the National Science Foundation?s Arctic Observing Network to enhance effectiveness and interconnections of observational activities, and the field program will continue to accommodate other National Science foundation- funded projects when possible. Data will be available on the project website and at the National Science Foundation's Arctic Data Center.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1719280</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Proshutinsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrey Proshutinsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aproshutinsky@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5082892796</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000472837</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Krishfield</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard A Krishfield</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rkrishfield@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5082892849</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000107567</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<ZipCode>025431535</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082892623</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>266 Wood Hole Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Fenno House, MS#39]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001766682</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WOODS HOLE OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTITUTION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001766682</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution]]></Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>025431535</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[266 Woods Hole Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5293</Code>
<Text>AON-Arctic Observing Network</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~1579287</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Beaufort Gyre (BG) is one of the Arctic Ocean's main dynamical sea-ice and ocean circulation systems, its major freshwater reservoir, and a centerpiece for Arctic and global change. From 2003 to 2019 (seventeen years the Beaufort Gyre Observing System (BGOS) lifetime) freshwater content in this region has increased almost 40%, and there has been an alarming doubling in upper-ocean heat content. These changes have critical consequences for Arctic sea-ice and climate. Physical changes have been accompanied by fundamental biogeochemical changes, including ocean acidification and transformations in food-web structure. Understanding the evolution and fate of BG freshwater and heat content, and the biogeochemical change underway in the system, requires the continuous measurements of environmental parameters of the Beaufort Gyre system in the same uninterrupted manner and at the same sustained locations. Data returned from BGOS, distributed freely via the project website and archived with the NSF Arctic Data Center advances understanding of the physical, chemical, and biological drivers of environmental change in the Arctic, their relationship to the climate system, and their linkages to global processes. The BGOS ocean moorings sample seawater properties and sea-ice to resolve sub-daily to interannual variability. Annual ship-based ocean sampling, in collaboration with Canadian scientists, augment the year-round mooring measurements. Project activities are coordinated with the broader research community through conference special sessions and workshops, and special volume issues of publications. Educational broader impacts include training of students, providing them with the opportunity to participate in BGOS expeditions and advising them in BGOS data analysis. The project website unifies all program activities, providing visitors access to the full set of BGOS data and expedition information, as well as educational project context and historical information on Arctic exploration and discovery.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/16/2020<br>      Modified by: Andrey&nbsp;Proshutinsky</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Beaufort Gyre (BG) is one of the Arctic Ocean's main dynamical sea-ice and ocean circulation systems, its major freshwater reservoir, and a centerpiece for Arctic and global change. From 2003 to 2019 (seventeen years the Beaufort Gyre Observing System (BGOS) lifetime) freshwater content in this region has increased almost 40%, and there has been an alarming doubling in upper-ocean heat content. These changes have critical consequences for Arctic sea-ice and climate. Physical changes have been accompanied by fundamental biogeochemical changes, including ocean acidification and transformations in food-web structure. Understanding the evolution and fate of BG freshwater and heat content, and the biogeochemical change underway in the system, requires the continuous measurements of environmental parameters of the Beaufort Gyre system in the same uninterrupted manner and at the same sustained locations. Data returned from BGOS, distributed freely via the project website and archived with the NSF Arctic Data Center advances understanding of the physical, chemical, and biological drivers of environmental change in the Arctic, their relationship to the climate system, and their linkages to global processes. The BGOS ocean moorings sample seawater properties and sea-ice to resolve sub-daily to interannual variability. Annual ship-based ocean sampling, in collaboration with Canadian scientists, augment the year-round mooring measurements. Project activities are coordinated with the broader research community through conference special sessions and workshops, and special volume issues of publications. Educational broader impacts include training of students, providing them with the opportunity to participate in BGOS expeditions and advising them in BGOS data analysis. The project website unifies all program activities, providing visitors access to the full set of BGOS data and expedition information, as well as educational project context and historical information on Arctic exploration and discovery.       Last Modified: 12/16/2020       Submitted by: Andrey Proshutinsky]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
