<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Effects of Ammonia on the Chemical and Physical Properties of Atmospheric Secondary Organic Aerosol</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>335713.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>363345</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020104</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Edgerton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sedgerto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928522</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will investigate the effects of ammonia on the chemical and physical properties of small particles in the atmosphere.  It will also look at the effects of ammonia on brown carbon in the atmosphere.  The approach will combine ambient measurements, 3-D chemical transport modeling, and the analysis of past field campaign data. This work will provide important insight into the sources and formation processes of secondary organic aerosol, critical for a better understanding of both air quality and climate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives of the proposal are to: (1) Characterize the effects of NH3 on the concentration and reversible/irreversible nature of aqueous SOA (aqSOA); (2) Characterize the effect of NH3 on atmospheric BrC formation; and (3) Determine the spatial and temporal scales of the NH3 impacts on aqSOA and BrC formation.  The two processes that will be evaluated include aqueous reactions that are either catalyzed by or directly involve NH4 and represent a significant source of highly oxidized, lower-volatility SOA, and the reaction of NH4 with organic compounds and the production of SOA that may be light-absorbing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ambient measurements will be made at an urban site in the eastern U.S. that is heavily influenced by biogenic VOC emissions, mobile sources, and regional NH3 emissions from agriculture.  Modeling studies, using WRF-CMAQ, will provide an analysis of temporal and spatial variability in the NH3 effects on SOA and BrC formation and the impacts on air quality and climate.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1719252</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Hennigan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher Hennigan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hennigan@umbc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4104553515</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000645394</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland Baltimore County</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212500002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4104553140</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 Hilltop Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>061364808</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND BALTIMORE COUNTY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland Baltimore County]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212500002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>Atmospheric Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~335713</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~27632</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Atmospheric particles, or aerosols, exert important effects on Earth?s climate system by scattering and absorbing incoming solar radiation and by controlling key properties of clouds (e.g., cloud lifetime and brightness).&nbsp; Aerosols also impart detrimental effects on human health.&nbsp; Aerosols have diverse chemical compositions, but almost always contain a complex mixture of organics, most of which are secondary (that is, they are formed in the atmosphere from the reaction of gaseous precursors).&nbsp; Ammonia, the most abundant basic compound in the atmosphere, plays a critical role in secondary aerosol formation and can affect aerosol optical properties.&nbsp; The objective of this collaborative proposal was to characterize the role of ammonia in forming secondary organic aerosols (SOA).&nbsp; We focused on SOA formed through the uptake of soluble organics to the liquid water contained in clouds, fog, and aqueous particles.&nbsp; We set out to characterize processes in the ambient atmosphere that laboratory studies had previously identified as important.&nbsp; This work involved a combination of chemical transport modeling, highly time-resolved atmospheric measurements, and laboratory analysis of cloud water samples.&nbsp; A number of key project outcomes were achieved:</p> <p>Light-absorbing organic compounds, collectively called brown carbon (BrC), can form efficiently in the aqueous phase.&nbsp; We found that drying aqueous particles in the eastern U.S. did not lead to enhancements in aerosol BrC concentrations, a result that was consistent in measurements across multiple seasons.&nbsp; We also found that drying cloud water (collected at Whiteface Mountain, NY) did not lead to production of BrC either.&nbsp; In both cases, low concentrations of water-soluble BrC precursors, such as glyoxal and methylglyoxal, is the likely reason we did not observe a phenomenon that has been widely reported in prior laboratory studies.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>We carried out different modeling analyses to characterize the importance of liquid water in aerosol formation across the U.S.&nbsp; We found that biogenic SOA is strongly affected by SO<sub>2</sub> emissions from electricity generation and NO<sub>x</sub> from mobile sources when an aerosol liquid water pathway is included in SOA formation.&nbsp; We also found that filter sampling protocols to remove aerosol liquid water cause biases in the measurements of PM mass (a criteria pollutant regulated by the EPA) due to both residual water and the evaporation of semi-volatile components, a phenomenon that affects most measurement sites in the contiguous U.S.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>We carried out measurements of gas and particle-phase species at a land-water transition site as part of the second Ozone Water-Land Environmental Transition Study (OWLETS-2).&nbsp; We observed gas-phase ammonia concentrations that were significantly higher than a nearby inland site.&nbsp; The highest ammonia concentrations appear to originate from agricultural operations in southern PA and the Delmarva peninsula (<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Del</span>aware-<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Mar</span>yland-<span style="text-decoration: underline;">V</span>irgini<span style="text-decoration: underline;">a</span>). &nbsp;Such an influence from reginal agricultural sources was expected because it is the dominant ammonia source globally; however, we also identified multiple events that appear to originate near downtown Baltimore, though the precise industrial source was unknown.&nbsp; The high ammonia concentrations enhanced formation of ammonium nitrate aerosol, which was much higher than expected, especially during the warmer summer months.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Overall, our results have advanced understanding of aerosol processes and the human activities that alter aerosol abundances in the atmosphere.&nbsp; This project supported two PhD students, one postdoctoral researcher, and numerous undergraduates.&nbsp; The project resulted in seven peer-reviewed publications, and more than 15 presentations at national conferences. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/04/2021<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;Hennigan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Atmospheric particles, or aerosols, exert important effects on Earth?s climate system by scattering and absorbing incoming solar radiation and by controlling key properties of clouds (e.g., cloud lifetime and brightness).  Aerosols also impart detrimental effects on human health.  Aerosols have diverse chemical compositions, but almost always contain a complex mixture of organics, most of which are secondary (that is, they are formed in the atmosphere from the reaction of gaseous precursors).  Ammonia, the most abundant basic compound in the atmosphere, plays a critical role in secondary aerosol formation and can affect aerosol optical properties.  The objective of this collaborative proposal was to characterize the role of ammonia in forming secondary organic aerosols (SOA).  We focused on SOA formed through the uptake of soluble organics to the liquid water contained in clouds, fog, and aqueous particles.  We set out to characterize processes in the ambient atmosphere that laboratory studies had previously identified as important.  This work involved a combination of chemical transport modeling, highly time-resolved atmospheric measurements, and laboratory analysis of cloud water samples.  A number of key project outcomes were achieved:  Light-absorbing organic compounds, collectively called brown carbon (BrC), can form efficiently in the aqueous phase.  We found that drying aqueous particles in the eastern U.S. did not lead to enhancements in aerosol BrC concentrations, a result that was consistent in measurements across multiple seasons.  We also found that drying cloud water (collected at Whiteface Mountain, NY) did not lead to production of BrC either.  In both cases, low concentrations of water-soluble BrC precursors, such as glyoxal and methylglyoxal, is the likely reason we did not observe a phenomenon that has been widely reported in prior laboratory studies.     We carried out different modeling analyses to characterize the importance of liquid water in aerosol formation across the U.S.  We found that biogenic SOA is strongly affected by SO2 emissions from electricity generation and NOx from mobile sources when an aerosol liquid water pathway is included in SOA formation.  We also found that filter sampling protocols to remove aerosol liquid water cause biases in the measurements of PM mass (a criteria pollutant regulated by the EPA) due to both residual water and the evaporation of semi-volatile components, a phenomenon that affects most measurement sites in the contiguous U.S.       We carried out measurements of gas and particle-phase species at a land-water transition site as part of the second Ozone Water-Land Environmental Transition Study (OWLETS-2).  We observed gas-phase ammonia concentrations that were significantly higher than a nearby inland site.  The highest ammonia concentrations appear to originate from agricultural operations in southern PA and the Delmarva peninsula (Delaware-Maryland-Virginia).  Such an influence from reginal agricultural sources was expected because it is the dominant ammonia source globally; however, we also identified multiple events that appear to originate near downtown Baltimore, though the precise industrial source was unknown.  The high ammonia concentrations enhanced formation of ammonium nitrate aerosol, which was much higher than expected, especially during the warmer summer months.    Overall, our results have advanced understanding of aerosol processes and the human activities that alter aerosol abundances in the atmosphere.  This project supported two PhD students, one postdoctoral researcher, and numerous undergraduates.  The project resulted in seven peer-reviewed publications, and more than 15 presentations at national conferences.              Last Modified: 08/04/2021       Submitted by: Christopher Hennigan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
