<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Travel Support for Young Topologists Meeting - Stockholm, Sweden - July 2017</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>snaik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This travel grant provides partial support for U.S. participation in the Young Topologists Meeting 2017, held in Stockholm, Sweden by the Royal Institute of Technology and Stockholm University, July 3rd-7th, 2017. The Young Topologists Meeting (YTM) is an annual European conference focused on the work of graduate students and young researchers in topology that brings in participants from all over the world. At the YTM, junior topologists present their work to a large international audience, and also attend mini-courses taught by senior topologists. The conference provides opportunities for the participants to meet new colleagues and mentors, to learn about current progress of researchers in their fields, and to form research collaborations. Its open and supportive atmosphere encourages young mathematicians, including those from underrepresented groups, to pursue research careers in topology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The YTM is an annual event, first started in 2007, which traditionally alternates between Copenhagen, Denmark and Lausanne, Switzerland until 2017 when it will be hosted in Stockholm, Sweden. The conference features parallel sessions of contributed talks by graduate students and young researchers, covering a broad spectrum of topics in topology. In addition to these talks, there will be mini-courses by two senior topologists, focusing in particular on techniques that expose underlying structure and connections in algebraic topology and in general on new applications, avenues of research, and open problems. This year the mini-courses will be on group homology and stability ("Topology interacting with number theory, representation theory, and algebraic geometry") and on the comparison of the differential graded world and spectra ("The equivalence of differential graded modules and HZ-module spectra, applications, and generalizations").  More details are available on the conference web page: &lt;br/&gt;https://www.math-stockholm.se/konferenser-och-akti/young-topologists-meeting-2017-1.670396</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/25/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1719564</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Yeakel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah Yeakel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sarah.yeakel@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7345523491</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000737688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~25000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 2017 Young Topologist Meeting was held July 3-7 in Stockholm, Sweden at the main campus of KTH Royal Institute of Technology. The Young Topologists Meeting (YTM) is an annual conference focusing on the scientific work of graduate students and young researchers in topology. It is the largest annual conference for young topologists in Europe, hosting a total of 167 participants in 2017. The funds from the NSF travel grant were used to support the travel and accommodation for 18 participants from US institutions, helping them&nbsp;to connect with an international community of their peers, exchange knowledge, and broaden each other's horizons. In the effort to bring more diversity to the field of topology, it was decided to prioritize funding the travel of underrepresented groups in mathematics, resulting in the support of ten (of the 18 supported participants) who identify as women/genderqueer.</p> <p>The conference featured two plenary speakers who are senior researchers, Brooke Shipley (University of Illinois Chicago) and Benson Farb (University of Chicago), who gave minicourses on connections of topology with other areas of mathematics including number theory, representation theory, algebraic geometry, and differential graded algebra. The talks focused on current research, new results, and open questions in the field of topology with fruitful applications.</p> <p>A major outcome of the conference is the many contributed talks by young researchers (predominantly graduate students),&nbsp;giving junior participants an opportunity to present their research to their peers and make connections with future colleagues. Of the 49 contributed talks, ten were supported by this NSF grant. The YTM&nbsp;gives the speakers an ideal setting in which to present their work to a large audience, often for the first time, and it also helps young researchers find mentors outside their existing circles.&nbsp;</p> <p>The conference website can be found at https://www.math-stockholm.se/en/konferenser-och-akti/young-topologists-meeting-2017-1.670396.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;Yeakel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 2017 Young Topologist Meeting was held July 3-7 in Stockholm, Sweden at the main campus of KTH Royal Institute of Technology. The Young Topologists Meeting (YTM) is an annual conference focusing on the scientific work of graduate students and young researchers in topology. It is the largest annual conference for young topologists in Europe, hosting a total of 167 participants in 2017. The funds from the NSF travel grant were used to support the travel and accommodation for 18 participants from US institutions, helping them to connect with an international community of their peers, exchange knowledge, and broaden each other's horizons. In the effort to bring more diversity to the field of topology, it was decided to prioritize funding the travel of underrepresented groups in mathematics, resulting in the support of ten (of the 18 supported participants) who identify as women/genderqueer.  The conference featured two plenary speakers who are senior researchers, Brooke Shipley (University of Illinois Chicago) and Benson Farb (University of Chicago), who gave minicourses on connections of topology with other areas of mathematics including number theory, representation theory, algebraic geometry, and differential graded algebra. The talks focused on current research, new results, and open questions in the field of topology with fruitful applications.  A major outcome of the conference is the many contributed talks by young researchers (predominantly graduate students), giving junior participants an opportunity to present their research to their peers and make connections with future colleagues. Of the 49 contributed talks, ten were supported by this NSF grant. The YTM gives the speakers an ideal setting in which to present their work to a large audience, often for the first time, and it also helps young researchers find mentors outside their existing circles.   The conference website can be found at https://www.math-stockholm.se/en/konferenser-och-akti/young-topologists-meeting-2017-1.670396.          Last Modified: 08/07/2018       Submitted by: Sarah Yeakel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
