<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Blue light emitting antimicrobial bandage</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is based on reduction of catheter-related infections and associated healthcare costs. Central line associated blood stream infections (CLABSI) are extremely dangerous and are associated with significant morbidity, mortality, and cost. Patients with catheters are significantly more likely to develop an infection than those without a catheter. With an average cost of approximately $45k per patient, CLABSI are the most expensive hospital associated infection to treat. Hospitals spend an estimated $1.38 billion treating inpatient infections due to central lines, and Medicare and insurance companies spend an additional $1.7 billion treating outpatient infections from central line catheters in dialysis patients. More broadly, market opportunities for the technology include: sterilization of urinary tract catheters, prevention of catheter based infections in multi-trauma patients such as military personnel, and wound infection treatment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project will evaluate the commercial potential for an antimicrobial wound dressing that exploits the bactericidal effect of blue light to inactivate bacteria commonly colonizing the surface of catheters. The light-emitting catheter dressing is designed to be easily integrated with current standards of care to reduce central line associated blood stream infections. Blue light activates photosensitizers in bacteria, which release reactive oxygen species that are highly cytotoxic by damage of proteins and DNA. Blue light is significantly less harmful to mammalian cells as compared to ultraviolet irradiation, which is commonly used for disinfection of medical facilities, medical devices, water and food. Increasing rates of bacterial resistance indicate the need for infection treatment methods that do not require the use drugs. This device would be marketed to hospitals to reduce cost and patient morbidity and mortality.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1720693</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristen</FirstName>
<LastName>Maitland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristen C Maitland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kmaitland@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9794587617</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000601144</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>847205572</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433120</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3120 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project, the NSF I-Corps: Blue light emitting antimicrobial bandage, 113 customer interviews were performed, providing a strong understanding of the problems hospitals face in preventing healthcare associate infections (HAIs) and how to commercialize our technology to implement clinical solutions.&nbsp; These interviews revealed the growing prevalence of multidrug-resistant organisms (MDROs) were contributing to these infections; however, the lack of hospital staff compliance to infection prevention protocols was also a major contributor to the occurrence of HAIs. These customer discovery interviews revealed that a solution would need to be easily incorporated into standard protocols without negatively affecting the nurses&rsquo; workflow while improving accountability.</p> <p>This project began with the intended clinical use of the technology for addressing and preventing central line associated bloodstream infections (CLABSIs). &nbsp;However, through the rigorous I-Corps process and customer discovery interviews, we determined that the market for commercialization of this antimicrobial blue light technology was larger than solely addressing CLABSIs, and would best be introduced and designed as an infection prevention product for surgical site infections (SSIs). Due to this discovery of shifting the use of this technology for SSI prevention, it provided a clear pathway for device development and user needs.</p> <p>In the interviews, multiple hospitals expressed that they evaluate products such as ours on a value-based approach and would be willing to pay as much as the value our product provides in patient outcomes. In the customer interviews, multiple hospitals stated that preventing one SSI can be worth more than $100,000 in cost-savings to a hospital. Some of the outcomes of this project were having multiple hospital systems such as Memorial Hermann, Baylor Scott and White Health, Texas Health Resources, Texas Back Institute, and CHI, being interested in coordinating clinical studies with our team to ultimately integrate this technology and device into their infection prevention protocol hospital system-wide.</p> <p>The impact the results from this project are likely to make beyond the bounds of science, engineering, and the academic world, are its impact on society as a whole and healthcare as an industry. The findings made in this project are likely to provide the justification for businesses to develop products utilizing antimicrobial blue light for use in healthcare for prevention and treatment of infections. This technology and the project&rsquo;s findings provide a novel approach to addressing the antibiotic resistance crisis we are currently in. This provides a technology that can kill bacteria including drug-resistant organisms, and can do so in a way that does not increase resistance, while being easily integrated into clinical protocols. It is a sustainable approach to combating the antibiotic resistance crisis both in a technology and as a business.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/29/2018<br>      Modified by: Kristen&nbsp;C&nbsp;Maitland</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project, the NSF I-Corps: Blue light emitting antimicrobial bandage, 113 customer interviews were performed, providing a strong understanding of the problems hospitals face in preventing healthcare associate infections (HAIs) and how to commercialize our technology to implement clinical solutions.  These interviews revealed the growing prevalence of multidrug-resistant organisms (MDROs) were contributing to these infections; however, the lack of hospital staff compliance to infection prevention protocols was also a major contributor to the occurrence of HAIs. These customer discovery interviews revealed that a solution would need to be easily incorporated into standard protocols without negatively affecting the nurses? workflow while improving accountability.  This project began with the intended clinical use of the technology for addressing and preventing central line associated bloodstream infections (CLABSIs).  However, through the rigorous I-Corps process and customer discovery interviews, we determined that the market for commercialization of this antimicrobial blue light technology was larger than solely addressing CLABSIs, and would best be introduced and designed as an infection prevention product for surgical site infections (SSIs). Due to this discovery of shifting the use of this technology for SSI prevention, it provided a clear pathway for device development and user needs.  In the interviews, multiple hospitals expressed that they evaluate products such as ours on a value-based approach and would be willing to pay as much as the value our product provides in patient outcomes. In the customer interviews, multiple hospitals stated that preventing one SSI can be worth more than $100,000 in cost-savings to a hospital. Some of the outcomes of this project were having multiple hospital systems such as Memorial Hermann, Baylor Scott and White Health, Texas Health Resources, Texas Back Institute, and CHI, being interested in coordinating clinical studies with our team to ultimately integrate this technology and device into their infection prevention protocol hospital system-wide.  The impact the results from this project are likely to make beyond the bounds of science, engineering, and the academic world, are its impact on society as a whole and healthcare as an industry. The findings made in this project are likely to provide the justification for businesses to develop products utilizing antimicrobial blue light for use in healthcare for prevention and treatment of infections. This technology and the project?s findings provide a novel approach to addressing the antibiotic resistance crisis we are currently in. This provides a technology that can kill bacteria including drug-resistant organisms, and can do so in a way that does not increase resistance, while being easily integrated into clinical protocols. It is a sustainable approach to combating the antibiotic resistance crisis both in a technology and as a business.          Last Modified: 04/29/2018       Submitted by: Kristen C Maitland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
