<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Semiclassical Approach to Classical Simulation of Quantum Annealers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>290000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>290000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Cronin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>acronin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Quantum mechanics governs the behavior of the microscopic world, and its rules are very different from the laws of physics that are most familiar from everyday life. A scientific challenge of the 21st century is to harness the unique features of quantum mechanics for new technologies. For example, a computer that works on the basis of quantum logic would offer speed-ups and other advantages when compared with familiar classical computers, at least for some nearly intractable computational problems. Another type of machine called a quantum annealer can be used to solve optimization problems. While not a full-fledged quantum computer, a quantum annealer uses tunneling and entanglement during its operation, and its advantages over conventional machines is a topic of much current research. This project will attempt to show that the restrictions present in current quantum annealers mean that these machines are not yet sufficiently quantum mechanical to provide a fundamental computational advantage over conventional computation methods. If successful, this work will make clear that proposed modifications to current annealers, which are technologically feasible, are necessary for these devices to provide useful improvements over conventional computing approaches. If this claim is not proven, this work may provide insights into when current quantum annealers can be expected to outperform conventional computers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Quantum computation promises advantages over classical computation for certain problems. However, the experimental obstacles to the construction of a large scale quantum computer are formidable. Quantum annealing is an intermediate approach to obtaining some quantum advantage, and over the last decade it has been implemented on a reasonably large scale. Quantum annealers solve optimization problems, and there is experimental evidence for quantum effects such as tunneling and entanglement during their operation. A general theory of when these machines provide a quantum advantage is absent, but because of the existence of actual hardware a large body of empirical knowledge is accumulating about their operation. This work will address whether they can provide a uniquely quantum advantage over classical approaches. The project will address the following question for quantum annealers: Is there a local hidden variable theory that describes the operation of all current quantum annealing hardware?  Theoretical tools to address this question include Wigner functions for discrete systems that give a description in terms of quasi-probabilities that sum to one, but which may be negative. When all the quasi-probabilities associated with states, operations and measurements are positive, the system admits a completely classical hidden variable description. This team will investigate whether such a positive, classical description can be accurate for quantum annealers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1720395</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Love</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Love</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>peter.love@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176271065</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000082471</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tufts University</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>021111817</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176273696</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>136 Harrison Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073134835</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF TUFTS COLLEGE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073134835</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tufts University]]></Name>
<CityName>Medford</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021555807</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[574 Boston Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7281</Code>
<Text>QIS - Quantum Information Scie</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~105201</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~184799</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Quantum computers are a promising new technology for the solution of problems in several specialized areas, including quantum chemistry and materials science. Realizing the full power of quantum computation requires error correction, and current quantum computers do not posess this error correction technology. Hence, the power of existing quantum computers is limited by uncontrolled interactions with the outside world. To date, no existing quantum computers have displayed any advantage for any practical problem.&nbsp;<br /><br />Two main types of quantum computer exist today. The first are quantum annealers, which use the lowest energy states of engineered superconducting quantum systems to represent very difficult problems. The output of these quantum annealers give approximations to the solutions to the problems programmed into the annealer. These quantum annealers have reached very large sizes (currently 5000 qubits), but only realize limited operations and can only be applied to a subset of problems addressable by quantum computation.</p> <p>The second type of quantum computer are noisy intermediate scale quantum (NISQ) computers. These are made with the same approach that can eventually realize error corrected quantum computation and operate by executing discrete quantum operations (quantum gates) that realize a quantum computer program (quantum circuit). The largest NISQ devices in 2021 still have fewer than 100 quantum bits and can execute only a few thousand quantum gates.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p><br />These two forms of nascent quantum technology have been the subject of extensive scientific investigation. The goal of the project "<span>Semiclassical Approach to Classical Simulation of Quantum Annealers</span>" was to apply or extend techniques of so-called semi-classical physics to understand the quantum nature, or lack thereof of such quantum technology. The early focus of the project was quantum annealers but the project also considered NISQ devices as they became more prominent in the field.<br /><br />Semiclassical physics has a history extending back to before quantum mechanics was a fully formed subject. The so-called old quantum mechanics that predated Schroedinger and Heisenberg providing a full definition of the theory contains many ideas that live half in the world of Newton and half in the world of the new atomic phenomena that drove the development of quantum mechanics at the beginning of the last century.<br /><br />In this project we considered two main notions of semiclassicality. The first is the quasi-probability function, or Wigner function representation of quantum mechanics. Quantum states differ from classical probabilities. Classical probabilities for a finite set of outcomes must be positive, be less than one, and sum to one. The probabilities associated with rolling a particular total on a pair of dice are a typical example. Quantum states instead use numbers that are not positive, and may be complex numbers involving the square root of minus 1. Quasi probabilities make quantum states as similar to probability distributions as possible. Howeever, quasiprobabilities can be negative. These quasiprobabilitoes have been widely used in semiclassical physics and in quantum optics. In this project we wanted to analyze quantum annealers, and later NISQ devices.<br /><br />We accomplished several goals during this project. Firstly we made several connections between the "old" semiclassical theories and theories of quantum bits and gates. We showed that contextuality, a measure of how "quantum" a system is, is closely related to the way that quantumness is evaluated in semiclassical physics. We showed how to define quasiprobabilty representations of qubit systems using so-called Grassman variables. We extended several existing techniques for simulating quantum computers using classical computers. We also were able to adapt a powerful technique of semiclassical analysis, the stationary phase method, to the analysis of quantum circuits.&nbsp;In related work on NISQ devices we also invented a test to see when a particular type of NISQ computation is truly quantum and when it can be thought of in purely classical terms.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;Broader Impacts</p> <p>Classical simulation techniques for quantum technology are important because of the need to verify and understand new quantum computer systems. They also help clarify when such quantum computers can be useful for solving problems - and when they are equivalent to classical computation. This project funded the completion of one PhD and one postdoc.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/27/2021<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;Love</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Quantum computers are a promising new technology for the solution of problems in several specialized areas, including quantum chemistry and materials science. Realizing the full power of quantum computation requires error correction, and current quantum computers do not posess this error correction technology. Hence, the power of existing quantum computers is limited by uncontrolled interactions with the outside world. To date, no existing quantum computers have displayed any advantage for any practical problem.   Two main types of quantum computer exist today. The first are quantum annealers, which use the lowest energy states of engineered superconducting quantum systems to represent very difficult problems. The output of these quantum annealers give approximations to the solutions to the problems programmed into the annealer. These quantum annealers have reached very large sizes (currently 5000 qubits), but only realize limited operations and can only be applied to a subset of problems addressable by quantum computation.  The second type of quantum computer are noisy intermediate scale quantum (NISQ) computers. These are made with the same approach that can eventually realize error corrected quantum computation and operate by executing discrete quantum operations (quantum gates) that realize a quantum computer program (quantum circuit). The largest NISQ devices in 2021 still have fewer than 100 quantum bits and can execute only a few thousand quantum gates.     Intellectual Merit   These two forms of nascent quantum technology have been the subject of extensive scientific investigation. The goal of the project "Semiclassical Approach to Classical Simulation of Quantum Annealers" was to apply or extend techniques of so-called semi-classical physics to understand the quantum nature, or lack thereof of such quantum technology. The early focus of the project was quantum annealers but the project also considered NISQ devices as they became more prominent in the field.  Semiclassical physics has a history extending back to before quantum mechanics was a fully formed subject. The so-called old quantum mechanics that predated Schroedinger and Heisenberg providing a full definition of the theory contains many ideas that live half in the world of Newton and half in the world of the new atomic phenomena that drove the development of quantum mechanics at the beginning of the last century.  In this project we considered two main notions of semiclassicality. The first is the quasi-probability function, or Wigner function representation of quantum mechanics. Quantum states differ from classical probabilities. Classical probabilities for a finite set of outcomes must be positive, be less than one, and sum to one. The probabilities associated with rolling a particular total on a pair of dice are a typical example. Quantum states instead use numbers that are not positive, and may be complex numbers involving the square root of minus 1. Quasi probabilities make quantum states as similar to probability distributions as possible. Howeever, quasiprobabilities can be negative. These quasiprobabilitoes have been widely used in semiclassical physics and in quantum optics. In this project we wanted to analyze quantum annealers, and later NISQ devices.  We accomplished several goals during this project. Firstly we made several connections between the "old" semiclassical theories and theories of quantum bits and gates. We showed that contextuality, a measure of how "quantum" a system is, is closely related to the way that quantumness is evaluated in semiclassical physics. We showed how to define quasiprobabilty representations of qubit systems using so-called Grassman variables. We extended several existing techniques for simulating quantum computers using classical computers. We also were able to adapt a powerful technique of semiclassical analysis, the stationary phase method, to the analysis of quantum circuits. In related work on NISQ devices we also invented a test to see when a particular type of NISQ computation is truly quantum and when it can be thought of in purely classical terms.    Broader Impacts  Classical simulation techniques for quantum technology are important because of the need to verify and understand new quantum computer systems. They also help clarify when such quantum computers can be useful for solving problems - and when they are equivalent to classical computation. This project funded the completion of one PhD and one postdoc.                Last Modified: 05/27/2021       Submitted by: Peter Love]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
