<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Testing the Chert Sourcing Application of Reflectance Spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>186297.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>186297</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Drs. Ryan M. Parish and Dr. David H. Dye, of the University of Memphis and collaborator Dr. Haluk Cetin from Murray State University are investigating the application of reflectance spectroscopy in studying prehistoric use of stone resources to determine the geographic source of artifacts recovered in archaeological sites. The researchers' broad goals are to understand past resource consumption in order to better contextualize the present use of natural resources.  The structure provided by studying past adaptation to finite resources directly provides modern societies with a basis for current resource strategies and sustainable practices.  The researchers are building upon previous studies demonstrating the wealth of cultural data gained by sourcing stone resources and the need to do so with greater precision.  Accurate source data allows archaeologists to understand prehistoric procurement, selection, consumption, organization, technology, social networking, and adaptation to dwindling resources.  The application of reflectance spectroscopy in archaeological sourcing studies will provide an increased ability to identify specific exploited deposits.  The reflectance data paired with existing geologic spectral databases will allow researchers to link stone molecular and mineral variation with the geologic processes that formed the deposit, the theoretical framework of all sourcing studies.  The project provides funding for one graduate student in addition to providing training for undergraduate archaeology and anthropology majors at the University of Memphis.  Instrumentation will establish a hyperspectral provenance lab at the University of Memphis providing contract services in both the public and private sectors.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Parish and colleagues will focus on the broader development of reflectance spectroscopy in archaeological source studies.  A specific focus of the study will be on the geologic characterization of multiple deposits of chert/flint known to have been exploited in prehistory.  Linking variation with how the deposit formed is crucial in matching artifacts back to their respected sources.  Reflectance spectroscopy is a technique well suited to addressing very sensitive geologic information through the analysis of atomic and molecular structure relating to composition.  Whereas, the large amount of chemical variation in chert/flint has frustrated the majority of previous studies, the successful ability to characterize variation will lead to a greater understanding of prehistoric stone resource consumption</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1720376</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Dye</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David H Dye</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daviddye@memphis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9016783330</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000349103</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Parish</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan M Parish</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rmparish@memphis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9016782606</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000589950</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Memphis</Name>
<CityName>Memphis</CityName>
<ZipCode>381523370</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9016783251</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Administration 315</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>055688857</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MEMPHIS, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>878135631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Memphis]]></Name>
<CityName>Memphis</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>381523370</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1393</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOMETRY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1393</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOMETRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~186297</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Archaeology seeks to reconstruct and understand the lives of past peoples.&nbsp; Stone artifacts preserve and understanding where and how people got stone resources is crucial.&nbsp; Studying how prehistoric people used finite resources such as stone benefits current society as we deal with resource overexploitation, social networking for critical resources, and the effects of climate change on resource decisions.&nbsp; The study tested the ability of reflectance spectroscopy on identify chert/flint sources used to make stone tools.&nbsp; Reflectance spectroscopy gathers the interaction of radiation (light) with matter at the atomic and molecular level.&nbsp; An object&rsquo;s composition determines these interactions and is different depending on what the object is made of as well as other characteristics. The study of the decisions and strategies regarding where prehistoric people got their stone resources can help us by providing a deep time perspective.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Goals</strong></p> <p>The primary goal of the study was to test the ability of reflectance spectroscopy as a non-destructive, fast, low-cost, and accurate method.&nbsp; Previous research on identifying chert resources has been limited in most of these areas.&nbsp; The second goal of the study was to add to the existing large &lsquo;library&rsquo; of chert geologic samples. This database is necessary as a reference of known sources with which to compare artifacts within.&nbsp; To achieve these goals analysis of over 6,000 chert samples from the Western, Midwestern, and Southern United States were conducted.&nbsp; Also, independent experiments were preformed that looked at the effects of outer surface weathering and thermal alteration had on the results.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Outcomes</strong></p> <p>Reflectance spectroscopy was shown through multiple applications to be a fast, accurate, low cost, and non-destructive method to identify the source of stone artifacts made from chert/flint.&nbsp; In past studies, archaeologists have only sought to identify the type of chert, meaning what geologic parent formation the resource came from.&nbsp; This is sometimes problematic as the formations containing chert are often extensive.&nbsp; Reflectance spectroscopy was repeatedly able to separate different chert types and outcrops.&nbsp; What this means is that we can source an artifact back to the spot on the landscape where prehistoric people got the material not just the general region.&nbsp; Severe outer surface weathering on some artifacts appear to affect the accuracy of the technique in the visible part of the spectrum though the data in the near and middle infrared regions is not greatly altered. &nbsp;The heating of artifacts in ancient fires or modern appear to not affect the accuracy of reflectance spectroscopy in identifying the chert source.&nbsp;&nbsp; What this means is that it is always important as a researcher to know the context of the artifacts you are analyzing and the processes that have affected them over time.&nbsp; The library of chert geologic samples making up the extensive reference collection consists of 6,660 samples from 222 deposits across much of the continental United States, Chile, Argentina, Poland, and Hungary.&nbsp; The results of the analysis of this reference collection consistently demonstrate that reflectance spectroscopy is able to source chert artifacts.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Applications</strong></p> <p>The project established a reflectance spectroscopy lab at the University of Memphis, trained 30 undergraduate students in the use of the techniques, four graduate students, one international researcher, and added to one of the largest chert/flint reference libraries in the world.&nbsp; Results of the project have been presented at 17 professional conferences with three additional presentations planned, published in 11 peer reviewed journal articles and book chapters, and has contributed to 10 national and three international studies.&nbsp; Exciting and ongoing research include the analysis of flint from Poland used by Neolithic and Mesolithic hunter-gatherers, studying chert resource selection by Archaic communities in the Atacama Desert, Chile, and examining hunter-gatherer selection of quartzite in the Pampas region of Argentina.&nbsp; International colleagues are also using the techniques in southern Germany.&nbsp; At the University of Memphis, we are currently studying how Hopewell communities in Ohio close to 2,000 years ago deposited 10,000 plus chert disks in a burial mound.&nbsp; Also, we are investigating where people at the Poverty Point, Louisiana got their rock from in an area without nearby chert resources.&nbsp; Recently, we are using reflectance spectroscopy to analyze large caches of 6,000 year old spear points in Mississippi, studying the stone source for 450 wood working tools dating to the Woodland Period from Indiana, and differentiating 10,000 plus year old Ice Age quarry sites along the Savanna River, South Carolina.&nbsp; Source data is also giving us a better understanding of Ice Age hunter-gatherer mobility along the Tennessee River.&nbsp; Through the continued use of reflectance spectroscopy in sourcing chert/flint resources used by prehistoric peoples we will gain a greater understanding for how they lived, how they used their finite resources, and how shifting social networks, climate change, and other factors affected them.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/11/2021<br>      Modified by: Ryan&nbsp;M&nbsp;Parish</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628696104306_DFAscatterplots,geologicsamples--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628696104306_DFAscatterplots,geologicsamples--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Chile research"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628696104306_DFAscatterplots,geologicsamples--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Chile research"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Scatter plots of geologic chert samples from Chile showing clear differentiation of the soures used by Archaic hunter-gatherers.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ryan M. Parish</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ryan&nbsp;M&nbsp;Parish</div> <div class="imageTitle">Chile research</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628694148786_DSC_0072--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628694148786_DSC_0072--rgov-800width.jpg" title="VNIR spectrometer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628694148786_DSC_0072--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="VNIR spectrometer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">VNIR spectrometer in laboratory configuration.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ryan M. Parish</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ryan&nbsp;M&nbsp;Parish</div> <div class="imageTitle">VNIR spectrometer</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628694252384_DSC_0075--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628694252384_DSC_0075--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FTIR spectrometer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628694252384_DSC_0075--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FTIR spectrometer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">FTIR spectrometer which collects spectral data in the middle infrared.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ryan M. Parish</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ryan&nbsp;M&nbsp;Parish</div> <div class="imageTitle">FTIR spectrometer</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628695182302_DSC_0100--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628695182302_DSC_0100--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Weathering test"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628695182302_DSC_0100--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Weathering test"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Analysis of outer surface weathering and it's effects on chert source using reflectance spectroscopy.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ryan M. Parish</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ryan&nbsp;M&nbsp;Parish</div> <div class="imageTitle">Weathering test</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628695849290_DSC_0368(2)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628695849290_DSC_0368(2)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hopewell chert disks"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628695849290_DSC_0368(2)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hopewell chert disks"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Analysis of Hopewell chert disks at the Field Museum, Chicago.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ryan M. Parish</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ryan&nbsp;M&nbsp;Parish</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hopewell chert disks</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628694981153_DSC_0029--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628694981153_DSC_0029--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Poverty Point analysis"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720376/1720376_10500763_1628694981153_DSC_0029--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Poverty Point analysis"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Analysis of over 800 projectile points at the Poverty Point Site, Louisiana.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ryan M. Parish</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ryan&nbsp;M&nbsp;Parish</div> <div class="imageTitle">Poverty Point analysis</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Archaeology seeks to reconstruct and understand the lives of past peoples.  Stone artifacts preserve and understanding where and how people got stone resources is crucial.  Studying how prehistoric people used finite resources such as stone benefits current society as we deal with resource overexploitation, social networking for critical resources, and the effects of climate change on resource decisions.  The study tested the ability of reflectance spectroscopy on identify chert/flint sources used to make stone tools.  Reflectance spectroscopy gathers the interaction of radiation (light) with matter at the atomic and molecular level.  An object’s composition determines these interactions and is different depending on what the object is made of as well as other characteristics. The study of the decisions and strategies regarding where prehistoric people got their stone resources can help us by providing a deep time perspective.   Goals  The primary goal of the study was to test the ability of reflectance spectroscopy as a non-destructive, fast, low-cost, and accurate method.  Previous research on identifying chert resources has been limited in most of these areas.  The second goal of the study was to add to the existing large ‘library’ of chert geologic samples. This database is necessary as a reference of known sources with which to compare artifacts within.  To achieve these goals analysis of over 6,000 chert samples from the Western, Midwestern, and Southern United States were conducted.  Also, independent experiments were preformed that looked at the effects of outer surface weathering and thermal alteration had on the results.   Outcomes  Reflectance spectroscopy was shown through multiple applications to be a fast, accurate, low cost, and non-destructive method to identify the source of stone artifacts made from chert/flint.  In past studies, archaeologists have only sought to identify the type of chert, meaning what geologic parent formation the resource came from.  This is sometimes problematic as the formations containing chert are often extensive.  Reflectance spectroscopy was repeatedly able to separate different chert types and outcrops.  What this means is that we can source an artifact back to the spot on the landscape where prehistoric people got the material not just the general region.  Severe outer surface weathering on some artifacts appear to affect the accuracy of the technique in the visible part of the spectrum though the data in the near and middle infrared regions is not greatly altered.  The heating of artifacts in ancient fires or modern appear to not affect the accuracy of reflectance spectroscopy in identifying the chert source.   What this means is that it is always important as a researcher to know the context of the artifacts you are analyzing and the processes that have affected them over time.  The library of chert geologic samples making up the extensive reference collection consists of 6,660 samples from 222 deposits across much of the continental United States, Chile, Argentina, Poland, and Hungary.  The results of the analysis of this reference collection consistently demonstrate that reflectance spectroscopy is able to source chert artifacts.   Applications  The project established a reflectance spectroscopy lab at the University of Memphis, trained 30 undergraduate students in the use of the techniques, four graduate students, one international researcher, and added to one of the largest chert/flint reference libraries in the world.  Results of the project have been presented at 17 professional conferences with three additional presentations planned, published in 11 peer reviewed journal articles and book chapters, and has contributed to 10 national and three international studies.  Exciting and ongoing research include the analysis of flint from Poland used by Neolithic and Mesolithic hunter-gatherers, studying chert resource selection by Archaic communities in the Atacama Desert, Chile, and examining hunter-gatherer selection of quartzite in the Pampas region of Argentina.  International colleagues are also using the techniques in southern Germany.  At the University of Memphis, we are currently studying how Hopewell communities in Ohio close to 2,000 years ago deposited 10,000 plus chert disks in a burial mound.  Also, we are investigating where people at the Poverty Point, Louisiana got their rock from in an area without nearby chert resources.  Recently, we are using reflectance spectroscopy to analyze large caches of 6,000 year old spear points in Mississippi, studying the stone source for 450 wood working tools dating to the Woodland Period from Indiana, and differentiating 10,000 plus year old Ice Age quarry sites along the Savanna River, South Carolina.  Source data is also giving us a better understanding of Ice Age hunter-gatherer mobility along the Tennessee River.  Through the continued use of reflectance spectroscopy in sourcing chert/flint resources used by prehistoric peoples we will gain a greater understanding for how they lived, how they used their finite resources, and how shifting social networks, climate change, and other factors affected them.           Last Modified: 08/11/2021       Submitted by: Ryan M Parish]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
