<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CQIS:   Quantum Chaos and Quantum Gravity from Entanglement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>270000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Cronin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>acronin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project addresses physics questions such as: How does the "arrow of time" emerge from quantum mechanics? How can one characterize chaos in quantum systems with many particles? Does information get lost in a black hole? How can we develop a quantum gravity theory that unifies general relativity and quantum mechanics? These seemingly distinct fundamental questions are all deeply related to the concept of quantum entanglement.  In classical mechanics in systems with many particles (many-body systems), because of chaos, it is difficult to predict anything about the future of a complicated system.  At the same time, however, the complexity induced by chaos can generate a kind of simplicity that allows us to ignore most details about the individual motion of the particles and describe a many-body system efficiently by macroscopic theories such as hydrodynamics and thermodynamics. This project will investigate how to describe chaos in quantum many-body systems, as opposed to classical many-body systems, and how to relate it to thermodynamics and hydrodynamics. Since the famous work of Bekenstein and Hawking, it has been gradually realized that thermodynamics is also deeply related to another deep mystery of nature, namely gravity. Einstein's general relativity theory describes gravity as a theory of curved and dynamical space-time geometry.  This project will investigate how the space-time geometry may emerge as a description of quantum entanglement in many-body systems. The project will provide graduate students with a unique research experience in the interdisciplinary area of quantum information science, high-energy physics and condensed matter physics. The PI will make sustained efforts to introduce the proposed research to undergraduate students and to disseminate the research results of this project beyond the physics community, by lectures, classes and articles.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project studies quantum chaos and quantum gravity using quantum entanglement. The PI plans to characterize quantum chaos by the nonlocal propagation of quantum information, and generalize the criteria in classical chaos such as Lyapunov exponents to quantum systems. Using entanglement criteria of many-body quantum chaos, the relation of chaos with thermalization of an isolated system will be investigated. Physically, chaos in many-body systems is associated with nonlocal propagation of quantum information, which plays an essential role in thermalization process of an isolated system. In addition to providing a more solid foundation to understand quantum thermalization, the PI plans to further develop a general framework of non-equilibrium dynamics based on the new understanding of quantum chaos. Furthermore, chaos will also be studied using special models that are solvable under certain limit but still preserve chaos. Related to quantum gravity, the PI plans to study holographic duality and quantum gravity using random tensor networks, a framework suitable for describing highly entangled quantum states. With the new language of random tensor networks, it is possible to quantify how entanglement properties are encoded in emergent geometry. Different aspects of the holographic duality will be investigated, including global symmetries, geometrical fluctuation and how Einstein's equations can possibly emerge from entanglement. The PI also plans to apply the new understanding obtained to the long-standing black hole information paradox.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1720504</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoliang</FirstName>
<LastName>Qi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoliang Qi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xlqi@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507245259</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000550557</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943054060</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Room 312 McCullough Bldg.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7281</Code>
<Text>QIS - Quantum Information Scie</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Thermodynamics describes how a cup of water gradually cools down to room temperature. Gravity describes how a star&nbsp;collapses into a black hole. Surprisingly, more and more evidences suggest that these two dramatically different kinds of phenomena are deeply connected, &nbsp;with quantum information as their common origin. In this project, we studied the structure of quantum information in systems with many degrees of freedom, and investigate its relation to quantum gravity. We developed new tools for studying the structure of correlation and entanglement in space-time in a general system. We showed how to probe causality---the key concept in relativity which discusses whether an event can influence another one---in a general quantum system. Using these tools helps us to understand how spacetime geometry and locality can emerge from the chaotic motion of many particles. We also studied fundamental questions, such as why our world looks classical, despite everything is described by quantum mechanics. We proved how this is a generic phenomena in a large system: even if quantum mechanics seem to allow arbitrary linear superpositions and many phenomena which do not occur classically, these do not happen generically. A large system with a lot of particles (or qubits) always tend to do the job of quantum measurement to a small subsystem, which leads to the familiar phenomenon of ``wavefunction collapse?. More precisely, in a large system, quantum information can either be protected and remains unknown to most of the system, or becomes classical through a measurement and be shared.</p> <p>On the relation between quantum information and quantum gravity, we studied how to control the ``dual space-time? in a toy model known as the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model. This simple model provides an example of a chaotic system that can be studied quantitatively, and in the mean time has a relatively well-understood ?dual? gravity theory. In general relativity, it is well-known that wormholes are possible, but making a traversable wormhole---one that a particle or even a person can travel through---is impossible, unless there is a way to create negative energy. The advantage of having a toy model like the SYK model is that we can explicitly construct ways to create negative energy, and therefore build a traversable wormhole. The trip of a particle through the wormhole has an interesting connection with quantum teleportation. This correspondence between a quantum mechanics model and simple gravity systems enables us to study a wide range of phenomena including black hole evaporation and black hole information paradox.</p> <p>Our works in this project has a broad influence in the interdisciplinary field of quantum information, quantum chaos and quantum gravity. The works have been introduced in various lectures and perspective articles to the broader audience.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Xiaoliang&nbsp;Qi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720504/1720504_10520422_1612053756760_fig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720504/1720504_10520422_1612053756760_fig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Schroedinger's elephant"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720504/1720504_10520422_1612053756760_fig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Schroedinger's elephant"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">When a small amount of quantum information is encoded in a large system, even if the entire system could be in a quantum superposition, most of its parts look classical. We provide a general proof of this phenomenon.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Xiao-Liang Qi and Daniel Ranard</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaoliang&nbsp;Qi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Schroedinger's elephant</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720504/1720504_10520422_1612053850474_fig2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720504/1720504_10520422_1612053850474_fig2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Traversable wormhole"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1720504/1720504_10520422_1612053850474_fig2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Traversable wormhole"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">By turning on a coupling between two SYK models, it is possible to great a traversable wormhole in the dual spacetime. A particle (red arrow) can go from one boundary to the other through the wormhole. The vertical direction is time and horizontal direction is space.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Juan Maldacena and Xiao-Liang Qi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaoliang&nbsp;Qi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Traversable wormhole</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Thermodynamics describes how a cup of water gradually cools down to room temperature. Gravity describes how a star collapses into a black hole. Surprisingly, more and more evidences suggest that these two dramatically different kinds of phenomena are deeply connected,  with quantum information as their common origin. In this project, we studied the structure of quantum information in systems with many degrees of freedom, and investigate its relation to quantum gravity. We developed new tools for studying the structure of correlation and entanglement in space-time in a general system. We showed how to probe causality---the key concept in relativity which discusses whether an event can influence another one---in a general quantum system. Using these tools helps us to understand how spacetime geometry and locality can emerge from the chaotic motion of many particles. We also studied fundamental questions, such as why our world looks classical, despite everything is described by quantum mechanics. We proved how this is a generic phenomena in a large system: even if quantum mechanics seem to allow arbitrary linear superpositions and many phenomena which do not occur classically, these do not happen generically. A large system with a lot of particles (or qubits) always tend to do the job of quantum measurement to a small subsystem, which leads to the familiar phenomenon of ``wavefunction collapse?. More precisely, in a large system, quantum information can either be protected and remains unknown to most of the system, or becomes classical through a measurement and be shared.  On the relation between quantum information and quantum gravity, we studied how to control the ``dual space-time? in a toy model known as the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev (SYK) model. This simple model provides an example of a chaotic system that can be studied quantitatively, and in the mean time has a relatively well-understood ?dual? gravity theory. In general relativity, it is well-known that wormholes are possible, but making a traversable wormhole---one that a particle or even a person can travel through---is impossible, unless there is a way to create negative energy. The advantage of having a toy model like the SYK model is that we can explicitly construct ways to create negative energy, and therefore build a traversable wormhole. The trip of a particle through the wormhole has an interesting connection with quantum teleportation. This correspondence between a quantum mechanics model and simple gravity systems enables us to study a wide range of phenomena including black hole evaporation and black hole information paradox.  Our works in this project has a broad influence in the interdisciplinary field of quantum information, quantum chaos and quantum gravity. The works have been introduced in various lectures and perspective articles to the broader audience.          Last Modified: 01/30/2021       Submitted by: Xiaoliang Qi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
