<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: School-based Wellness Integrated Systems Hub: a comprehensive online health service management system designed for school health centers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Kamei</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is maximizing chances for improved health, academic success, and post-secondary achievement of students who use School Based Health Centers (SBHCs) through creating more efficient, tailored services. These gains will contribute to students' improved social, economic, and health outcomes as adults, and a healthier U.S. population overall. The School-based Wellness Integrated Systems Hub (SWISH) will offer a comprehensive, online service documentation and data management system designed specifically for SBHCs. In contrast with traditional electronic health record systems, SWISH will serve as a single hub between data sources, eliminating the need for multiple systems. SWISH offers mechanisms for staff to identify clinical service priorities and those students in need of care. The platform, which complies with health, security and privacy regulations, provides functionality that supports the assessment, triage, coordination and provision of care across multiple roles within SBHCs. SWISH will also facilitate evaluation of service impact on student health, wellbeing and academic performance. This capability - not provided by existing market solutions - serves program efficiency and effectiveness goals and is likely to be well received by SBHC staff and administrators leading to robust commercialization of the product.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will develop and test a prototype data management system for School Based Health Centers (SBHCs). SBHCs are proliferating in the U.S; they are well positioned to address the unmet physical and mental health needs of underserved youth by increasing accessibility and continuity of health care on the school campus. Notably, while health information technology systems play a critical role in SBHC quality improvement, operations, and sustainability, a minority of SBHCs report having a data management system in place. This represents a critical infrastructure gap. The proposed technology will address this gap by providing a secure, shared environment specifically designed for SBHC providers to document service, utilize "smart list" algorithms to identify students in need of services, serve students efficiently, and coordinate care and resources within and outside the SBHC. To achieve these goals, the project team will: 1) apply their expertise in design, technology and project management to the creation of a Minimally Viable Product prototype; and 2) usability test SWISH with members of the target audience.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1721319</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tamara</FirstName>
<LastName>Kuhn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tamara Kuhn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tamara.kuhn@dfusioninc.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8314402104</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000697216</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>dfusion</Name>
<CityName>Scotts Valley</CityName>
<ZipCode>950663245</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8314402162</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 Enterprise Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite G300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079336099</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DFUSION INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[dfusion]]></Name>
<CityName>Scotts Valley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>950663248</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 Enterprise Way, Suite G300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-size: small;">In the United States, over 2,000 schools boast the presence of fully operational School-Based Health Centers (SBHCs). Students from disadvantaged backgrounds in schools with an SBHC have been found to have increased access to health care, including mental health services.&nbsp; </span><span style="font-size: small;">There is ample evidence that SBHCs greatly enhance health care access among school-aged minority and low-income youth,</span><sup><span style="font-size: x-small;"> </span></sup><span style="font-size: small;">and growing evidence that SBHCs improve health and mental health outcomes across populations.</span><span style="font-size: small;"> And yet, as SBHCs work to manage health and wellness services, assess links between health and academic outcomes, and recoup payment from health payers, they commonly deal with limited data management systems. No truly comprehensive technologies exist to support SBHC practitioners with decision-making, coordination of care, and evaluation of health outcomes and academic performance impact. While existing electronic health record (EHR) systems are being integrated by other types of health settings they have not been designed for the unique needs of SBHCs and uptake of those systems by SBHCs has been limited. </span></p> <p><span style="font-size: small;">This Phase I Small Business Innovation Research project completed development of a prototype for the <em>School-based Wellness Integrated Systems Hub</em>, an innovative, technology-based solution for addressing these needs by offering a comprehensive, online service documentation and data management system designed specifically for SBHCs. The platform: a) serves as a single hub between data sources, including student information systems, eliminating the need for multiple data systems; b) offers predictive &ldquo;smart lists&rdquo;, data analytic dashboards and system-generated recommendations to help define real-time service priorities; c) provides functionality that supports the assessment, triage, coordination and provision of care across multiple roles within SBHCs (e.g., nurses, social workers, therapists, administrators) and d) complies with health, security and privacy regulations in both the school and healthcare arenas. At the conclusion of the Phase I project period the prototype included the overall architecture for the platform and four modules: </span></p> <p><span style="font-size: small;">1) Provider dashboard - Serves as an entry point for the provider that ensures they see their tasks and activities, and provides a representation of their recent service activity. The dashboard displays a list of &ldquo;tasks&rdquo; assigned to the provider, made up of appointments, service and referral follow ups, newly assigned students, and assessment reminders.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: small;">2) Service documentation - Each SBHC provider has a distinct form that will allow them to log direct and indirect services for a student/students. This is the primary method of documenting every service provided to students.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: small;">3) Limited smart list capability - Allows creation of Smart Lists for easier filtering of groups of students. Smart Lists are dynamically created with membership based on one or more &ldquo;rules&rdquo; (or filters) and data characteristics of student demographics, medical, academic, and service usage.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: small;">4) Key performance indicators &ndash; allows providers and supervisors to assess the efficiency of services through looking at performance data, filtered by school, provider, role, and time period. All data is accompanied by a data visualization/graph.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: small;">In addition, the platform was thoroughly and iteratively QA/bug tested and was subjected to usability testing with SBHC staff and administrators. The outcomes of usability testing were positive with the user assessment of the platform reaching or exceeding the benchmarks. The testers found the system easy to use, with the functionality, appearance and potential usefulness as good or better than expected. The system can be considered a minimum viable product and ready for beta testing.</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: small;"><em>School-based Wellness Integrated Systems Hub</em><strong><em> </em></strong>in<strong><em> </em></strong>addressing the technology infrastructure gaps in SBHCs by providing a secure, shared environment for school-based health providers to serve students efficiently, coordinating care and resources within the SBHC allows providers to better able to identify students in need of care and who at risk. This, in turn, will improve health and academic outcomes among SBHC clients, particularly those at high-risk. By providing improved health services the societal outcomes include improved health of youth, particularly disadvantaged and minority youth typically served by SBHCs, which in turn improves their academic successes, and possibly in turn, future health and success.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/16/2018<br>      Modified by: Tamara&nbsp;Kuhn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721319/1721319_10500841_1531790187193_pic2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721319/1721319_10500841_1531790187193_pic2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Key Performance Indicators"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721319/1721319_10500841_1531790187193_pic2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Key Performance Indicators"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Screen with an overview of the key performance indicators for the last 30 days.</div> <div class="imageCredit">dfusion/ETR</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tamara&nbsp;Kuhn</div> <div class="imageTitle">Key Performance Indicators</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721319/1721319_10500841_1531790080346_pic6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721319/1721319_10500841_1531790080346_pic6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Service Documentation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721319/1721319_10500841_1531790080346_pic6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Service Documentation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Screen capture of a service documentation screen where providers would log a service provided to a student</div> <div class="imageCredit">dfusion/ETR</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tamara&nbsp;Kuhn</div> <div class="imageTitle">Service Documentation</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721319/1721319_10500841_1531790349354_pic7--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721319/1721319_10500841_1531790349354_pic7--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Key Performance Indicator Analysis Screen"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721319/1721319_10500841_1531790349354_pic7--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Key Performance Indicator Analysis Screen"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Portion of a Key Performance Indicator Analysis Screen for Referrals within 1 day. Shows goals, performance, and performance broken down by time period.</div> <div class="imageCredit">dfusion/ETR</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tamara&nbsp;Kuhn</div> <div class="imageTitle">Key Performance Indicator Analysis Screen</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the United States, over 2,000 schools boast the presence of fully operational School-Based Health Centers (SBHCs). Students from disadvantaged backgrounds in schools with an SBHC have been found to have increased access to health care, including mental health services.  There is ample evidence that SBHCs greatly enhance health care access among school-aged minority and low-income youth, and growing evidence that SBHCs improve health and mental health outcomes across populations. And yet, as SBHCs work to manage health and wellness services, assess links between health and academic outcomes, and recoup payment from health payers, they commonly deal with limited data management systems. No truly comprehensive technologies exist to support SBHC practitioners with decision-making, coordination of care, and evaluation of health outcomes and academic performance impact. While existing electronic health record (EHR) systems are being integrated by other types of health settings they have not been designed for the unique needs of SBHCs and uptake of those systems by SBHCs has been limited.   This Phase I Small Business Innovation Research project completed development of a prototype for the School-based Wellness Integrated Systems Hub, an innovative, technology-based solution for addressing these needs by offering a comprehensive, online service documentation and data management system designed specifically for SBHCs. The platform: a) serves as a single hub between data sources, including student information systems, eliminating the need for multiple data systems; b) offers predictive "smart lists", data analytic dashboards and system-generated recommendations to help define real-time service priorities; c) provides functionality that supports the assessment, triage, coordination and provision of care across multiple roles within SBHCs (e.g., nurses, social workers, therapists, administrators) and d) complies with health, security and privacy regulations in both the school and healthcare arenas. At the conclusion of the Phase I project period the prototype included the overall architecture for the platform and four modules:   1) Provider dashboard - Serves as an entry point for the provider that ensures they see their tasks and activities, and provides a representation of their recent service activity. The dashboard displays a list of "tasks" assigned to the provider, made up of appointments, service and referral follow ups, newly assigned students, and assessment reminders.  2) Service documentation - Each SBHC provider has a distinct form that will allow them to log direct and indirect services for a student/students. This is the primary method of documenting every service provided to students.  3) Limited smart list capability - Allows creation of Smart Lists for easier filtering of groups of students. Smart Lists are dynamically created with membership based on one or more "rules" (or filters) and data characteristics of student demographics, medical, academic, and service usage.  4) Key performance indicators &ndash; allows providers and supervisors to assess the efficiency of services through looking at performance data, filtered by school, provider, role, and time period. All data is accompanied by a data visualization/graph.  In addition, the platform was thoroughly and iteratively QA/bug tested and was subjected to usability testing with SBHC staff and administrators. The outcomes of usability testing were positive with the user assessment of the platform reaching or exceeding the benchmarks. The testers found the system easy to use, with the functionality, appearance and potential usefulness as good or better than expected. The system can be considered a minimum viable product and ready for beta testing.  School-based Wellness Integrated Systems Hub in addressing the technology infrastructure gaps in SBHCs by providing a secure, shared environment for school-based health providers to serve students efficiently, coordinating care and resources within the SBHC allows providers to better able to identify students in need of care and who at risk. This, in turn, will improve health and academic outcomes among SBHC clients, particularly those at high-risk. By providing improved health services the societal outcomes include improved health of youth, particularly disadvantaged and minority youth typically served by SBHCs, which in turn improves their academic successes, and possibly in turn, future health and success.       Last Modified: 07/16/2018       Submitted by: Tamara Kuhn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
