<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Novel Three Dimensional Flocked Carbon Fiber Microwave Absorbers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224956.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224956</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will support the development, characterization, and commercialization of nonconductive, magnetically loaded, carbon fiber (CF) composite microwave absorbers. Manufacturers use absorbers to protect their products from unwanted Electromagnetic Interference (EMI) and to meet Federal Communications Commission (FCC) regulations and standards. EMI from external and internal sources can degrade the operation and performance of electronics. The demand for EMI absorbing materials that are cost effective, lightweight, thin, flexible and wide-spectrum continues to grow rapidly as microwave communications and mobile technologies become ubiquitous. The overall EMI shielding market exceeded $5.4 billion in 2015 and is expected to grow to $7.8 billion in the next 5 years. Absorber materials developed in this project can be applied to almost any type of antenna, circuit board, cable, gasket or enclosure. The project goal and broader impacts of this technology are development of lightweight, thin, high performance, microwave absorber materials that provide increased energy efficiency, design flexibility, reduced costs and improved connectivity for a wide range of markets, applications, products and devices. The product is suitable for many market sectors including automotive, consumer electronics, telecom and aerospace where thin, lightweight and wide-spectrum response is needed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the project will be the creation of new CF composites for microwave absorption. This project will measure and define the fundamental electromagnetic absorption parameters of these composites in the 1 - 12 GHz range. Characterization data such as dielectric constants, complex electric permittivity, magnetic permeability, loss tangents and layer thickness of the absorbers will be measured and derived. Such parameterization is essential for simulation modeling and design optimization of such absorbers for various markets and applications. Absorber attenuation and frequency response will be simulated and validated with laboratory transmission line and reflectivity testing. These composites use both magnetic and dielectric mechanisms to absorb microwave energy. Composite CF absorber materials are nonconductive and rely on insertion loss and impedance matching and/or cavity resonance effects. Processes, techniques and equipment needed for commercial production will be investigated. Graduate students and faculty will be supported in development of test, measurement and modeling techniques. The execution of the project will demonstrate the effectiveness and advantages of using CF composites as microwave absorbing materials and will provide a pathway to commercialization and product design. Successful completion of the project will create new high performance materials for the aerospace, automotive and consumer markets.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1721863</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Doneker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert L Doneker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>doneker@tangitek.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5032223837</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000696842</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>TangiTek, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<ZipCode>972052539</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5032223837</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 SW Yamhill St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Ste 301]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079828466</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TANGITEK, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[TangiTek, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>972052539</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1033 SW Yamhill St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~224956</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="WordSection1"> <p>The explosive growth and ubiquitous use of electronics, wireless communication, automation systems and devices in the 21st century have led to a corresponding increase in electromagnetic interference (EMI).&nbsp; EMI from external and internal sources can severely affect the operation and performance of critical electronics based infrastructure, devices and degrade connectivity in communication platforms.&nbsp; Microwave absorbers are used in EMI mitigation in antennas, cables, enclosures, chipsets, and electronic components. Microwave absorbers include radar absorbing materials (RAM). RAM is used for electromagnetic (EM) signature management, stealth, and protection of assets such as aircraft, submarines, ships, tanks, and soldier equipment used in national security applications.</p> <p>Conventional absorbers are generally either magnetic or dielectric types. Magnetic absorbers are thin and offer broadband absorption. The main disadvantages of magnetic absorbers are excessive weight and cost. Dielectric absorbers generally have no magnetic properties. They are usually made using low cost, lightweight foams and elastomers, are narrowband, and are relatively thick. The main disadvantages of dielectric absorbers are their narrowband response and thickness.</p> <p>With NSF SBIR Phase I support, TangiTek has developed and characterized a novel class of patent-pending magnetically loaded, flocked carbon fiber (CF) microwave absorbers (MF-RAM). MF-RAM prototypes developed in this project are lightweight (&gt; 80% weight reduction compared to conventional magnetic absorbers), thin (&gt; 40% thickness reduction), high attenuation (-10 to -40 dB reflection loss), and broadband (&gt; 5 dB attenuation) over the X and Ku frequency bands. Flocking is a process of electrostatically depositing small carbon fibers (flock) onto an adhesive substrate. The flocked CF and high-loss dielectric fillers absorb higher frequency EM energy, while the magnetic loading absorbs lower frequency EM energy, yielding a broadband absorber. The three dimensional CF flocked structure allows the use of relatively small amounts of magnetic materials and CF, thus leading to a lightweight, thin, broadband absorber with all the benefits of conventional absorbers and none of their drawbacks.</p> <p>NSF support has helped demonstrate the feasibility of MF-RAM successfully, validating the intellectual merits of the project. Frequency-dependent material EM parameters (electric permittivity, magnetic permeability, and loss tangents) were determined through waveguide measurements. Absorption performance was measured in an anechoic chamber using arch reflectivity testing. EM simulation modeling confirmed absorber performance using derived lost tangents. TangiTek constructed waveguide sections, sample holders and horn antennas for the S, C, X, Ku, K and Ka (2-40 GHz) frequency bands. An all wood, height-adjustable arch (for Navy Research Laboratory (NRL) type reflectivity measurements) was built by TangiTek to measure the reflection loss in the anechoic chamber at Portland State University. TangiTek developed high-quality microwave test and measurement equipment in-house using 3D printing additive manufacturing, and electroplating in a cost-effective manner. A grant from Business Oregon enabled the purchase of a high precision Vector Network Analyzer (VNA) measurement equipment. We are now in a strong position to leverage our test and measurement capability developed during the NSF project to rapidly respond to future client requests for specialized, application-specific absorber material in support of cost-effective, rapid prototyping, product development, and commercialization efforts.</p> <p>Ongoing commercialization efforts include customer discovery to identify a Minimum Viable Product (MVP). Likely commercialization prospects for MF-RAM include the aerospace, military, and communication infrastructure markets where MF-RAM can be introduced as flexible liners, drapes, panels, PSA-backed sheets, and conformal coatings. Typical applications include EMI shielding, Electromagnetic Compatibility (EMC), antenna isolation, beamforming, surface current attenuation and EM signature management for defense protection systems. TangiTek won the (ASA (ARL)) Army xTechSearch Phase I, II, and III challenges for its MF-RAM white paper, pitch, and trade show exhibit at the Innovators Corner at the AUSA Expo 2018 respectively for MF-RAM X and Ku band absorbers. TangiTek is one of twelve companies that will compete in the final Phase IV capstone technology demonstration of MF-RAM application to soldier protection systems in March 2019.</p> <p>From a broader perspective, the impact of this project will be the development of new materials to improve telecommunications infrastructure. Lightweight materials will reduce transportation energy costs in airborne and mobile platforms. It will increase energy efficiency in electronics by improving the signal to noise ratio by lowering noise without the need to for additional power. Thin, light broadband materials will enhance the survivability of our soldiers and equipment with improved signature management.</p> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/17/2018<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;L&nbsp;Doneker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545080367818_Outcomes-Image-5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545080367818_Outcomes-Image-5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Prototypes of MF-RAM microwave absorber developed in this project."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545080367818_Outcomes-Image-5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Prototypes of MF-RAM microwave absorber developed in this project."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Magnified side view of flocked carbon fiber absorber with magnetic loading; flexible thin MF-RAM prototypes with different encapsulations; MF-RAM applied as conformal coating on a 3D printed head; MF-RAM applied to an Army helmet and armor vest during a feasibility analysis for product development.</div> <div class="imageCredit">TangiTek, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;L&nbsp;Doneker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Prototypes of MF-RAM microwave absorber developed in this project.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545080885437_Outcomes-Image-02--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545080885437_Outcomes-Image-02--rgov-800width.jpg" title="3D printing of microwave test and measurement equipment."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545080885437_Outcomes-Image-02--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="3D printing of microwave test and measurement equipment."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A complete set of horn antennas and waveguides were designed and 3D printed in-house for use in test and measurement of absorbers developed in this project.This cost-effective tooling provides a strong foundation for rapid prototyping, product development, and commercialization.</div> <div class="imageCredit">TangiTek, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;L&nbsp;Doneker</div> <div class="imageTitle">3D printing of microwave test and measurement equipment.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545081167977_Outcomes-Image-03--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545081167977_Outcomes-Image-03--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Suite of 3D printed horns, waveguides, sample holders and mounts fabricated during this project."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545081167977_Outcomes-Image-03--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Suite of 3D printed horns, waveguides, sample holders and mounts fabricated during this project."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A complete set of horn antennas and waveguides were designed and 3D printed in-house for use in test and measurement of absorbers developed in this project.This cost-effective tooling provides a strong foundation for rapid prototyping, product development, and commercialization.</div> <div class="imageCredit">TangiTek, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;L&nbsp;Doneker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Suite of 3D printed horns, waveguides, sample holders and mounts fabricated during this project.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545081403630_Outcomes-Image-04--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545081403630_Outcomes-Image-04--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Measurement of absorber EM parameters using waveguides and VNA."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545081403630_Outcomes-Image-04--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Measurement of absorber EM parameters using waveguides and VNA."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Measurement of MF-RAM S-parameters using waveguides, sample holders and Vector Network Analyzer (VNA) - (a) TangiTek 3D-printed WR-90 waveguide set for X band, (b) commercial metal WR-90 waveguide set  and (c) 3D-printed sample holders with different materials under test.</div> <div class="imageCredit">TangiTek, LLC</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;L&nbsp;Doneker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Measurement of absorber EM parameters using waveguides and VNA.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545081896218_Outcomes-Image-05--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545081896218_Outcomes-Image-05--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Navy Research Lab (NRL) Arch Reflectivity measurement set up inside Portland State University anechoic chamber for reflection loss measurement of MF-RAM material."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1721863/1721863_10500539_1545081896218_Outcomes-Image-05--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Navy Research Lab (NRL) Arch Reflectivity measurement set up inside Portland State University anechoic chamber for reflection loss measurement of MF-RAM material."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An optimized, all wood- NRL arch was constructed and installed in the PSU anechoic lab for use in this project. The performance of MF-RAM prototypes was characterized by measuring the reflection loss from the absorber as a function of frequency and angle of incidence.</div> <div class="imageCredit">TangiTek, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;L&nbsp;Doneker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Navy Research Lab (NRL) Arch Reflectivity measurement set up inside Portland State University anechoic chamber for reflection loss measurement of MF-RAM material.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The explosive growth and ubiquitous use of electronics, wireless communication, automation systems and devices in the 21st century have led to a corresponding increase in electromagnetic interference (EMI).  EMI from external and internal sources can severely affect the operation and performance of critical electronics based infrastructure, devices and degrade connectivity in communication platforms.  Microwave absorbers are used in EMI mitigation in antennas, cables, enclosures, chipsets, and electronic components. Microwave absorbers include radar absorbing materials (RAM). RAM is used for electromagnetic (EM) signature management, stealth, and protection of assets such as aircraft, submarines, ships, tanks, and soldier equipment used in national security applications.  Conventional absorbers are generally either magnetic or dielectric types. Magnetic absorbers are thin and offer broadband absorption. The main disadvantages of magnetic absorbers are excessive weight and cost. Dielectric absorbers generally have no magnetic properties. They are usually made using low cost, lightweight foams and elastomers, are narrowband, and are relatively thick. The main disadvantages of dielectric absorbers are their narrowband response and thickness.  With NSF SBIR Phase I support, TangiTek has developed and characterized a novel class of patent-pending magnetically loaded, flocked carbon fiber (CF) microwave absorbers (MF-RAM). MF-RAM prototypes developed in this project are lightweight (&gt; 80% weight reduction compared to conventional magnetic absorbers), thin (&gt; 40% thickness reduction), high attenuation (-10 to -40 dB reflection loss), and broadband (&gt; 5 dB attenuation) over the X and Ku frequency bands. Flocking is a process of electrostatically depositing small carbon fibers (flock) onto an adhesive substrate. The flocked CF and high-loss dielectric fillers absorb higher frequency EM energy, while the magnetic loading absorbs lower frequency EM energy, yielding a broadband absorber. The three dimensional CF flocked structure allows the use of relatively small amounts of magnetic materials and CF, thus leading to a lightweight, thin, broadband absorber with all the benefits of conventional absorbers and none of their drawbacks.  NSF support has helped demonstrate the feasibility of MF-RAM successfully, validating the intellectual merits of the project. Frequency-dependent material EM parameters (electric permittivity, magnetic permeability, and loss tangents) were determined through waveguide measurements. Absorption performance was measured in an anechoic chamber using arch reflectivity testing. EM simulation modeling confirmed absorber performance using derived lost tangents. TangiTek constructed waveguide sections, sample holders and horn antennas for the S, C, X, Ku, K and Ka (2-40 GHz) frequency bands. An all wood, height-adjustable arch (for Navy Research Laboratory (NRL) type reflectivity measurements) was built by TangiTek to measure the reflection loss in the anechoic chamber at Portland State University. TangiTek developed high-quality microwave test and measurement equipment in-house using 3D printing additive manufacturing, and electroplating in a cost-effective manner. A grant from Business Oregon enabled the purchase of a high precision Vector Network Analyzer (VNA) measurement equipment. We are now in a strong position to leverage our test and measurement capability developed during the NSF project to rapidly respond to future client requests for specialized, application-specific absorber material in support of cost-effective, rapid prototyping, product development, and commercialization efforts.  Ongoing commercialization efforts include customer discovery to identify a Minimum Viable Product (MVP). Likely commercialization prospects for MF-RAM include the aerospace, military, and communication infrastructure markets where MF-RAM can be introduced as flexible liners, drapes, panels, PSA-backed sheets, and conformal coatings. Typical applications include EMI shielding, Electromagnetic Compatibility (EMC), antenna isolation, beamforming, surface current attenuation and EM signature management for defense protection systems. TangiTek won the (ASA (ARL)) Army xTechSearch Phase I, II, and III challenges for its MF-RAM white paper, pitch, and trade show exhibit at the Innovators Corner at the AUSA Expo 2018 respectively for MF-RAM X and Ku band absorbers. TangiTek is one of twelve companies that will compete in the final Phase IV capstone technology demonstration of MF-RAM application to soldier protection systems in March 2019.  From a broader perspective, the impact of this project will be the development of new materials to improve telecommunications infrastructure. Lightweight materials will reduce transportation energy costs in airborne and mobile platforms. It will increase energy efficiency in electronics by improving the signal to noise ratio by lowering noise without the need to for additional power. Thin, light broadband materials will enhance the survivability of our soldiers and equipment with improved signature management.        Last Modified: 12/17/2018       Submitted by: Robert L Doneker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
