<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Beam Steering Full Duplex Wireless Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to enable the efficient use of wireless&lt;br/&gt;spectrum. Over the last decade, the world has seen a sharp increase in the number and diversity&lt;br/&gt;of mobile devices. With this surge in mobile devices, access to spectrum has become an&lt;br/&gt;overarching issue impacting the everyday life of citizens. The demand is expected to grow&lt;br/&gt;exponentially in the coming years, with the rapid adoption of the Internet of Things (IoT) linking&lt;br/&gt;everything we interact with in daily life. The technology developed under this project will allow&lt;br/&gt;communication devices to listen and broadcast simultaneously, on the same frequency, thus&lt;br/&gt;effectively doubling spectrum utilization by operating in Full Duplex (FD) mode. By improving&lt;br/&gt;spectral efficiency and simplifying frequency planning, the results from this project will enable&lt;br/&gt;newer paradigms for the rapid design, development and deployment of mobile devices. Society&lt;br/&gt;as a whole will benefit from the increased array of applications enabled by robust, spectrally&lt;br/&gt;efficient communication devices. Furthermore, valuable spectrum assets will be released and can&lt;br/&gt;be redirected to create new opportunities for growth.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will demonstrate a practical Full-duplex&lt;br/&gt;communication system prototype. The goal of the project is to develop a functional prototype&lt;br/&gt;showing the ability of fast cancellation that enables reliable full duplex operation at transmit&lt;br/&gt;powers suitable for outdoor deployment. While Full Duplex has been shown to be achievable&lt;br/&gt;under static channel conditions, maintaining the desired isolation between transmit and receive&lt;br/&gt;path in a dynamic channel is difficult, mainly due to the high level of reflected power into the&lt;br/&gt;radio system that can limit its performance. By deploying novel and efficient cancellation&lt;br/&gt;methodologies the prototype will be able to track and compensate for moving targets as they&lt;br/&gt;appear in the radiation space of the FD system. Innovative co-designed spatial, analog and digital&lt;br/&gt;approaches will be used to converge on the optimal parameters for cancellation, while ensuring&lt;br/&gt;a rapid response time. All proposed algorithms under this project will be tested on a real-time FD&lt;br/&gt;prototype system, under realistic wireless channel condition, to ensure that practical issues are&lt;br/&gt;accounted for.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1722372</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Waleed</FirstName>
<LastName>Younis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Waleed Younis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sbir@lextrum.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8584058793</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000741105</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/11/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Carr</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frank Carr</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>frank@lextrum.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9492945862</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000755889</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lextrum Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926173062</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3102106888</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5141 California Ave., Ste 250</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080048490</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LEXTRUM INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>080996892</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lextrum Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926173062</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5141 California Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Wireless communication is at the core of almost every innovation in the 21<sup>st</sup> century. The ability to send signals wirelessly without necessarily having a line of sight between the transmitter and the receiver lies at the heart of the freedom associated with wireless connections. However, the available spectrum that supports Non-Line of Sight (NLoS) communication (generally considered to be less than 6GHz) is rapidly diminishing, thus stifling innovation and limiting the potential of current wireless systems. </span></p> <p><span>All currently deployed wireless systems maintain bi-directional communication links in one of two ways. &nbsp;In the first method, users taking turns in time (traditional walkie-talkie &ldquo;over and out&rdquo; approaches, generally referred to as time division multiplexing), which by definition is slow, as users need to wait their turn. The second method involves using two different frequencies, one for each direction of communication, which is wasteful of scarce spectrum. A new technology referred to as in-band Full Duplex (FD) systems allows communication devices to receive and broadcast simultaneously, on the same frequency, effectively doubling spectrum utilization, while relaxing frequency management. However, in order to function correctly, the transmitting circuits have to be almost perfectly isolated from the receiving circuits, such that the weak received signals from a faraway transmitter can be &ldquo;heard&rdquo; without being overpowered by the node&rsquo;s own transmission. </span></p> <p><span>With the upcoming deployment of 5G networks, the community is gearing up towards 1000x improvement in capacity. Two approaches stand-out as perfect candidates for FD, namely network densification and improved spectrum efficiency. Network densification can be achieved by increasing the number and density of small cells, eventually migrating from a centralized network architecture in favor of a more distributed network architecture. The main challenge in such a deployment is how to back-haul network elements to the infrastructure. The current approach of using fiber or microwave links, increases the total cost of ownership due to the need to build, operate and maintain the wired backhaul network. FD provides a wireless, spectrally efficient, network transparent, low-cost solution for this problem.</span></p> <p><span>Under this SBIR, Lextrum has developed small cell FD transceiver intellectual property and platforms that can be easily integrated into current systems, leading to improved capacity and quality of service. By utilizing FD systems, spectrum assets worth billions of dollars can be redirected to create new opportunities for growth.&nbsp; The intellectual merit of work stems from the theoretical foundation needed to create a system that not only achieves almost perfect isolation between transmit and receiver circuits (&gt;110dB), but maintains that isolation as the environment surrounding the transceiver changes. i.e. as new objects such as people and cars move around the transceiver. The system operates at bandwidth up to 20 MHz with a transmit power of up to 25 dBm which is sufficient for most small cell wireless applications. </span></p> <p><span>From a broader impact perspective, today, wireless devices, in general, are not only the most ubiquitous of consumer products, but are also increasingly becoming important for mission-critical tasks spanning healthcare, emergency response, scientific exploration, etc. With the advent of the Internet of Things (IoT), the demand is expected to grow exponentially in the coming years, literally linking everything we interact with in daily life. Society as a whole will benefit from the increased array of applications associated with efficient wireless systems. The results from this SBIR will enable newer paradigms for the rapid design, development and deployment of such devices.&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2018<br>      Modified by: Frank&nbsp;Carr</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Wireless communication is at the core of almost every innovation in the 21st century. The ability to send signals wirelessly without necessarily having a line of sight between the transmitter and the receiver lies at the heart of the freedom associated with wireless connections. However, the available spectrum that supports Non-Line of Sight (NLoS) communication (generally considered to be less than 6GHz) is rapidly diminishing, thus stifling innovation and limiting the potential of current wireless systems.   All currently deployed wireless systems maintain bi-directional communication links in one of two ways.  In the first method, users taking turns in time (traditional walkie-talkie "over and out" approaches, generally referred to as time division multiplexing), which by definition is slow, as users need to wait their turn. The second method involves using two different frequencies, one for each direction of communication, which is wasteful of scarce spectrum. A new technology referred to as in-band Full Duplex (FD) systems allows communication devices to receive and broadcast simultaneously, on the same frequency, effectively doubling spectrum utilization, while relaxing frequency management. However, in order to function correctly, the transmitting circuits have to be almost perfectly isolated from the receiving circuits, such that the weak received signals from a faraway transmitter can be "heard" without being overpowered by the node?s own transmission.   With the upcoming deployment of 5G networks, the community is gearing up towards 1000x improvement in capacity. Two approaches stand-out as perfect candidates for FD, namely network densification and improved spectrum efficiency. Network densification can be achieved by increasing the number and density of small cells, eventually migrating from a centralized network architecture in favor of a more distributed network architecture. The main challenge in such a deployment is how to back-haul network elements to the infrastructure. The current approach of using fiber or microwave links, increases the total cost of ownership due to the need to build, operate and maintain the wired backhaul network. FD provides a wireless, spectrally efficient, network transparent, low-cost solution for this problem.  Under this SBIR, Lextrum has developed small cell FD transceiver intellectual property and platforms that can be easily integrated into current systems, leading to improved capacity and quality of service. By utilizing FD systems, spectrum assets worth billions of dollars can be redirected to create new opportunities for growth.  The intellectual merit of work stems from the theoretical foundation needed to create a system that not only achieves almost perfect isolation between transmit and receiver circuits (&gt;110dB), but maintains that isolation as the environment surrounding the transceiver changes. i.e. as new objects such as people and cars move around the transceiver. The system operates at bandwidth up to 20 MHz with a transmit power of up to 25 dBm which is sufficient for most small cell wireless applications.   From a broader impact perspective, today, wireless devices, in general, are not only the most ubiquitous of consumer products, but are also increasingly becoming important for mission-critical tasks spanning healthcare, emergency response, scientific exploration, etc. With the advent of the Internet of Things (IoT), the demand is expected to grow exponentially in the coming years, literally linking everything we interact with in daily life. Society as a whole will benefit from the increased array of applications associated with efficient wireless systems. The results from this SBIR will enable newer paradigms for the rapid design, development and deployment of such devices.        Last Modified: 09/29/2018       Submitted by: Frank Carr]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
