<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Perovskite Solar Cells with Tin Oxide Electron Transport Layers for Optimized Performance and Lifetime</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>223823.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>223823</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rick Schwerdtfeger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will be seen in the strengthening of the renewable energy landscape, in the diversification of our energy sources, and ultimately in the reduction of fossil fuel?s impact on human health and the environment as our society moves toward clean electrification of our energy supply and distribution systems. Due to the low cost of its raw materials, intrinsic scalability and rapid evolution of efficiencies, perovskite solar cells are the ideal candidates to validate thin film photovoltaics as a safe, commercially viable and economically sustainable source of energy. This rapidly emerging technology is compatible with existing silicon photovoltaics and can be combined with them to enhance their efficiencies, or can be used as stand-alone devices that can ultimate meet or exceed the performance of silicon while enabling an intrinsically inexpensive and scalable manufacturing process. Initial studies predict an estimated cost of production of modules lower than $0.28/W after amortization of initial capital investment, which translates into a cost of production ~30% lower than that of current photovoltaic technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will provide a solution to a key degradation mechanism that affects the lifetime performance of perovskite photovoltaics. Degradation is caused by trapping of charges at the interface between the light absorbing perovskite layer and the electron transport layer, typically TiO2, which leads to the breakdown of the perovskite structure through a sequence of chemical reactions. In this project TiO2 will be replaced by SnO2 (either intrinsic or doped) which has an electronic band structure that matches very closely with new high efficiency perovskite compositions. Additionally, SnO2 is considerable less expensive than TiO2, easier to deposit with high quality, i.e. low density of electronic defects,  and it is more environmentally robust in the presence of moisture and oxygen than TiO2. SnO2 also does not photocatalyze degradation pathways of the perovskite layer, which is recently thought to be occurring with TiO2. Preliminary laboratory work using SnO2 as an electron transport layer yielded efficiencies comparable to cells manufactured using TiO2 (~18%), but more importantly, tests showed virtually no degradation after 500 hours of operation. Our goal is to further improve the properties of the perovskite cells (efficiency and stability) while developing a robust, inexpensive deposition process for SnO2.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1722390</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
<LastName>Shaheen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sean E Shaheen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sean.shaheen@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034929627</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000213234</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Augusto</FirstName>
<LastName>Kunrath</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Augusto Kunrath</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>akunrath@mvsystemsinc.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3032719907</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000713277</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>MVSystems LLC</Name>
<CityName>Arvada</CityName>
<ZipCode>800023945</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>303513588</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6770 West 52nd Avenue, Unit A</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080082665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MVSYSTEMS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[MVSystems LLC]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>800023945</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~223823</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes</strong><br />In this project, research was carried out on the emerging solar cell technology of organic metal halide perovskites, otherwise known as perovskite solar cells (PSCs). It was aimed on the development of the electron transport layer (ETL) in the devices, which is critical in allowing them to achieve maximum performance. The project focused on the development of ETLs made from the inorganic compound ZnO, using the deposition technique of atomic layer deposition (ALD). ZnO has excellent electron transport characteristics while being a low-cost material. ALD provides a method to fabricate high quality thin film materials with excellent conformal coverage of surfaces and low pinhole density that are required for good performance in the solar cell. The outcomes of the project were centered on the development an optimized structure for the ZnO layer that involved modifying the amount of oxidation of the thin film, a procedure that is readily carried out in a precise manner with the ALD process. Other film parameters that were optimized include the film thickness, smoothness, and uniformity. The resulting films were incorporated into PSCs, and the results showed improved device performance in both their solar power conversion efficiency and reproducibility. Performance results showed typical increases in efficiency from 13% to 16% with the improved ZnO layer, using the prototype device architectures used for the purposes of the study. A greatly improved fabrication yield of &gt;90% of the approximately 50 individual devices in a given fabrication run was also found.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit<br /></strong>The intellectual merit of the work was rooted in the understanding of the role that oxidation level plays on the structural, electronic, and interfacial properties of ZnO thin layers in PSCs as well as the impact of ALD processing on thin film uniformity and quality. These provide greater fundamental understanding of mechanisms of electron extraction from the PSC active layer and subsequent transport to the negative electrode of the device, along with better understanding of the thin film growth mechanisms that arise from ALD growth of nanometer-scale films necessary for high performance PSCs.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts<br /></strong>The broader impacts of the work include the development of a ZnO film structure for improved PSC efficiency, which can be generalized to other fabrication strategies that are suitable for a variety of industrial fabrication processes such as sputter deposition or non-vacuum, solution-based processing. The improvements in fabrication yield that the project demonstrated can have important implications for the future industrialization of the technology, which will require high yields for large-scale production. More broadly, the development of PSCs as a renewable energy technology shows increasing promise to augment or ultimately succeed silicon-based photovoltaics, particularly with tandem-device approaches that can exceed the power conversion efficiency of the commercial PV modules available today. The project also resulted in the training and Ph.D. dissertation of a female graduate student, who intends to go on to an academic career, thus extending the broader impacts to subsequent generations of students and trainees.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/17/2019<br>      Modified by: Sean&nbsp;E&nbsp;Shaheen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes In this project, research was carried out on the emerging solar cell technology of organic metal halide perovskites, otherwise known as perovskite solar cells (PSCs). It was aimed on the development of the electron transport layer (ETL) in the devices, which is critical in allowing them to achieve maximum performance. The project focused on the development of ETLs made from the inorganic compound ZnO, using the deposition technique of atomic layer deposition (ALD). ZnO has excellent electron transport characteristics while being a low-cost material. ALD provides a method to fabricate high quality thin film materials with excellent conformal coverage of surfaces and low pinhole density that are required for good performance in the solar cell. The outcomes of the project were centered on the development an optimized structure for the ZnO layer that involved modifying the amount of oxidation of the thin film, a procedure that is readily carried out in a precise manner with the ALD process. Other film parameters that were optimized include the film thickness, smoothness, and uniformity. The resulting films were incorporated into PSCs, and the results showed improved device performance in both their solar power conversion efficiency and reproducibility. Performance results showed typical increases in efficiency from 13% to 16% with the improved ZnO layer, using the prototype device architectures used for the purposes of the study. A greatly improved fabrication yield of &gt;90% of the approximately 50 individual devices in a given fabrication run was also found.  Intellectual Merit The intellectual merit of the work was rooted in the understanding of the role that oxidation level plays on the structural, electronic, and interfacial properties of ZnO thin layers in PSCs as well as the impact of ALD processing on thin film uniformity and quality. These provide greater fundamental understanding of mechanisms of electron extraction from the PSC active layer and subsequent transport to the negative electrode of the device, along with better understanding of the thin film growth mechanisms that arise from ALD growth of nanometer-scale films necessary for high performance PSCs.   Broader Impacts The broader impacts of the work include the development of a ZnO film structure for improved PSC efficiency, which can be generalized to other fabrication strategies that are suitable for a variety of industrial fabrication processes such as sputter deposition or non-vacuum, solution-based processing. The improvements in fabrication yield that the project demonstrated can have important implications for the future industrialization of the technology, which will require high yields for large-scale production. More broadly, the development of PSCs as a renewable energy technology shows increasing promise to augment or ultimately succeed silicon-based photovoltaics, particularly with tandem-device approaches that can exceed the power conversion efficiency of the commercial PV modules available today. The project also resulted in the training and Ph.D. dissertation of a female graduate student, who intends to go on to an academic career, thus extending the broader impacts to subsequent generations of students and trainees.             Last Modified: 06/17/2019       Submitted by: Sean E Shaheen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
