<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Large Arrays for 5G MU-MIMO Wireless Access Operating in mm-wave Frequency Bands</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The commercial potential of this project lies in enabling much needed high wireless data rates and equal quality of service (QoS) to both densely populated areas as well as remote rural areas. 4G cellular and WiFi networks are facing a bottleneck due to proliferation of wireless devices and limited spectrum available in the currently allocated bands for wireless communications. Improving data connectivity would require new physical fiber to be laid out which is becoming impractical due to high costs vs. return on investment. The Federal Communications Commission has opened more spectrum in the mm-wave frequency spectrum (between 28-70 GHz) for mobile users to alleviate some of these issues. This project will enable spectrally efficient communication through frequency reuse for spatially separated mobile users in the mm-wave frequencies. It will also allow low cost dense deployment of 5G cellular base-stations to boost QoS. With this new paradigms in human machine interaction using machine learning can be advanced further. Remote educational programs, virtual and augmented reality (VR/AR) based learning, online health care and other new services around Internet of Things will be enhanced by better wireless connectivity. These technologies will uplift people?s lives delivering major economic and broad societal impact.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project proposes a revolutionary architecture that will enable massive multi-user MIMO techniques for mm-wave wireless systems to solve the spectrum scarcity issue. The mm-wave radio front end module (FEM) can reuse the same frequencies for spatially diverse mobile users with active beamforming thus enhancing the capacity of current cellular networks by 100x. A multitude of modules (1000s) will be used in a large array as a part of the mm-wave FEM making it crucial to achieve excellent power efficiency at the module level. This project will investigate a variant of Doherty power amplifier (PA) architecture to achieve highly efficient mm-wave transmitter. Module to module variation and within module variations can disturb accurate beamforming capability. Impact of these variations on forming coherent beams will be studied. A new method to calibrate a large array to tune out any module to module variation will be proposed through sufficient redundancies incorporated in the module design. Low sensitivity to calibration errors will be achieved while also trying to lower the calibration time. A new algorithm that achieves accurate simultaneous tracking of spatial mobile users to within 5-degrees using the new architecture will be proposed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1722199</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sriramkumar</FirstName>
<LastName>Venugopalan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sriramkumar Venugopalan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sriram@rf-pixels.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5103643110</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000732975</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>RF Pixels, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Sunnyvale</CityName>
<ZipCode>940871307</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5103643110</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>333 W El Camino Real Ste 250</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080362027</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RF PIXELS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[RF Pixels, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Fremont</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>945382215</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3340 Walnut Ave, Ste 112]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~224996</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-38cbccf3-8f94-7afd-61a9-a2f323ebf681"><br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>Having access to internet data has become a basic utility necessity akin to water and electricity. However ever increasing data rich content like 4K video, AR/VR etc. are beginning to clog the pipes. This data is provided to the end customer either through wired connections or in a wireless manner. For wired connections copper based cable connections are reaching its limits in terms of the data rates it can deliver. Fiber-to-the-home (FTTH) is turning out to be expensive to deploy leading to longer return on investments for internet service providers. We are in a spectrum drought, there is no more wireless spectrum available to transmit high data-rates over the air. mmWave bands such as 28GHz, 39GHz and 60GHz are here to relieve us from this drought offering plentiful spectrum bandwidth enabling a replacement to gigabit fiber.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>However there is a lack of highly integrated and low cost mmWave radio front-ends available commercially for the 28GHz and 39GHz bands. Early prototypes that are being commercially trialled are targeting single beam based solutions optimizing for coverage. However mmWave networks of the future are required to cater to multiple mobile user scenarios. Multi-user MIMO (MU-MIMO) techniques have been shown to provide enhanced throughput by spatially focussing the power to multiple data hotspots. Digital beamforming arrays are cost and computation complexity prohibitive. Radio hardware conducive to MU-MIMO techniques require research and development of novel radio front-end architectures.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>RF Pixels&rsquo; is developing a highly integrated mmWave front end radio module that aims to keep the cost of wireless infrastructure low. The novel scalable tile based architecture can cater to varying requirements on both infrastructure and user equipment side. This tile based architecture also enable massive multi-user MIMO techniques to be applied on the infrastructure side leading to 10x enhancements in throughput delivered in comparison to single link architectures that are being deployed currently in the market.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Through this award period, two semiconductor ICs using TSMC 40nm technology were designed, fabricated and tested. Key IPs that enable the proposed tile architecture were validated as a proof of concept. In the next phase, these IPs will be put together to create a working tile that could actually be used to demonstrate next generation cellular equipments. Further, additional validation from system level performance will allow for creation of production ready IC modules.</span></p> </span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/12/2018<br>      Modified by: Sriramkumar&nbsp;Venugopalan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Having access to internet data has become a basic utility necessity akin to water and electricity. However ever increasing data rich content like 4K video, AR/VR etc. are beginning to clog the pipes. This data is provided to the end customer either through wired connections or in a wireless manner. For wired connections copper based cable connections are reaching its limits in terms of the data rates it can deliver. Fiber-to-the-home (FTTH) is turning out to be expensive to deploy leading to longer return on investments for internet service providers. We are in a spectrum drought, there is no more wireless spectrum available to transmit high data-rates over the air. mmWave bands such as 28GHz, 39GHz and 60GHz are here to relieve us from this drought offering plentiful spectrum bandwidth enabling a replacement to gigabit fiber. However there is a lack of highly integrated and low cost mmWave radio front-ends available commercially for the 28GHz and 39GHz bands. Early prototypes that are being commercially trialled are targeting single beam based solutions optimizing for coverage. However mmWave networks of the future are required to cater to multiple mobile user scenarios. Multi-user MIMO (MU-MIMO) techniques have been shown to provide enhanced throughput by spatially focussing the power to multiple data hotspots. Digital beamforming arrays are cost and computation complexity prohibitive. Radio hardware conducive to MU-MIMO techniques require research and development of novel radio front-end architectures. RF Pixels? is developing a highly integrated mmWave front end radio module that aims to keep the cost of wireless infrastructure low. The novel scalable tile based architecture can cater to varying requirements on both infrastructure and user equipment side. This tile based architecture also enable massive multi-user MIMO techniques to be applied on the infrastructure side leading to 10x enhancements in throughput delivered in comparison to single link architectures that are being deployed currently in the market. Through this award period, two semiconductor ICs using TSMC 40nm technology were designed, fabricated and tested. Key IPs that enable the proposed tile architecture were validated as a proof of concept. In the next phase, these IPs will be put together to create a working tile that could actually be used to demonstrate next generation cellular equipments. Further, additional validation from system level performance will allow for creation of production ready IC modules.        Last Modified: 07/12/2018       Submitted by: Sriramkumar Venugopalan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
