<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:   Scalable and Flexible Algorithms to Detect Structural Change in Complex Sequence Data</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47484.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>47484</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Modern technologies in science and engineering generate data that become bigger in size and more complex in content. It is important and challenging to understand such data using statistical and computational methods, especially to identify trends in the data. Examples include large scale sequence data from genomics and market data from economics. In genomics, researchers search for copy number variations (CNVs) by examining hundreds of thousands of measurements of biomarkers along the whole genome. In financial engineering, it is useful to identify and interpret abrupt changes of stock prices. In these examples, a premier goal is to discover structural changes from massive sequence data. In this collaborative project, the investigators intend to develop and study theoretically sound and practically flexible and portable strategies to analyze complex sequence data and apply the proposed algorithms to real data for scientific discovery. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The investigators aim to develop scalable and flexible algorithms to identify and infer structural changes in contemporary high-throughput data. In particular, they will work on (a) fast change-point detection techniques which are flexible enough to handle non-Gaussian data and dependent data; (b) new statistical framework for joint analysis of multiple-sequence data; (c) theoretical foundations for inference of change points which can assign significant levels for detected change points and achieves the control of false discovery rate (FDR); (d) applications to CNV data for scientific discoveries. Moreover, the investigators plan to develop user-friendly and publicly accessible software for the proposed methods so that researchers can apply the proposed methodologies directly to their research problems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1722562</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Feifei</FirstName>
<LastName>Xiao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Feifei Xiao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xiaof@mailbox.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8037778936</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000739472</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Carolina at Columbia</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Awards Management</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1600 Hampton Street, Suite 414]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041387846</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH CAROLINA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041387846</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Carolina]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbia</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>292010001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[915 Greene St. Room 440]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8069</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E-MSS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~47484</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goals of this project are to design and implement new scalable algorithms to detect structural changes in modern big and complex data, to establish theoretical foundation to these new methods, and to apply them to real applications for scientific discoveries.&nbsp;</p> <p>It is a fundamental problem to uncover structural changes in big and complex data. Due to the tremendous sizes and complex noise distributions that are commonly observed in modern data, scalability and flexibility are two main concerns in developing change-point detection and segment detection algorithms. We have completed a couple of projects, which develop fast change-point detection algorithms for non-Gaussian data. In Xiao et al. (2019), we proposed modSaRa2 that can incorporate a non-Gaussian sequence, called B-Allele Frequency (BAF), for copy number variant (CNV) detection. In Hao et al. (2020), we proposed a nonparametric segment detection algorithm, called super scalable short segment (4S) algorithm, which requires minimal condition on the noise distribution and is robust against heavy-tailed distributions. Besides flexibility, both algorithms are scalable with complexity linear to the length of data sequence. In particular, the 4S algorithm is super-fast, costing only less than 5n operations to analyze a sequence of length n. It outperforms many existing methods in terms of scalability and flexibility.&nbsp;More importantly, it is equipped with an inference framework, which gives a significant level for each detected segment. More recently, in Luo et al., (2020), we proposed a correlation structure integrated segmentation method.&nbsp;Many segmentation algorithms have been developed assuming independent observations in the genetic loci.&nbsp;However, this assumption is violated in the`` genetics perspective due to&nbsp;the existence of correlation among genomic positions such as linkage disequilibrium (LD).&nbsp;We theoretically demonstrated the correlation structure of CNV data and&nbsp;proposed a novel algorithm, LDcnv (Luo et al., 2020), that models the CNV data with its biological characteristics relating to genetic correlation (i.e., LD).</p> <p>In applications, detecting weak CNV signals given the noisy background from genotyping data is the most challenging point. In the new method we developed, modSaRa2 (Xiao et al., 2019), we proposed to integrate more genetic information and external information to increase accuracy and power. By both simulations and real data application, we illustrate its superiority over existing methods.&nbsp;The application of the modSaRa2 to a whole genome melanoma dataset identified novel candidate melanoma risk associated deletions on chromosome regions 1p22.2 and duplications on 6p22, 6q25 and 19p13 regions, which may facilitate the understanding of the possible roles of germline copy number variants in the etiology of melanoma. In our more recently method development (Luo et al., 2020), the LDcnv algorithm may open a door for integrating biological characteristics in CNV detection methodology development with change-point methods.This new segmentation algorithm has a wide scope of application with next-generation sequencing data analysis and single-cell sequencing analysis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/12/2020<br>      Modified by: Feifei&nbsp;Xiao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goals of this project are to design and implement new scalable algorithms to detect structural changes in modern big and complex data, to establish theoretical foundation to these new methods, and to apply them to real applications for scientific discoveries.   It is a fundamental problem to uncover structural changes in big and complex data. Due to the tremendous sizes and complex noise distributions that are commonly observed in modern data, scalability and flexibility are two main concerns in developing change-point detection and segment detection algorithms. We have completed a couple of projects, which develop fast change-point detection algorithms for non-Gaussian data. In Xiao et al. (2019), we proposed modSaRa2 that can incorporate a non-Gaussian sequence, called B-Allele Frequency (BAF), for copy number variant (CNV) detection. In Hao et al. (2020), we proposed a nonparametric segment detection algorithm, called super scalable short segment (4S) algorithm, which requires minimal condition on the noise distribution and is robust against heavy-tailed distributions. Besides flexibility, both algorithms are scalable with complexity linear to the length of data sequence. In particular, the 4S algorithm is super-fast, costing only less than 5n operations to analyze a sequence of length n. It outperforms many existing methods in terms of scalability and flexibility. More importantly, it is equipped with an inference framework, which gives a significant level for each detected segment. More recently, in Luo et al., (2020), we proposed a correlation structure integrated segmentation method. Many segmentation algorithms have been developed assuming independent observations in the genetic loci. However, this assumption is violated in the`` genetics perspective due to the existence of correlation among genomic positions such as linkage disequilibrium (LD). We theoretically demonstrated the correlation structure of CNV data and proposed a novel algorithm, LDcnv (Luo et al., 2020), that models the CNV data with its biological characteristics relating to genetic correlation (i.e., LD).  In applications, detecting weak CNV signals given the noisy background from genotyping data is the most challenging point. In the new method we developed, modSaRa2 (Xiao et al., 2019), we proposed to integrate more genetic information and external information to increase accuracy and power. By both simulations and real data application, we illustrate its superiority over existing methods. The application of the modSaRa2 to a whole genome melanoma dataset identified novel candidate melanoma risk associated deletions on chromosome regions 1p22.2 and duplications on 6p22, 6q25 and 19p13 regions, which may facilitate the understanding of the possible roles of germline copy number variants in the etiology of melanoma. In our more recently method development (Luo et al., 2020), the LDcnv algorithm may open a door for integrating biological characteristics in CNV detection methodology development with change-point methods.This new segmentation algorithm has a wide scope of application with next-generation sequencing data analysis and single-cell sequencing analysis.          Last Modified: 08/12/2020       Submitted by: Feifei Xiao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
