<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: MAKER: Developing a Model for Expanding Informal Tech Education for Underrepresented Communities through Makerspaces</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249960.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299525</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Russell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rlrussel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922995</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will advance efforts of the Innovative Technology Experiences for Students and Teachers (ITEST) program to better understand and promote practices that increase students' motivations and capacities to pursue careers in fields of science, technology, engineering, or mathematics (STEM). Building on a successful approach to technical education training with minority youth through the Baltimore-based Digital Harbor Foundation (DHF), the project will identify efficient and effective methods of scaling maker-based technology education programs, beginning with middle and high school youth. Maker education models provide multiple points of entry for youth to gain exposure, interest, and skill-building in high-growth technology skills. The DH model presents a holistic, scaffolded approach to providing a long-term support for educators and organizations as they integrate maker-based tech learning into their youth offerings.  Project research will inform best practices of scaling youth makerspaces and tech education programs, especially for underrepresented youth. Maker, academic, and youth-service communities will benefit from our training materials, tech education curriculum, and evaluations of diverse engagement strategies. The project will share its experiences, materials, and strategies publicly through DH website, as well as via conferences, papers, as well as dissemination of our training materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will test three professional development models: Satellite-Site, Home-Site, and Remote Engagements. The goal is to find cost-efficient, yet successful mechanisms to disseminate training for informal educators to establish a safe, youth-focused makerspace inside their existing spaces; provide starter curriculum to build basic competencies and maker mindsets for educators and youth; support educators as they independently integrate their own tech projects into future courses and activities in their programs. Project research will: 1) compare three training and deployment methods to integrating a youth-focused makerspace and entry-level curriculum into existing after-school programs; 2) explore an innovative, scaffolded professional development approach that encourages program ownership and continued skill-building for youth-service providers.  Methods and analysis will respond to common techniques of afterschool program management and STEM professional development approaches. As an immediate result of this project, three independent afterschool programs serving diverse audiences will receive basic equipment, training, and curriculum to run their own tech education programs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1723610</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Foad</FirstName>
<LastName>Hamidi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Foad Hamidi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>foadhamidi@umbc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000763249</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Coy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Coy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>andrew@digitalharbor.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4104024189</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000791853</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shawn</FirstName>
<LastName>Grimes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shawn Grimes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Shawn@digitalharbor.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034089094</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000721290</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/30/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Grimes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephanie Grimes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>steph@digitalharbor.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4436819384</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000737520</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/30/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Digital Harbor Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212304017</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4436436085</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1045 Light Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079284215</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DIGITAL HARBOR FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Digital Harbor Foundation]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212304017</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1045 Light Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>058Z</Code>
<Text>EAGER: MAKER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~249960</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~49565</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The <em>EAGER: MAKER: Developing a Model for Expanding Informal Tech Education for Underrepresented Communities through Makerspaces</em> research project accomplished three primary goals, namely: (1) transforming three existing underused spaces into technology-rich makerspaces, (2) utilizing three different models of professional training to train a cohort of educators and administrators in a scaffolded technical maker curriculum for youth, and (3) supporting the new educators in recruiting youth, planning, delivering and assessing programs at each site. The study answered questions relating to efficient and effective methods for scaling maker-based technology education programs for middle and high school aged youth. The project provided empirical evidence on the challenges and opportunities that such deployment and scaling poses to educators and administrators, with a view of informing the design of future programs to empower community initiatives to create and sustain their own programs. <br /><br />Three sites (two in Maryland and one in DC) participated in the program and received training in one of three modes: (1) an home-site engagement where at least 2 educators underwent 3 days of intensive training at the Digital Harbor Foundation (DHF); (2) a satellite-site engagement where a DHF mentor traveled to the site to work side-by-side with at least two educators in their afterschool space for intensive in-person curriculum training over three days; and (3) a remote engagement, where all training and support took place remotely using online resources text- and photo-based task descriptions and session outcomes, with supplementary video demonstrations and talks of complex tasks and course subjects developed by DHF. The sites then recruited 17 youth who completed the program with ongoing support, including multiple visits to each site and monthly check-in calls.<br /><br />Over the course of the grant period, our research found that the programs generated considerable interest in the youth and resulted in positive shifts in career aspirations and social and technical skills. Additionally, educators and administrators reported on the importance of creating hybrid online and offline resources and training materials, and found value in both the technical and pedagogical support provided. It is also of importance to note that the quantitative and qualitative assessment strategies we developed and refined successfully supported self-reflection and the documentation of divergent thinking. Of particular note, we found that retrospective surveys that ask youth to reflect on shifts in their attitudes after completing a program are more effective than the same surveys deployed twice, pre- and post- a program.<br />&nbsp;<br />When asked, "If another youth asked you 'Why should I take this course?', what would you tell them?" youth participant responses included: "It will help you discover who you want to be in your future" and "First you have [a] lot of fun and also have the opportunity to make awesome things and learned about things you are interested in."<br /><br />Findings from research were published and presented at FabLearn 2017, the American Society of Engineering Education 2018, the American Society of Engineering Education (ASEE2020), the Frontiers in Education (FIE20) conference, and Assets-based Design workshop at the Computer Supported Collaborative Work CSCW. Additionally, participants from the research project presented at a National Rec-to-Tech Summit specifically convened to disseminate the project's outcomes and findings, identify areas of needed future work and research, and support implementation of the findings. These publications shared outcomes and learnings generated from the research, including proposing a new method of retrospective assessment that provided a frame of reference for participants, outlining of the impact of participating in the Rec-to-Tech training on educators and administrators, exploration of how our process can be viewed from an assets-based perspective.<br /><br />Findings from this project directly informed a larger collaborative Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) project that builds on and expands on it by setting up four new makerspaces in Baltimore and Pittsburgh using an equity-based approach that emphasizes localization and community-engagement that was awarded in July 2020 (Award Number: 2005502 and 2005484).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;Coy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The EAGER: MAKER: Developing a Model for Expanding Informal Tech Education for Underrepresented Communities through Makerspaces research project accomplished three primary goals, namely: (1) transforming three existing underused spaces into technology-rich makerspaces, (2) utilizing three different models of professional training to train a cohort of educators and administrators in a scaffolded technical maker curriculum for youth, and (3) supporting the new educators in recruiting youth, planning, delivering and assessing programs at each site. The study answered questions relating to efficient and effective methods for scaling maker-based technology education programs for middle and high school aged youth. The project provided empirical evidence on the challenges and opportunities that such deployment and scaling poses to educators and administrators, with a view of informing the design of future programs to empower community initiatives to create and sustain their own programs.   Three sites (two in Maryland and one in DC) participated in the program and received training in one of three modes: (1) an home-site engagement where at least 2 educators underwent 3 days of intensive training at the Digital Harbor Foundation (DHF); (2) a satellite-site engagement where a DHF mentor traveled to the site to work side-by-side with at least two educators in their afterschool space for intensive in-person curriculum training over three days; and (3) a remote engagement, where all training and support took place remotely using online resources text- and photo-based task descriptions and session outcomes, with supplementary video demonstrations and talks of complex tasks and course subjects developed by DHF. The sites then recruited 17 youth who completed the program with ongoing support, including multiple visits to each site and monthly check-in calls.  Over the course of the grant period, our research found that the programs generated considerable interest in the youth and resulted in positive shifts in career aspirations and social and technical skills. Additionally, educators and administrators reported on the importance of creating hybrid online and offline resources and training materials, and found value in both the technical and pedagogical support provided. It is also of importance to note that the quantitative and qualitative assessment strategies we developed and refined successfully supported self-reflection and the documentation of divergent thinking. Of particular note, we found that retrospective surveys that ask youth to reflect on shifts in their attitudes after completing a program are more effective than the same surveys deployed twice, pre- and post- a program.   When asked, "If another youth asked you 'Why should I take this course?', what would you tell them?" youth participant responses included: "It will help you discover who you want to be in your future" and "First you have [a] lot of fun and also have the opportunity to make awesome things and learned about things you are interested in."  Findings from research were published and presented at FabLearn 2017, the American Society of Engineering Education 2018, the American Society of Engineering Education (ASEE2020), the Frontiers in Education (FIE20) conference, and Assets-based Design workshop at the Computer Supported Collaborative Work CSCW. Additionally, participants from the research project presented at a National Rec-to-Tech Summit specifically convened to disseminate the project's outcomes and findings, identify areas of needed future work and research, and support implementation of the findings. These publications shared outcomes and learnings generated from the research, including proposing a new method of retrospective assessment that provided a frame of reference for participants, outlining of the impact of participating in the Rec-to-Tech training on educators and administrators, exploration of how our process can be viewed from an assets-based perspective.  Findings from this project directly informed a larger collaborative Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) project that builds on and expands on it by setting up four new makerspaces in Baltimore and Pittsburgh using an equity-based approach that emphasizes localization and community-engagement that was awarded in July 2020 (Award Number: 2005502 and 2005484).       Last Modified: 12/30/2020       Submitted by: Andrew Coy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
