<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CNS: Travel Support for the 2017 International Conference on Autonomic Computing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marilyn McClure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmcclure@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The International Conference on Autonomic Computing (ICAC) to be held in Columbus, Ohio on July 17-21, 2017.  The conference is the leading conference on autonomic computing techniques, foundations, and applications.  The conference covers a wide range of topics that impacts the core of Computer Network and Systems Research (CNS).  This includes but are not limited to data centers, cloud computing, smart cities, cyber-physical systems, sensors, and embedded systems, which are all applications for autonomic computing. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference focuses on exposing the state of the art in the area of autonomic computing systems that reduce the burden of large unwieldy systems by allowing the systems to more effectively manage their own behavior in ways that maximizes performance and minimizes cost reliably and securely. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ICAC 2017 will offer many opportunities for students to meet, interact, and exchange ideas in both a formal and an informal atmosphere to ensure that students and experts interact. It is important for the US to remain engaged and competitive in this area.  This grant will fund US graduate and undergraduate students who would not normally be able to attend.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/03/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/03/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1724811</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Stewart</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher Stewart</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cstewart@cse.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5857197769</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000534897</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2015 Neil Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 14th International Conference on Autonomic Computing (ICAC) was hosted in Columbus, OH during July 17-21.&nbsp; ICAC is the leading conference on autonomic computing techniques, foundations, and applications. Large-scale systems of all types, such as data centers, computer clouds, smart cities, cyber-physical systems, sensor networks, and embedded or pervasive environments, are becoming increasingly complex and burdensome for people to manage. Autonomic computing systems reduce this burden by managing their own behavior in accordance with high-level goals.&nbsp;</p> <p>This year, 20 people received partial or full travel grants.&nbsp; These participants represented a wide range of backgrounds: 8 were from R1 doctoral instutitions, 8 were from liberal arts colleges or smaller universities in the mainland US or Puerto Rico, 4 were international students, 4 were women, 1 was a first-generation college student from a rural setting, and 1 was an underrepresented minority.&nbsp;</p> <p>NSF Award #1724811 sponsored only the 16 attendees from the United States.&nbsp; Google sponsored international students ($3000 gift).&nbsp; Students received either (1) full grants which covered registration and hotel (roughly $1209), (2) partial grants which covered only registration ($549), or (3) partial grants that offset part of registration costs ($200).&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The travel grant program was organized by PI Stewart with assistance from administrative staff in the Computer Science and Engineering Department at The Ohio State University.&nbsp; We used Google Docs to accept applications where students described (1) anticipated travel dates and costs, (2) interest in attending ICAC, and (3) references from faculty.&nbsp; To increase participation, we preferred students that would be first-time attendees to ICAC.&nbsp; This was crucial.&nbsp; More than half of the awardees were not regular ICAC participants.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>More generally, ICAC 2017 was well received by the community.&nbsp; Participation and submissions aligned with previous iterations of the conference while the acceptance rate fell to 19%.&nbsp; Attendees raved about the strength of accepted papers and the rigorous discussion after talks.&nbsp; Travel grant participants actively questioned presenters and were engaged during the poster session.&nbsp; ICAC 2017, with NSF support, added to the US reputation as a research leader in this critical area.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/08/2017<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;Stewart</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 14th International Conference on Autonomic Computing (ICAC) was hosted in Columbus, OH during July 17-21.  ICAC is the leading conference on autonomic computing techniques, foundations, and applications. Large-scale systems of all types, such as data centers, computer clouds, smart cities, cyber-physical systems, sensor networks, and embedded or pervasive environments, are becoming increasingly complex and burdensome for people to manage. Autonomic computing systems reduce this burden by managing their own behavior in accordance with high-level goals.   This year, 20 people received partial or full travel grants.  These participants represented a wide range of backgrounds: 8 were from R1 doctoral instutitions, 8 were from liberal arts colleges or smaller universities in the mainland US or Puerto Rico, 4 were international students, 4 were women, 1 was a first-generation college student from a rural setting, and 1 was an underrepresented minority.   NSF Award #1724811 sponsored only the 16 attendees from the United States.  Google sponsored international students ($3000 gift).  Students received either (1) full grants which covered registration and hotel (roughly $1209), (2) partial grants which covered only registration ($549), or (3) partial grants that offset part of registration costs ($200).    The travel grant program was organized by PI Stewart with assistance from administrative staff in the Computer Science and Engineering Department at The Ohio State University.  We used Google Docs to accept applications where students described (1) anticipated travel dates and costs, (2) interest in attending ICAC, and (3) references from faculty.  To increase participation, we preferred students that would be first-time attendees to ICAC.  This was crucial.  More than half of the awardees were not regular ICAC participants.    More generally, ICAC 2017 was well received by the community.  Participation and submissions aligned with previous iterations of the conference while the acceptance rate fell to 19%.  Attendees raved about the strength of accepted papers and the rigorous discussion after talks.  Travel grant participants actively questioned presenters and were engaged during the poster session.  ICAC 2017, with NSF support, added to the US reputation as a research leader in this critical area.          Last Modified: 11/08/2017       Submitted by: Christopher Stewart]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
