<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of FACS Cell Sorter for Research on Antibiotic Resistance and Environmental Toxicant Receptors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224246.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224246</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rfleisch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An award is made to Kenyon College to obtain a fluorescence-activated cell sorter (FACS). The cell sorter will enable separation and quantitation of cell types for experimental evolution of bacteria to study antibiotic resistance and survival in acid. This project may reveal chemical agents important in the fitness of bacterial populations. The instrument will also enable measurement of DNA content in animal cells, revealing how cells divide and respond to environmental toxicants. Both these aims have potential benefits for environmental quality. The FACS will enhance two undergraduate research programs serving approximately 25 undergraduates who publish transformative research at Kenyon College; many of them subsequently enter the nation?s science research pipeline. First-year students will participate in research, an important high-impact practice (HIP) that enhances STEM retention. The undergraduate research population includes economically disadvantaged students in Kenyon's NSF-funded S-STEM program. In subsequent years, the instrument will serve additional undergraduate research projects in environmental microbiology and immunology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The FACS will be employed to test chemical agents that may reverse antibiotic resistance in bacterial populations. This instrument enables rapid screening of resistance-reversal agents by cell analysis for fitness competition assays. It will also facilitate a novel means of isolating bacterial mutants that have altered cytoplasmic pH, using a fluorophore with pH-dependent excitation peaks. Another undergraduate research program addresses the mechanism of amphibian receptors for dioxins and other important environmental pollutants called aryl hydrocarbons. The FACS will enable testing of an exciting hypothesis that aryl hydrocarbon receptors play distinct roles in regulating the cell cycle, a key process for development and carcinogenesis. Beyond the grant period, the FACS will enable development of new research on the microbial community structure of aquatic systems subject to human disturbance. An immunology program will investigate the role of macrophage activation in stress induction of asthma.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1725426</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joan</FirstName>
<LastName>Slonczewski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joan L Slonczewski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>slonczewski@kenyon.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7404275397</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000122764</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wade</FirstName>
<LastName>Powell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wade H Powell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>powellw@kenyon.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7404275396</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000345880</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kenyon College</Name>
<CityName>Gambier</CityName>
<ZipCode>430229623</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7404275114</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>22 Ransom Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>063580369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KENYON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>063580369</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Kenyon College]]></Name>
<CityName>Gambier</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>430229623</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 N. College Road, Kenyon Coll]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~224246</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Kenyon College biologists obtained a FACSMelody fluorescence-activated cell sorter, an instrument that separates living cells tagged by fluorescent molecules. This instrument enabled exciting investigations in three fields: the evolution and reversal of bacterial drug resistance, the molecular biology of frog cell response to environmental toxicants, and the immunology of maternal stress response.</p> <p>The cell sorter enables us to count individual cells and identify distinct mutants and physiological forms. Joan Slonczewski uses the FACS to count drug-resistant and drug-sensitive cells cultured in the presence of aspirin derivatives. These experiments show how pharmaceuticals may help select against dangerous drug-resistant bacteria. The study was submitted for publication by Honors undergraduate Samantha Schaffner and ten additional students. The excitement of this powerful technique inspires the next generation of young scientists.</p> <p>Wade Powell uses the instrument to observe cell cycle regulation in cultured frog cells that have a mutant receptor for environmental toxicants such as dioxins. Surprisingly, the FACS revealed a new class of cell population (called sub-G1) that may evade apoptosis (programmed cell death). Undergraduate researcher Wyatt Cole pioneered this work, earning a national prize from the Society for Toxicology for his presentation.</p> <p>Arianna Smith studies how maternal stress leads to allergies in the offspring. She uses the FACS instrument to identify leukocytes (a type of immune cells) from the lungs of mice. Her undergraduates Myanna Cook and Liana Valin compare cell populations between mouse offspring born to stressed and non-stressed mothers. Smith serves as a role model for underserved minority students, attracting them to participate in research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/06/2020<br>      Modified by: Joan&nbsp;L&nbsp;Slonczewski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1725426/1725426_10518373_1607295989040_MRI_2020_Outcomes--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1725426/1725426_10518373_1607295989040_MRI_2020_Outcomes--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FACS Cell Analysis"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1725426/1725426_10518373_1607295989040_MRI_2020_Outcomes--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FACS Cell Analysis"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">FACS analysis of drug-resistant bacteria and of toxicant receptor mutant frog cells</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joan Slonczewski and Wade Powell</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joan&nbsp;L&nbsp;Slonczewski</div> <div class="imageTitle">FACS Cell Analysis</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1725426/1725426_10518373_1607296084699_MRI_2020_Outcomes_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1725426/1725426_10518373_1607296084699_MRI_2020_Outcomes_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FACS Analysis of Immune Cells"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1725426/1725426_10518373_1607296084699_MRI_2020_Outcomes_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FACS Analysis of Immune Cells"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">FACS identifies CD45+ immune cells</div> <div class="imageCredit">Arianna Smith</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joan&nbsp;L&nbsp;Slonczewski</div> <div class="imageTitle">FACS Analysis of Immune Cells</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Kenyon College biologists obtained a FACSMelody fluorescence-activated cell sorter, an instrument that separates living cells tagged by fluorescent molecules. This instrument enabled exciting investigations in three fields: the evolution and reversal of bacterial drug resistance, the molecular biology of frog cell response to environmental toxicants, and the immunology of maternal stress response.  The cell sorter enables us to count individual cells and identify distinct mutants and physiological forms. Joan Slonczewski uses the FACS to count drug-resistant and drug-sensitive cells cultured in the presence of aspirin derivatives. These experiments show how pharmaceuticals may help select against dangerous drug-resistant bacteria. The study was submitted for publication by Honors undergraduate Samantha Schaffner and ten additional students. The excitement of this powerful technique inspires the next generation of young scientists.  Wade Powell uses the instrument to observe cell cycle regulation in cultured frog cells that have a mutant receptor for environmental toxicants such as dioxins. Surprisingly, the FACS revealed a new class of cell population (called sub-G1) that may evade apoptosis (programmed cell death). Undergraduate researcher Wyatt Cole pioneered this work, earning a national prize from the Society for Toxicology for his presentation.  Arianna Smith studies how maternal stress leads to allergies in the offspring. She uses the FACS instrument to identify leukocytes (a type of immune cells) from the lungs of mice. Her undergraduates Myanna Cook and Liana Valin compare cell populations between mouse offspring born to stressed and non-stressed mothers. Smith serves as a role model for underserved minority students, attracting them to participate in research.                Last Modified: 12/06/2020       Submitted by: Joan L Slonczewski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
