<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Fluorescence Activated Cell Sorting System to Expand Synergistic Research and Educational Opportunities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256080.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256080</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rfleisch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An award is made to Miami University for the acquisition of a fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) system.  The FACS system will expand synergistic research and educational opportunities in southwest Ohio. This instrument will enhance Miami University's substantial commitment to undergraduate education and community outreach at all levels of education and socioeconomic status. New undergraduate laboratory exercises will incorporate the use of hands-on cell sorting experiences using the new FACS system. Miami University will also use the FACS system to enrich several existing community outreach programs including Talawanda Science Week, designed to inspire local elementary school students to enter STEM fields, and the Cincinnati Museum Center STEM Girls Day Out program serving 8-14 year old girls from the eight county area surrounding Cincinnati, Ohio tri-state region. The FACS system will create a centerpiece to solicit partners from agriculture and industry in collaboration with the BioOhio organization that serves the needs of biotechnology-driven companies in Ohio. Miami University's Hefner Museum of Natural History will also create an interactive, student-curated exhibit to introduce the principles of cell sorting, and how cell sorting technology can advance multidisciplinary scientific inquiry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The FACS system will support a broad range of ongoing, interdisciplinary research that ranges from tissues, to organs, to ecological communities. Regeneration research supported by the FACS system, at Miami University, include programs designed at bioengineering retina, bone, adipose tissue and liver. The FACS system will also enhance current Miami University research programs investigating inflammation, neuronal survival following injury, mitochondrial metabolism and male reproductive physiology. Furthermore, the FACS system will open up new avenues of investigation supporting current ecological work at Miami University studying algae and abiotic stress, microbial metabolism, and climate change impacts on autotroph/heterotroph interactions in lake ecosystems. In addition to providing an essential tool for current research, the FACS system will also foster the development of new collaborations and research areas to support economic, intellectual, and educational development in the southwest Ohio region.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1726645</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katia</FirstName>
<LastName>Del Rio-Tsonis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katia Del Rio-Tsonis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>delriok@miamioh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5135292161</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000439633</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Robinson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael L Robinson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robinsm5@miamioh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5135292353</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000539388</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>James</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul F James</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jamespf@miamioh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5135293129</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000560474</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Saul</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin M Saul</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sauljm@miamioh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5135290769</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000682021</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Wilson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy J Wilson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tim.wilson@miamioh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5135293600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000748578</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Miami University</Name>
<CityName>Oxford</CityName>
<ZipCode>450563653</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5135293600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 E High Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Roudebush Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041065129</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MIAMI UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041065129</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Miami University]]></Name>
<CityName>Oxford</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>450561602</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 E. High Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~256080</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Major Research Instrumentation award (1726645) entitled Acquisition of a Fluorescence Activated Cell Sorting System to Expand Synergistic Research and Educational Opportunities provided the funding to acquire a FACS-Melody system from Benton, Dickinson &amp; Company to conduct fluorescence activated cell sorting (FACS) at Miami University.&nbsp; Prior to this award, there were no opportunities to use this technology for teaching or research at the Miami University campus. The award has resulted in several key research, teaching and broader impacts outcomes briefly summarized here.</p> <p>RESEARCH HIGHLIGHTS</p> <ul> <li>The FACS system facilitated the development of a unique human pluripotent stem cell line that can act as a reporter for the differentiation of three neural retina cell types in human retinal organoids, human retinal tissue differentiated <em>in vitro</em>. Following publication, these cells were distributed to laboratories throughout the world.&nbsp; These cells also were used as a basis for a winning Phase II proposal for the 3D-Retinal Organoid Challenge sponsored by the National Eye Institute to screen drugs to treat human retinal diseases (see <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gh0IqFZV_I0">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gh0IqFZV_I0</a>).</li> <li>The use of the FACS system led to the development of a successful, NIH-funded research project to elucidate how epigenetic changes in DNA regulate sperm physiology.</li> <li>The FACS system at Miami University has been instrumental in establishing a strong molecular immunology program that has made fundamental discoveries in how mammals respond to vaccination or microbial infection.</li> <li>The FACS Melody system is the cornerstone of a new flow cytometry/cell sorter suite available for use by Miami University faculty and students in the renovated lower level of Pearson Hall (Rm 072).</li> </ul> <p>EDUCATIONAL HIGHLIGHTS</p> <ul> <li>At least five graduate students and over twenty undergraduate students have been trained in the use of the FACS machine.&nbsp; </li> <li>Dr. Timothy Wilson incorporated the FACS Melody system into laboratory exercises in his undergraduate immunology course.</li> <li>A group of undergraduate students from diverse backgrounds participated in an independent study course to design an exhibit through the Hefner Museum of Natural History to convey the use of fluorescence activated cell sorting to the general public.</li> </ul> <p>BROADER IMPACTS</p> <ul> <li>The use of the FACS machine has been demonstrated to several high school groups visiting Miami University during undergraduate recruiting events.</li> <li>The FACS machine was a feature of science demonstrations for Careers Involving Quantitative Skills (CIQS) day. CIQS Day is a day for high school women to come to the Oxford campus of Miami University, participate in activities with faculty and current students, listen to student presentations, and converse with women who are working in STEM fields and in fields where good quantitative skills are needed. Activities included topics from analytics, biology, chemistry, geography, information systems, mathematics, psychology, and statistics.</li> <li>We collaborated with the Hefner Museum of Natural History to create a Discovery Trunk entitled "The Science of Sorting." This science kit is offered to grades K-8 and this material has been published on Qubes, an Open Educational Resources platform. (Robinson, J., Liechty, M. t., Kramer, A. (2021). Science of Sorting. QUBES Educational Resources. doi:10.25334/E4PB-4V21). Qubes makes it possible to track usage of published materials to see how the materials impact educational opportunities across the country. This recently released publication (April 21, 2021) was viewed by 45 educators in the first week after publication. If each of these educators has just 10 students, the Discovery Trunk materials will have impacted 450 students in the first week.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;L&nbsp;Robinson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Major Research Instrumentation award (1726645) entitled Acquisition of a Fluorescence Activated Cell Sorting System to Expand Synergistic Research and Educational Opportunities provided the funding to acquire a FACS-Melody system from Benton, Dickinson &amp; Company to conduct fluorescence activated cell sorting (FACS) at Miami University.  Prior to this award, there were no opportunities to use this technology for teaching or research at the Miami University campus. The award has resulted in several key research, teaching and broader impacts outcomes briefly summarized here.  RESEARCH HIGHLIGHTS  The FACS system facilitated the development of a unique human pluripotent stem cell line that can act as a reporter for the differentiation of three neural retina cell types in human retinal organoids, human retinal tissue differentiated in vitro. Following publication, these cells were distributed to laboratories throughout the world.  These cells also were used as a basis for a winning Phase II proposal for the 3D-Retinal Organoid Challenge sponsored by the National Eye Institute to screen drugs to treat human retinal diseases (see https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gh0IqFZV_I0). The use of the FACS system led to the development of a successful, NIH-funded research project to elucidate how epigenetic changes in DNA regulate sperm physiology. The FACS system at Miami University has been instrumental in establishing a strong molecular immunology program that has made fundamental discoveries in how mammals respond to vaccination or microbial infection. The FACS Melody system is the cornerstone of a new flow cytometry/cell sorter suite available for use by Miami University faculty and students in the renovated lower level of Pearson Hall (Rm 072).   EDUCATIONAL HIGHLIGHTS  At least five graduate students and over twenty undergraduate students have been trained in the use of the FACS machine.   Dr. Timothy Wilson incorporated the FACS Melody system into laboratory exercises in his undergraduate immunology course. A group of undergraduate students from diverse backgrounds participated in an independent study course to design an exhibit through the Hefner Museum of Natural History to convey the use of fluorescence activated cell sorting to the general public.   BROADER IMPACTS  The use of the FACS machine has been demonstrated to several high school groups visiting Miami University during undergraduate recruiting events. The FACS machine was a feature of science demonstrations for Careers Involving Quantitative Skills (CIQS) day. CIQS Day is a day for high school women to come to the Oxford campus of Miami University, participate in activities with faculty and current students, listen to student presentations, and converse with women who are working in STEM fields and in fields where good quantitative skills are needed. Activities included topics from analytics, biology, chemistry, geography, information systems, mathematics, psychology, and statistics. We collaborated with the Hefner Museum of Natural History to create a Discovery Trunk entitled "The Science of Sorting." This science kit is offered to grades K-8 and this material has been published on Qubes, an Open Educational Resources platform. (Robinson, J., Liechty, M. t., Kramer, A. (2021). Science of Sorting. QUBES Educational Resources. doi:10.25334/E4PB-4V21). Qubes makes it possible to track usage of published materials to see how the materials impact educational opportunities across the country. This recently released publication (April 21, 2021) was viewed by 45 educators in the first week after publication. If each of these educators has just 10 students, the Discovery Trunk materials will have impacted 450 students in the first week.           Last Modified: 04/30/2021       Submitted by: Michael L Robinson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
