<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Adaptive Cluster for Performance and Forensics Analysis of Distributed Machine Learning</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>115100.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>147100</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rita Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rrodrigu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project, acquiring a computational cluster, aims to provide opportunities for research in machine-learning, algorithm development, and protection of information in multiple environments. The capacity to evaluate and analyze performance and residue data generation in data mining, machine learning computations, should allow better control and less risk of breaches in cybersecurity. The availability of these enhancements would also permit use of these systems for applied, interdisciplinary research using large-scale data and cross-correlation analyses for predictive modeling. The investigators measure performance systematically to support forensic analysis of data residues, in order to detect possible security risks in the use of such platforms. The procurement of the instrumentation yields a significant expansion in data mining, security, and forensics research. Core research foci in cyber security, digital forensics, and data mining research enables a work plan based on defined problems in distributed computing environments related to performance, algorithms, and data security. The gained instrument and expertise provide the institution with the ability to support national level customers such as U.S. Army Aviation &amp; Missile Research, Development and Engineering Center, National Institute of Health (NIH), and other government agencies that depend on effective and secure distributed learning to analyze and process sensitive data. A key issue with solving both the forensics challenges and the performance analysis is having access to an instrument such that investigators can&lt;br/&gt;- Tune, adjust, and redeploy environments, &lt;br/&gt;- Take nodes offline to be examined forensically, &lt;br/&gt;- Ensure a consistent baseline exists against which other environments are compared, and &lt;br/&gt;- Run meaningful experiments within their discipline while enabling the collection of valuable performance and forensics data (permitting non-data mining and utilizing digital forensics).&lt;br/&gt;The proposed adaptive cluster instrument enables these four goals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:&lt;br/&gt;The computational research capabilities provide essential resources for undergraduate and graduate students' research as well as for training and exposure activities involving K-12. Students will be afforded hands-on opportunities in research and classroom activities directly utilizing the cluster. The skills gained should lead directly to internships and permanent employment opportunities for doctoral students in the six colleges and/or institutes. The university services a high percentage of rural and financially depressed areas; has a 34% enrollment of non-white students, with 60% female enrollment. The instrumentation offers exposure opportunities for cohort activities to Scholarships for Service Program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/14/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1726069</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Benton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan G Benton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rbenton@southalabama.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2514606298</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000057761</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jordan</FirstName>
<LastName>Shropshire</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jordan Shropshire</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jshropshire@southalabama.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2514607888</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000600692</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Glisson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William B Glisson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>glisson@shsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9362941579</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000671420</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Alabama</Name>
<CityName>Mobile</CityName>
<ZipCode>366880002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2514606333</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>307 University Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>172750234</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH ALABAMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>172750234</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Alabama]]></Name>
<CityName>Mobile</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>366880002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[150 Jaguar Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>049Y</Code>
<Text>ATW-Alan T Waterman Award</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>050Y</Code>
<Text>NMS-National Medal of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>053Y</Code>
<Text>SSIP-Summer Scholars Internshi</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~115100</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Cloud computing has become an affordable and prevalent solution for companies, non-profits, and government agencies. However, it also offers many challenges, including the securing of the infrastructure, digital forensic analysis related to breeches within the cloud infrastructure, workload optimization, and efficient data analysis pipelines, among others.</p> <p>This project&rsquo;s goal was to acquire, at the University of South Alabama, a computational cluster that was configured to support cloud infrastructure.&nbsp; The infrastructure was designed to enable two main research thrusts: (a) determine impacts of cloud infrastructure choices on the performance of machine learning/data mining algorithms and (b) develop tools and techniques to enable efficient and robust digital forensic investigations of compromised cloud infrastructures.&nbsp; The former would allow for enhanced configurations of data analysis pipelines, as well as guide the design of the underlying distributed machine learning algorithms.&nbsp; The latter is needed, as there are relatively few studies providing detailed methods, techniques, and tools to gather forensic data from cloud environments.</p> <p>We acquired a sixteen node cluster, composed of two management nodes and fourteen computational nodes, two dedicated switches, as well as the rack and uninterrupted power supply. It has been subdivided into a thirteen node system, which allows the system managers to create and deploy several multiple virtual machine environments.&nbsp; These environments can be configured to meet various project needs, ranging from a single virtual machine that enables standard algorithm development and testing, to multiple virtual machines hosting a Big Data platform, to a heterogeneous set of virtual machines that allows for a range of web-based development.&nbsp; This setup&rsquo;s flexibility allows us to host multiple applications, which allows for testing the impact of different environments of data analysis techniques and allows for the testing of what can be recovered using developed cloud forensic methods and tools.&nbsp; The remaining three nodes are designed for a bare-metal environment, allowing for the testing of forensics techniques that expect, or would benefit, from analyzing the cloud layer from the base nodes all the way to the applets running within containers.</p> <p>The system has supported the research and development efforts of over 25 students, including undergraduates in biology, biomedical sciences, computer science, information technology, and computing, master&rsquo;s students in biological sciences and computer science, and doctoral students in medical science, basic medical science and computing. This includes two doctoral dissertations that deal with (a) stack performance analysis and (b) forensics of distributed file systems.&nbsp; It has supported at least seven funded projects in the computing field to digital forensics and machine learning; many of the projects involve a technology transfer component and has been incorporated into at least ten grants. Acquired funding has included REU supplements, which supported three undergraduate researchers and an NSF grant (2030080) pertaining to transfer RNA fragment analysis. Finally, the cluster has presented opportunities for concept and technology demonstrations in undergraduate and graduate courses in Data Mining, Advanced Big Data, Concurrent and Distributed Computing, and Cloud Computing.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/20/2021<br>      Modified by: Ryan&nbsp;G&nbsp;Benton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Cloud computing has become an affordable and prevalent solution for companies, non-profits, and government agencies. However, it also offers many challenges, including the securing of the infrastructure, digital forensic analysis related to breeches within the cloud infrastructure, workload optimization, and efficient data analysis pipelines, among others.  This project’s goal was to acquire, at the University of South Alabama, a computational cluster that was configured to support cloud infrastructure.  The infrastructure was designed to enable two main research thrusts: (a) determine impacts of cloud infrastructure choices on the performance of machine learning/data mining algorithms and (b) develop tools and techniques to enable efficient and robust digital forensic investigations of compromised cloud infrastructures.  The former would allow for enhanced configurations of data analysis pipelines, as well as guide the design of the underlying distributed machine learning algorithms.  The latter is needed, as there are relatively few studies providing detailed methods, techniques, and tools to gather forensic data from cloud environments.  We acquired a sixteen node cluster, composed of two management nodes and fourteen computational nodes, two dedicated switches, as well as the rack and uninterrupted power supply. It has been subdivided into a thirteen node system, which allows the system managers to create and deploy several multiple virtual machine environments.  These environments can be configured to meet various project needs, ranging from a single virtual machine that enables standard algorithm development and testing, to multiple virtual machines hosting a Big Data platform, to a heterogeneous set of virtual machines that allows for a range of web-based development.  This setup’s flexibility allows us to host multiple applications, which allows for testing the impact of different environments of data analysis techniques and allows for the testing of what can be recovered using developed cloud forensic methods and tools.  The remaining three nodes are designed for a bare-metal environment, allowing for the testing of forensics techniques that expect, or would benefit, from analyzing the cloud layer from the base nodes all the way to the applets running within containers.  The system has supported the research and development efforts of over 25 students, including undergraduates in biology, biomedical sciences, computer science, information technology, and computing, master’s students in biological sciences and computer science, and doctoral students in medical science, basic medical science and computing. This includes two doctoral dissertations that deal with (a) stack performance analysis and (b) forensics of distributed file systems.  It has supported at least seven funded projects in the computing field to digital forensics and machine learning; many of the projects involve a technology transfer component and has been incorporated into at least ten grants. Acquired funding has included REU supplements, which supported three undergraduate researchers and an NSF grant (2030080) pertaining to transfer RNA fragment analysis. Finally, the cluster has presented opportunities for concept and technology demonstrations in undergraduate and graduate courses in Data Mining, Advanced Big Data, Concurrent and Distributed Computing, and Cloud Computing.       Last Modified: 01/20/2021       Submitted by: Ryan G Benton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
