<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: SusChEM: Acquisition of a hybrid distributed computer system to enhance integration of chemical theory, computation, and experimental research at Duquesne University</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>265060.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>265060</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carlos Murillo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cmurillo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924970</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) and the Chemistry Research Instrumentation Programs. Professor Jeffrey Evanseck from Duquesne University and colleagues Jeffry Madura, Ellen Gawalt, Mihaela-Rita Mihailescu, and Tomislav Pintauer are acquiring a hybrid computer cluster having central processing units (CPUs) and graphics processing units (GPUs).  The cluster is used in computational chemistry research projects.  These projects employ theoretical chemistry programs and algorithms or processes using principles from quantum mechanics or molecular mechanics (often called molecular dynamics simulations).  The acquisition enables graduate and undergraduate students to undertake computational research projects. Using theoretical methods coded into computer programs, they provide insight on projects involving the development of novel materials for energy conversion, gas storage, sensors and catalysis, and the development of new biomaterials with superior properties. The computer cluster is a resource for students and researchers at other institutions such as Lincoln, Chatham, Slippery Rock, Washington and Jefferson, and Franciscan Universities as well as the University of Texas Rio Grande Valley.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The computer cluster enhances research and education at all levels. It enables investigations of the intrinsic structure and reactivity of actinide ions, diamond-like semiconductors, and catalyst regeneration in transition metal mediated atom addition and cyclation reactions. The instrumentation is also used for studies of dopamine and serotonin transporters and of thermodynamics of chlatrate hydrates. The cluster benefits the study of formyl and alpha-hydrogen bonds and the investigation of friction and wear in organic films.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1726824</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Seybert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David W Seybert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>seybert@duq.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4123966465</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000218538</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffry</FirstName>
<LastName>Madura</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffry D Madura</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>madura@duq.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4123964129</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000224167</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/30/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Evanseck</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey D Evanseck</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>evanseck@duq.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4123966337</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000288320</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ellen</FirstName>
<LastName>Gawalt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ellen S Gawalt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gawalte@duq.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4123964709</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000245305</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mihaela-Rita</FirstName>
<LastName>Mihailescu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mihaela-Rita Mihailescu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mihailescum@duq.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4123961430</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000114277</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tomislav</FirstName>
<LastName>Pintauer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tomislav Pintauer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pintauert@duq.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4123966326</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000225626</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/30/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duquesne University</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152193016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4123961537</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Room 310 Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[600 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004501193</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUQUESNE UNIVERSITY OF THE HOLY SPIRIT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004501193</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duquesne University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152820001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[600 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>Chemical Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8009</Code>
<Text>Scientifc Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~265060</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We have been successful in accomplishing our goals outlined in the CHE-1726824 grant titled &ldquo;MRI: Acquisition of a hybrid distributed computer system to enhance integration of chemical theory, computation and experimental research at Duquesne University&rdquo;. Specifically, in the short 17 months of operation, we have&nbsp;<strong>(1) established high performance computing (HPC)&nbsp;</strong>that provides faculty and students the ability to investigate large molecular systems of interest using modern computational techniques with fast enough turn-around times to make timely and significant advances in chemical research and discovery that complement collaborative experimental efforts. The MRI supercomputer is a distributed-memory, high-performance cluster of 572 cores, 8.448 Tb memory, 11 GPUs and 180 Tb of disk. It is significant that more than seven regional research teams and more than half of the Duquesne faculty members have been using the machine since it became operational on July 3, 2019. Moreover, we have&nbsp;<strong>(2) had regional impact</strong>&nbsp;by creating meaningful and regional research teams of faculty and students from primarily undergraduate institutions (PUIs) in the Appalachian Region with limited research infrastructure, serious financial hardships due to declining enrollments from several factors including COVID-19, and especially those encouraging underrepresented populations of students. Pittsburgh is one of the few urban areas within the Appalachian region that can serve regional faculty and students from Slippery Rock University, Westminster College, Franciscan University of Steubenville OH, Washington and Jefferson College, and Saint Mary&rsquo;s College of Maryland, which have become continuous users of the supercomputer center. Duquesne has served as an essential resource that addresses the need for higher education and HPC training of the Appalachian workforce. The use of the supercomputer has enhanced the scholarship productivity of Duquesne and regional faculty, and motivated the next generation of student chemists. In 17 months, the users have ten publications in print or submitted in the peer-review process along with 45 student presentations and one patent application.&nbsp;&nbsp;By providing HPC equipment, we have also&nbsp;<strong>(3) provided training of chemists</strong>&nbsp;by creating a series of seven skilled workshops coupled with ten in-depth lectures on HPC by academic and industrial experts on the fundamentals of molecular modeling, and the use of state of-the-art computational facilities and modern software to advance experimental research. The workshops targeted the scientific method, scientific computing, and HPC. The workshops started with instruction on the use of electronic laboratory notebooks, literature workshop, and ten lectures on the aspects of integrating theory and computations into experimental research. We have been successful in creating a unique learning environment with specialized workshops to inspire creativity and boost research productivity. In addition, we have recruited&nbsp;<strong>(4) underrepresented populations</strong>&nbsp;of students and faculty. Specifically, we have offered opportunities to underrepresented students, female scientists, and those who might not otherwise have the opportunity of a research experience, particularly those from institutions where research programs are limited in the Appalachian Region. Finally, we have encouraged and provided&nbsp;<strong>(5) career development and networking</strong>&nbsp;for the students. Professional development was realized through exposure to world-renowned industrial experts from Gaussian (Doug Fox) and academic faculty, a weekly seminar program, and travel (Zoom) to regional and national ACS meetings. Specifically, the students were encouraged to attend the 2020 University of Michigan Research Symposium (Uranium) along with Duquesne&rsquo;s 2020 Undergraduate Research Regional Symposium. Our completed efforts on CHE-1726824 has the added consequence of enhancing and diversifying the U.S. workforce by adding experts in the fields of high-performance computing specializing in chemistry or biochemistry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/12/2021<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;D&nbsp;Evanseck</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We have been successful in accomplishing our goals outlined in the CHE-1726824 grant titled "MRI: Acquisition of a hybrid distributed computer system to enhance integration of chemical theory, computation and experimental research at Duquesne University". Specifically, in the short 17 months of operation, we have (1) established high performance computing (HPC) that provides faculty and students the ability to investigate large molecular systems of interest using modern computational techniques with fast enough turn-around times to make timely and significant advances in chemical research and discovery that complement collaborative experimental efforts. The MRI supercomputer is a distributed-memory, high-performance cluster of 572 cores, 8.448 Tb memory, 11 GPUs and 180 Tb of disk. It is significant that more than seven regional research teams and more than half of the Duquesne faculty members have been using the machine since it became operational on July 3, 2019. Moreover, we have (2) had regional impact by creating meaningful and regional research teams of faculty and students from primarily undergraduate institutions (PUIs) in the Appalachian Region with limited research infrastructure, serious financial hardships due to declining enrollments from several factors including COVID-19, and especially those encouraging underrepresented populations of students. Pittsburgh is one of the few urban areas within the Appalachian region that can serve regional faculty and students from Slippery Rock University, Westminster College, Franciscan University of Steubenville OH, Washington and Jefferson College, and Saint Mary’s College of Maryland, which have become continuous users of the supercomputer center. Duquesne has served as an essential resource that addresses the need for higher education and HPC training of the Appalachian workforce. The use of the supercomputer has enhanced the scholarship productivity of Duquesne and regional faculty, and motivated the next generation of student chemists. In 17 months, the users have ten publications in print or submitted in the peer-review process along with 45 student presentations and one patent application.  By providing HPC equipment, we have also (3) provided training of chemists by creating a series of seven skilled workshops coupled with ten in-depth lectures on HPC by academic and industrial experts on the fundamentals of molecular modeling, and the use of state of-the-art computational facilities and modern software to advance experimental research. The workshops targeted the scientific method, scientific computing, and HPC. The workshops started with instruction on the use of electronic laboratory notebooks, literature workshop, and ten lectures on the aspects of integrating theory and computations into experimental research. We have been successful in creating a unique learning environment with specialized workshops to inspire creativity and boost research productivity. In addition, we have recruited (4) underrepresented populations of students and faculty. Specifically, we have offered opportunities to underrepresented students, female scientists, and those who might not otherwise have the opportunity of a research experience, particularly those from institutions where research programs are limited in the Appalachian Region. Finally, we have encouraged and provided (5) career development and networking for the students. Professional development was realized through exposure to world-renowned industrial experts from Gaussian (Doug Fox) and academic faculty, a weekly seminar program, and travel (Zoom) to regional and national ACS meetings. Specifically, the students were encouraged to attend the 2020 University of Michigan Research Symposium (Uranium) along with Duquesne’s 2020 Undergraduate Research Regional Symposium. Our completed efforts on CHE-1726824 has the added consequence of enhancing and diversifying the U.S. workforce by adding experts in the fields of high-performance computing specializing in chemistry or biochemistry.             Last Modified: 01/12/2021       Submitted by: Jeffrey D Evanseck]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
