<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI:  Acquisition of a Microfocus X-Ray Diffractometer as a Regionwide Resource for Chemistry and Materials Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>262689.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>262689</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carlos Murillo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cmurillo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924970</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) and the Chemistry Research Instrumentation (CRIF) Programs. Professor LeGrande Slaughter from the University of North Texas (UNT) and colleagues Michael Richmond, Francis D'Souza, Mohammad Omary and Hong Wang have acquired a microfocus X-ray diffractometer. In general, an X-ray diffractometer allows accurate and precise measurements of the full three-dimensional structure of a molecule, including bond distances and angles.  The instrument also provides accurate information about the spatial arrangement of a molecule relative to neighboring molecules. The research efforts may impact many areas, including organic and inorganic chemistry, materials chemistry and biochemistry. This instrument is an integral part of the teaching and research activities of undergraduate students at UNT.  Collaborators in chemistry and biochemistry from regional institutions such as the Texas Woman's University, University of Texas at Arlington, Austin College and Miami University of Ohio also share use of the instrument.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The diffractometer enhances research and education at all levels. It may impacts research on noncovalent influences on catalyst selectivity, artificial photosynthesis, and excitonic solar cells. The instrumentation is also used to investigate multifunctional metal-organic optoelectronic materials, metal cluster chemistry, and materials precursors to organic materials and asymmetric catalysts. The diffractometer benefits research on the structural determinations and computational modeling of metal complexes and small molecule characterization for metabolomics. studies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1726652</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Richmond</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael G Richmond</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cobalt@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9405653515</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000161391</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Francis</FirstName>
<LastName>D'Souza</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Francis D'Souza</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Francis.DSouza@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9403698832</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000492390</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohammad</FirstName>
<LastName>Omary</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mohammad A Omary</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>omary@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9405652443</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000088537</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>LeGrande</FirstName>
<LastName>Slaughter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>LeGrande M Slaughter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>legrande@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9405654350</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000368920</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hong</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hong Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hong.wang@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9403698238</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000492647</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Texas</Name>
<CityName>Denton</CityName>
<ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9405653940</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1155 Union Circle #305250</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>614168995</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH TEXAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>064117963</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Texas]]></Name>
<CityName>Denton</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>Chemical Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8607</Code>
<Text>Solar Energy Capture&amp;Conver</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~262689</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The design of new molecules and materials with technologically useful properties requires researchers to understand and control the three-dimensional structure of matter at the atomic scale.&nbsp; One powerful research tool that is unmatched in its ability to shed light on this atomic-scale structure is single crystal X-ray diffraction analysis.&nbsp; In this method, solid crystalline materials scatter X-rays in patterns that reveal the intimate details of their structures.&nbsp; Although most substances will form crystals under the right conditions, certain classes of materials form small or disordered crystals that only weakly diffract X-rays, with the unfortunate result that conventional X-ray diffractometers cannot extract structural information from them.</p> <p>The goal of this Major Research Instrumentation grant was to acquire a new X-ray diffractometer with a microfocus X-ray source to provide researchers at the University of North Texas and at partnering institutions across the Dallas-Fort Worth/North Texas region with new capabilities for structural analysis.&nbsp; The new instrument featured two innovations that are "game changers" for the studies of weakly diffracting materials:&nbsp; a dual-wavelength microfocus X-ray source, providing an intense beam only a tenth of a millimeter in width; and a hybrid photon-counting detector, which can sense even tiny fluxes of X-ray without background interference.&nbsp; Together, these features make the instrument more than 20 times more sensitive to diffracted X-rays for some types of samples, compared with earlier generations of diffractometers.</p> <p>The new microfocus diffractometer has opened new doorways for UNT researchers and their partners to conduct research on materials that could previously not be analyzed by X-ray diffraction.&nbsp; Several classes of materials that have important medicinal or technological applications, but that tend to form small and weakly diffracting crystals, have been successfully analyzed with the new instrument.&nbsp; These include:&nbsp; 1) electron donor-acceptor nanostructures for light-energy harvesting; 2) "pi-extended" aromatic organic compounds with strong absorption in the near-IR spectrum, for potential use in dye-sensitized solar cells or non-linear optical devices; 3) porous metal-organic framework structures with gas-storage or environmental remediation applications; 4) highly active organometallic catalysts for efficient synthesis of medically important organic compounds; and 5) luminescent complexes of Earth-abundant metals with potential applications as sustainable materials for energy-efficient lighting.&nbsp; In the 2.5 years since the diffractometer was commissioned, it has generated structural data that have appeared in over 40 conference presentations by students and faculty, and in 19 peer-reviewed papers, including many in top international journals.&nbsp; Many more research products, that would not have been possible without this instrument, are expected to ensue in coming years.&nbsp; The instrument has been directly used by 28 graduate students and 22 undergraduates, and has indirectly impacted many others; these numbers are sure to grow much larger with time.</p> <p>Of equal importance is the impact of the new instrument on education and research training in the North Texas region.&nbsp; The PI and co-PIs have cultivated a network of researchers at ten non-Ph.D. granting institutions, including four Hispanic-serving institutions, to facilitate access to this powerful research tool in support of undergraduate research experiences.&nbsp; The diffractometer has also served as a research and training tool for students from diverse backgrounds (30% of them Hispanic or Latinx) who attend the UNT Chemistry Research Experiences for Undergraduates summer residential program.&nbsp; Undergrad researchers and their faculty advisors have gained hands-on experience with the diffractometer through one-on-one trainings, boot camps, and workshops designed to explain the theory and operation of the instrument in an accessible yet educational way.&nbsp; Thus far, six peer-reviewed papers with co-authors from non-Ph.D.-granting partner institutions have been published as a result of these efforts, and the partnerships will continue.&nbsp; More importantly, the instrument has served as a showcase for the power of science to solve problems of real-world importance, in hopes that many of the undergraduates who experienced the instrument's capabilities will be inspired to pursue graduate students and careers in research.&nbsp; Lastly, the UNT Chemistry X-ray diffraction facility has hosted 10 or more visits per year from high school classes or undergraduate groups, as well has hosting a research showcase for the UNT McNair Scholars program, with a goal of inspiring young scientists to pursue their dreams.</p> <p>For the longer term, the new microfocus diffractometer obtained through this award will continue to support leading-edge research in technologically relevant new molecules and materials at UNT, while also growing its role as a regionwide resource for researchers.&nbsp; In particular, it will be available to researchers from non-Ph.D. granting institutions in the region free of charge, and UNT is prepared to accommodate increased usage by these partners.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Legrande&nbsp;M&nbsp;Slaughter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The design of new molecules and materials with technologically useful properties requires researchers to understand and control the three-dimensional structure of matter at the atomic scale.  One powerful research tool that is unmatched in its ability to shed light on this atomic-scale structure is single crystal X-ray diffraction analysis.  In this method, solid crystalline materials scatter X-rays in patterns that reveal the intimate details of their structures.  Although most substances will form crystals under the right conditions, certain classes of materials form small or disordered crystals that only weakly diffract X-rays, with the unfortunate result that conventional X-ray diffractometers cannot extract structural information from them.  The goal of this Major Research Instrumentation grant was to acquire a new X-ray diffractometer with a microfocus X-ray source to provide researchers at the University of North Texas and at partnering institutions across the Dallas-Fort Worth/North Texas region with new capabilities for structural analysis.  The new instrument featured two innovations that are "game changers" for the studies of weakly diffracting materials:  a dual-wavelength microfocus X-ray source, providing an intense beam only a tenth of a millimeter in width; and a hybrid photon-counting detector, which can sense even tiny fluxes of X-ray without background interference.  Together, these features make the instrument more than 20 times more sensitive to diffracted X-rays for some types of samples, compared with earlier generations of diffractometers.  The new microfocus diffractometer has opened new doorways for UNT researchers and their partners to conduct research on materials that could previously not be analyzed by X-ray diffraction.  Several classes of materials that have important medicinal or technological applications, but that tend to form small and weakly diffracting crystals, have been successfully analyzed with the new instrument.  These include:  1) electron donor-acceptor nanostructures for light-energy harvesting; 2) "pi-extended" aromatic organic compounds with strong absorption in the near-IR spectrum, for potential use in dye-sensitized solar cells or non-linear optical devices; 3) porous metal-organic framework structures with gas-storage or environmental remediation applications; 4) highly active organometallic catalysts for efficient synthesis of medically important organic compounds; and 5) luminescent complexes of Earth-abundant metals with potential applications as sustainable materials for energy-efficient lighting.  In the 2.5 years since the diffractometer was commissioned, it has generated structural data that have appeared in over 40 conference presentations by students and faculty, and in 19 peer-reviewed papers, including many in top international journals.  Many more research products, that would not have been possible without this instrument, are expected to ensue in coming years.  The instrument has been directly used by 28 graduate students and 22 undergraduates, and has indirectly impacted many others; these numbers are sure to grow much larger with time.  Of equal importance is the impact of the new instrument on education and research training in the North Texas region.  The PI and co-PIs have cultivated a network of researchers at ten non-Ph.D. granting institutions, including four Hispanic-serving institutions, to facilitate access to this powerful research tool in support of undergraduate research experiences.  The diffractometer has also served as a research and training tool for students from diverse backgrounds (30% of them Hispanic or Latinx) who attend the UNT Chemistry Research Experiences for Undergraduates summer residential program.  Undergrad researchers and their faculty advisors have gained hands-on experience with the diffractometer through one-on-one trainings, boot camps, and workshops designed to explain the theory and operation of the instrument in an accessible yet educational way.  Thus far, six peer-reviewed papers with co-authors from non-Ph.D.-granting partner institutions have been published as a result of these efforts, and the partnerships will continue.  More importantly, the instrument has served as a showcase for the power of science to solve problems of real-world importance, in hopes that many of the undergraduates who experienced the instrument's capabilities will be inspired to pursue graduate students and careers in research.  Lastly, the UNT Chemistry X-ray diffraction facility has hosted 10 or more visits per year from high school classes or undergraduate groups, as well has hosting a research showcase for the UNT McNair Scholars program, with a goal of inspiring young scientists to pursue their dreams.  For the longer term, the new microfocus diffractometer obtained through this award will continue to support leading-edge research in technologically relevant new molecules and materials at UNT, while also growing its role as a regionwide resource for researchers.  In particular, it will be available to researchers from non-Ph.D. granting institutions in the region free of charge, and UNT is prepared to accommodate increased usage by these partners.       Last Modified: 11/30/2020       Submitted by: Legrande M Slaughter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
