<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Election Sciences Workshop</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9350.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9350</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brian Humes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhumes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927284</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>General Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Election sciences is an emerging field of scholarship that focuses on the systematic study of election administration and conduct. The aim of scholars in this field is to identify problems, provide valuable data and performance measures to assess and reform election systems to ensure the highest levels of integrity and voter access.  The Election Sciences summer conference will bring together a group of political scientists, statisticians, computer scientists, and legal scholars interested in building and diversifying the field. The conference complements scholarly efforts to identify the intellectual boundaries of election sciences, define primary research questions, create a network to support junior scholars and graduate students, and create curricular materials for use in graduate and undergraduate education.  The conference embodies NSF's mission to broaden participation in science that benefits the national interest and enhances security. This conference and the research that will come out of the conference will help to assure that American elections are accepted as legitimate, use safe and secure technology, and maximize public participation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;The Election Sciences summer conference complements a national effort led by senior scholars in political science, and in partnership with selected scholars in law, computer science, and public policy. The primary aim of these efforts is to build and institutionalize election sciences as a scholarly field of study. Political scientists played a central role in helping to understand the problems in the American election system that contributed to the election crisis of 2000.  This work helped to shape subsequent federal election reform legislation, and contributed research for the presidential commission established after the 2012 elections. Significant barriers to entry to the election sciences field still exist for younger scholars. Election scientists work primarily with voter registration and voter history files, both of which present challenging data and statistical inference problems. The field also lacks recognition as a defined "section" in professional organizations, making it difficult to participate in professional conferences as a cohesive intellectual field, thereby diluting the intellectual contributions. Scholars need to be trained how to interact with election officials, state legislators, and other policy makers in meaningful ways. Finally, there is no agreed upon set of curricular materials train a new generation of election scientist.  This conference will work to reduce such barriers. The conference follows established models in our field (political methodology, visions in methodology, law and politics, history of congress) by offering a series of small, focused summer conferences, targeted particularly at younger scholars and graduate students. The deliverables from the conference, beyond valuable professional connections, will be a series of research papers, curricular materials, and ideally an academic volume or special issue of an academic journal.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1727458</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Gronke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul Gronke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>paul.gronke@reed.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5035177393</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000173879</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Reed College</Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<ZipCode>972028138</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5037711112</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3203 S E Woodstock Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>054972955</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REED INSTITUTE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Reed College]]></Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>972028199</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1371</Code>
<Text>Political Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~9350</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="md-end-block"><span>The 2017 Election Sciences, Reform, and Administration (ESRA) Conference was the inaugural meeting of scholars and practitioners interested in bringing together scientific research and practical experiences to improve the performance of elections in the United States. The conference brought together political scientists, advocates, and election administrators from state and local government. The conference supported 53 attendees. Of the 53, 7 were current or recent local or state election administrators and 8 were junior scholars early in their career researching election systems. Additionally, four Reed College undergraduate students participated in the conference providing exposure to this emerging community of scholars.</span></p> <p class="md-end-block"><span>The conference was designed to share emerging research and practitioner expertise, in plenary sessions and in topic-based breakout groups. The first day of the conference focused on research topics including election management, voter registration list maintenance, voter identification laws, and voter turnout. The second day shifted to practitioners, with topics on election administration professionalization, voter registration modernization, and the role of nonprofit and philanthropic groups in supporting election research. The day ended with breakout sessions to map out research needs for both academic and practitioner communities. </span></p> <p class="md-end-block"><span>Following the conference, attendees were asked to share their experience and the benefits of attending. Sixty percent of those who attended shared their thoughts in the post-event survey. Nearly all of the respondents found the academic panels engaging and relevant to their work, the practitioner day was only slightly less relevant, though still very informative. Because the conference used various forms of engagement, we asked participants which types of meetings or presentations they preferred. Panel presentations with question and answer sessions were the top way to engage based on survey results. But the informal gatherings at lunch and dinner events were the next most valuable form of interaction. Other engagements included break out discussion sessions, and plenary discussions. </span></p> <p class="md-end-block"><span>In addition to presentations, the informal interactions created many opportunities for new professional connections. Almost everyone who responded to the survey noted they made many new contacts, eighty percent of respondents made 6-15 new contacts at the conference. Ninety percent of respondents then followed up with at least one of these new contacts after the conference. The conference was able so provide travel stipends to participants who needed funding. Only one third of the respondents would have attended if there had not been funding, showing the importance of having travel support. </span></p> <p class="md-end-block"><span>The full conference agenda and selected papers are accessible at: </span><span class="md-link"><a href="https://blogs.reed.edu/election-science/conference-program/">https://blogs.reed.edu/election-science/conference-program/</a></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/08/2019<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;Gronke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The 2017 Election Sciences, Reform, and Administration (ESRA) Conference was the inaugural meeting of scholars and practitioners interested in bringing together scientific research and practical experiences to improve the performance of elections in the United States. The conference brought together political scientists, advocates, and election administrators from state and local government. The conference supported 53 attendees. Of the 53, 7 were current or recent local or state election administrators and 8 were junior scholars early in their career researching election systems. Additionally, four Reed College undergraduate students participated in the conference providing exposure to this emerging community of scholars. The conference was designed to share emerging research and practitioner expertise, in plenary sessions and in topic-based breakout groups. The first day of the conference focused on research topics including election management, voter registration list maintenance, voter identification laws, and voter turnout. The second day shifted to practitioners, with topics on election administration professionalization, voter registration modernization, and the role of nonprofit and philanthropic groups in supporting election research. The day ended with breakout sessions to map out research needs for both academic and practitioner communities.  Following the conference, attendees were asked to share their experience and the benefits of attending. Sixty percent of those who attended shared their thoughts in the post-event survey. Nearly all of the respondents found the academic panels engaging and relevant to their work, the practitioner day was only slightly less relevant, though still very informative. Because the conference used various forms of engagement, we asked participants which types of meetings or presentations they preferred. Panel presentations with question and answer sessions were the top way to engage based on survey results. But the informal gatherings at lunch and dinner events were the next most valuable form of interaction. Other engagements included break out discussion sessions, and plenary discussions.  In addition to presentations, the informal interactions created many opportunities for new professional connections. Almost everyone who responded to the survey noted they made many new contacts, eighty percent of respondents made 6-15 new contacts at the conference. Ninety percent of respondents then followed up with at least one of these new contacts after the conference. The conference was able so provide travel stipends to participants who needed funding. Only one third of the respondents would have attended if there had not been funding, showing the importance of having travel support.  The full conference agenda and selected papers are accessible at: https://blogs.reed.edu/election-science/conference-program/       Last Modified: 02/08/2019       Submitted by: Paul Gronke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
