<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research:   Processes of State Administration in Caring for the Isolated Deceased</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>23532.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>23532</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research funded by this award will investigate a little studied aspect of contemporary urban life: what happens when people die anonymously. Individuals once died in multigenerational homes; deaths were mourned by extended family networks and funerary rituals were observed by kin, friends, and neighbors. Anthropologists have documented such funerary systems all over the world and have found that their variability provides one lens through which to understand the variability of the different societies and cultures. This project asks, how is death treated differently now that families are smaller and geographically dispersed? What happens to the dead when more people are living alone and in cities? Do funerary rituals change and what do these changes tell us about shifts in kinship and social relations? When the state intervenes in this highly intimate sphere, caring for the body, property, and memory of the dead, does this signal a simple extension of state authority or a major shift in the role of the state bureaucracy? This research is important because it will contribute to understanding the wide-ranging implications of the global trend to urban living.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will document and analyze the role of the state and its network of contractors in laying to rest the isolated dead in an American city. Princeton University anthropology doctoral candidate Sofia Pinedo-Padoch, under the supervision of Dr. Carol Greenhouse, will carry out the research at the Public Administrator's office in New York City. The Public Administrator is a city agency that intervenes when an individual dies without a will, family, or other heirs. It is the agency's job to ensure a decedent's body is laid to rest, and to attend to the distribution and liquidation of any property and assets. Ms. Pinedo-Padoch will conduct participant observation research at the Public Administrator's office, as well as within the network of public and private contractors that assist the agency. She will also carry out archival research and interviews to trace a sample of cases of individual deaths from beginning to end, documenting the full process of state activity and the individuals who become subject to it. The research will produce a comprehensive portrait of the state's increasingly frequent work as caretaker for the dead, illuminating what death looks like in a changed, contemporary urban world, and what that reveals about social and cultural life today.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1728932</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carol</FirstName>
<LastName>Greenhouse</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carol J Greenhouse</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cgreenho@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092587369</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000117663</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sofia</FirstName>
<LastName>Pinedo-Padoch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sofia M Pinedo-Padoch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sofiamp@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9179686873</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000742640</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[116 Aaron Burr Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7605</Code>
<Text>Cult Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~23532</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Sofia Pinedo-Padoch has completed research for her dissertation, "Processes of State Administration in Caring for the Isolated Deceased," supported by the NSF's Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant. During her funding period, she spent 18 months conducting research at the Public Administrator's Office in New York City, as well as with the public and private contractors that assist the agency. She examined the role of the state in laying to rest individuals who pass away without a will, family, or other heirs. Specifically, she was interested in looking at what happens when American city dwellers die in isolation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During the course of her research, Ms. Pinedo-Padoch conducted participant observation in the office of the Public Administrator, and well as on field investigations to decedents' homes. During investigations, she spoke to investigators about their professional experiences, activities and expertise, as well as their feelings towards their work. In the office, she helped case managers close decedents' bank accounts, proofreading legal documents, and organizing decedents' case files. After 18 months of participant observation, Ms. Pinedo-Padoch become deeply familiar with the Public Administrator's investigatory, financial, legal, and bureaucratic work.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Ms. Pinedo-Padoch conducted research on events and individuals associated with the Public Administrator's Office. Her research sites included real estate auctions, personal property auctions, flea markets, funeral homes, and the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner. In addition, she conducted extended interviews with the friends and family members of several selected decedents whose cases she followed closely during the course of her research.</p> <p><br /> Though she began the project suggesting that individuals who die intestate experience "isolated" deaths, during the course of her research, Ms. Pinedo-Padoch determined that these individuals were not all "isolated" as she had initially proposed. Researching the activities of the Public Administrator and its associates, it became apparent that many different kinds of individuals who die in different circumstances all ended up in the hands of one state agency. Her focus has since shifted to examining why such radically different cases are grouped into a single legal category. Her research also revealed the importance of property, particularly objects belonging to the deceased, to the work of estate administration.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Ms. Pinedo-Padoch's research will form the basis of her dissertation. To be completed in 2020, her dissertation will make important contributions to anthropology by bringing together various disciplinary subfields, namely the anthropology of death, bureaucracy, law, and material culture. This work will also contribute to more effective administration of the estates of individuals who die alone and intestate.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Sofia&nbsp;M&nbsp;Pinedo-Padoch</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Sofia Pinedo-Padoch has completed research for her dissertation, "Processes of State Administration in Caring for the Isolated Deceased," supported by the NSF's Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant. During her funding period, she spent 18 months conducting research at the Public Administrator's Office in New York City, as well as with the public and private contractors that assist the agency. She examined the role of the state in laying to rest individuals who pass away without a will, family, or other heirs. Specifically, she was interested in looking at what happens when American city dwellers die in isolation.     During the course of her research, Ms. Pinedo-Padoch conducted participant observation in the office of the Public Administrator, and well as on field investigations to decedents' homes. During investigations, she spoke to investigators about their professional experiences, activities and expertise, as well as their feelings towards their work. In the office, she helped case managers close decedents' bank accounts, proofreading legal documents, and organizing decedents' case files. After 18 months of participant observation, Ms. Pinedo-Padoch become deeply familiar with the Public Administrator's investigatory, financial, legal, and bureaucratic work.     Ms. Pinedo-Padoch conducted research on events and individuals associated with the Public Administrator's Office. Her research sites included real estate auctions, personal property auctions, flea markets, funeral homes, and the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner. In addition, she conducted extended interviews with the friends and family members of several selected decedents whose cases she followed closely during the course of her research.    Though she began the project suggesting that individuals who die intestate experience "isolated" deaths, during the course of her research, Ms. Pinedo-Padoch determined that these individuals were not all "isolated" as she had initially proposed. Researching the activities of the Public Administrator and its associates, it became apparent that many different kinds of individuals who die in different circumstances all ended up in the hands of one state agency. Her focus has since shifted to examining why such radically different cases are grouped into a single legal category. Her research also revealed the importance of property, particularly objects belonging to the deceased, to the work of estate administration.     Ms. Pinedo-Padoch's research will form the basis of her dissertation. To be completed in 2020, her dissertation will make important contributions to anthropology by bringing together various disciplinary subfields, namely the anthropology of death, bureaucracy, law, and material culture. This work will also contribute to more effective administration of the estates of individuals who die alone and intestate.       Last Modified: 05/01/2019       Submitted by: Sofia M Pinedo-Padoch]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
