<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Reliable and Robust Infant Brain Responses During Face Learning</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>513124.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>516424</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Vishton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pvishton@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928132</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding how to provide quality learning experiences for children is a priority for parents, educators, clinicians, and policymakers. Significant effort has been put into designing formal educational programs that promote and support learning. However, there is surprisingly little known about learning during the most rapid period of developmental change, the first year of life. Long before infants speak, the words they hear contribute to detailed perceptual and conceptual representations of the surrounding world, but we still know little about how the brain changes in early infancy and how to best support infants' learning. These gaps in our knowledge limit the extent to which we can develop and optimize evidence-based early learning programs. The primary goal of this project is to uncover critical environmental factors that promote behavioral and brain development, as well as foundational learning skills during infancy. Knowledge gained from this research will advance our understanding of the building blocks of learning and how caregivers can best support development in the first year of life.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using both cross-sectional and longitudinal designs and a constellation of EEG (electroencephalography) methods, this research will determine the extent to which neural responses, indicative of learning, change and specialize over time and with experience. Specifically, the brain responses of 6-, 9-, and 12-month-old infants will be measured before, during, and after a learning period. During the learning period, infants will be shown faces or objects and hear names, labels, or sounds. The first goal of this work is to examine the impact of label learning on visual perception of faces and objects. The second goal is to better characterize neural specialization and development across the first year of life. Finally, the third goal is to identify the most robust and reliable EEG markers of infant learning by examining differences both within and across individual infants at different ages. The results of this project could transform our understanding of the trajectory of infant learning and the link between language development and perceptual development in the first year of life. This knowledge is critical for providing infants with a supportive learning environment that promotes behavioral and brain development as well as key foundational skills important for later learning.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1728133</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Scott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lisa S Scott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lscott@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3522732125</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000070844</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326112250</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[945 Center Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1698</Code>
<Text>DS -Developmental Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1699</Code>
<Text>Cognitive Neuroscience</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1698</Code>
<Text>DS-Developmental Sciences</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1699</Code>
<Text>COGNEURO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~513124</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~3300</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
