<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Welfare Effects of E-Commerce and Entry in U.S. Retail</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>406000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>406000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Lutz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nlutz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927280</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research team will use a unique data set to analyze competition in U.S. retailing, data on billions of credit card transactions. The first project will look at the impact of e-commerce with a focus on which consumers benefit the most from the growth in internet commerce. A second project uses the same data source to examine retail entry and how new stores grow and acquire customers. They want to characterize the growth of new retail outlets, the extent to which a new store will pull sales away from competitors, and the benefit to consumers from new store openings. This project will increase our understanding of consumer spending and retail competition in the United States. The results will be able to guide policymakers; policies that affect internet commerce and traditional retailing have a substantial effect on the U.S. economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first project evaluates the impact of e-commerce on consumer welfare. The PIs develop a model in which consumers choose an optimal bundle of merchants to shop at, allowing imperfect substitution between online and offline transactions. They will use the data to estimate the model?s parameters and obtain quantitative estimates of welfare gains associated with the expansion of e-commerce. They will also consider how those kinds are distributed across different classes of consumers. The second project examines retail entry. The PIs use a discrete choice demand model for stores, using detailed data on store and customer location and the date a new store opens to obtain distance elasticities for each for each merchant and consumer type. These are then mapped to estimates of consumer welfare.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1729395</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Liran</FirstName>
<LastName>Einav</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Liran Einav</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Leinav@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507233704</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000104871</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Klenow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter J Klenow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>klenow@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507258169</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000466399</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Levin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Levin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jdlevin@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507235962</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000113326</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943041222</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3160 Porter Drive, Suite 100]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~406000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project uses the universe of US credit and debit card transactions that were processed through the Visa network (accounting for more than half of card transactions in the US) during 2007-2019 to study two question. First, we study the welfare impact of the rising share of e-commerce in the United States. Second, we study the determinants of retail sales.</p> <p>Focusing on the first question, we estimate that e-commerce spending reached 8% of consumption by 2017, yielding consumers the equivalent of a 1% permanent boost to their consumption, or over$ 1,000 per household. While some of the gains arose from saving travel costs of buying from local merchants, most of the gains stemmed from substituting to online merchants. Higher income cardholders gained more, as did consumers in more densely populated counties.</p> <p>Focusing on the second question, one of the key findings is that a statistical decopomposition of retails sales assigns the vast majority of variation (approximately 80%) to the number ofunique customers per period, and very little (20%) to the frequency of visits or to the size of the transaction. This implies that acquiring and retaining customers is by far the most important determinant of retail success. These results apply both for variation in sales across merchants,variation across stores within a chain, and variation over time of a given store. It holds for different level of aggregation and across different retail sectors. The results motivates economic modeling, which assigns greater focus to this extensive, customer relatiobship margin.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2021<br>      Modified by: Liran&nbsp;Einav</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project uses the universe of US credit and debit card transactions that were processed through the Visa network (accounting for more than half of card transactions in the US) during 2007-2019 to study two question. First, we study the welfare impact of the rising share of e-commerce in the United States. Second, we study the determinants of retail sales.  Focusing on the first question, we estimate that e-commerce spending reached 8% of consumption by 2017, yielding consumers the equivalent of a 1% permanent boost to their consumption, or over$ 1,000 per household. While some of the gains arose from saving travel costs of buying from local merchants, most of the gains stemmed from substituting to online merchants. Higher income cardholders gained more, as did consumers in more densely populated counties.  Focusing on the second question, one of the key findings is that a statistical decopomposition of retails sales assigns the vast majority of variation (approximately 80%) to the number ofunique customers per period, and very little (20%) to the frequency of visits or to the size of the transaction. This implies that acquiring and retaining customers is by far the most important determinant of retail success. These results apply both for variation in sales across merchants,variation across stores within a chain, and variation over time of a given store. It holds for different level of aggregation and across different retail sectors. The results motivates economic modeling, which assigns greater focus to this extensive, customer relatiobship margin.        Last Modified: 08/05/2021       Submitted by: Liran Einav]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
