<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Climbing Performance in African Apes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9828.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9828</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Compared to the living apes, humans are notably different in having relatively short arms and long legs, which is functionally related to our unique, two-legged gait (bipedalism) and life on the ground. To better understand hominin locomotor evolution, researchers want to know when and how bipedalism affected other aspects of hominin mobility. In this dissertation project, the student co-PI will compare aspects of climbing performance in humans, chimpanzees, and gorillas to see how a range of body sizes and limb proportions affects climbing ability. The research has broad implications for understanding human evolution, movement and mechanics. Understanding more about climbing performance can also address how to limit climbing injuries, assess risk, and design technology for both sport and military climbing pursuits. This project will also support graduate student training, and science outreach to groups underrepresented in STEM fields and to local communities and athletes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this study is to establish the effects of limb proportions and body size on the climbing performance of humans, chimpanzees, and gorillas by assessing three aspects of climbing performance: energetic cost, fatigue, and canopy access. The co-PI will collect behavioral locomotor data in sympatric human, chimpanzee, and gorilla populations in Nouabale-Ndoki National Park, Republic of Congo, and in human rock climbers, to control for environmental variation and observe a range of size and proportion variation. Whether, and to what extent, hominins were arboreal continues to be debated, and, more specifically, the relative prominence of vertical climbing in the locomotor repertoires of various hominin taxa remains an issue. This study will result in a more comprehensive understanding of the form/function relationship for climbing, and enable the assessment of how selection for bipedal adaptations affected climbing abilities during human evolution. It may also improve assessments of the ecology of fossil taxa.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1732194</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Herman</FirstName>
<LastName>Pontzer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Herman Pontzer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pontzer@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196844124</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000224620</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elaine</FirstName>
<LastName>KOZMA</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elaine KOZMA</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kozma.elaine@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128177523</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000725868</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Hunter College</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100655024</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2127724020</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>695 Park Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>620127915</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Hunter College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100655024</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[695 Park Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~9828</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many human populations regularly climb trees, but their arboreal positional behavior is not well studied. Adaptations to terrestrial bipedalism are generally thought to limit arboreal behavior in humans and their ancestors as compared to living apes.</p> <p>For this project, we tested whether and how humans and apes differ in arboreal ecology, using a comparative data set of human positional behavior in trees compared with chimpanzees and gorillas in northern Republic of Congo. Data were collected during full day follows. At two-minute intervals we recorded a subject&rsquo;s position, height, support diameter, and location within the tree. The sample consisted of <em>P. troglodytes troglodytes</em> (22 individuals), <em>G. gorilla gorilla</em> (19 individuals;), and indigenous Mbenjele men (17 individuals). Among key results we find that: 1) In trees, humans spend significantly more time standing bipedally than apes; 2) humans spend significantly more time in the core region near the main trunk (as opposed to the peripheral branches) than apes; and 3) minimum support diameter is not significantly different in humans and other apes. These data suggest humans use trees differently than apes but are nonetheless adept in an arboreal environment and capable of foraging in the canopy. These results have implications for understanding the ecology and evolution of living apes, indigenous peoples, and&nbsp; humans ancestors.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In the context of this study, we presented preliminary data to local children and researchers in the Republic of Congo and a climbing gym in the US. This grant has contributed to the education of a doctoral student. In addition, she worked directly with Congolese researchers and contributed to their training and ongoing research collaboration between the United States and the Republic of Congo. The work will be presented at the 2019 American Association of Physical Anthropology meetings. Publication of the work in peer reviewed journal is in progress.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2018<br>      Modified by: Elaine&nbsp;Kozma</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many human populations regularly climb trees, but their arboreal positional behavior is not well studied. Adaptations to terrestrial bipedalism are generally thought to limit arboreal behavior in humans and their ancestors as compared to living apes.  For this project, we tested whether and how humans and apes differ in arboreal ecology, using a comparative data set of human positional behavior in trees compared with chimpanzees and gorillas in northern Republic of Congo. Data were collected during full day follows. At two-minute intervals we recorded a subject?s position, height, support diameter, and location within the tree. The sample consisted of P. troglodytes troglodytes (22 individuals), G. gorilla gorilla (19 individuals;), and indigenous Mbenjele men (17 individuals). Among key results we find that: 1) In trees, humans spend significantly more time standing bipedally than apes; 2) humans spend significantly more time in the core region near the main trunk (as opposed to the peripheral branches) than apes; and 3) minimum support diameter is not significantly different in humans and other apes. These data suggest humans use trees differently than apes but are nonetheless adept in an arboreal environment and capable of foraging in the canopy. These results have implications for understanding the ecology and evolution of living apes, indigenous peoples, and  humans ancestors.              In the context of this study, we presented preliminary data to local children and researchers in the Republic of Congo and a climbing gym in the US. This grant has contributed to the education of a doctoral student. In addition, she worked directly with Congolese researchers and contributed to their training and ongoing research collaboration between the United States and the Republic of Congo. The work will be presented at the 2019 American Association of Physical Anthropology meetings. Publication of the work in peer reviewed journal is in progress.          Last Modified: 11/28/2018       Submitted by: Elaine Kozma]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
