<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Award: The Effects of Warfare and Violence on the Development of Social Complexity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10565.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10565</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Doctoral dissertation student Omar Alcover Firpi will examine how war shaped settlement design and social organization among early, small-scale villages. In particular, he will examine how networks of communities in defensive positions formed in response to real, or perceived, external threats in pre-modern societies. Previous archaeological scholarship on violence has focused on the formation and maintenance of large states with formalized armies, yet few studies have addressed the role of war in the emergence of social and political complexity among modest sized groups. Because archaeologists can identify long-term social trends in human activity the field is well-suited to answer how societies engaged with, and were altered by, war. In this project, researchers will answer how and why fortresses built and used among early Maya communities in Guatemala, as well as the long-term effects warfare had on the regional development of authority and defensive networks. Building on the premise that collective violence is not an innate human condition, this project will evaluate how war is socially and situationally employed by communities to defend themselves from perceived threats. Results from this investigation provide critical insight into why small communities engage in violence and the long-term effects of such negative encounters. The project will provide educational and professional training for American and Guatemalan students, furthering collaborative ties between the two countries. Moreover, the interdisciplinary dataset will integrate methods in remote sensing analysis along with archaeological survey, excavation, and material analysis to determine the long-term effects of violence during the establishment of early communities in the Americas. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;A research team including local community members will examine how fortresses and other defensive features were constructed and used by Maya villagers during the Preclassic period (400BC- AD250) at the hilltop fortress of Macabilero.  Macabilero is located on the banks of the Usumacinta River in northwestern Guatemala, in a region that has been continuously occupied since the 4th century BC.  Previous archaeological research in the Usumacinta Valley has produced abundant archaeological and historical evidence for warfare during the 6th through 8th century AD, when royal dynasties strove with one another for territorial control. Focusing on the community at Macabilero in the Preclassic period, before the rise of dynastic kingdoms, this research will clarify the intensity and effect of warfare in the emergence of state society in the region. The investigators will lead an interdisciplinary team that includes archaeologists, remote sensing specialists, and environmental scientists to clarify how violence shaped settlement organization in this fractured landscape, and how defensive features relate to different ecological zones in the region. Through excavation of this ancient fortress, in addition to extensive pedestrian survey of the region, and detailed remote sensing analyses, the project will determine how ubiquitous defensive settlements were, and what their role was in the development of political complexity in the region.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1733551</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Scherer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Scherer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>andrew_scherer@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018637059</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000385706</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Omar</FirstName>
<LastName>Alcover</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Omar Alcover</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>omar_alcover@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7873421258</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000740511</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brown University</Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[350 Eddy Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BROWN UNIVERSITY IN PROVIDENCE IN THE STATE OF RHODE ISLAND AND PROVIDENCE PLANTATIONS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brown University]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>Archaeology DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~10565</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Funding was received from the NSF DDIG to support a multifaceted archaeological investigation on warfare and violence in the Maya lowlands. The investigation focused on determining if and how early conflict affected the social, political, and economic development of early Maya peoples during the Preclassic occupation (500 BCE &ndash; 350 CE) of the Usumacinta River Valley in northwestern Guatemala. Although field research supported by this grant has been completed, further analysis of artifacts and other materials will continue through the end of 2018 and the first months of 2019. The aims of the multinational project were to determine (1) if defensive features at Macabilero were contemporaneous with the Preclassic period occupation of the site, or if they were built later; (2) if the defensive structures at Macabilero date to the Preclassic period, what processes led to the emergence of these early fortifications prior to the development of centralized authority in the Usumacinta River region; and, (3) if the fortifications at Macabilero were a unique development in the region, and if not, how fortifications related to local geography, especially geology, ecology, and access to ritual space.</p> <p>To answer these questions, the PI and Co-PI investigated the Late Preclassic Maya fortress of Macabilero, located on a hilltop overlooking the Usumacinta River on the modern border between Peten, Guatemala and Chiapas, Mexico (Figure 1). Macabilero is distinguished by an extensive network of masonry walls and terraces that circumscribe the site, and is surrounded by tropical forest, swamps, lakes, <em>cenotes</em>, rivers, caves, as well as jagged limestone ridges (Figure 2). First identified by Edwin Shook in the 1930&rsquo;s, Macabilero had received little attention until its rediscovery in the early 2000s.</p> <p>NSF-funded research by the PI and Co-PI uncovered large caches of limestone slingstones at the site (Figure 3), which are early weapons used throughout the Americas, as well as other ritual objects, such as imitation stingray spines carved out of bone (Figure 4). Research at Macabilero suggests that the site was not initially built as a fortress but was quickly transformed into one by early settlers who took advantage of its already defensible position on the landscape. From our excavations, we determined that during the end of the Abal (300 BC &ndash; 175 CE) and beginning of the Pom (175 &ndash; 350 CE) phase, there were important structural changes to the site. In the south plaza the original buildings were leveled and buried, and their orientations changed. Along with this shift, we also witness the creation of an elevated plaza and at least two modifications of the terrace walls. With this defensive shift at the site, the occupants built seven levels of megalithic terraces that enclosed the site&rsquo;s main group on the east, with the west protected by a natural 120m high limestone wall. Around this same time, the occupants developed a regional system of defensive walls that limited access to the site from the surrounding valleys. These walls share the same construction style as the terraces, but at a smaller scale. Most of these walls are located at natural bottlenecks between limestone ridges, closing off access to the site. It is important to note that this structural shift required time, labor, and the organization of a considerable amount of people to bring fill materials, cut the stone blocks, and create the plaster that coated the plaza surfaces. The concerted effort to fortify the site, with most walls facing the valleys to the north, indicates the likelihood that Macabilero was built in response to the rising power of dynasts at Piedras Negras, whose power was beginning to be consolidated at this transitional point. By 350 CE, the socio-political experiment at Macabilero ultimately fails, the site is abandoned, and its people move to nearby capitals such as Piedras Negras and El Cayo.</p> <p>Fieldwork at Macabilero indicates that the site not only served as a significant defensive refuge for both the local community as well as those in nearby areas, but that it also functioned as an important ceremonial space regionally. At Macabilero, ceremonial activity took place in the nearby caves, as well as in its plazas and pyramids. It is notable that ceremonial architecture focused on creating large open spaces in proximity to caves and not in developing E Groups assemblages as their contemporaries in the central Peten did. The absence of an E Group at Macabilero was not due to cultural isolation, given that the materials recovered from the site, particularly its ceramics, share many of the same styles and elements typical of the Preclassic in the rest of the lowlands. Macabilero then evidences a divergent socio-political tradition that developed in the Usumacinta River Valley, one that is unique in both its form and function compared with other Preclassic sites in the Peten.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/09/2018<br>      Modified by: Omar&nbsp;Alcover</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1733551/1733551_10491297_1544385991753_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1733551/1733551_10491297_1544385991753_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2: Map of Macabilero"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1733551/1733551_10491297_1544385991753_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2: Map of Macabilero"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map of the Preclassic fortress of Macabilero. The map presents the main group at the site, with labeled structures and plazas.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Omar Alcover Firpi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Omar&nbsp;Alcover</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2: Map of Macabilero</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1733551/1733551_10491297_1544386987173_Figure1UsumacintaSites-01--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1733551/1733551_10491297_1544386987173_Figure1UsumacintaSites-01--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1: Archaeological Sites in the Usumacinta River Valley"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1733551/1733551_10491297_1544386987173_Figure1UsumacintaSites-01--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1: Archaeological Sites in the Usumacinta River Valley"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map labels the relevant archaeological sites in the region, with others only designated as black dots.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Omar Alcover Firpi</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Omar&nbsp;Alcover</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1: Archaeological Sites in the Usumacinta River Valley</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1733551/1733551_10491297_1544386990680_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1733551/1733551_10491297_1544386990680_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3: Sling stones"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1733551/1733551_10491297_1544386990680_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3: Sling stones"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure shows a selection of possible sling stones recovered from archaeological excavations at Macabilero. In this past season, we documented over 150 sling stones from a variety of contexts, pointing to their ubiquity in this early fortress.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Omar Alcover Firpi</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Omar&nbsp;Alcover</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3: Sling stones</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1733551/1733551_10491297_1544387001305_Figure4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1733551/1733551_10491297_1544387001305_Figure4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4: Imitation Stingray Spine"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1733551/1733551_10491297_1544387001305_Figure4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4: Imitation Stingray Spine"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This imitation stingray spine was found in a cache in one of the main structures at the site, along with over 100 sling stones and canid bones suggesting it was a ritual deposit. This imitation stingray spine points towards the importance of ritual objects at the site.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Omar Alcover Firpi</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Omar&nbsp;Alcover</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4: Imitation Stingray Spine</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Funding was received from the NSF DDIG to support a multifaceted archaeological investigation on warfare and violence in the Maya lowlands. The investigation focused on determining if and how early conflict affected the social, political, and economic development of early Maya peoples during the Preclassic occupation (500 BCE &ndash; 350 CE) of the Usumacinta River Valley in northwestern Guatemala. Although field research supported by this grant has been completed, further analysis of artifacts and other materials will continue through the end of 2018 and the first months of 2019. The aims of the multinational project were to determine (1) if defensive features at Macabilero were contemporaneous with the Preclassic period occupation of the site, or if they were built later; (2) if the defensive structures at Macabilero date to the Preclassic period, what processes led to the emergence of these early fortifications prior to the development of centralized authority in the Usumacinta River region; and, (3) if the fortifications at Macabilero were a unique development in the region, and if not, how fortifications related to local geography, especially geology, ecology, and access to ritual space.  To answer these questions, the PI and Co-PI investigated the Late Preclassic Maya fortress of Macabilero, located on a hilltop overlooking the Usumacinta River on the modern border between Peten, Guatemala and Chiapas, Mexico (Figure 1). Macabilero is distinguished by an extensive network of masonry walls and terraces that circumscribe the site, and is surrounded by tropical forest, swamps, lakes, cenotes, rivers, caves, as well as jagged limestone ridges (Figure 2). First identified by Edwin Shook in the 1930?s, Macabilero had received little attention until its rediscovery in the early 2000s.  NSF-funded research by the PI and Co-PI uncovered large caches of limestone slingstones at the site (Figure 3), which are early weapons used throughout the Americas, as well as other ritual objects, such as imitation stingray spines carved out of bone (Figure 4). Research at Macabilero suggests that the site was not initially built as a fortress but was quickly transformed into one by early settlers who took advantage of its already defensible position on the landscape. From our excavations, we determined that during the end of the Abal (300 BC &ndash; 175 CE) and beginning of the Pom (175 &ndash; 350 CE) phase, there were important structural changes to the site. In the south plaza the original buildings were leveled and buried, and their orientations changed. Along with this shift, we also witness the creation of an elevated plaza and at least two modifications of the terrace walls. With this defensive shift at the site, the occupants built seven levels of megalithic terraces that enclosed the site?s main group on the east, with the west protected by a natural 120m high limestone wall. Around this same time, the occupants developed a regional system of defensive walls that limited access to the site from the surrounding valleys. These walls share the same construction style as the terraces, but at a smaller scale. Most of these walls are located at natural bottlenecks between limestone ridges, closing off access to the site. It is important to note that this structural shift required time, labor, and the organization of a considerable amount of people to bring fill materials, cut the stone blocks, and create the plaster that coated the plaza surfaces. The concerted effort to fortify the site, with most walls facing the valleys to the north, indicates the likelihood that Macabilero was built in response to the rising power of dynasts at Piedras Negras, whose power was beginning to be consolidated at this transitional point. By 350 CE, the socio-political experiment at Macabilero ultimately fails, the site is abandoned, and its people move to nearby capitals such as Piedras Negras and El Cayo.  Fieldwork at Macabilero indicates that the site not only served as a significant defensive refuge for both the local community as well as those in nearby areas, but that it also functioned as an important ceremonial space regionally. At Macabilero, ceremonial activity took place in the nearby caves, as well as in its plazas and pyramids. It is notable that ceremonial architecture focused on creating large open spaces in proximity to caves and not in developing E Groups assemblages as their contemporaries in the central Peten did. The absence of an E Group at Macabilero was not due to cultural isolation, given that the materials recovered from the site, particularly its ceramics, share many of the same styles and elements typical of the Preclassic in the rest of the lowlands. Macabilero then evidences a divergent socio-political tradition that developed in the Usumacinta River Valley, one that is unique in both its form and function compared with other Preclassic sites in the Peten.             Last Modified: 12/09/2018       Submitted by: Omar Alcover]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
