<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>An Examination of the Long Term Relationship between Urban Planning and Social Control</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249730.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>254770</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Dr. Timothy Pugh and a team of scholars from the United States and Guatemala will investigate the emergence of cities among the ancient Maya between 800 and 400 BC. The majority of people worldwide currently live in cities, yet little is known about what cities do or how they initially formed. Balancing complex social interactions, transportation, and urban planning needs is critical to the success of cities in the present as well as the past. However, such balancing becomes even more complex during the emergence of social inequality and occupational specialization. Archaeology allows the study of social phenomena over long periods of time and without historical documents. Thus, this research will contribute to understanding the long-term relationships between central administration and cities: What roles did cities play in helping societies adapt to emerging social complexity? How does the development of central leadership relate to urban planning? What are the long-term dynamics of tensions between public and private spaces? How do such dynamics relate to the emergence of social inequality? The project explores the invention of what is currently the earliest known urban grid in the Americas at the lowland Maya site of Nixtun-Chich in Peten, northern Guatemala. How did such complex city planning emerge in an area without a tradition of such planning? Nixtun-Chich is also the only Maya city known to have an urban grid. Why were urban grids not as successful among the Maya as they were among the ancient Chinese, Indus Valley, and Greek civilizations? In sum, the project will examine how cities can act as a sort of administrative tool to organize increasingly large and socioeconomically diverse populations. This research will train both United States and Guatemalan students and will support student efforts to complete research practicums and theses at various levels. Project results will be published in English and Spanish in books and journals, and presented at conferences in Guatemala, the United States, and elsewhere. Information will be uploaded to an ongoing website (http://www.itzaarchaeology.com/), which summarizes project findings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the Maya lowlands of Mesoamerica, the typical city includes low-density urban settlement. However, between 800 and 500 BC, Nixtun-Chich developed a unique urban grid formed by a series of perpendicular corridors and was densely settled. This research project will test the hypothesis that the settlement of Nixtun-Chich was rationalized through a gridded layout to organize and manage an increasingly large and complex population. The project will also investigate whether private space began to impinge upon public space by the end of the Middle Preclassic period (400/300 BC) at the city, perhaps leading to social dissipation and ultimately dispersion. These propositions will be tested through a multiyear archaeological program of extensive excavations in the urban grid. This research will make a number of broader impacts. The knowledge of the diversity, successes, and failures of ancient cities can contribute to modern discussions of urbanization and policymaking. The proposed work will add some historical depth to understanding the importance of a positive balance of social interactivity, transportation costs, and settlement patterns, which is critical for sensible policymaking. Accordingly, the work has the potential to illuminate the social functions of public goods and the potential drawbacks of privatization.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1734036</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Pugh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy W Pugh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>timothy.pugh@qc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7189972896</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000346562</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Queens College</Name>
<CityName>Flushing</CityName>
<ZipCode>113671575</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7189975400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>65 30 Kissena Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>619346146</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Queens College]]></Name>
<CityName>Flushing</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>113671575</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[65 30 Kissena Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>Archaeology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~249730</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~5040</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>With support from the National Science Foundation (BCS-1734036), Timothy Pugh and a team of archaeologists from the United States, Guatemala, and Japan have discovered critical details about city formation at Nixtun-Ch&rsquo;ich&rsquo; in Peten, Guatemala. The prime target of the work was the site&rsquo;s urban grid and how this grid structured daily life in the city.&nbsp; At the time that the team initiated the project, the site had the only known prehispanic example of gridded roads in the Maya region. Major outcomes of the research include the following:</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The initial urban grid of Nixtun-Ch&rsquo;ich&rsquo; (Figures 1 and 2) seems to have been planned and built all at once sometime between 750 and 450 B.C. Urban grids are formed by a series of streets organized at right angles forming intersections and blocks. Thus, they involve greater centralized planning than many known Maya cities.</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Addition survey indicated that the central axis of Nixtun-Ch&rsquo;ich&rsquo;, formed by a line of ceremonial buildings, was over 3 kilometers (1.86 miles) long. Thus, this planned element was much longer than previously thought. Central axes form foundation points in urban design. At Nixtun-Ch&rsquo;ich&rsquo;, the central axis forms the midline of the site&rsquo;s bilateral symmetry.</p> <p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The planning at the site was likely influenced by sites in the nearby Middle Usumacinta region. Recent work in that region by Takeshi Inomata and Daniela Triadan, also supported by NSF (BCS 1826909), has revealed centralized planning before 800 B.C. (<a href="https://www.nsf.gov/discoveries/disc_summ.jsp?cntn_id=300785">https://www.nsf.gov/discoveries/disc_summ.jsp?cntn_id=300785</a>).</p> <p>4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The team surveyed areas near Nixtun-Ch&rsquo;ich&rsquo; and located T&rsquo;up, a second site with an urban grid (Figure 3). This smaller site seems to have been a satellite of Nixtun-Ch&rsquo;ich&rsquo; and indicates a settlement hierarchy. This find is critical as hierarchy in one of the most common forms of organization of complex social systems.&nbsp; Complex systems are those with a number of interconnected parts&mdash;hierarchies connect and organize parts within the whole.</p> <p>5)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The occupants Nixtun-Ch&rsquo;ich&rsquo; largely stripped the site before the construction of the grid, but the team discovered remnants of earlier (pre-800 B.C) settlements beneath large buildings.</p> <p>6)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; While the grid was initially built all at once, it changed from its initial construction to its latest modifications (ca. A.D. 200). In particular, the streets became much narrower over time. Given that streets were the most abundant form of public space at Nixtun-Ch&rsquo;ich&rsquo;, the amount of public space decrease over time. This gradual decline likely reflects a shift away from a more cooperative form of social organization.</p> <p>7)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The planned street grid at Nixtun-Ch&rsquo;ich&rsquo; was also designed to channel standing water out of the city. In some areas, the team encountered walkways alongside drainage canals.</p> <p>8)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Nixtun-Ch&rsquo;ich&rsquo; also incorporated several water reservoirs. Excavations revealed that the reservoirs were locations of important ritual events. In addition, some still fill yearly during the rainy season producing a hydraulic calendar. Two of these reservoirs were located along the site&rsquo;s central axis. It is clear that the ancient Maya were adept at harnessing the water table.</p> <p>9)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The team encountered evidence of the long-distance exchange of obsidian, marine shell, ceramics, and jade. One jade artifact appears to have originated in the Olmec region. In addition to allowing insights into the Maya economic system, trade provides direct evidence of interaction between regions.</p> <p>10) The findings of the project have already been submitted, accepted for publication, or published in peer review journals <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10816-018-9404-0">https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10816-018-9404-0</a>;</p> <p><a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00934690.2019.1656322">https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00934690.2019.1656322</a>;</p> <p><a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10816-017-9352-0">https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10816-017-9352-0</a></p> <p><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2352409X17305746">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2352409X17305746</a></p> <p><a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/ancient-mesoamerica/article/faceless-hierarchy-at-nixtunchich-peten-guatemala/3B5F2E4929F991A15B5C42DFE473313B">https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/ancient-mesoamerica/article/faceless-hierarchy-at-nixtunchich-peten-guatemala/3B5F2E4929F991A15B5C42DFE473313B</a>).</p> <p>11) The research has been mentioned in publications directed toward the general public (<a href="https://www.archaeology.org/issues/303-1807/features/6684-maya-urban-grid">https://www.archaeology.org/issues/303-1807/features/6684-maya-urban-grid</a>).</p> <p>12) The data from the project are being uploaded to an ongoing website that will ultimately be available to the public and is currently being used for teaching purposes at Queens College (<a href="https://www.itzaarchaeology.com/">https://www.itzaarchaeology.com/</a>).</p> <p>13) The team included a number of undergraduate and graduate students from the United States and Guatemala and helped train them in archaeological field and laboratory methods (Figure 5).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/23/2020<br>      Modified by: Timothy&nbsp;W&nbsp;Pugh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595203740609_Figure2PetenItzaSites--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595203740609_Figure2PetenItzaSites--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1. Peten Sites"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595203740609_Figure2PetenItzaSites--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1. Peten Sites"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Nixtun-Ch'ich' and Other Middle Preclassic Sites on Lake Peten Itza</div> <div class="imageCredit">Timothy Pugh and Gabriela Zygadlo</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Timothy&nbsp;W&nbsp;Pugh</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1. Peten Sites</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595204473297_Figure3NewSitePlanb--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595204473297_Figure3NewSitePlanb--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2. Nixtun-Ch'ich'"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595204473297_Figure3NewSitePlanb--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2. Nixtun-Ch'ich'"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Nixtun-Ch'ich', Peten, Guatemala</div> <div class="imageCredit">Timothy Pugh and Gabiela Zygadlo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Timothy&nbsp;W&nbsp;Pugh</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2. Nixtun-Ch'ich'</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595204666355_Figure7T'up--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595204666355_Figure7T'up--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3. T'up"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595204666355_Figure7T'up--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3. T'up"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3. T'up, Peten, Guatemala</div> <div class="imageCredit">Timothy Pugh and Gabriela Zygadlo</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Timothy&nbsp;W&nbsp;Pugh</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3. T'up</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595534021510_Nixtundrain--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595534021510_Nixtundrain--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4. Drainage Canal, Nixtun-Chich"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595534021510_Nixtundrain--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4. Drainage Canal, Nixtun-Chich"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Drainage Canal, Nixtun-Ch'ich', Peten, Guatemala</div> <div class="imageCredit">Timothy Pugh</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Timothy&nbsp;W&nbsp;Pugh</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4. Drainage Canal, Nixtun-Chich</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595543077836_NCteam2019--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595543077836_NCteam2019--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 5. Proyecto Itza 2019"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1734036/1734036_10506373_1595543077836_NCteam2019--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 5. Proyecto Itza 2019"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 5. Proyecto Itza 2019</div> <div class="imageCredit">Timothy Pugh</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Timothy&nbsp;W&nbsp;Pugh</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 5. Proyecto Itza 2019</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ With support from the National Science Foundation (BCS-1734036), Timothy Pugh and a team of archaeologists from the United States, Guatemala, and Japan have discovered critical details about city formation at Nixtun-Ch’ich’ in Peten, Guatemala. The prime target of the work was the site’s urban grid and how this grid structured daily life in the city.  At the time that the team initiated the project, the site had the only known prehispanic example of gridded roads in the Maya region. Major outcomes of the research include the following:  1)    The initial urban grid of Nixtun-Ch’ich’ (Figures 1 and 2) seems to have been planned and built all at once sometime between 750 and 450 B.C. Urban grids are formed by a series of streets organized at right angles forming intersections and blocks. Thus, they involve greater centralized planning than many known Maya cities.  2)    Addition survey indicated that the central axis of Nixtun-Ch’ich’, formed by a line of ceremonial buildings, was over 3 kilometers (1.86 miles) long. Thus, this planned element was much longer than previously thought. Central axes form foundation points in urban design. At Nixtun-Ch’ich’, the central axis forms the midline of the site’s bilateral symmetry.  3)    The planning at the site was likely influenced by sites in the nearby Middle Usumacinta region. Recent work in that region by Takeshi Inomata and Daniela Triadan, also supported by NSF (BCS 1826909), has revealed centralized planning before 800 B.C. (https://www.nsf.gov/discoveries/disc_summ.jsp?cntn_id=300785).  4)    The team surveyed areas near Nixtun-Ch’ich’ and located T’up, a second site with an urban grid (Figure 3). This smaller site seems to have been a satellite of Nixtun-Ch’ich’ and indicates a settlement hierarchy. This find is critical as hierarchy in one of the most common forms of organization of complex social systems.  Complex systems are those with a number of interconnected parts&mdash;hierarchies connect and organize parts within the whole.  5)    The occupants Nixtun-Ch’ich’ largely stripped the site before the construction of the grid, but the team discovered remnants of earlier (pre-800 B.C) settlements beneath large buildings.  6)    While the grid was initially built all at once, it changed from its initial construction to its latest modifications (ca. A.D. 200). In particular, the streets became much narrower over time. Given that streets were the most abundant form of public space at Nixtun-Ch’ich’, the amount of public space decrease over time. This gradual decline likely reflects a shift away from a more cooperative form of social organization.  7)    The planned street grid at Nixtun-Ch’ich’ was also designed to channel standing water out of the city. In some areas, the team encountered walkways alongside drainage canals.  8)    Nixtun-Ch’ich’ also incorporated several water reservoirs. Excavations revealed that the reservoirs were locations of important ritual events. In addition, some still fill yearly during the rainy season producing a hydraulic calendar. Two of these reservoirs were located along the site’s central axis. It is clear that the ancient Maya were adept at harnessing the water table.  9)    The team encountered evidence of the long-distance exchange of obsidian, marine shell, ceramics, and jade. One jade artifact appears to have originated in the Olmec region. In addition to allowing insights into the Maya economic system, trade provides direct evidence of interaction between regions.  10) The findings of the project have already been submitted, accepted for publication, or published in peer review journals https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10816-018-9404-0;  https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00934690.2019.1656322;  https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10816-017-9352-0  https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2352409X17305746  https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/ancient-mesoamerica/article/faceless-hierarchy-at-nixtunchich-peten-guatemala/3B5F2E4929F991A15B5C42DFE473313B).  11) The research has been mentioned in publications directed toward the general public (https://www.archaeology.org/issues/303-1807/features/6684-maya-urban-grid).  12) The data from the project are being uploaded to an ongoing website that will ultimately be available to the public and is currently being used for teaching purposes at Queens College (https://www.itzaarchaeology.com/).  13) The team included a number of undergraduate and graduate students from the United States and Guatemala and helped train them in archaeological field and laboratory methods (Figure 5).          Last Modified: 07/23/2020       Submitted by: Timothy W Pugh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
