<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Theory and Models of Ice Sheet Surface Melting Instabilities in the Past and Future</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224758.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224758</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marc Stieglitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mstiegli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924354</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Sudden accelerations in melting at the junction of merged ice sheets are thought to have caused some of the most rapid sea level rise events in history. Existing theories of ice sheet surface melting do not consider such regions and are not able to reproduce these sudden accelerations in ice sheet surface melting. To predict the likelihood of such rapid sea level rise events in the future, it is important to understand why such events happened in the past. This project will develop a new mathematical theory for ice sheet surface melting instabilities within ice saddle regions. It will compare the predictions of this theory to complex ice sheet models and perform more realistic simulations to determine whether the Greenland Ice Sheet may undergo such a sudden acceleration in melting under future warming. This project includes a number of broader impacts. Sea level rise threatens life and infrastructure along coastlines throughout the world. Accurate projections of potential periods of rapid future sea level rise will inform strategic decision-making about mitigation strategies and infrastructure design. The project will also contribute to STEM workforce development by supporting the training of a post-doctoral associate and a graduate student. A web-based application employing the simple model developed during this project will be produced as an effective outreach tool for explaining ice sheet dynamics to the public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary goal of this project is to develop a theory that explains the occurrence of deglacial meltwater pulses from land-based ice sheets under a warming climate. A new variant on the classical single-dome ice sheet model that relaxes previous assumptions and considers an ice-saddle geometry will be produced. This new ice-saddle model will be numerically tested to determine the conditions under which it produces a significant deglacial meltwater pulse. Asymptotic mathematical techniques, such as multiple time scales analysis, will be used to derive functional expressions for the magnitude and speed of meltwater pulses predicted by these models. The utility of the ice-saddle theory in explaining reality will be evaluated by comparing it to more complex ice sheet models and proxy records of sea level rise during meltwater pulses. Finally, multi-millennial simulations of the Greenland Ice Sheet under different scenarios of future climate change will be developed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1735715</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Victor</FirstName>
<LastName>Tsai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Victor C Tsai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>victor_tsai@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018632801</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000582916</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Pasadena</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E. California Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5280</Code>
<Text>ANS-Arctic Natural Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~224758</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Sea level rise threatens life and infrastructure along coastlines throughout the world. Having an accurate projection of the potential for periods of rapid sea level rise in the future can help decision makers assess the potential damage associated with future climate change for the purposes of designing mitigation strategies. Furthermore, to adapt current infrastructure and plan for future coastal building, accurate sea level projections are needed by local planners. While recent theoretical advances have shown how disintegration of ice shelves may contribute to the collapse of the large ice sheets, it has remained poorly understood how direct melting of the ice sheet surface contributes to rapid sea level rise. To address this challenge, we have undertaken a two-pronged approach to first better quantify how much melt is produced under different physical conditions and then to understand how this melt causes instability in ice sheet behavior, particularly at the junction of merged ice sheets.</p> <p>To better estimate how much melting occurs under different physical conditions, we developed a physical melt model that estimates melt rates solely based on surface temperatures. Unlike other commonly used models, this new model is based on physical principles while not needing measurements of all of the various energy fluxes. We verified that the new model improves on previous models that only use surface temperature observations as inputs, with the new model predicting less early summer melting compared with previous models. Since early summer melt is thought to be more important for causing ice sheet acceleration compared with later melt, the new theoretical model will help improve the accuracy of ice sheet acceleration estimates, particularly during past or future times when direct measurements of melt rates are lacking.</p> <p>To understand the role of melting merged ice sheets, which is thought to have caused some of the most rapid sea level rise events in recent Earth history, we have constructed a new mathematical theory for ice sheet surface melting instabilities within these junction regions. The model demonstrates that the amplitude and timing of meltwater pulses is sensitively dependent on the rate of climate warming during the deglaciation and the relative sizes of the ice sheets undergoing deglaciation. This new understanding of what controls the fastest meltwater pulses can be used to improve our estimates of how fast and when future melting of the Greenland Ice Sheet will occur as temperatures in Greenland increase.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/10/2020<br>      Modified by: Victor&nbsp;C&nbsp;Tsai</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Sea level rise threatens life and infrastructure along coastlines throughout the world. Having an accurate projection of the potential for periods of rapid sea level rise in the future can help decision makers assess the potential damage associated with future climate change for the purposes of designing mitigation strategies. Furthermore, to adapt current infrastructure and plan for future coastal building, accurate sea level projections are needed by local planners. While recent theoretical advances have shown how disintegration of ice shelves may contribute to the collapse of the large ice sheets, it has remained poorly understood how direct melting of the ice sheet surface contributes to rapid sea level rise. To address this challenge, we have undertaken a two-pronged approach to first better quantify how much melt is produced under different physical conditions and then to understand how this melt causes instability in ice sheet behavior, particularly at the junction of merged ice sheets.  To better estimate how much melting occurs under different physical conditions, we developed a physical melt model that estimates melt rates solely based on surface temperatures. Unlike other commonly used models, this new model is based on physical principles while not needing measurements of all of the various energy fluxes. We verified that the new model improves on previous models that only use surface temperature observations as inputs, with the new model predicting less early summer melting compared with previous models. Since early summer melt is thought to be more important for causing ice sheet acceleration compared with later melt, the new theoretical model will help improve the accuracy of ice sheet acceleration estimates, particularly during past or future times when direct measurements of melt rates are lacking.  To understand the role of melting merged ice sheets, which is thought to have caused some of the most rapid sea level rise events in recent Earth history, we have constructed a new mathematical theory for ice sheet surface melting instabilities within these junction regions. The model demonstrates that the amplitude and timing of meltwater pulses is sensitively dependent on the rate of climate warming during the deglaciation and the relative sizes of the ice sheets undergoing deglaciation. This new understanding of what controls the fastest meltwater pulses can be used to improve our estimates of how fast and when future melting of the Greenland Ice Sheet will occur as temperatures in Greenland increase.       Last Modified: 10/10/2020       Submitted by: Victor C Tsai]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
