<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Cognitive Control Theoretic Mechanisms of Real-time fMRI-Guided Neuromodulation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>422610.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>422610</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan Fritz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jfritz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927923</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Real-time measurement of neural activity with functional magnetic resonance imaging (rtfMRI) can be used as a source of feedback to guide volitional control (neuromodulation) of cognitive processing. Previous research has demonstrated broad success of rtfMRI-guided neuromodulation of cognitive processes. However, the neural mechanisms by which rtfMRI-guidance produces these outcomes remain largely unknown. Engineering control theory posits a small set of elements with specific component functions and causal associations necessary to achieve closed-loop control. The engine of this loop is the control law in which past control outcomes are evaluated to inform the selection of current control decisions. Cognitive control theory, meanwhile, posits numerous empirically justified measures by which the control law may evaluate outcomes as well as neural processing regions that may support these evaluation and selection functions, specifically, the medial and lateral prefrontal cortices. Dr. Keith Bush of the University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences will merge the predictions of these theories to model and explain brain activity observed during rtfMRI-guided neuromodulation. By advancing a mechanistic understanding of guided neuromodulation, this research will benefit multiple disciplines within cognitive science, psychology, and psychiatry that focus on self-control processes such as brain-computer interfaces, cognitive skills development, and cognitive therapeutics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will conduct rtfMRI-guided neuromodulation experiments designed to facilitate volitional control of affective processing in healthy individuals. Affective processing will be volitionally modulated independently for the dimensions of valence and arousal to explore task-generality of the underlying closed-loop control system.  In the first experiment, medial prefrontal cortex activity will be modeled with respect to multiple measures of control outcome (error, conflict, predicted error-likelihood, predicted response outcome, and expected value of control) to determine the most likely basis of its function. In the second experiment, control theoretic signals derived from this function will be used to locate brain regions implementing control signal selection and execution.  Finally, the role of rtfMRI-guidance will be incorporated into the model to identify an anatomical locus of external feedback processing and a mechanistic prediction of how feedback informs the selection of control signals to improve closed-loop performance. The control system identified in this project would represent a biological basis of self-control processes across broad behavioral domains.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1735820</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Bush</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Keith Bush</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kabush@uams.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5015268347</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000572485</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arkansas Medical Sciences Campus</Name>
<CityName>Little Rock</CityName>
<ZipCode>722057101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5016865502</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4301 West Markham</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>122452563</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARKANSAS SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>055600001</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Little Rock</CityName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>722057199</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4301 West Markham St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>004Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Learning</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1699</Code>
<Text>Cognitive Neuroscience</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>059Z</Code>
<Text>Science of Learning</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1699</Code>
<Text>COGNEURO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~422610</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-fe04caeb-7fff-9d58-97ed-d2d4431ef239"> </span></p> <p style="text-align: center;" dir="ltr"><strong>PROJECT OUTCOMES</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) non-invasively records neural activity in the human brain, thereby allowing interrogation of the complex neurocircuitry underlying critical brain functions. The primary goal of this project is to generate and analyze fMRI data in order to understand the neurocircuitry governing the regulation of human emotions. Unique to this project is the use of engineering control theory, which describes the control of physical systems to desired outcomes, to specify the roles of individual regions within the emotion regulation neurocircuit. One related project goal is the comparison of competing mathematical theories by which the brain evaluates its emotion control performance. Another related project goal is the use of real-time fMRI (an imaging technique in which a subject is presented with their brain activity as it is recorded in order to guide its alteration) to test whether subjects may take advantage of objective measurements of their emotion neurocircuit to improve control. Here we describe our findings related to these project goals as well as the project?s broader outcomes.</span></p> <p><strong>Control theoretic modeling of emotion regulation.</strong> A control system consists of two interacting parts: the system to be controlled (termed the plant), which in this project is the emotion processing neurocircuit, and the control law, which monitors the plant and perturbs it until it reaches a desired outcome (termed the goal). Past research has found that medial and lateral regions of the brain?s prefrontal cortex, respectively, monitor performance and drive change, suggesting functional encoding sites of an emotion-related control law.&nbsp; To test this hypothesis, we first used machine learning to construct computational models that predict emotion levels directly from brief recordings of fMRI data, allowing for precise predictions of emotion to be made over time as subjects perform tasks during fMRI acquisition. We then validated these models using independent psychophysiological correlates of emotion recorded concurrently with fMRI. Subjects then performed tasks during fMRI that required them to consciously or unconsciously regulate their emotions. By comparing the fMRI data recorded during these two disparate tasks and taking into account the emotion predictions made by our machine learning models we were able to identify a neurocircuit involving the lateral prefrontal cortex that is most likely associated with the control law?s perturbation of the plant, thus confirming our hypothesis.</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Multiple competing theoretical measures describe how the medial prefrontal cortex (widely acknowledged as the locus for this role) monitors emotion regulation performance, ranging from a simple difference between the current and desired level of emotion to more complicated theories in which the trade-offs of regulating emotion, for example, balancing the benefits of achieving the desired emotion against the expense of effort (termed action-values), are prospectively computed. Using emotion predictions produced by our machine learning models (described above) when applied to fMRI data recorded during an emotion regulation task with known goals, we constructed numerical representations of the leading theoretical measures and tested the agreement between&nbsp; these measures and the neural activity observed in the medial prefrontal cortex. We find that emotion regulation performance is most likely monitored according to action-values.</span></p> <p><strong>Real-time fMRI-guided emotion regulation. </strong>An open question in emotion regulation is whether natural regulation processes may be augmented by the introduction of objective information about regulation performance, such as the representations of brain activity (termed neurofeedback) available through the use of real-time fMRI techniques. To answer this question, we had subjects perform emotion regulation tasks during real-time fMRI. During each task, subjects received simple visual representations of the emotion levels within their brain relative to the task?s goal. To account for heightened attention associated with these types of experiments, we randomly assigned subjects to receive either real neurofeedback (based on the subject?s brain activity) or sham neurofeedback (visually realistic but unrelated to the subject?s brain activity). We found that subjects in both groups were able to consciously regulate their emotions to the desired goals for certain forms of emotion; however, the type of feedback (real or sham) did not alter emotion regulation performance.</p> <p><strong>Broader Outcomes. </strong><span>Beyond its </span><span>technical and scientific</span><span> achievements, this project supported the training of a post-baccalaureate intern in scientific programming and statistical analysis (Python, Matlab) as well as psychophysiological and neuroimaging data processing (Kubios, AFNI) resulting in this intern?s first first-authorship of a scientific journal article. This project also helped support the training of a 2nd year medical student research intern at the University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences (UAMS) resulting in this intern?s first first-authorship of a scientific journal manuscript. Resources from this project (e.g., open-source machine learning models and psychophysiological processing pipelines) also supported the research of two MD/PhD students who performed their doctoral training in the UAMS Brain Imaging Research Center (BIRC).</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/14/2021<br>      Modified by: Keith&nbsp;Bush</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   PROJECT OUTCOMES Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) non-invasively records neural activity in the human brain, thereby allowing interrogation of the complex neurocircuitry underlying critical brain functions. The primary goal of this project is to generate and analyze fMRI data in order to understand the neurocircuitry governing the regulation of human emotions. Unique to this project is the use of engineering control theory, which describes the control of physical systems to desired outcomes, to specify the roles of individual regions within the emotion regulation neurocircuit. One related project goal is the comparison of competing mathematical theories by which the brain evaluates its emotion control performance. Another related project goal is the use of real-time fMRI (an imaging technique in which a subject is presented with their brain activity as it is recorded in order to guide its alteration) to test whether subjects may take advantage of objective measurements of their emotion neurocircuit to improve control. Here we describe our findings related to these project goals as well as the project?s broader outcomes.  Control theoretic modeling of emotion regulation. A control system consists of two interacting parts: the system to be controlled (termed the plant), which in this project is the emotion processing neurocircuit, and the control law, which monitors the plant and perturbs it until it reaches a desired outcome (termed the goal). Past research has found that medial and lateral regions of the brain?s prefrontal cortex, respectively, monitor performance and drive change, suggesting functional encoding sites of an emotion-related control law.  To test this hypothesis, we first used machine learning to construct computational models that predict emotion levels directly from brief recordings of fMRI data, allowing for precise predictions of emotion to be made over time as subjects perform tasks during fMRI acquisition. We then validated these models using independent psychophysiological correlates of emotion recorded concurrently with fMRI. Subjects then performed tasks during fMRI that required them to consciously or unconsciously regulate their emotions. By comparing the fMRI data recorded during these two disparate tasks and taking into account the emotion predictions made by our machine learning models we were able to identify a neurocircuit involving the lateral prefrontal cortex that is most likely associated with the control law?s perturbation of the plant, thus confirming our hypothesis. Multiple competing theoretical measures describe how the medial prefrontal cortex (widely acknowledged as the locus for this role) monitors emotion regulation performance, ranging from a simple difference between the current and desired level of emotion to more complicated theories in which the trade-offs of regulating emotion, for example, balancing the benefits of achieving the desired emotion against the expense of effort (termed action-values), are prospectively computed. Using emotion predictions produced by our machine learning models (described above) when applied to fMRI data recorded during an emotion regulation task with known goals, we constructed numerical representations of the leading theoretical measures and tested the agreement between  these measures and the neural activity observed in the medial prefrontal cortex. We find that emotion regulation performance is most likely monitored according to action-values.  Real-time fMRI-guided emotion regulation. An open question in emotion regulation is whether natural regulation processes may be augmented by the introduction of objective information about regulation performance, such as the representations of brain activity (termed neurofeedback) available through the use of real-time fMRI techniques. To answer this question, we had subjects perform emotion regulation tasks during real-time fMRI. During each task, subjects received simple visual representations of the emotion levels within their brain relative to the task?s goal. To account for heightened attention associated with these types of experiments, we randomly assigned subjects to receive either real neurofeedback (based on the subject?s brain activity) or sham neurofeedback (visually realistic but unrelated to the subject?s brain activity). We found that subjects in both groups were able to consciously regulate their emotions to the desired goals for certain forms of emotion; however, the type of feedback (real or sham) did not alter emotion regulation performance.  Broader Outcomes. Beyond its technical and scientific achievements, this project supported the training of a post-baccalaureate intern in scientific programming and statistical analysis (Python, Matlab) as well as psychophysiological and neuroimaging data processing (Kubios, AFNI) resulting in this intern?s first first-authorship of a scientific journal article. This project also helped support the training of a 2nd year medical student research intern at the University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences (UAMS) resulting in this intern?s first first-authorship of a scientific journal manuscript. Resources from this project (e.g., open-source machine learning models and psychophysiological processing pipelines) also supported the research of two MD/PhD students who performed their doctoral training in the UAMS Brain Imaging Research Center (BIRC).          Last Modified: 04/14/2021       Submitted by: Keith Bush]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
