<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Science Policy Research Report: A Synthesis of Available Information and Analysis of Knowledge Gaps to Advance Groundwater Security Under Drought</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cassidy Sugimoto</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Groundwater provides 25 percent of fresh water used in the United States, which is especially significant during drought when pumping is increased to compensate for reduced surface supplies. Groundwater depletion is extensive in many areas and there is a critical need to reduce drought vulnerability. This project summarizes the scientific evidence, makes policy recommendations, and illuminates important information gaps, regarding the important relationships between groundwater and drought. This policy research report integrates physical and social science research to provide an understanding of the relationship between groundwater management and drought resilience and communicates results and policy recommendations to local, state and federal agencies and policymakers, academic scholars, water management utilities and water users, as they consider future strategies to reduce drought impacts, including water shortages, through more effective groundwater management. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Effective groundwater management requires an interdisciplinary proces.  This project synthesizes and reviews  data from the physical sciences, the social sciences, and the legal and policy literature, to identify knowledge gaps. Issues that will be addressed include the hydrogeophysical characteristics of a basin as these affect groundwater use and management and water supply security, and the potential impact of future droughts under climate change on water supplies and the effect of competing interests and climate uncertainty on decisionmaking regarding groundwater use and management, and the benefits and impacts of particular management approaches and their distribution.  The legal and policy programs that exist to support groundwater security and sustainability and increase drought resilience, and potential incentives that can reduce resource degradation and promote more equitable access are considered. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1735654</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ruth</FirstName>
<LastName>Langridge</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ruth Langridge</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rlangrid@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8314592836</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000561811</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
<CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>125084723</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA CRUZ</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Cruz]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SciSIP-Sci of Sci Innov Policy</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Groundwater is an essential and life-sustaining resource that is under increasing strain throughout the world.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit: </span></strong>This<strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span></strong>research provided a unique interdisciplinary synthesis to better understand what is known regarding the physical, institutional and social barriers and opportunities confronting groundwater security and sustainability under drought and climate change. It analyzed research from the physical sciences, the social sciences and the legal and policy literature and identified critical knowledge gaps for both future research and applied needs..</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader impacts</span></strong> Research addressed a critical problem that has received insufficient attention. Multi-disciplinary research information presented in this report will allow scientists, decisionmakers, water practitioners and stakeholders to better adapt to drought <em>and</em> secure greater groundwater sustainability.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Highlights:</span></strong></p> <ul> <li>Groundwater is affected by changes to the global hydrological cycle, including drought. During drought, groundwater levels are reduced, while concomitant surface water shortages drive increased groundwater pumping. This can result in groundwater deletion. Globally, overdraft has significantly reduced groundwater storage, the baseflow to rivers, and the discharge of springs-all key to sustaining ecosystem and human water needs during drought.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Climate anomalies in both temperature and precipitation can result in even greater deficits in precipitation, soil moisture and streamflow or runoff that will reduce both surface water supplies and groundwater recharge. </li> </ul> <ul> <li>Studies on the impacts of climate change and drought on groundwater are limited compared to surface water. An explicit mention of groundwater drought is missing from standard drought categories. There is insufficient linkage of both drought and climate change models to hydrologic groundwater models. </li> </ul> <ul> <li>The net effect of drought on groundwater quality and storage depends not just on climate or the physical attributes of a region, but also on human actions. Interdisciplinary research is thus critical to understand both the physical and social factors influencing the implementation of policies to effectively manage groundwater under climate change and drought. </li> </ul> <ul> <li>Governing groundwater has been impeded by its unique physical attributes and the challenges of governing a common pool resource where rules of access and use are frequently contested. Drought governance is also challenging as its impacts accumulate slowly and may linger for years. </li> </ul> <ul> <li>Groundwater governance needs to be linked to whether and how inequities in access to the resource are affected by climate change and drought.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Drought planning and groundwater management plans rarely intersect. Drought plans give limited attention to sustaining groundwater, while groundwater management plans provide limited attention to drought. </li> </ul> <ul> <li>Linking groundwater <em>and</em> drought governance approaches presents issues of scale?groundwater governance is primarily local while drought governance is frequently focused on larger geographic areas.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Training and scholarship are generally focused on single-discipline areas, and, within the physical and social science literature, groundwater, drought and climate change are frequently investigated as independent phenomena. </li> </ul> <p>This report highlights several drought and groundwater challenges in California.</p> <ul> <li>While 3-year periods of persistent below-average soil moisture are not uncommon, the 2012?2016 drought was the most severe drought in the last century. New strategies are examining flooding fields for both irrigation and recharge and new laws passed during the drought will change groundwater governance.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>California was first U.S. state to adopt a Human Right to Water, in 2012, requiring that: ?? state agencies have a duty to consider this as they establish policies and regulations.? California is working to actualize this Right, in the context of a changing climate.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Knowledge Gaps:</span></strong></p> <ul> <li><strong><em>Studies on the dynamics and linkages between drought, climate change and groundwater lag behind</em></strong><strong><em> those on surface waters</em></strong>. </li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong><em>A better understanding of the uncertainties in groundwater, drought and climate change research is needed</em></strong></li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong><em>The direct and indirect relationships of anthropogenic-global warming and natural climate variability on components in the global hydrologic cycle, including groundwater,</em></strong> <strong><em>have not been sufficiently explored</em></strong> </li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong><em>A better understanding is needed of the linkages between water demand and the dynamics associated with multiple climate, oceanic, meteorological and hydrological parameters</em></strong> </li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong><em>Research is needed to understand the effectiveness of different institutional approaches and management options to reduce drought risks for water-stressed areas and how </em></strong><strong><em>con&#64258;ict resolution can increase adaptive capacity&nbsp; to drought.</em></strong></li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong><em>More understanding is needed of the space-time development of groundwater and hydrological droughts as a response to a meteorological drought and the associated soil moisture drough</em></strong><strong><em>t</em></strong>.</li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong><em>The integration of drought management into relevant water policies is needed </em></strong></li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong><em>More research is needed within each discipline: </em></strong></li> </ul> <p><strong><em>1) To understand how regions will be affected by processes in the Pacific Ocean and Arctic</em></strong></p> <p><strong><em>2) To provide long-term groundwater data</em></strong>.</p> <p><strong><em>3) To understand the complex physical processes responsible for changes in regional climate extremes</em></strong></p> <p><strong><em><br /></em></strong></p> <p>Actions taken in response to interdisciplinary research have the potential to reduce drought?s negative impacts to groundwater by increasing our understanding of knowledge gaps, and by optimizing groundwater management strategies that increase drought resilience.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Ruth&nbsp;Langridge</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Groundwater is an essential and life-sustaining resource that is under increasing strain throughout the world.  Intellectual Merit: This research provided a unique interdisciplinary synthesis to better understand what is known regarding the physical, institutional and social barriers and opportunities confronting groundwater security and sustainability under drought and climate change. It analyzed research from the physical sciences, the social sciences and the legal and policy literature and identified critical knowledge gaps for both future research and applied needs..  Broader impacts Research addressed a critical problem that has received insufficient attention. Multi-disciplinary research information presented in this report will allow scientists, decisionmakers, water practitioners and stakeholders to better adapt to drought and secure greater groundwater sustainability.  Highlights:  Groundwater is affected by changes to the global hydrological cycle, including drought. During drought, groundwater levels are reduced, while concomitant surface water shortages drive increased groundwater pumping. This can result in groundwater deletion. Globally, overdraft has significantly reduced groundwater storage, the baseflow to rivers, and the discharge of springs-all key to sustaining ecosystem and human water needs during drought.   Climate anomalies in both temperature and precipitation can result in even greater deficits in precipitation, soil moisture and streamflow or runoff that will reduce both surface water supplies and groundwater recharge.    Studies on the impacts of climate change and drought on groundwater are limited compared to surface water. An explicit mention of groundwater drought is missing from standard drought categories. There is insufficient linkage of both drought and climate change models to hydrologic groundwater models.    The net effect of drought on groundwater quality and storage depends not just on climate or the physical attributes of a region, but also on human actions. Interdisciplinary research is thus critical to understand both the physical and social factors influencing the implementation of policies to effectively manage groundwater under climate change and drought.    Governing groundwater has been impeded by its unique physical attributes and the challenges of governing a common pool resource where rules of access and use are frequently contested. Drought governance is also challenging as its impacts accumulate slowly and may linger for years.    Groundwater governance needs to be linked to whether and how inequities in access to the resource are affected by climate change and drought.   Drought planning and groundwater management plans rarely intersect. Drought plans give limited attention to sustaining groundwater, while groundwater management plans provide limited attention to drought.    Linking groundwater and drought governance approaches presents issues of scale?groundwater governance is primarily local while drought governance is frequently focused on larger geographic areas.   Training and scholarship are generally focused on single-discipline areas, and, within the physical and social science literature, groundwater, drought and climate change are frequently investigated as independent phenomena.    This report highlights several drought and groundwater challenges in California.  While 3-year periods of persistent below-average soil moisture are not uncommon, the 2012?2016 drought was the most severe drought in the last century. New strategies are examining flooding fields for both irrigation and recharge and new laws passed during the drought will change groundwater governance.   California was first U.S. state to adopt a Human Right to Water, in 2012, requiring that: ?? state agencies have a duty to consider this as they establish policies and regulations.? California is working to actualize this Right, in the context of a changing climate.      Knowledge Gaps:  Studies on the dynamics and linkages between drought, climate change and groundwater lag behind those on surface waters.    A better understanding of the uncertainties in groundwater, drought and climate change research is needed   The direct and indirect relationships of anthropogenic-global warming and natural climate variability on components in the global hydrologic cycle, including groundwater, have not been sufficiently explored    A better understanding is needed of the linkages between water demand and the dynamics associated with multiple climate, oceanic, meteorological and hydrological parameters    Research is needed to understand the effectiveness of different institutional approaches and management options to reduce drought risks for water-stressed areas and how con&#64258;ict resolution can increase adaptive capacity  to drought.   More understanding is needed of the space-time development of groundwater and hydrological droughts as a response to a meteorological drought and the associated soil moisture drought.   The integration of drought management into relevant water policies is needed    More research is needed within each discipline:    1) To understand how regions will be affected by processes in the Pacific Ocean and Arctic  2) To provide long-term groundwater data.  3) To understand the complex physical processes responsible for changes in regional climate extremes     Actions taken in response to interdisciplinary research have the potential to reduce drought?s negative impacts to groundwater by increasing our understanding of knowledge gaps, and by optimizing groundwater management strategies that increase drought resilience.             Last Modified: 01/30/2019       Submitted by: Ruth Langridge]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
