<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID:   Investigating  changes to  metal oxide nanoparticle stability in a contaminated stream during the initial period of remediation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nosavage@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>There are known impacts to streams in the United States as a result of pollution from abandoned mines.  Even after the impact of the acidic mine effluents are removed by treatment, the streambeds themselves will continue to release metals that are toxic to aquatic species.  The metal-containing sediments must be naturally removed in order for the stream to recover and allow both restoration of aquatic life and beneficial use by society.  The sediments consist primarily of very small nanoparticles of iron oxide that can contain As, Cd, Cu, Pb, and Zn. These small particles, which have stuck to the streambed, may be more quickly removed if they become more stable in water due to changes in the chemistry of their surfaces.  A treatment plant that removes the metals and acid from the mine effluents has just begun operation.  The treatment process also alters the composition of the stream water in such a way that the particles may become more stable in water and, thus, removed more quickly. This study will provide data that will lead to better estimates of how quickly other streams will recover if similar mine waste treatment is performed.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Incidental nanoparticulate iron oxides (NP-FeOx) are formed in streams receiving acidic mine waters.  NP-FeOx is capable of transporting contaminant metals such as Cu, Zn, and As. In early 2017 a lime treatment plant will go online in the North Fork of Clear Creek (NFCC), which will dramatically alter the water chemistry of the stream.  The colloidal stability of NP-FeOX is dependent on solution composition (ionic strength, divalent cations, pH, DOC) and is thus likely to be affected.  The project goal is to understand how the removal of metals will be influenced by changes in the stability of the NP-FeOx.  In order to determine the immediate impact of the water treatment plant (WTP) on NP-FeOx stability in the water column, the dispersion of existing NP-FeOx contained in the streambed will be studied using spICP-MS, DLS, zeta potential, and ICP-OES. It is expected that preexisting NP-FeOX will disperse from the creek bed into the water during early WTP operation, which may result in a temporary increase in toxic metal concentrations.  This will be of long-term benefit, as this process may accelerate the restoration of the streambed.  This is the first time that nanoparticle stability under variable water chemistry conditions has been examined in an actual stream setting.  Additionally, the manipulation of pH and hardness in laboratory experiments will allow us to understand the effects of isolated water chemistry variables on particle dispersion in an AMD system.  A summer field session aimed at local high school students and college seniors at the Colorado School of Mines will participate in a field session at the study site. In addition, a partnership with the Upper Clear Creek Watershed Foundation will be forged to involve community volunteers on the proposed project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1736102</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Ranville</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James F Ranville</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jranvill@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3032733004</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000327148</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/17/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado School of Mines</Name>
<CityName>Golden</CityName>
<ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3032733000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1500 Illinois</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>010628170</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE COLORADO SCHOOL OF MINES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>010628170</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado School of Mines]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1179</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Interactions Program</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Weathering of mining waste or abandoned mine shafts produces acid mine drainage (AMD), an acidic runoff concentrated with heavy metals, which can cause ongoing contamination to streams. AMD entering fresh water causes the geochemical precipitation of Fe and Al oxide particles, which play an important role in the fate and transport of toxic metals such as As, Cu, and Zn. These precipitates are typically nanoparticles (NPs), which form aggregates that settle to the stream bed. The North Fork of Clear Creek is one example of an AMD-impacted stream whose water quality was poor enough to be designated as a superfund site in 1983. The final step to restore the creek&rsquo;s water quality was taken in 2016 with the construction of a water treatment plant, which began operating in 2017. The aim of this research project was to examine how the changing water chemistry would affect the Fe oxide NPs that had previously accumulated on the creek bed.</p> <p>We monitored the water quality and the NP size and concentrations during the first six months of treatment plant activity. Since this period overlapped with spring snowmelt, both water treatment and runoff flushing and scouring acted together to rapidly remove NPs, as is apparent in the images shown in Figure 1. The initial pH of the contaminated (Downstream) sampling site was slightly acidic compared to the uncontaminated upstream (Reference) sites (Figure 2, left) and soon increased as treatment and spring runoff began. Meanwhile the conductivity, resulting primarily from metal cations and sulfate anions, initially decreased sharply (Figure 2, middle) due to the combined effects of treatment removing most ions, except sulfate, and runoff diluting what remained. Conductivity rebounded after runoff ended in the late summer, but other measurements of the water composition (data not shown) indicate this is due to Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup>, and sulfate. These ions, unlike the toxic heavy metals of concern, are not removed during water treatment. Figure 2, right shows the stream hydrology over the study period both as discharge (data from USGS National Water Information site #06718550) and water velocity, measured in the field at the time of sampling. Peak streamflow was observed in early June.</p> <p>These changes in water composition and streamflow were accompanied by a decrease in the Fe and Cu NP&nbsp;&nbsp;concentrations (Figure 3) as well as Fe NP size (Figure 4), which were measured by single particle ICP-MS. Because of exceedingly low NP concentrations during runoff, only the pretreatment (Before) and end of summer (After) NP concentrations are considered in Figure 3 (right panel). Navigating the analytical challenges of measuring NPs in a dynamic natural system was an important highlight of the study.</p> <p>In order to address the project goal of understanding the effect of post-remediation changes in water chemistry on NP stability, aggregation experiments were conducted.&nbsp;&nbsp;A model Fe oxide NP was suspended in filtered creek water samples. While the pre-treatment water conditions caused near-zero surface charge and rapid aggregation, NPs in the treated water were negatively charged and did not aggregate (Figure 5). The dependence of surface charge on water pH and ionic strength is shown as a heat map in Figure 6, where the black line marks the -10 mV border between the unstable and stable surface charge regions.&nbsp; It is well established that charged surfaces are needed to prevent particle aggregation and there is typically a zone of instability near the point-of-zero-charge. It is expected that a pH increase will cause a more negatively charged surface, which was observed in our results (Figure 6). The removal of ions during treatment, reflected by the decrease in conductivity (Figure 2) is also likely to contribute to the decreasing aggregation rate since ionic strength is known to promote aggregation. Our results are therefore in good accordance with surface chemistry theory and suggest that the changes in water chemistry resulting from treatment prevent any new NP formation and aggregation in the stream.</p> <p>The completed project met the intellectual merit criteria as discussed in the original proposal. The study successfully improved knowledge of particle behavior within AMD systems as it relates to water quality and surface chemistry. Additionally, the work provided an exciting opportunity to apply single particle ICP-MS, a recently developed nanoparticle analysis technique, to AMD water samples. To our knowledge, this is the first instance the technique has been utilized in this type of environmental system. We also met our broader impacts goals for incorporating outreach into the project by introducing high school students to the field site.&nbsp;The results have been presented at several international conferences as well as having been used in three short course presented by the PI.&nbsp;&nbsp;One graduate student and three undergraduate students were trained in nanogeoscience as part of the project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/28/2018<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;F&nbsp;Ranville</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532703134657_PORFig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532703134657_PORFig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532703134657_PORFig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Photos of the North Fork of Clear Creek before treatment (left), when treatment of one principal AMD source began and during spring runoff (middle), and when full treatment was underway and runoff had ended (right).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Logan Rand and James Ranville</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;F&nbsp;Ranville</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532703916812_PORFig2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532703916812_PORFig2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532703916812_PORFig2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">pH (left) and conductivity (middle) of the uncontaminated upstream creek water (Reference 1, 2) and AMD contaminated creek water (Downstream), and hydrology (right) of the creek during the study period.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Logan Rand and James Ranville</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;F&nbsp;Ranville</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532710671698_PORFig3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532710671698_PORFig3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532710671698_PORFig3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Number concentrations of micron-sized particles (left), measured by laser-scattering, and Cu and Fe nanoparticles (right), measured by single particle ICP-MS, in the North Fork of Clear Creek uncontaminated (Reference) and AMD contaminated (Downstream) sampling locations.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Logan Rand and James Ranville</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;F&nbsp;Ranville</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532710875864_PORFig4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532710875864_PORFig4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532710875864_PORFig4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fe nanoparticle size distributions in the contaminated, downstream creek water without treatment (black), during treatment and peak runoff (red), and during treatment and when stream flow had returned to normal after runoff (gold), determined by single particle ICP-MS.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Logan Rand and James Ranville</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;F&nbsp;Ranville</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532711154561_PORFig5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532711154561_PORFig5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 5."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1736102/1736102_10482080_1532711154561_PORFig5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 5."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Surface charge, measured as zeta potential, (left) and aggregation rates, calculated from the increase in size over one hour measured by dynamic light scattering, (right) of hematite suspended in filtered water samples from the uncontaminated (Reference) and contaminated (Downstream) creek sites.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Logan Rand and James Ranville</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;F&nbsp;Ranville</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 5.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Weathering of mining waste or abandoned mine shafts produces acid mine drainage (AMD), an acidic runoff concentrated with heavy metals, which can cause ongoing contamination to streams. AMD entering fresh water causes the geochemical precipitation of Fe and Al oxide particles, which play an important role in the fate and transport of toxic metals such as As, Cu, and Zn. These precipitates are typically nanoparticles (NPs), which form aggregates that settle to the stream bed. The North Fork of Clear Creek is one example of an AMD-impacted stream whose water quality was poor enough to be designated as a superfund site in 1983. The final step to restore the creek?s water quality was taken in 2016 with the construction of a water treatment plant, which began operating in 2017. The aim of this research project was to examine how the changing water chemistry would affect the Fe oxide NPs that had previously accumulated on the creek bed.  We monitored the water quality and the NP size and concentrations during the first six months of treatment plant activity. Since this period overlapped with spring snowmelt, both water treatment and runoff flushing and scouring acted together to rapidly remove NPs, as is apparent in the images shown in Figure 1. The initial pH of the contaminated (Downstream) sampling site was slightly acidic compared to the uncontaminated upstream (Reference) sites (Figure 2, left) and soon increased as treatment and spring runoff began. Meanwhile the conductivity, resulting primarily from metal cations and sulfate anions, initially decreased sharply (Figure 2, middle) due to the combined effects of treatment removing most ions, except sulfate, and runoff diluting what remained. Conductivity rebounded after runoff ended in the late summer, but other measurements of the water composition (data not shown) indicate this is due to Ca2+, Mg2+, and sulfate. These ions, unlike the toxic heavy metals of concern, are not removed during water treatment. Figure 2, right shows the stream hydrology over the study period both as discharge (data from USGS National Water Information site #06718550) and water velocity, measured in the field at the time of sampling. Peak streamflow was observed in early June.  These changes in water composition and streamflow were accompanied by a decrease in the Fe and Cu NP  concentrations (Figure 3) as well as Fe NP size (Figure 4), which were measured by single particle ICP-MS. Because of exceedingly low NP concentrations during runoff, only the pretreatment (Before) and end of summer (After) NP concentrations are considered in Figure 3 (right panel). Navigating the analytical challenges of measuring NPs in a dynamic natural system was an important highlight of the study.  In order to address the project goal of understanding the effect of post-remediation changes in water chemistry on NP stability, aggregation experiments were conducted.  A model Fe oxide NP was suspended in filtered creek water samples. While the pre-treatment water conditions caused near-zero surface charge and rapid aggregation, NPs in the treated water were negatively charged and did not aggregate (Figure 5). The dependence of surface charge on water pH and ionic strength is shown as a heat map in Figure 6, where the black line marks the -10 mV border between the unstable and stable surface charge regions.  It is well established that charged surfaces are needed to prevent particle aggregation and there is typically a zone of instability near the point-of-zero-charge. It is expected that a pH increase will cause a more negatively charged surface, which was observed in our results (Figure 6). The removal of ions during treatment, reflected by the decrease in conductivity (Figure 2) is also likely to contribute to the decreasing aggregation rate since ionic strength is known to promote aggregation. Our results are therefore in good accordance with surface chemistry theory and suggest that the changes in water chemistry resulting from treatment prevent any new NP formation and aggregation in the stream.  The completed project met the intellectual merit criteria as discussed in the original proposal. The study successfully improved knowledge of particle behavior within AMD systems as it relates to water quality and surface chemistry. Additionally, the work provided an exciting opportunity to apply single particle ICP-MS, a recently developed nanoparticle analysis technique, to AMD water samples. To our knowledge, this is the first instance the technique has been utilized in this type of environmental system. We also met our broader impacts goals for incorporating outreach into the project by introducing high school students to the field site. The results have been presented at several international conferences as well as having been used in three short course presented by the PI.  One graduate student and three undergraduate students were trained in nanogeoscience as part of the project.          Last Modified: 07/28/2018       Submitted by: James F Ranville]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
