<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Broadening Participation in Engineering: Workshop on Reducing Attrition in Precalculus Pathways</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49711.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49711</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paige Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>There are many pathways to an engineering degree and all of them pass through calculus. In South Carolina, there is a significant racial and socioeconomic disparity between engineering students who place below calculus and those who enter college calculus-ready. Engineering ­intending students from underrepresented minority backgrounds are significantly more likely to place below calculus than their white counterparts. That disparity translates into a dramatic gap in engineering degree completion rates. Narrowing the gap and broadening participation in engineering by reducing attrition rates along the precalculus pathway to an engineering degree requires that secondary schools, two-year colleges, and four-year colleges work together to identify barriers and develop coordinated action plans for surmounting those barriers. The project will bring together 30 action teams of three people from selected secondary and post-secondary institutions across South Carolina for a two-day workshop. The project is designed to meet three goals:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. Identify common barriers to success within institutions and between institutions,&lt;br/&gt;2. Establish cross-institutional collaborations, and&lt;br/&gt;3. Build upon existing best practices to develop specific action plans for reducing attrition among precalculus students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will contribute to understanding the specific focal predictors most relevant to precalculus pathways to engineering degrees for South Carolina students, particularly those who are first-generation college students and/or from racially underrepresented or low socioeconomic backgrounds. The data collected from the workshop will help us understand the barriers to engineering success as perceived by faculty and administrators in secondary and post-secondary colleges. Action plans developed during the workshop will establish a range of potential pilot studies for addressing specific barriers at specific points along the pathways, and will set the stage for larger-scale interventions to reduce attrition. These action plans may serve as pilot projects or proof of concept for statewide interventions to broaden the engineering participation of first-generation college students, racially underrepresented minorities, and students from lower-income families. The lessons learned from the project and from subsequent interventions may be transferable to other systems with similar demographics. Themes that emerge will increase our understanding of the complex interactions between high school course selection, choice of higher education institution, and placement and performance in the first college math course.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1737686</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Serita</FirstName>
<LastName>Acker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Serita W Acker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wserita@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8036563311</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000257070</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sez</FirstName>
<LastName>Atamturktur Russcher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sez Atamturktur Russcher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sez@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8646437909</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574977</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eliza</FirstName>
<LastName>Gallagher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eliza Gallagher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>egallag@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8646562424</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000708773</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristin</FirstName>
<LastName>Frady</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristin K Frady</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>frady@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8646562424</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000710116</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clemson University</Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296345701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLEMSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clemson University]]></Name>
<CityName>Clemson</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>EDA-Eng Diversity Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~49711</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Workshop on Reducing Attrition in Precalculus Pathways to Engineering Degrees (WRAPPED) brought together 72 educators from around the state of South Carolina for a two-day workshop on March 20-21, 2018. During each of three plenary sessions, attendees heard a "state of the state" for the K-12 system, the two-year technical college system, and the four-year system. A poster session allowed each attending institution to present their own best practices and see those of other institutions. During four working sessions, attendees worked in cross-institutional and cross-level teams to identify common barriers to mathematical success in the Grade 10 -- Second Year of College band, and then worked to create action plans for reducing those barriers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Each institution sent a team of three, including on instructional faculty member in either math or engineering, one advising faculty or staff member, and one administrator. On the first day of the workshop, attendees worked with others in their same role to identify barriers, first within the same educational grouping, and then across educational levels. All three groups identified a gap in expectations as a key barrier in student success in mathematics, although the specific gap differed across groups: gaps between student and teacher expectations for content mastery, gaps between high school and college expectations for mathematical preparedness and rigor, gaps between soft skills needed for success and those students had in hand. The groups also identified financial, legislative, and cultural barriers of different types.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>On the second day, attendees worked within geographical regions to first brainstorm interventions, and then later to select one idea and develop a specific action plan. One group detailed plans for vertical alignment professional development in which they would work together to align state standards for K-12 mathematics instruction to the curriculum for first-year post-secondary students, identify gaps, and then create engineering-based modules for implementation in the schools. A second group proposed an intervention to start in 8<sup>th</sup>-grade, with high school and college faculty working together to deliver curricular modules designed for students to experience failure with support to encourage resilience, perseverance, and a growth mindset for mathematics. A third group focused on developing the engineering knowledge of high school mathematics teachers through internships with industry and field trips to the college campuses, so that those teachers could bring working knowledge of engineering into their classrooms and lessons.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to the specific knowledge generated from the workshop, the activities also served to create working relationships between educators at different points in the state-wide educational system. The long-term goal of this first step is to broaden participation in STEM so that the demographics of the STEM workforce match the demographics of the state.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/03/2018<br>      Modified by: Eliza&nbsp;Gallagher</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Workshop on Reducing Attrition in Precalculus Pathways to Engineering Degrees (WRAPPED) brought together 72 educators from around the state of South Carolina for a two-day workshop on March 20-21, 2018. During each of three plenary sessions, attendees heard a "state of the state" for the K-12 system, the two-year technical college system, and the four-year system. A poster session allowed each attending institution to present their own best practices and see those of other institutions. During four working sessions, attendees worked in cross-institutional and cross-level teams to identify common barriers to mathematical success in the Grade 10 -- Second Year of College band, and then worked to create action plans for reducing those barriers.     Each institution sent a team of three, including on instructional faculty member in either math or engineering, one advising faculty or staff member, and one administrator. On the first day of the workshop, attendees worked with others in their same role to identify barriers, first within the same educational grouping, and then across educational levels. All three groups identified a gap in expectations as a key barrier in student success in mathematics, although the specific gap differed across groups: gaps between student and teacher expectations for content mastery, gaps between high school and college expectations for mathematical preparedness and rigor, gaps between soft skills needed for success and those students had in hand. The groups also identified financial, legislative, and cultural barriers of different types.     On the second day, attendees worked within geographical regions to first brainstorm interventions, and then later to select one idea and develop a specific action plan. One group detailed plans for vertical alignment professional development in which they would work together to align state standards for K-12 mathematics instruction to the curriculum for first-year post-secondary students, identify gaps, and then create engineering-based modules for implementation in the schools. A second group proposed an intervention to start in 8th-grade, with high school and college faculty working together to deliver curricular modules designed for students to experience failure with support to encourage resilience, perseverance, and a growth mindset for mathematics. A third group focused on developing the engineering knowledge of high school mathematics teachers through internships with industry and field trips to the college campuses, so that those teachers could bring working knowledge of engineering into their classrooms and lessons.     In addition to the specific knowledge generated from the workshop, the activities also served to create working relationships between educators at different points in the state-wide educational system. The long-term goal of this first step is to broaden participation in STEM so that the demographics of the STEM workforce match the demographics of the state.       Last Modified: 11/03/2018       Submitted by: Eliza Gallagher]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
