<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ATD:   Spatio-Temporal Model for the Propagation of Internet Traffic Anomalies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project seeks to develop a statistical model for the propagation of internet traffic anomalies. The model will serve as a tool in an on-going, multidirectional effort aimed at increasing the security of the backbone internet network in the United States and the detection of threats to its operation caused either by suboptimal design or malicious attacks. The model will be constructed using a large publicly available data set of various internet traffic measurements. The work will involve statistical analysis of the data, probabilistic modeling, and simulation. The research will combine expertise of statistics and computer science researchers. By involving Ph.D. students in the field at the nexus of statistics and computer networks, it will train highly educated personnel in an area of national importance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While modeling normal network traffic has received a great deal of attention in the last twenty years, only certain local aspects of stochastic modeling of anomalous behavior have been addressed. Normal traffic models have been used to extract anomalies, but they do not provide information on the statistical properties of the propagation and size of anomalies, nor do they imply a stochastic mechanism that may be used to simulate the flow of anomalies. Developing a stochastic model for the propagation of network anomalies requires a new synthesis of statistical spatio-temporal modeling and discrete event simulation techniques. Spatio-temporal models currently used in various applications including industrial mining, geophysical, climate and environmental research, and public health are not transferable to the setting of internet traffic, where physical distances play no role, while network topology and link utilization become prominent. This research aims to create a new class of mathematical models that will open up new directions of research on network anomaly propagation. The models will be based on state-of-the-art statistical analysis applied to practically-relevant anomaly traffic attributes.  The work will also stimulate research in the mathematical sciences on models of this type.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1737795</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Piotr</FirstName>
<LastName>Kokoszka</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Piotr S Kokoszka</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Piotr.Kokoszka@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704916870</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000105640</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Haonan</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Haonan Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wanghn@stat.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704912449</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000250127</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Liuqing</FirstName>
<LastName>Yang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Liuqing Yang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>qingqing@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126256306</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000238007</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>785979618</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>948905492</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805214593</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 W. Lake Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>046Y</Code>
<Text>ATD-Algorithms for Threat Dete</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>Q218</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6877</Code>
<Text>ALGORITHMS IN THREAT DETECTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~62135</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~137862</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: left;">The objective of research funded by this award was to develop a probabilistic model for the movement of internet traffic anomalies over main internet links in the United States. Additional goals were to develop statistical tools for inference on various variables that can be computed from traffic measurements. Internet anomalies usually manifest themselves as traffic of intensity so high that it may cause malfunctioning or shut down of parts of the network. There are several causes for the occurrence of internet anomalies. They may occur by chance, for example,&nbsp; due to news related to natural disasters of political events. They may be due to malfunctioning of equipment. Finally, they may result from malicious activity intended to disrupt the operation of the internet, or operation of specific users in the United States. While causes may differ, the adverse effects of anomalies should be minimized.&nbsp; An important step to achieve it is to understand how anomalies propagate over the internet. Since they must be viewed as random events, rather than events occurring in some prescribed, regular manner, a probabilistic model is needed. Such a model allows many useful computations to be performed. For example, for a given link, say New York to Chicago, one should be able to compute the probability that an anomaly will occur within the next two days. We can never be sure whether an anomaly will actually occur or not, but we should be able to provide probabilities of an anomaly occurring in certain links over certain time intervals. The probabilistic modelwe developed allows internet operators to perform such calculations. It uses asinput a data base of anomalies extracted from historical internet traffic&nbsp;measurements. It then estimates required parameters according to specific&nbsp;rules we clearly formulated. Based on these estimates it allows us to&nbsp;compute various probabilities, and other quantities, like expected waiting times for certain events to occur. Our model contains several sub-models that focus on specific aspect of anomalous internet traffic. Research conducted to solve theproblems outlined above advanced the fields of applied probability and statistics in many other aspects, which are to complex to explain in this summary. It contributed to increasing the competitiveness of the United States by educating five PhD students and one MS students in a field&nbsp; at the intersectionof statistics, mathematics and engineering.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/07/2020<br>      Modified by: Piotr&nbsp;S&nbsp;Kokoszka</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The objective of research funded by this award was to develop a probabilistic model for the movement of internet traffic anomalies over main internet links in the United States. Additional goals were to develop statistical tools for inference on various variables that can be computed from traffic measurements. Internet anomalies usually manifest themselves as traffic of intensity so high that it may cause malfunctioning or shut down of parts of the network. There are several causes for the occurrence of internet anomalies. They may occur by chance, for example,  due to news related to natural disasters of political events. They may be due to malfunctioning of equipment. Finally, they may result from malicious activity intended to disrupt the operation of the internet, or operation of specific users in the United States. While causes may differ, the adverse effects of anomalies should be minimized.  An important step to achieve it is to understand how anomalies propagate over the internet. Since they must be viewed as random events, rather than events occurring in some prescribed, regular manner, a probabilistic model is needed. Such a model allows many useful computations to be performed. For example, for a given link, say New York to Chicago, one should be able to compute the probability that an anomaly will occur within the next two days. We can never be sure whether an anomaly will actually occur or not, but we should be able to provide probabilities of an anomaly occurring in certain links over certain time intervals. The probabilistic modelwe developed allows internet operators to perform such calculations. It uses asinput a data base of anomalies extracted from historical internet traffic measurements. It then estimates required parameters according to specific rules we clearly formulated. Based on these estimates it allows us to compute various probabilities, and other quantities, like expected waiting times for certain events to occur. Our model contains several sub-models that focus on specific aspect of anomalous internet traffic. Research conducted to solve theproblems outlined above advanced the fields of applied probability and statistics in many other aspects, which are to complex to explain in this summary. It contributed to increasing the competitiveness of the United States by educating five PhD students and one MS students in a field  at the intersectionof statistics, mathematics and engineering.        Last Modified: 09/07/2020       Submitted by: Piotr S Kokoszka]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
