<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ATD: Multimode Machine Learning and Deep GeoNetworks for Anomaly Detection</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399994.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>415536</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research effort creates mathematical concepts and numerical methods for the analysis of spatiotemporal datasets with a special emphasis on anomaly detection.  Early and accurate detection of unusual events and forecasts of future threats are critical in designing an effective response to them. Current algorithms for threat detection are often unable to keep up with the numerous demands, changing environments, and the huge amounts of spatiotemporal data that need to be processed and analyzed to accomplish these tasks.  Uncertainty, scale, non-stationarity, noise, and heterogeneity are fundamental issues impeding progress at all phases of the pipeline that creates knowledge from data.  The goal of this research effort is to develop novel mathematical concepts and computational methods that can detect anomalies in heterogenous, large-scale, spatiotemporal datasets.  Beyond the project's broad technological impact, it serves as a model for the kind of cross-disciplinary activity critical for research and education at the mathematics/engineering frontier.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will devise efficient, robust, and scalable algorithms for unsupervised and semi-supervised learning.  In particular, the PI will focus on the development of two approaches: (i) A multimodal diffusion framework for unsupervised prediction of anomalies from spatiotemporal data. Here, multimode refers to the fact that data may have different modalities, such as text, images, geolocations, etc. (ii) A scalable framework for semi-supervised learning on graph-structured data, based on the aforementioned multimodal diffusion framework and on a novel variant of deep convolutional networks specifically designed to operate on spatiotemporal data.  The expected success of this project is based on existing achievements by the investigator in developing advanced mathematical concepts and turning them into real-world applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/04/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1737943</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Strohmer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Strohmer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>strohmer@math.ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307521071</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000487508</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956168633</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>046Y</Code>
<Text>ATD-Algorithms for Threat Dete</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>P412</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>P413</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>P414</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6877</Code>
<Text>ALGORITHMS IN THREAT DETECTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~399994</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~15542</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Early and accurate detection of unusual events and forecast of future threats are critical to an effective response. Current algorithms for threat detection are in many cases no longer able to keep up with the numerous demands and changing environments as well as the huge amounts of spatiotemporal data that need to be processed and analyzed in order to accomplish these tasks. Uncertainty, scale, non-stationarity, noise, and heterogeneity are fundamental issues impeding progress at all phases of the pipeline that creates knowledge from data. In this research effort&nbsp; the PI has developed novel mathematical concepts and computational methods for the analysis of heterogenous, large-scale, spatiotemporal datasets.&nbsp; One concrete application is the task to group a<br />set of single-modal or multi-modal data into clusters based on some notion of similarity between the individual objects.&nbsp; Community detection is another important task in data science that is also of major important in threat<br />detection and in geo-spatial datasets.&nbsp; Among others, the PI has devised efficient and robust scalable algorithms for unsupervised and semi-supervised learning that come with provable performance guarantees that apply for data clustering and community detection. In another line of work the PI has developed new methods for data analysis onbattery-, memory-, and computing powerlimited sensors. This was accomplished by combining two recent advances in<br />data science, namely compressive sensing and deep learning. The potential impact of machine learning on society at large is expected to be huge, and this research effort will make a contribution to this impact. Data science and AI will play a key role in successfully tackling many of the grand challenges our society faces over the coming years. Some important examples include feeding the growing world population, mitigating climate change, combating environmental damage, and providing effective, affordable healthcare for everyone.&nbsp; Many of these problems will involve gathering data via distributed smart sensors<br />connected via the IoT. The outcomes of this research helps in paving the way to bring machine learning to the Internet-of-Things, and thus it has the potential in playing a useful role in adressing some of the grand challenges of our society that involve data science.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/12/2021<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Strohmer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1737943/1737943_10508521_1626112786501_compdeeplearning--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1737943/1737943_10508521_1626112786501_compdeeplearning--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Compressive Deep Learning"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1737943/1737943_10508521_1626112786501_compdeeplearning--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Compressive Deep Learning"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic depiction of compressive deep learning: Data acquisition and compression arecarried out simultaneously. Compression is achieved at the hardware level via a projection specifically tailored to the desired machine learning task. The so compressed data are thenfed into a specific task.</div> <div class="imageCredit">T.Strohmer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Strohmer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Compressive Deep Learning</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1737943/1737943_10508521_1626112609473_compdeeplearning--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1737943/1737943_10508521_1626112609473_compdeeplearning--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Compressive Deep Learning"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1737943/1737943_10508521_1626112609473_compdeeplearning--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Compressive Deep Learning"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic depiction of compressive deep learning: Data acquisition and compression arecarried out simultaneously. Compression is achieved at the hardware level via a projection specifically tailored to the desired machine learning task. The so compressed data are then fed into a specific task.</div> <div class="imageCredit">T.Strohmer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Strohmer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Compressive Deep Learning</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Early and accurate detection of unusual events and forecast of future threats are critical to an effective response. Current algorithms for threat detection are in many cases no longer able to keep up with the numerous demands and changing environments as well as the huge amounts of spatiotemporal data that need to be processed and analyzed in order to accomplish these tasks. Uncertainty, scale, non-stationarity, noise, and heterogeneity are fundamental issues impeding progress at all phases of the pipeline that creates knowledge from data. In this research effort  the PI has developed novel mathematical concepts and computational methods for the analysis of heterogenous, large-scale, spatiotemporal datasets.  One concrete application is the task to group a set of single-modal or multi-modal data into clusters based on some notion of similarity between the individual objects.  Community detection is another important task in data science that is also of major important in threat detection and in geo-spatial datasets.  Among others, the PI has devised efficient and robust scalable algorithms for unsupervised and semi-supervised learning that come with provable performance guarantees that apply for data clustering and community detection. In another line of work the PI has developed new methods for data analysis onbattery-, memory-, and computing powerlimited sensors. This was accomplished by combining two recent advances in data science, namely compressive sensing and deep learning. The potential impact of machine learning on society at large is expected to be huge, and this research effort will make a contribution to this impact. Data science and AI will play a key role in successfully tackling many of the grand challenges our society faces over the coming years. Some important examples include feeding the growing world population, mitigating climate change, combating environmental damage, and providing effective, affordable healthcare for everyone.  Many of these problems will involve gathering data via distributed smart sensors connected via the IoT. The outcomes of this research helps in paving the way to bring machine learning to the Internet-of-Things, and thus it has the potential in playing a useful role in adressing some of the grand challenges of our society that involve data science.       Last Modified: 07/12/2021       Submitted by: Thomas Strohmer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
