<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SCC-Planning: Pedestrian Safe and Secure Communities with Ambient Machine Vision</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99156.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99156</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ralph Wachter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rwachter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project with the University of North Carolina at Charlotte in cooperation with the Charlotte-Mecklenburg counties addresses community challenges of pedestrian safety and community policing, building on advances in cyber-physical systems (CPS).  As communities adopt technologies such as vision-based traffic cameras and smart traffic signs at intersections, the data from these technologies possess traces of the activity within a community of which a few might need a response because of risk to individual and public safety or suggest a local police response.  Such technologies may provide a more accurate community-wide operational picture.  With this data communities can have a better understanding of itself and within established law and custom will better serve and protect individuals and the public at large.  This planning grant will enable community planners, local government, and businesses along with technologists, urban planners and traffic engineers to explore the potential of these emerging technologies for improving the quality of life of a community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This planning grant will leverage research in CPS, big data, and urban transportation planning to provide new capabilities for community engagement. It will draw upon technologies from computer vision, machine learning, edge computing, and generally CPS and the Internet of Things. This will set the stage for designing edge computing systems for ambient vision processing at city street intersections with cooperative processing over the entire edge network in a city. The project will advance knowledge of pedestrian and driver behaviors and models, specifically in urban transportation settings. It will enable the study and characterization of driver behaviors for driver-in-the-loop traffic control system. The planned extensive community engagement will facilitate ascertaining community goals and concerns, especially regarding privacy and transportation mobility planning in future community deployment of these proposed technologies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1737586</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Srinivas</FirstName>
<LastName>Pulugurtha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Srinivas S Pulugurtha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sspulugurtha@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046871233</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000426823</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arun</FirstName>
<LastName>Ravindran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arun Ravindran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aravindr@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046878427</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000284205</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tao</FirstName>
<LastName>Han</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tao Han</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>th36@njit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9087680083</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000701987</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hamed</FirstName>
<LastName>Tabkhi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hamed Tabkhi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>htabkhiv@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046870291</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000719441</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shannon</FirstName>
<LastName>Reid</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shannon Reid</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sreid33@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046871888</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000740241</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9201 University City Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066300096</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHARLOTTE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina Charlotte]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlotte</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9201 University Blvd. Office: EP]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~99156</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This project performed extensive planning activities to bring recent advances in Artificial Intelligence (AI) to enhance the safety of our communities while maintaining the privacy of residents. It brought academic researchers,  law enforcement and communities together to design a technology solution that can widen data collection opportunities, maintain citizen privacy, and ultimately, lead to reduced crime, fewer unnecessary police-citizen interactions, and minimized tensions between law enforcement and communities.</span></p> <p><span>The performed planning activities identified and formalized technological and social challenges to enhance public safety with direct input from community residents, neighborhood leaders, and local business owners as well as the City of Charlotte and local law enforcement agencies in Charlotte-Mecklenburg and Gaston counties. Throughout this planning project, the research team has developed (1) an early version of the proposed technology for privacy-built-in pedestrian detection and tracking, (2) addressed privacy and transparency concerns by creating, formalizing and distributing Data Governance and Privacy Process, as well as Privacy Policy, (3) conducted rigorous engagement with our institutional community partners, including the City of Charlotte's Office of Sustainability, and Charlotte Mecklenburg Police Department (CMPD), (4) organized a Charlotte Regional summit based on Smart and Connected Community themes titled &ldquo;Technology and AI for Social Good&rdquo;.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Following the planning activities, this project has received full funding from the National Science Foundation (NSF) under award number&nbsp;</span><strong>1831795</strong><span>, to research and development. If successful, there will be reductions of bias-associated issues related to (racial) profiling and unnecessary conflicts between law enforcement and community residents and safer, more walkable community environments.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/05/2020<br>      Modified by: Hamed&nbsp;Tabkhi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project performed extensive planning activities to bring recent advances in Artificial Intelligence (AI) to enhance the safety of our communities while maintaining the privacy of residents. It brought academic researchers,  law enforcement and communities together to design a technology solution that can widen data collection opportunities, maintain citizen privacy, and ultimately, lead to reduced crime, fewer unnecessary police-citizen interactions, and minimized tensions between law enforcement and communities.  The performed planning activities identified and formalized technological and social challenges to enhance public safety with direct input from community residents, neighborhood leaders, and local business owners as well as the City of Charlotte and local law enforcement agencies in Charlotte-Mecklenburg and Gaston counties. Throughout this planning project, the research team has developed (1) an early version of the proposed technology for privacy-built-in pedestrian detection and tracking, (2) addressed privacy and transparency concerns by creating, formalizing and distributing Data Governance and Privacy Process, as well as Privacy Policy, (3) conducted rigorous engagement with our institutional community partners, including the City of Charlotte's Office of Sustainability, and Charlotte Mecklenburg Police Department (CMPD), (4) organized a Charlotte Regional summit based on Smart and Connected Community themes titled "Technology and AI for Social Good".   Following the planning activities, this project has received full funding from the National Science Foundation (NSF) under award number 1831795, to research and development. If successful, there will be reductions of bias-associated issues related to (racial) profiling and unnecessary conflicts between law enforcement and community residents and safer, more walkable community environments.       Last Modified: 01/05/2020       Submitted by: Hamed Tabkhi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
