<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Dynamic Real-Time Energy Management System</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is reducing energy cost in future buildings and communities, and improving grid operations. Specifically,  this project can benefit society by providing: 1) a software and hardware packaged solution for future smart buildings and communities; 2) the opportunity to save energy and money by reducing utility bills; 3) enabling technology for the next generation of proactive buildings. With the increasing penetration of distributed energy resources such as photovoltaic systems, electric vehicles, and battery energy storage systems at the individual building level, electrical load patterns becomes uncertain and variable, contributing to grid instability and energy waste. At the grid level, the introduction of renewable energy also makes the power system status more uncertain and variable, which requires more ancillary services to ensure system supply adequacy and reliability. Thus, the need for ancillary service provisions will increase substantially, and utility will require more flexible loads.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project will 1) conduct customer and user interviews and investigate the broader needs of the technology to verify product value proposition; 2) conduct analysis based on customer needs through face to face meetings with customers and users in 1); and 3) develop business plan based on customer interviews and value proposition validation. The proposed technology is an innovative hardware and software solution for buildings that includes modeling of occupancy behavior patterns, forecasting solar energy generation and building energy demand, and predictive controlling smart energy devices through the incorporation of dynamic grid signals. These innovative energy-efficient technologies show a clear application to both residential and commercial buildings in the future. Based on previous research outcomes, a software platform has been developed that demonstrated significant energy cost saving capability  in both residential and commercial buildings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/28/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1737707</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bing</FirstName>
<LastName>Dong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bing Dong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bidong@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154431293</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000639898</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/28/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at San Antonio</Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2104584340</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One UTSA Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Grants, Contracts & Ind. Agr.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800189185</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT SAN ANTONIO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Texas at San Antonio]]></Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One UTSA Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary energy consumption of buildings accounted for 40% (38.5 Quadrillion BTUs) of total energy consumption in the United States in 2014, which was greater than that attributable to either the industry (33%) or transportation (27%) sector. The building energy consumption represented a cost of approximately $416 billion in 2012 dollars. &nbsp;The proposed innovative hardware and software solutions include modeling of occupant behavior patterns, forecasting solar energy generation and building energy demand, and controlling smart home devices through the incorporation of dynamic grid signals. The goal of this project is to conduct interviews for potential customers, investigate the broader needs of the technology to verify product value proposition, and develop a business plan based on interviews.</p> <p>During this project, 102 interviews have been conducted for hotel industries, including 87 face to face and 15 phones. Specifically, 20 general managers, and 25 directors of engineering from 10 hotel owners and owners group have been interviewed. 10 managers and directors from utilities have been also interviewed. 15 potential partners including 2 are outside of U.S., and 22 green building professionals have been talked and discussed.</p> <p>In conclusion, it is found that there is a &ldquo;pull&rdquo; and &ldquo;push&rdquo; process between ownership group and corporate managers. The sale channel could be lodging associations. The influencers are hotel brand, corporate management group and hotel managers. The partner could be different software and hardware vendors. Based on analysis, the proposed product will target over 22,000 small and medium sized hotels. This will lead to 7% market share in 2023, which is around $47M sales revenue per year. &nbsp;In summary,&nbsp; more than 80% of interviewed GMs, Directors of Engineer, and Owners have strong positive feedback about the energy saving potential of our product. Hence, the final decision for this project is a &ldquo;Go&rdquo; decision.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2017<br>      Modified by: Bing&nbsp;Dong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary energy consumption of buildings accounted for 40% (38.5 Quadrillion BTUs) of total energy consumption in the United States in 2014, which was greater than that attributable to either the industry (33%) or transportation (27%) sector. The building energy consumption represented a cost of approximately $416 billion in 2012 dollars.  The proposed innovative hardware and software solutions include modeling of occupant behavior patterns, forecasting solar energy generation and building energy demand, and controlling smart home devices through the incorporation of dynamic grid signals. The goal of this project is to conduct interviews for potential customers, investigate the broader needs of the technology to verify product value proposition, and develop a business plan based on interviews.  During this project, 102 interviews have been conducted for hotel industries, including 87 face to face and 15 phones. Specifically, 20 general managers, and 25 directors of engineering from 10 hotel owners and owners group have been interviewed. 10 managers and directors from utilities have been also interviewed. 15 potential partners including 2 are outside of U.S., and 22 green building professionals have been talked and discussed.  In conclusion, it is found that there is a "pull" and "push" process between ownership group and corporate managers. The sale channel could be lodging associations. The influencers are hotel brand, corporate management group and hotel managers. The partner could be different software and hardware vendors. Based on analysis, the proposed product will target over 22,000 small and medium sized hotels. This will lead to 7% market share in 2023, which is around $47M sales revenue per year.  In summary,  more than 80% of interviewed GMs, Directors of Engineer, and Owners have strong positive feedback about the energy saving potential of our product. Hence, the final decision for this project is a "Go" decision.           Last Modified: 10/31/2017       Submitted by: Bing Dong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
