<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Leveraging Multilingualism to Support Computer Science Education through Translanguaging Pedagogies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>316000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allyson Kennedy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aykenned@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928905</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Expertise in technology is critical to our national economy and security, and is knowledge that all citizens need to meaningfully participate in our digital age. However, computer science education has failed to make progress at including women, minorities, people with disabilities, and people of low income in computing fields. In response, many states and federal agencies have joined an effort called CS for All to ensure all K-12 students have a chance to learn computer science concepts. In New York City, the city's Department of Education (DOE) has committed to rolling out computer science learning opportunities to all schools. One barrier the district faces is how best to teach computer science to students who are learning English. Using an approach called translanguaging, this project is a partnership between city educators, researchers in computer science education, and researchers in language and literacy. Translanguaging is an approach that allows teachers to tailor their teaching to whatever language skills children bring to the table. There are reasons to suspect that some of the skills multilingual kids use to learn multiple languages may also be useful in helping them learn to program computers. This project will explore whether that is the case, and will develop and test approaches for bilingual educators to incorporate computer science concepts in their teaching.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project begins a research-practice partnership between New York University, the City University of New York, and three NYC public middle schools serving predominantly low-income Latino/a students, many of whom are becoming bilingual. The project is structured around a design-based implementation research approach, which emphasizes shared problem definition, co-design between educators and researchers, field-based scaling friendly testing of interventions, and increasing capacity for partners to create sustainable change. The intellectual merit includes addressing three research questions: How, when and why do students translanguage as they learn computational thinking? How can teachers support and leverage students' translanguaging in computer science education through curricular design and adaptation approaches based on translanguaging pedagogy and literate programming practices? And, are students' translanguaging practices linked to learning processes or outcomes in computational thinking? The research methodology is a three iteration, design-based research study involving students in Science and English and Language Arts courses using primarily qualitative data sources including analysis of design narratives, classroom observation, and interviews and focus groups. The broader impacts of the project include linking research in literacy education and computer science education, which have not intersected much before; capacity building within the NYC DOE which will help guide New York City's rollout of CS for All; and creating ways to support emergent bilinguals that do not rely on fixed curricula for speakers of particular languages, but rather on professional development that helps teachers create and adapt curricula to support students whatever their language backgrounds. The project will develop a draft toolkit for teacher professional development which leverages translanguaging pedagogy for integration of computational thinking topics in the middle grades. This toolkit will be available both in NYC and nationwide.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1738645</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoadley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher Hoadley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tophe@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2129985520</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000318339</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kate</FirstName>
<LastName>Menken</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kate Menken</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kmenken@gc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128177523</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000746713</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
<LastName>Ascenzi-Moreno</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Laura Ascenzi-Moreno</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lascenzimoreno@brooklyn.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7189515000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000746714</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University]]></Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112013838</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2 MetroTech Ctr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>023Z</Code>
<Text>Computer Science for All (CS for All)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-1b812a7c-7fff-916f-4970-4dfb6a0997be"> <p dir="ltr"><span>This grant, &ldquo;Leveraging Multilingualism to Support Computer Science Education through Translanguaging Pedagogies&rdquo; funded the beginning of a research-practice partnership to support and study computer science education for bilingual learners in New York City. The partnership is called &ldquo;Participating in Literacies and Computer Science&rdquo; or PiLa-CS (</span><a href="http://pila-cs.org"><span>http://pila-cs.org</span></a><span>) and brings together researchers from NYU and CUNY in applied linguistics, bilingual education, and computer science education with the New York City Department of Education. The key intellectual merit contributions of the work undertaken in this grant was first, documenting how bilingual students use language when learning computer science in three middle schools in NYC, and second, developing proof of concept curricula that help learners leverage their diverse language backgrounds to not only learn language skills and subjects in the existing curriculum, but also to learn computer science in the context of their non-CS courses (language arts, science, math, etc.). The key broader impact of the project under this grant was supporting New York City in developing strategies to ensure their CS for All initiative would reach bilingual learners effectively, by creating and delivering new kinds of professional development for teachers to help them teach bilingual students. This is of great importance because New York City is not only the largest school system in the United States (larger than most US statewide systems) but also serves highly multilingual students, approximately 40% of whom speak languages other than English in the home.&nbsp;</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>This grant supported the development of curricula in partnership with middle school teachers in three middle schools with bilingual education programs in the Washington Heights neighborhood of New York City. Researchers studied how students used language while participating in these units, and ways in which using English, Spanish, etc. and other forms of language (like pictures, gestures, etc.) allowed them to learn to code (to write computer programs), and ways that learning to code could support learning the school subjects the units were taught in. Findings showed that specific ways of inviting students to use their whole language repertoires in conjunction with computer programming code allow the students to learn computational thinking skills, school subjects, and language. (In the academic literature, these techniques are called &ldquo;translanguaging pedagogy&rdquo;.) Although computer programming languages are not &lsquo;language&rsquo; in the traditional sense, they were still found to be helpful in supporting students to work with ideas and literacies across the curriculum, demonstrating that including computer science units in existing subjects can support, rather than compete with, other learning goals. Professional development activities supported by the grant included teacher training for hundreds of New York City teachers; development of informational videos for educators and others; support for three graduate students including one PhD dissertation on the project; and involving undergrad students in Research Experiences for Undergraduates.</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/12/2021<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;Hoadley</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This grant, "Leveraging Multilingualism to Support Computer Science Education through Translanguaging Pedagogies" funded the beginning of a research-practice partnership to support and study computer science education for bilingual learners in New York City. The partnership is called "Participating in Literacies and Computer Science" or PiLa-CS (http://pila-cs.org) and brings together researchers from NYU and CUNY in applied linguistics, bilingual education, and computer science education with the New York City Department of Education. The key intellectual merit contributions of the work undertaken in this grant was first, documenting how bilingual students use language when learning computer science in three middle schools in NYC, and second, developing proof of concept curricula that help learners leverage their diverse language backgrounds to not only learn language skills and subjects in the existing curriculum, but also to learn computer science in the context of their non-CS courses (language arts, science, math, etc.). The key broader impact of the project under this grant was supporting New York City in developing strategies to ensure their CS for All initiative would reach bilingual learners effectively, by creating and delivering new kinds of professional development for teachers to help them teach bilingual students. This is of great importance because New York City is not only the largest school system in the United States (larger than most US statewide systems) but also serves highly multilingual students, approximately 40% of whom speak languages other than English in the home.    This grant supported the development of curricula in partnership with middle school teachers in three middle schools with bilingual education programs in the Washington Heights neighborhood of New York City. Researchers studied how students used language while participating in these units, and ways in which using English, Spanish, etc. and other forms of language (like pictures, gestures, etc.) allowed them to learn to code (to write computer programs), and ways that learning to code could support learning the school subjects the units were taught in. Findings showed that specific ways of inviting students to use their whole language repertoires in conjunction with computer programming code allow the students to learn computational thinking skills, school subjects, and language. (In the academic literature, these techniques are called "translanguaging pedagogy".) Although computer programming languages are not ‘language’ in the traditional sense, they were still found to be helpful in supporting students to work with ideas and literacies across the curriculum, demonstrating that including computer science units in existing subjects can support, rather than compete with, other learning goals. Professional development activities supported by the grant included teacher training for hundreds of New York City teachers; development of informational videos for educators and others; support for three graduate students including one PhD dissertation on the project; and involving undergrad students in Research Experiences for Undergraduates.             Last Modified: 01/12/2021       Submitted by: Christopher Hoadley]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
