<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Discovery of a Novel Signal that Enhances Germination and Seedling Growth</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/14/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>419922.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>419922</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne W. Sylvester</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asylvest@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927168</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Plant hormones control how and when plants grow, and how plants react to their environment. Manipulating plant hormones with chemical and genetic tools has been instrumental in the green revolution; a deeper understanding of how hormones control plant growth will likely fuel future advances in agriculture. In this project, biological sensors will be developed to detect a recently recognized plant hormone called strigolactone, and an unknown molecule in plants (KL) that controls seed germination, seedling growth, and leaf shape. The biological sensors will be used in this project to purify KL, which may be a novel hormone, and to identify genes that produce it. Discovery of KL may lead to the development of new agrichemicals or genetic modifications that promote uniform seed germination and seedling vigor, thus increasing crop yields. Strigolactone sensors will be useful tools for plant breeders to more easily develop crops with altered strigolactone levels, which can in turn influence the fertilizer requirements of crops and their susceptibility to weeds. Undergraduate students and a postdoctoral researcher will be trained in research skills and scientific communication, leading to enhancement of the scientific workforce. Research discoveries will be communicated to the public through journal publications, press releases, news articles, and local speaking opportunities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Karrikins are compounds found in smoke that promote seed germination after fire and enhance seedling vigor. The karrikin signaling pathway is highly similar to the strigolactone signaling pathway, suggesting common ancestry. A receptor that is necessary for karrikin responses, KARRIKIN INSENSITIVE 2 (KAI2), has been identified, but karrikins are unlikely to be its native ligand. The aims of this project are to (1) develop sensitive and specific biological assays to detect the unknown KAI2 ligand (KL) and strigolactones, (2) identify genes involved in KL biosynthesis, and (3) highly purify KL from plant extracts as a stepping stone toward its identification. Biological sensors for karrikins/KL and strigolactones based on transcriptional or proteolytic responses will be engineered. These bioassays will be used in genetic screens to identify KL-deficient mutants. Finally, bioassay-guided fractionation will be used to isolate KL in small molecule extracts from plants. The discovery of KL and KL biosynthesis genes will catalyze a new field of research in plant biology that impacts the understanding of seed dormancy, seedling photomorphogenesis, and leaf development. It will also provide insights into the ancestral function of the KAI2 signaling mechanism in basal land plants, which later duplicated and evolved to mediate growth control by strigolactones.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1740560</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Nelson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David C Nelson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david.nelson@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518274397</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000607740</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research &amp; Economic Development</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[245 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627797426</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName>Riverside</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1118</Code>
<Text>PLANT FUNGAL &amp; MICROB DEV MECH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~219921</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>Karrikins are chemicals found in smoke that trigger germination of many species that grow after fire. When karrikins are applied to plants, they can also affect seedling growth, root and root hair growth, and stress tolerance. Prior work showed that the protein KAI2 is necessary for karrikin responses. A protein that is closely related to KAI2, D14, is a receptor for the plant hormone strigolactone. It is thought that KAI2 also functions as a receptor, but for an unknown signal in plants known as KAI2 ligand (KL), and that karrikins can act as a natural substitute for KL. Identification of KL will provide insights into the evolution of karrikin and strigolactone signaling pathways, and may also provide a new class of plant growth regulator that can be used to improve agricultural productivity. The primary goals of this project were to develop biological sensors that can be used to sensitively and specifically detect the presence of KL, identify genes that are involved in the production of KL in plant cells, and initiate the isolation of KL from plant extracts with the help of KL sensors.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Upon activation, KAI2 targets the protein SMAX1 for degradation. KAI2 is also degraded at a slower rate. We developed several ways to monitor the degradation of KAI2 and SMAX1 using fluorescent or luminescent proteins, creating a specific readout for chemicals that activate KAI2. These tools also enabled us to study how SMAX1 degradation occurs. We found a portion of the SMAX1 protein that mediates its degradation after karrikin perception, and another portion that mediates its physical interaction with KAI2. This latter portion is important for maintaining specific signaling relationships in karrikin and strigolactone pathways. We determined that SMAX1 is highly unstable due to an unknown turnover mechanism in addition to regulation by KAI2. KAI2 itself must localize in the nucleus to be degraded effectively. We explored KL biosynthesis through genetic screens and through evaluation of several candidate genes. The most promising mutant we identified was in the gene KUF1. Loss of this gene likely causes an increase in KL abundance as well as an increased ability to metabolize karrikin into an active signal. The proteins that are negatively regulated by KUF1 might be directly involved in KL and karrikin metabolism, and their identification will be a priority for future work. Our attempts to isolate KL with the aid of the biological sensors have not yet been successful. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>This project contributed to the development of a diverse, globally competitive STEM workforce. Five undergraduates participated in this project, of which three were supported for full-time summer research training by REU funds. The four students who have graduated so far have all gone on to post-graduate training in medical school, a PhD program in plant biology, or a Master&rsquo;s program in biotechnology, and the fifth student intends to pursue a PhD program in a biology field. Three of the students are from minority groups that are underrepresented in STEM disciplines. One graduate student and two postdoctoral scholars were also trained. One postdoctoral researcher entered a career in the biotechnology industry, and the other intends to do the same. Six of the eight project participants were women.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We developed a set of 18 vectors to aid studies of protein abundance dynamics in plants. These tools will be broadly useful to plant molecular biologists in fields beyond karrikin and strigolactone biology and have been made available to the scientific community. We published a detailed open-access protocol for the use of this system to enable its adoption.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We created mutations in the <em>D14</em> genes in <em>Nicotiana benthamiana</em>, a plant that is commonly used to transiently express and study foreign proteins. This strain will be a useful platform for the strigolactone community to study the effects of precise modifications to the D14 protein sequence and to identify new chemicals that can substitute for strigolactones. These discoveries may ultimately lead to refined control of crop architecture or novel methods to control parasitic weeds. We contributed to the analysis of the first draft genome sequence for a&nbsp; parasitic weed, <em>Striga asiatica</em>, which provides foundational knowledge useful for its control.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Project results were communicated broadly. Four peer-reviewed research articles and three review articles were published, so far garnering 57 and 236 citations, respectively. A peer-reviewed technical protocol was also published. The PI gave talks on this research at two international conferences, four professional symposia, and six department seminars at other institutions. Participants in the project gave 10 poster presentations at local and international conferences. Undergraduate education was enhanced through publication of an online book chapter on plant hormones and development of a free Teaching Tool in Plant Biology for the American Society of Plant Biologists on the topic of parasitic plants. It has been downloaded over a thousand times.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2020<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;C&nbsp;Nelson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  Karrikins are chemicals found in smoke that trigger germination of many species that grow after fire. When karrikins are applied to plants, they can also affect seedling growth, root and root hair growth, and stress tolerance. Prior work showed that the protein KAI2 is necessary for karrikin responses. A protein that is closely related to KAI2, D14, is a receptor for the plant hormone strigolactone. It is thought that KAI2 also functions as a receptor, but for an unknown signal in plants known as KAI2 ligand (KL), and that karrikins can act as a natural substitute for KL. Identification of KL will provide insights into the evolution of karrikin and strigolactone signaling pathways, and may also provide a new class of plant growth regulator that can be used to improve agricultural productivity. The primary goals of this project were to develop biological sensors that can be used to sensitively and specifically detect the presence of KL, identify genes that are involved in the production of KL in plant cells, and initiate the isolation of KL from plant extracts with the help of KL sensors.     Upon activation, KAI2 targets the protein SMAX1 for degradation. KAI2 is also degraded at a slower rate. We developed several ways to monitor the degradation of KAI2 and SMAX1 using fluorescent or luminescent proteins, creating a specific readout for chemicals that activate KAI2. These tools also enabled us to study how SMAX1 degradation occurs. We found a portion of the SMAX1 protein that mediates its degradation after karrikin perception, and another portion that mediates its physical interaction with KAI2. This latter portion is important for maintaining specific signaling relationships in karrikin and strigolactone pathways. We determined that SMAX1 is highly unstable due to an unknown turnover mechanism in addition to regulation by KAI2. KAI2 itself must localize in the nucleus to be degraded effectively. We explored KL biosynthesis through genetic screens and through evaluation of several candidate genes. The most promising mutant we identified was in the gene KUF1. Loss of this gene likely causes an increase in KL abundance as well as an increased ability to metabolize karrikin into an active signal. The proteins that are negatively regulated by KUF1 might be directly involved in KL and karrikin metabolism, and their identification will be a priority for future work. Our attempts to isolate KL with the aid of the biological sensors have not yet been successful.       Broader Impacts  This project contributed to the development of a diverse, globally competitive STEM workforce. Five undergraduates participated in this project, of which three were supported for full-time summer research training by REU funds. The four students who have graduated so far have all gone on to post-graduate training in medical school, a PhD program in plant biology, or a Master’s program in biotechnology, and the fifth student intends to pursue a PhD program in a biology field. Three of the students are from minority groups that are underrepresented in STEM disciplines. One graduate student and two postdoctoral scholars were also trained. One postdoctoral researcher entered a career in the biotechnology industry, and the other intends to do the same. Six of the eight project participants were women.     We developed a set of 18 vectors to aid studies of protein abundance dynamics in plants. These tools will be broadly useful to plant molecular biologists in fields beyond karrikin and strigolactone biology and have been made available to the scientific community. We published a detailed open-access protocol for the use of this system to enable its adoption.     We created mutations in the D14 genes in Nicotiana benthamiana, a plant that is commonly used to transiently express and study foreign proteins. This strain will be a useful platform for the strigolactone community to study the effects of precise modifications to the D14 protein sequence and to identify new chemicals that can substitute for strigolactones. These discoveries may ultimately lead to refined control of crop architecture or novel methods to control parasitic weeds. We contributed to the analysis of the first draft genome sequence for a  parasitic weed, Striga asiatica, which provides foundational knowledge useful for its control.     Project results were communicated broadly. Four peer-reviewed research articles and three review articles were published, so far garnering 57 and 236 citations, respectively. A peer-reviewed technical protocol was also published. The PI gave talks on this research at two international conferences, four professional symposia, and six department seminars at other institutions. Participants in the project gave 10 poster presentations at local and international conferences. Undergraduate education was enhanced through publication of an online book chapter on plant hormones and development of a free Teaching Tool in Plant Biology for the American Society of Plant Biologists on the topic of parasitic plants. It has been downloaded over a thousand times.          Last Modified: 07/31/2020       Submitted by: David C Nelson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
