<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference: Petrochronology 2017</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15934.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15934</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Wade</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwade@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924739</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support participants in a conference that will be convened in Seattle (WA) on October 2017 with the purpose of disseminating new knowledge and skills for the integration of petrology and geochronology. The primary audience for the conference is composed of graduate students, early-stage researchers as well as established professionals that would like to learn this new methodology. Through this type of training, early-career investigators will be able to develop future research directions that, in turn, will promote the advancement of the fields of petrology and tectonics. The conference will be held in the Washington State Convention Center, and will emphasize lecture-style presentations from experts in the discipline, and include a demonstration of data reduction software and possibly additional discussion time to identify areas of improvement of these methods. The first day will cover theory and analytical methods, and begin the systematic survey of relevant mineral systems. The second half-day will complete discussion of petrogenetically useful minerals and the presentation of useful software followed by discussion. Participants will be recruited from the broader communities interested in developing these new skills.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Petrochronology has emerged in the last 5-10 years as a preferred approach to geochronology, basically using chemistry and/or textures to integrate ages of individual crystals or crystal domains into a petrogenetic context. Examples in metamorphic systems include the use of crystal domain-specific trace element patterns or thermometers in minerals like zircon, monazite, titanite and garnet to link an age to an overall P-T-t evolution. Examples in igneous systems include resolution of crystal residence times, timing and rates of magma recharge, and rates of magma transport from zoning in quartz, olivine, feldspar, and melt (glass). Petrochronology directly benefits studies of tectonics, and metamorphic and igneous petrogenesis. It is expected that a corresponding book, published through "Reviews in Mineralogy and Geochemistry", will provide an important foundation accessible to high-level undergraduate students, graduate students, and junior professional researchers who are interested in theory and applications within this burgeoning field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1740555</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Kohn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew J Kohn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mattkohn@boisestate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2084262757</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000348582</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boise State University</Name>
<CityName>Boise</CityName>
<ZipCode>837250001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2084261574</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1910 University Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072995848</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOISE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072995848</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boise State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>837251135</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1572</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~15934</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The conference &ldquo;Petrochronology: Methods and Applications&rdquo; was held 21-22 October 2017 in Seattle. It was co-organized by Professors Matthew Kohn (Boise State Univ.), Pierre Lanari (Univ. Bern), and Martin Engi (Univ. Bern). The conference brought together 64 participants, including graduate students, early career scientists, and senior researchers, mostly from the United States, but included some participants from other countries. In addition to National Science Foundation support, sponsors included the Mineralogical Society of America, the Geochemical Society, Cameca, and ESI. Together these sponsors provided travel and housing support for all students, to encourage student participation.</p> <p>The conference followed materials presented in a new volume (v. 83) of the series Reviews in  Mineralogy and Geochemistry (RiMG) entitled Petrochronology: Methods and  Applications. This book is available to the public through the  Mineralogical Society of America.</p> <p>Presentations at the conference were grouped into 3 sections:</p> <p>1. Petrology and diffusion: The methods we use to understand the history of a rock, without recourse to direct chronologic methods</p> <p>2. Analytical methods of determining ages: Electron probe microanalysis, Laser-Ablation ICP-MS, Secondary ion mass spectrometry (ion probe), and Thermal ionization mass spectrometry.</p> <p>3. Mineral groups: Hadean zircon, rare-earth element minerals, titanite, rutile, and garnet.</p> <p>Interest in the course can perhaps be judged by the fact that  after all student registration slots had been filled, a few students  registered as professionals so that they could attend. We did add more slots of students after the course filled, and these slots were filled within a few days. We were also asked whether we would run the conference in future years.</p> <p>There were numerous supportive comments from students illustrating impact on education and outreach, for example:</p> <p>"<em>This [conference] gave me a solid background in potential analytical methods I would like to incorporate into future research. On another note, I will be giving a summary presentation to the graduate student geology club in my department so that they can also be made aware of potential methods that apply to their research."</em></p> <p><em>"<em>Not only did I learn from and interact with world experts in petrochronologic techniques, but I also gained a few insights that apply directly to the data sets I am currently working on. I am grateful to those that provided for my travel and for the [conference] itself."</em></em></p> <p><em><em>"<em>I now have vast amounts of information that I will be able to apply directly to my PhD work. &nbsp;I'm sure the Petrochronology: methods and applications volume will become somewhat of a Bible for me over the next few years!"</em></em></em></p> <p>These comments indicate that the impact of the conference was not limited to the immediate participants, but will be disseminated by attendees.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;J&nbsp;Kohn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1740555/1740555_10482635_1535398054826_Petrochronologyreportimages--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1740555/1740555_10482635_1535398054826_Petrochronologyreportimages--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Petrochronology workshop images"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1740555/1740555_10482635_1535398054826_Petrochronologyreportimages--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Petrochronology workshop images"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Top left: Cover of the Petrochornology book. Top right: breakdown of conference attendance. Center: Conference in progress. Bottom: Group photo</div> <div class="imageCredit">M Kohn</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Matthew&nbsp;J&nbsp;Kohn</div> <div class="imageTitle">Petrochronology workshop images</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The conference "Petrochronology: Methods and Applications" was held 21-22 October 2017 in Seattle. It was co-organized by Professors Matthew Kohn (Boise State Univ.), Pierre Lanari (Univ. Bern), and Martin Engi (Univ. Bern). The conference brought together 64 participants, including graduate students, early career scientists, and senior researchers, mostly from the United States, but included some participants from other countries. In addition to National Science Foundation support, sponsors included the Mineralogical Society of America, the Geochemical Society, Cameca, and ESI. Together these sponsors provided travel and housing support for all students, to encourage student participation.  The conference followed materials presented in a new volume (v. 83) of the series Reviews in  Mineralogy and Geochemistry (RiMG) entitled Petrochronology: Methods and  Applications. This book is available to the public through the  Mineralogical Society of America.  Presentations at the conference were grouped into 3 sections:  1. Petrology and diffusion: The methods we use to understand the history of a rock, without recourse to direct chronologic methods  2. Analytical methods of determining ages: Electron probe microanalysis, Laser-Ablation ICP-MS, Secondary ion mass spectrometry (ion probe), and Thermal ionization mass spectrometry.  3. Mineral groups: Hadean zircon, rare-earth element minerals, titanite, rutile, and garnet.  Interest in the course can perhaps be judged by the fact that  after all student registration slots had been filled, a few students  registered as professionals so that they could attend. We did add more slots of students after the course filled, and these slots were filled within a few days. We were also asked whether we would run the conference in future years.  There were numerous supportive comments from students illustrating impact on education and outreach, for example:  "This [conference] gave me a solid background in potential analytical methods I would like to incorporate into future research. On another note, I will be giving a summary presentation to the graduate student geology club in my department so that they can also be made aware of potential methods that apply to their research."  "Not only did I learn from and interact with world experts in petrochronologic techniques, but I also gained a few insights that apply directly to the data sets I am currently working on. I am grateful to those that provided for my travel and for the [conference] itself."  "I now have vast amounts of information that I will be able to apply directly to my PhD work.  I'm sure the Petrochronology: methods and applications volume will become somewhat of a Bible for me over the next few years!"  These comments indicate that the impact of the conference was not limited to the immediate participants, but will be disseminated by attendees.       Last Modified: 08/27/2018       Submitted by: Matthew J Kohn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
