<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: ICARUS - Index of Chamber Atmospheric Research in the United States</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>163798.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>163798</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020104</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Edgerton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sedgerto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928522</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This is a collaborative proposal to build an online, open-access, searchable, central repository for atmospheric chamber data in the United States called ICARUS (Index of Chamber Atmospheric Research in the United States).  Fundamental data obtained from chamber studies are routinely used as empirical inputs and constraints in atmospheric models. There are nine major U.S. research institutions participating in this project, including the National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR).  This sustainable web-based infrastructure for storing, sharing, and using atmospheric chamber data will synergistically facilitate atmospheric chemistry research in the U.S.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific objectives of the project are to (1) provide a searchable public index of the chamber experiments from each participating research group; (2) archive past chamber data from each participating group under their indexed chamber experiment; (3) standardize chamber data reporting formats; (4) provide a uniform template for chamber metadata; and (5) streamline future data submissions.  The data products included in ICARUS are: (A) gas phase data that describes the time-resolved profiles of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) such as gaseous hydrocarbons, oxidized VOCs, oxidants (OH, O3, NO3), NOx, SO2, and other data; (B) particle phase data that describes yields of secondary organic aerosols (SOA) as well as optical properties, composition (detailed molecular and bulk elemental ratios), and chemical functional groups; (C) supporting information such as relative humidity, temperature, and light flux; (D) the experimental notes required to understand the data (such as reaction timing, mixing procedures, seed particle addition, and so on); and (E) vapor and particulate wall deposition rates that are needed to correct chamber data.  At the end of the 3-year project, the database will be transitioned to the Data Stewardship Engineering Team at NCAR.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1740552</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Seinfeld</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John H Seinfeld</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>seinfeld@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263954635</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000167173</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Pasadena</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E. California Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>Atmospheric Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~163798</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Research conducted in environmental chambers has significantly improved our understanding of chemical and physical mechanisms in the atmosphere and provided opportunities to examine the complicated processes under precisely controlled conditions. While a great deal of valuable information has been obtained from different chamber facilities across the US, including the Caltech dual Teflon chambers, there has yet to be an infrastructure where data can be stored, shared, and used by the broader community. Previously, the results from chamber experiments could only be obtained through direct communication with the research groups that produced the results, and no public catalogue of results was available to guide the queries. Throughout this award project period, we developed a convention to report experimental data for the Caltech chamber users and carefully documented chamber and instrument characteristics to facilitate data organization and archiving. In addition, an online, open-access, searchable, central repository to store and share atmospheric chamber experimental data has also been established. The database, named the Index of Chamber Atmospheric Research in the United States (ICARUS), can promote collaboration between atmospheric researchers and facilitate the development of understanding chemical mechanisms by expanding modelers' access to atmospheric chamber data. Although these collaborative efforts are currently limited to the participating institutions in the US, they can be expanded to researchers in other countries as well. Moreover, as a sister initiative to EUROCHAMP, ICARUS will help to increase the global reach of atmospheric data sharing.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/21/2020<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;H&nbsp;Seinfeld</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Research conducted in environmental chambers has significantly improved our understanding of chemical and physical mechanisms in the atmosphere and provided opportunities to examine the complicated processes under precisely controlled conditions. While a great deal of valuable information has been obtained from different chamber facilities across the US, including the Caltech dual Teflon chambers, there has yet to be an infrastructure where data can be stored, shared, and used by the broader community. Previously, the results from chamber experiments could only be obtained through direct communication with the research groups that produced the results, and no public catalogue of results was available to guide the queries. Throughout this award project period, we developed a convention to report experimental data for the Caltech chamber users and carefully documented chamber and instrument characteristics to facilitate data organization and archiving. In addition, an online, open-access, searchable, central repository to store and share atmospheric chamber experimental data has also been established. The database, named the Index of Chamber Atmospheric Research in the United States (ICARUS), can promote collaboration between atmospheric researchers and facilitate the development of understanding chemical mechanisms by expanding modelers' access to atmospheric chamber data. Although these collaborative efforts are currently limited to the participating institutions in the US, they can be expanded to researchers in other countries as well. Moreover, as a sister initiative to EUROCHAMP, ICARUS will help to increase the global reach of atmospheric data sharing.       Last Modified: 09/21/2020       Submitted by: John H Seinfeld]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
