<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: US-Italy Collaborative Research in Advanced Manufacturing; Washington, D.C.; June 2017</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49930.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>59900</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Kramer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bkramer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925348</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides workshop support to foster collaboration between advanced manufacturing researchers in the Unites States and Italy. The advanced manufacturing landscape in both the U.S. and Italy shares many commonalities in terms of basic research portfolio, federal investments in research and infrastructural needs for next-generation manufacturing technology and process development. However, there exist limited venues through which U.S. and Italian researchers can interact to efficiently combine their complementary strengths and synergies, while minimizing significant overlap. To this end, the proposed workshop will bring together American and Italian researchers in advanced manufacturing to promote joint bilateral projects between the two countries, and make recommendations for best practices and mechanisms for efficient long-term collaborations between researchers from U.S. and Italy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop is consistent with the NSF-ERC Implementing Arrangement signed by Dr. Suresh with the European Commission in July 2012, and will be held in Washington, DC, in June 2017. About 40 American and Italian researchers in advanced manufacturing, with expertise in broad research areas and from a range of different universities / research institutions, will attend the workshop. The objectives of the workshop include: (a) examining research needs in advanced manufacturing across a broad spectrum of technologies; (b) identifying best practices and opportunities for collaboration between researchers from these two countries; (c) formulating recommendations for future joint research initiatives and funded projects; (d) providing a forum through which researchers can network and build collaborations; and (e) identifying administrative, organizational, structural and cultural challenges / barriers that impede effective collaboration between American and Italian researchers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1741722</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhijian</FirstName>
<LastName>Pei</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhijian Pei</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zjpei@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9794582334</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000303839</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dinakar</FirstName>
<LastName>Sagapuram</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dinakar Sagapuram</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dinakar@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9794582370</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000715612</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>847205572</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433136</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1468</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5920</Code>
<Text>ITALY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~59900</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award supported the workshop "US-Italy Collaborative Research in Advanced Manufacturing" at the Embassy of Italy in Washington, DC, November 29-30, 2017, and its follow-up workshop in Parma, Italy, March 28-29, 2019. These workshops brought together more than 100 American and Italian researchers in advanced manufacturing, with expertise in broad research areas and from a range of different universities/research institutions. The workshop participants specifically included manufacturing researchers who had prior experience in collaborative research between the US and Italy (or other countries) or who were interested in such collaborations (although did not have collaborative research experiences when they attended the workshops). The objectives of the workshops are to: (1) examine research needs in advanced manufacturing across a range of technologies; (2) identify best practices of collaboration between American and Italian researchers in advanced manufacturing; (3) formulate recommendations for future joint research initiatives; (4) provide a forum for researchers from the US and Italy to network and develop future collaborations; and (5) identify administrative and organizational challenges observed by researchers in both countries for collaboration between American and Italian researchers.</p> <p>At these workshops, American and Italian representatives, from government, academia, and industry, discussed their respective approach, prospective, and programs in advanced manufacturing. This led to identification of manufacturing research areas that were of interest and benefit to both nations, and suitable for collaborative research. These workshops facilitated formation of US-Italy teams to address industry-specific research needs in collaboration with Italian manufacturers. Several of these teams have submit proposals to funding agencies and some proposals are awarded.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/08/2021<br>      Modified by: Zhijian&nbsp;Pei</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award supported the workshop "US-Italy Collaborative Research in Advanced Manufacturing" at the Embassy of Italy in Washington, DC, November 29-30, 2017, and its follow-up workshop in Parma, Italy, March 28-29, 2019. These workshops brought together more than 100 American and Italian researchers in advanced manufacturing, with expertise in broad research areas and from a range of different universities/research institutions. The workshop participants specifically included manufacturing researchers who had prior experience in collaborative research between the US and Italy (or other countries) or who were interested in such collaborations (although did not have collaborative research experiences when they attended the workshops). The objectives of the workshops are to: (1) examine research needs in advanced manufacturing across a range of technologies; (2) identify best practices of collaboration between American and Italian researchers in advanced manufacturing; (3) formulate recommendations for future joint research initiatives; (4) provide a forum for researchers from the US and Italy to network and develop future collaborations; and (5) identify administrative and organizational challenges observed by researchers in both countries for collaboration between American and Italian researchers.  At these workshops, American and Italian representatives, from government, academia, and industry, discussed their respective approach, prospective, and programs in advanced manufacturing. This led to identification of manufacturing research areas that were of interest and benefit to both nations, and suitable for collaborative research. These workshops facilitated formation of US-Italy teams to address industry-specific research needs in collaboration with Italian manufacturers. Several of these teams have submit proposals to funding agencies and some proposals are awarded.       Last Modified: 06/08/2021       Submitted by: Zhijian Pei]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
