<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Travel and Attendance Grant Proposal for ISSTA/SPIN 2017</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sol Greenspan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sgreensp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927841</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant provides participant support for attendance at the International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA) and the International Symposium on Model Checking of Software (SPIN), which will be held in Santa Barbara, California, USA, on July 10-14, 2017. ISSTA and SPIN together cover verification, validation, testing, and analysis of software systems, a topic whose criticality increases with the growing complexity and distribution of software-intensive systems. This symposium is one of the top venues for researchers in this area.  The funds are to encourage mainly US-based students to attend ISSTA/SPIN. Priority will be given to students in groups typically underrepresented in ISSTA/SPIN communities, such as women, African-Americans, Native Americans, Hispanic Americans, and students from non-PhD-granting US universities.  The Symposium provides education, training and professional development of the supported participants, the building of the research community in this important area, and the exposure to senior people in the field and the international research community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1741648</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tevfik</FirstName>
<LastName>Bultan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tevfik Bultan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bultan@cs.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058933735</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000232096</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California - Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931065110</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7944</Code>
<Text>SOFTWARE ENG &amp; FORMAL METHODS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8206</Code>
<Text>Formal Methods and Verification</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~9000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA)and the International Symposium on Model Checking of Software (SPIN) washeld in Santa Barbara, California, USA, on July 10&ndash;14, 2017. ISSTA andSPIN together cover verification, validation, testing, and analysis ofsoftware systems, a topic whose criticality increases with the growingcomplexity and distribution of software-intensive systems. They aresynergistic events with SPIN focusing on formal approaches, model checkingin particular, and ISSTA having a broader scope that includes other rigorousapproaches to software testing and analysis. They are highly competitive,with a solid track record of quality submissions and excellent academicreputation. Together they attract around 150 top researchers in the fieldeach year. In 2017, they were sponsored by the Association of ComputingMachinery (ACM) Special Interest Group on Software Engineering (SIGSOFT).</p> <p>Our overall objective in this project was to increase student participation to ISSTA/SPIN2017. In allocating the Student Travel Grants, we gave priority studentswho were co-authors of a paper published in ISSTA or SPIN 2017 andstudents who were attending ISSTA 2017 doctoral symposium. We also gavepriority to students in groups typically underrepresented in ISSTA/SPINcommunities. Qualified US-based students were given priority. Studentslocated outside the US were considered, depending on availability of slotsafter selecting US-based awardees.</p> <p>We received 21 applications to ISSTA/SPIN 2017 Student Travel Grants thatcame from 5 students who were US citizens, 7 students attending US schoolsand 9 students attending international schools. We awarded 16 Student TravelGrants. The grants covered all registration and accommodation costs for 15students and only the registration cost for one attendee who was a residentof Santa Barbara.&nbsp; All recipients presented a research paper at the event.Of the 16 Student Travel Grant recipients, 6 were female students.<br />Overall, ISSTA/SPIN 2017 attracted 150 attendees that consisted ofacademic and industrial researchers and practitioners of software testing,verification and analysis. Of the 150 attendees 48 of them were students.</p> <p>By the support provided with this project, 16 graduate students were ableto attend the International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis(ISSTA) and the International Symposium on Model Checking of Software (SPIN)was held in Santa Barbara, California, USA, on July 10&ndash;14, 2017. Thesestudents were able to present their research results in front of aninternational group of leading professionals including researchers fromacademia and industry, and practitioners. Students were able to interactwith leaders in academia and industry, and exchange new ideas, problems,and experiences on how to verify, analyze and test software systems.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/23/2018<br>      Modified by: Tevfik&nbsp;Bultan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA)and the International Symposium on Model Checking of Software (SPIN) washeld in Santa Barbara, California, USA, on July 10&ndash;14, 2017. ISSTA andSPIN together cover verification, validation, testing, and analysis ofsoftware systems, a topic whose criticality increases with the growingcomplexity and distribution of software-intensive systems. They aresynergistic events with SPIN focusing on formal approaches, model checkingin particular, and ISSTA having a broader scope that includes other rigorousapproaches to software testing and analysis. They are highly competitive,with a solid track record of quality submissions and excellent academicreputation. Together they attract around 150 top researchers in the fieldeach year. In 2017, they were sponsored by the Association of ComputingMachinery (ACM) Special Interest Group on Software Engineering (SIGSOFT).  Our overall objective in this project was to increase student participation to ISSTA/SPIN2017. In allocating the Student Travel Grants, we gave priority studentswho were co-authors of a paper published in ISSTA or SPIN 2017 andstudents who were attending ISSTA 2017 doctoral symposium. We also gavepriority to students in groups typically underrepresented in ISSTA/SPINcommunities. Qualified US-based students were given priority. Studentslocated outside the US were considered, depending on availability of slotsafter selecting US-based awardees.  We received 21 applications to ISSTA/SPIN 2017 Student Travel Grants thatcame from 5 students who were US citizens, 7 students attending US schoolsand 9 students attending international schools. We awarded 16 Student TravelGrants. The grants covered all registration and accommodation costs for 15students and only the registration cost for one attendee who was a residentof Santa Barbara.  All recipients presented a research paper at the event.Of the 16 Student Travel Grant recipients, 6 were female students. Overall, ISSTA/SPIN 2017 attracted 150 attendees that consisted ofacademic and industrial researchers and practitioners of software testing,verification and analysis. Of the 150 attendees 48 of them were students.  By the support provided with this project, 16 graduate students were ableto attend the International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis(ISSTA) and the International Symposium on Model Checking of Software (SPIN)was held in Santa Barbara, California, USA, on July 10&ndash;14, 2017. Thesestudents were able to present their research results in front of aninternational group of leading professionals including researchers fromacademia and industry, and practitioners. Students were able to interactwith leaders in academia and industry, and exchange new ideas, problems,and experiences on how to verify, analyze and test software systems.       Last Modified: 03/23/2018       Submitted by: Tevfik Bultan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
