<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: The Future of Modeling and Simulation for Internal Combustion Engines</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>6519.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>6519</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Song-Charng Kong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1741545 Kokjohn&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is to partially support the workshop entitled, The Future of Modeling and Simulation for Internal Combustion Engines. The workshop will be hosted by the Engine Research Center, University of Wisconsin-Madison, June 14 to 15, 2017. Internal combustion engines will remain the primary power source for transportation in the foreseeable future. It is critical to advance the fundamental knowledge and capability to predict engine combustion performance. The objective of this workshop is to identify the future research directions in engine combustion modeling in order to help the industry meet future vehicle efficiency targets with low emissions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The transportation sector accounts for a significant portion of pollutant emissions to the environment. Throughout the world, pollutant emissions from engines are regulated by government agencies. These standards directly influence the engine design process, engine cost, and technology investment. Engine combustion is an extremely complex process, involving transient, multi-phase, chemically reacting flows. The ability to predict engine combustion performance is of great importance. This workshop will identify areas of deficiency in current modeling and simulation approaches and enable targeted efforts to address these deficiencies. The workshop will be attended by diverse stakeholders, including the industry, software companies, and academia.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1741545</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sage</FirstName>
<LastName>Kokjohn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sage L Kokjohn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kokjohn@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082631610</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000656468</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537061609</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1500 Engineering Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1407</Code>
<Text>CFS-Combustion &amp; Fire Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~6519</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">The Engine Research Center (ERC) successfully held a symposium on the &ldquo;Impact of Future </span><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">Regulations on Engine Technology&rdquo;. The symposium was held on June 14-15, 2017 in Madison, </span><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">Wisconsin. The focus of the symposium was on technology in four areas (sessions), </span><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">&lsquo;Combustion&rsquo;, &lsquo;Aftertreatment&rsquo;, &lsquo;Fuels&rsquo;, and an NSF funded workshop on &lsquo;The Future of Modeling and Simulation for Internal Combustion Engines&rsquo;. These areas address the science and technologies that the automotive and engine industries will need to implement to meet future vehicle efficiency targets with low emissions. The symposium and NSF workshop was attended by 110 registered attendees and ~20 graduate students from the Engine Research Center. The NSF workshop included five (5) speakers and a panel session. The presentations covered:</span></p> <ul> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">the role of computational tools in propulsion system development;</span><span style="color: #231f20;"> </span></li> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">approaches for moving from individual to ensemble-based internal combustion engine simulations;</span><span style="color: #231f20;"> </span></li> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">an overview of the hierarchical approach for combining measurements, applied engine CFD simulations (e.g., engineering level LES), and fundamental CFD simulations (i.e., direct numerical simulations (DNS));</span><span style="color: #231f20;"> </span></li> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">a conceptual comparison between LES (Large Eddy Simulation) and RANS (Reynolds Average Navier-Stokes);</span></li> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">high-fidelity simulations of spray injection and combustion at supercritical conditions. </span></li> </ul> <p><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">The overall outcomes and recommendations from the panel discussion were:</span></p> <ul> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">There is a need to train engineers to understand limitations of existing tools. </span></li> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">Effort is needed to improve numerics and sub-models rather than simply using existing approaches with finer and finer grids on advanced super computing resources.</span></li> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">Cross disciplinary efforts are expected to result in the largest advancements of the state of the art. Two areas that were discussed were collaborations between 1)</span><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">the mathematics and engineering communities and&nbsp;2) the </span><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">controls and combustion communities.&nbsp;</span></li> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">Current computational resource and sub-models are not yet at a level where they can be integrated into the engine calibration process. Accordingly, development of fast running models should not be neglected. </span></li> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">Several areas are of high importance include the development of&nbsp;</span> <ul> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">Eulerian &ndash; Eulerian spray models; </span></li> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">LES specific spray models/approaches with a physically-consistent treatment of the spray;</span></li> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">predictive models for cycle-to-cycle variability; </span></li> <li><span style="color: #231f20; font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">near wall models for combustion and prediction of hydrocarbon emissions.</span></li> </ul> </li> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/05/2018<br>      Modified by: Sage&nbsp;L&nbsp;Kokjohn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Engine Research Center (ERC) successfully held a symposium on the "Impact of Future Regulations on Engine Technology". The symposium was held on June 14-15, 2017 in Madison, Wisconsin. The focus of the symposium was on technology in four areas (sessions), ?Combustion?, ?Aftertreatment?, ?Fuels?, and an NSF funded workshop on ?The Future of Modeling and Simulation for Internal Combustion Engines?. These areas address the science and technologies that the automotive and engine industries will need to implement to meet future vehicle efficiency targets with low emissions. The symposium and NSF workshop was attended by 110 registered attendees and ~20 graduate students from the Engine Research Center. The NSF workshop included five (5) speakers and a panel session. The presentations covered:  the role of computational tools in propulsion system development;  approaches for moving from individual to ensemble-based internal combustion engine simulations;  an overview of the hierarchical approach for combining measurements, applied engine CFD simulations (e.g., engineering level LES), and fundamental CFD simulations (i.e., direct numerical simulations (DNS));  a conceptual comparison between LES (Large Eddy Simulation) and RANS (Reynolds Average Navier-Stokes); high-fidelity simulations of spray injection and combustion at supercritical conditions.    The overall outcomes and recommendations from the panel discussion were:  There is a need to train engineers to understand limitations of existing tools.  Effort is needed to improve numerics and sub-models rather than simply using existing approaches with finer and finer grids on advanced super computing resources. Cross disciplinary efforts are expected to result in the largest advancements of the state of the art. Two areas that were discussed were collaborations between 1) the mathematics and engineering communities and 2) the controls and combustion communities.  Current computational resource and sub-models are not yet at a level where they can be integrated into the engine calibration process. Accordingly, development of fast running models should not be neglected.  Several areas are of high importance include the development of   Eulerian &ndash; Eulerian spray models;  LES specific spray models/approaches with a physically-consistent treatment of the spray; predictive models for cycle-to-cycle variability;  near wall models for combustion and prediction of hydrocarbon emissions.          Last Modified: 01/05/2018       Submitted by: Sage L Kokjohn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
