<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>World Congress of Chemical Engineering, Barcelona 2017</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Triantafillos Mountziaris</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant is to provide travel support for US-based academic researchers to attend the 10th World Congress of Chemical Engineering (WCCE) in Barcelona, Spain, on October 1-5, 2017. The WCCE will cover the major current research topics in the field of chemical engineering with participants from over 70 countries. The conference will address global challenges with potentially significant benefits to society. It is anticipated that approximately 15 young researchers will receive partial travel support to attend this conference. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main topics of the 10th World Congress of Chemical Engineering include: Education, Unit Operations and Separation Processes, Chemical Reaction Engineering, Process Systems Engineering, Product Engineering and Advanced Materials, Applied Biotechnology, and Environmental and Sustainable Chemical Engineering. Furthermore, the unique feature of this World Congress of Chemical Engineering is that it will take place together with a number of other major meetings, including European Symposium of Computer-Aided Process Engineering, International Process Intensification Conference, International Congress on Sustainability Science and Engineering, Process Safety Symposium, European Congress of Applied Biotechnology. In addition, there will be two sessions on future international trends in education and research. The US-based conference participants supported by this grant will have the opportunity to network with leading researchers from around the world and exchange ideas about the current status and future directions in research and education. They will benefit from state-of-the-art reviews and presentations by leading experts and by debating controversial points with their peers. The meeting will also provide an opportunity for interaction and cooperation among industrial and academic researchers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1741750</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ignacio</FirstName>
<LastName>Grossmann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ignacio E Grossmann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>grossmann@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122683642</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000227253</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WQED Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133890</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1403</Code>
<Text>Proc Sys, Reac Eng &amp; Mol Therm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1417</Code>
<Text>Interfacial Engineering Progra</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>EchemS-Electrochemical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The NSF Grant <span>1741750 was used to support the participation of 15 US graduate students and faculty at the&nbsp;</span>10<sup>th</sup> World Congress of Chemical Engineering (WCCE10) which was held in Barcelona in 2017, together with the 11<sup>th</sup> European Congress (ECCE11) and the 4<sup>th</sup> European Congress of Applied Biotechnology (ECAB4). The WCCE10 was held on October 2<sup>nd</sup> &ndash; 5<sup>th</sup>, 2017, at the same time as the Spanish industrial meeting Expoquimia, in the FIRA of Barcelona, Spain. The WCCE10 was organized under the auspices of the World Chemical Engineering Council (WCEC), the European Federation of Chemical Engineering (EFCE) and the European Society of Biochemical Engineering Sciences (ESBES). The congress was hosted by the EFCE-Spain Group, formed by four Spanish societies: ANQUE, AIQS, SEQUI and AEIC.&nbsp; All the information on the congress is still available at the webpage: <a href="http://www.wcce10.com/">www.wcce10.com</a></p> <p>The theme of the congress was Chemical &amp; Biochemical Engineering in a Global World. The program was structured into two main branches:</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Chemical &amp; Biochemical Engineering Core</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Grand Challenges for 21st Century &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The Chemical &amp; Biochemical Engineering Core<strong>&nbsp;i</strong>nvolved the following six main topics:</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Unit Operation &amp; Separation Processes.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Chemical Reaction Engineering.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Process System Engineering.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Materials and Product Engineering.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Applied Biotechnology.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Environmental &amp; Sustainable Engineering.</p> <p>The Grand Challenges were classified as inter- or multi- disciplinary.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Energy.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Water.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Health &amp; Wellness.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Food &amp; Nutrition.</p> <p>In addition to the two above branches, there were a number of major Symposia in areas such as Process Systems Engineering, Process Intensification, Sustainability Science and Engineering, Process Safety Symposium, and Applied Biotechnology</p> <p>In coordination with the Fellows Council of AIChE, the PI organized together with Professors Engell from Technical University of Dortmund and Professor Arvind Varma two special sessions on future international trends in education and research, which will feature speakers from the U.S., Europe, Asia and Latin America. The details of the two sessions are the following (slides can be found in https://www.aiche.org/community/sites/fellows/events/slides-fellows-sponsored-sessions-10th-world-congress-chemical-engineering):</p> <p><strong>Session 1: Trends and Challenges in Chemical Engineering Education</strong></p> <p>Chair: Sebastian Engell, Co-chair: Ignacio Grossmann <em>Tuesday, October 3, 15:30 to 17:30.</em></p> <p>&nbsp;This session examined the evolution of chemical engineering education, and recent and future trends. An overview of the curriculum at each participating institution was given indicating recent changes in light of new areas like biotechnology, nanotechnology, sustainability and energy. The importance of promoting innovation in the curriculum was addressed to support the creation of new products and processes.&nbsp; Trends in student enrollments and hiring of new professors was&nbsp; also discussed, as well as breakdown of students pursuing industrial careers and postgraduate studies. The following speakers participated in this session.</p> <p>United States - Ignacio Grossmann, Carnegie Mellon University</p> <p>Germany - Norbert Kockmann, Technical University of Dortmund</p> <p>Spain - Rafael van Grieken, Universidad Rey Juan Carlos, Madrid</p> <p>United Kingdom -&nbsp; Marc Olivier Coppens, University College, London</p> <p>Brazil - Ofelia de Queiroz F. Araujo, Universidad Federal Rio de Janeiro</p> <p>China - Jinsong Zhao, Tsinghua University</p> <p>Korea - Jae Woo Lee, Korean Advanced Institute of Science and Technology</p> <p><strong>Session 2: Trends and Challenges in Chemical Engineering Research</strong></p> <p>Chair: Arvind Varma, Co-chair: Ignacio Grossmann&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>Tuesday, October 3, 17:30 to 19:00.</em></p> <p>This session was motivated by the grand challenges that are being faced related to human health, energy, climate change and food supply.&nbsp; Based on their grounding in the natural sciences, particularly chemistry, mathematics, physics and increasingly also biology, chemical engineers are uniquely equipped to handle these challenges.&nbsp; This session discussed the current trends and challenges in chemical engineering research, particularly in the availability of funding sources for research support, which generates new technologies and prepares students for future R&amp;D careers.&nbsp; The speakers in this session were the following:&nbsp;</p> <p>US &ndash; Arvind Varma, Purdue University</p> <p>US &ndash; Lakis Mountziaris, NSF&nbsp;</p> <p>Europe &ndash; Guy Marin, Ghent University, Belgium</p> <p>India &ndash; Devang Khakhar, IIT-Bombay</p> <p>China &ndash; Wei-Kang Yuan and Xing-Gui Zhou, East China University of Science and Technology (ECUST)</p> <p>&nbsp;The folowing 5 faculty under 35, 9 graduate students and 1 postdoc werre funded under this grant:</p> <table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" width="578"> <colgroup><col width="134"></col> <col width="218"></col> <col width="226"></col> </colgroup>  <tbody> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" width="134" height="21">Sarah   Davis</td> <td class="xl63" width="218">Auburn   University</td> <td class="xl65" width="226">Mario R. Eden</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Shubham Sharma</td> <td class="xl63">Brown University</td> <td class="xl65">Andrew Peterson</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Chao Ning</td> <td class="xl63">Cornell University</td> <td class="xl65">Fengqi You</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Feng Jiao</td> <td class="xl63">University of Delaware</td> <td class="xl64">Faculty</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Brian Pimentel</td> <td class="xl63">Georgia Tech</td> <td class="xl65">Ryan Lively</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Santiago D. Salas</td> <td class="xl63">Louisiana State University</td> <td class="xl65">Jose A. Romagnoli</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Dongxia Liu</td> <td class="xl63">University of Maryland</td> <td class="xl64">Faculty</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Shelly Peyton</td> <td class="xl63">Univ. of Massachusetts, Amherst</td> <td class="xl64">Faculty</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Amir Akbari</td> <td class="xl63">MIT</td> <td class="xl66">Paul Baron/postdoc</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Harshul Thakkar</td> <td class="xl63">Missouri University</td> <td class="xl65">Fateme Rezaei</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Andrew Radcliffe</td> <td class="xl63">Purdue University</td> <td class="xl65">Gintaras Reklaitis</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Faruque Hasan</td> <td class="xl63">Texas A&amp;M</td> <td class="xl64">Faculty</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Tamara Lozano</td> <td class="xl63">Villanova University</td> <td class="xl65">Rees Rankin</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Siwen Wang</td> <td class="xl63">Virginia Tech</td> <td class="xl65">Hongliang Xin</td> </tr> <tr height="21"> <td class="xl64" height="21">Hanjing Tian</td> <td class="xl63">West Virginia University</td> <td class="xl64">Faculty</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>They all had very positive comments about their participation at the WCCE10. They pointed out that the main value was to obtain a broader perspective of chemical engineering research and establishing contacts with international researchers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/24/2018<br>      Modified by: Ignacio&nbsp;E&nbsp;Grossmann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The NSF Grant 1741750 was used to support the participation of 15 US graduate students and faculty at the 10th World Congress of Chemical Engineering (WCCE10) which was held in Barcelona in 2017, together with the 11th European Congress (ECCE11) and the 4th European Congress of Applied Biotechnology (ECAB4). The WCCE10 was held on October 2nd &ndash; 5th, 2017, at the same time as the Spanish industrial meeting Expoquimia, in the FIRA of Barcelona, Spain. The WCCE10 was organized under the auspices of the World Chemical Engineering Council (WCEC), the European Federation of Chemical Engineering (EFCE) and the European Society of Biochemical Engineering Sciences (ESBES). The congress was hosted by the EFCE-Spain Group, formed by four Spanish societies: ANQUE, AIQS, SEQUI and AEIC.  All the information on the congress is still available at the webpage: www.wcce10.com  The theme of the congress was Chemical &amp; Biochemical Engineering in a Global World. The program was structured into two main branches:  -          Chemical &amp; Biochemical Engineering Core  -          Grand Challenges for 21st Century     The Chemical &amp; Biochemical Engineering Core involved the following six main topics:  -          Unit Operation &amp; Separation Processes.  -          Chemical Reaction Engineering.  -          Process System Engineering.  -          Materials and Product Engineering.  -          Applied Biotechnology.  -          Environmental &amp; Sustainable Engineering.  The Grand Challenges were classified as inter- or multi- disciplinary.  -          Energy.  -          Water.  -          Health &amp; Wellness.  -          Food &amp; Nutrition.  In addition to the two above branches, there were a number of major Symposia in areas such as Process Systems Engineering, Process Intensification, Sustainability Science and Engineering, Process Safety Symposium, and Applied Biotechnology  In coordination with the Fellows Council of AIChE, the PI organized together with Professors Engell from Technical University of Dortmund and Professor Arvind Varma two special sessions on future international trends in education and research, which will feature speakers from the U.S., Europe, Asia and Latin America. The details of the two sessions are the following (slides can be found in https://www.aiche.org/community/sites/fellows/events/slides-fellows-sponsored-sessions-10th-world-congress-chemical-engineering):  Session 1: Trends and Challenges in Chemical Engineering Education  Chair: Sebastian Engell, Co-chair: Ignacio Grossmann Tuesday, October 3, 15:30 to 17:30.   This session examined the evolution of chemical engineering education, and recent and future trends. An overview of the curriculum at each participating institution was given indicating recent changes in light of new areas like biotechnology, nanotechnology, sustainability and energy. The importance of promoting innovation in the curriculum was addressed to support the creation of new products and processes.  Trends in student enrollments and hiring of new professors was  also discussed, as well as breakdown of students pursuing industrial careers and postgraduate studies. The following speakers participated in this session.  United States - Ignacio Grossmann, Carnegie Mellon University  Germany - Norbert Kockmann, Technical University of Dortmund  Spain - Rafael van Grieken, Universidad Rey Juan Carlos, Madrid  United Kingdom -  Marc Olivier Coppens, University College, London  Brazil - Ofelia de Queiroz F. Araujo, Universidad Federal Rio de Janeiro  China - Jinsong Zhao, Tsinghua University  Korea - Jae Woo Lee, Korean Advanced Institute of Science and Technology  Session 2: Trends and Challenges in Chemical Engineering Research  Chair: Arvind Varma, Co-chair: Ignacio Grossmann   Tuesday, October 3, 17:30 to 19:00.  This session was motivated by the grand challenges that are being faced related to human health, energy, climate change and food supply.  Based on their grounding in the natural sciences, particularly chemistry, mathematics, physics and increasingly also biology, chemical engineers are uniquely equipped to handle these challenges.  This session discussed the current trends and challenges in chemical engineering research, particularly in the availability of funding sources for research support, which generates new technologies and prepares students for future R&amp;D careers.  The speakers in this session were the following:   US &ndash; Arvind Varma, Purdue University  US &ndash; Lakis Mountziaris, NSF   Europe &ndash; Guy Marin, Ghent University, Belgium  India &ndash; Devang Khakhar, IIT-Bombay  China &ndash; Wei-Kang Yuan and Xing-Gui Zhou, East China University of Science and Technology (ECUST)   The folowing 5 faculty under 35, 9 graduate students and 1 postdoc werre funded under this grant:         Sarah   Davis Auburn   University Mario R. Eden   Shubham Sharma Brown University Andrew Peterson   Chao Ning Cornell University Fengqi You   Feng Jiao University of Delaware Faculty   Brian Pimentel Georgia Tech Ryan Lively   Santiago D. Salas Louisiana State University Jose A. Romagnoli   Dongxia Liu University of Maryland Faculty   Shelly Peyton Univ. of Massachusetts, Amherst Faculty   Amir Akbari MIT Paul Baron/postdoc   Harshul Thakkar Missouri University Fateme Rezaei   Andrew Radcliffe Purdue University Gintaras Reklaitis   Faruque Hasan Texas A&amp;M Faculty   Tamara Lozano Villanova University Rees Rankin   Siwen Wang Virginia Tech Hongliang Xin   Hanjing Tian West Virginia University Faculty     They all had very positive comments about their participation at the WCCE10. They pointed out that the main value was to obtain a broader perspective of chemical engineering research and establishing contacts with international researchers.             Last Modified: 06/24/2018       Submitted by: Ignacio E Grossmann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
