<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID:  Time critical survey of great ape population size, health and genetics in threatened habitats</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>89494.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>89494</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This RAPID award will support a survey of wild chimpanzees living in an area that is immediately threatened by deforestation and agricultural expansion, near but outside of Gombe National Park. The demographics of this chimpanzee group, and the relationship of this group to wild chimpanzees on protected lands, are not well understood.  As part of the survey, biosamples will be non-invasively collected, so that genetic relationships and dispersal patterns can be understood in the context of habitat pressure and as comparative data for understanding hominin evolution. The project will foster international research collaborations and contribute to endangered primate conservation efforts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The chimpanzees of Gombe National Park, Tanzania, have played a central role in anthropological and biological studies, contributing to the understanding of human evolution through elucidating the similarities and differences between chimpanzees and humans, and providing fundamental insights into topics including behavior, ecology, life history, and disease ecology.  Also, a substantial chimpanzee population has persisted 10-20 km to the northeast of the park within a recently established network of village forest reserves along the Gombe-Burundi Ridge. Little is known about the extent to which these populations are currently connected. Moreover, recent surveys and satellite images show that the northern population faces immediate threats from tree cutting, farming, and other activities. The investigators will work with village forest monitors to conduct a thorough survey of these chimpanzees, procuring, before the population dwindles, fecal samples vital for future research. Non-invasive genetic and biomarker analyses will provide new insights into chimpanzee dispersal patterns, microbiome and pathogen diversity, and the speed at which anthropogenic habitat fragmentation influences population differentiation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1743506</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Pusey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne E Pusey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>anne.pusey@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196841848</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000459193</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Wilson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael L Wilson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wilso198@tc.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126251376</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000380656</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deus</FirstName>
<LastName>Mjungu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deus C Mjungu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmjungu@janegoodall.or.tz</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7036829220</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000569504</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lilian</FirstName>
<LastName>Pintea</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>PhD</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lilian Pintea</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lpintea@janegoodall.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7036829220</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000748897</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The Jane Goodall Institute</Name>
<CityName>Vienna</CityName>
<ZipCode>221822228</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7036829220</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1595 Spring Hill Road, Suite 550</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>186531687</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GOODALL, JANE INSTITUTE FOR WILDLIFE RESEARCH, EDUCATION AND CONSERVATION, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>186531687</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Jane Goodall Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Vienna</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>221822228</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1595 Spring Hill Road, Suite 550]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7338</Code>
<Text>TANZANIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~89494</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">We observed a total of 501 nests, which ranged from one day old (fresh nests) to over one year old (old nests). We directly observed chimpanzees on four occasions. They were in parties that ranged from two individuals to seven individuals. This survey thus confirmed that a population of chimpanzees persists in village forest reserves of the Gombe-Burundi ridge.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">We collected a total of 86 fecal samples, which ranged from very old to very fresh samples. Extracting genetic materials from these samples proved difficult, particularly for the old samples, which were dry and highly degraded. Nonetheless, 22 samples yielded analyzable quantities of genetic material from a minimum of seven distinct individuals. One of these individuals is a likely close relative (mother or sister) of a female that recently immigrated to Gombe, revealing a direct, recent connection between this population and Gombe. Four of the seven individuals tested positive for SIVcpz. Virus amplified from one individual is closely related to the virus infecting a female in Gombe that was first seen in Gombe in 1993, and is thus likely to have immigrated from the Gombe-Burundi Ridge population. Genetic analysis of samples from this survey thus detected both recent and historic connections between the chimpanzees of Gombe and the Gombe-Burundi Ridge population.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">The survey also found substantial evidence of anthropogenic habitat destruction, which is occurring at alarming rate, and which threatens the existence of Gombe-Burundi Ridge chimpanzees</p> <p class="Default">Long-term study of the chimpanzees of Gombe National Park has provided key data and discoveries for several related fields, including evolutionary anthropology, behavioral ecology, disease ecology, and conservation biology. Because Gombe is a small park, with a small population of chimpanzees, the long-term survival of the chimpanzee population in Gombe depends on maintaining connectivity with chimpanzee populations outside the park. This project contributed towards that long-term goal by obtaining evidence that a substantial population of chimpanzees persists in the village forest reserves 10-20 km north of Gombe. Genetic evidence indicates that females from this population have transferred to Gombe, both historically and in recent years, indicating that Gombe is not isolated, but retains connections to at least one population outside the park. By raising awareness of the existence of this population of chimpanzees, and the threats facing these chimpanzees and their habitat, this project has increased the likelihood that steps will be taken to reduce those threats. It also provides a baseline that can now be used to inform the development, implementation and evaluation of future conservation strategies and actions. Insofar as these efforts prove successful, this project will represent a step towards ensuring the long-term viability of the Gombe chimpanzees and the research in multiple fields of study that focuses on these chimpanzees.<br /><br /></p> <p>This project increased our understanding of the chimpanzees along the Gombe-Burundi Ridge, along with the challenges facing them and their habitats. This information contributed to the success of the Jane Goodall Institute?s application to the United States Agency for International Development, which funded a five-year, $20 million program called the Landscape Conservation in Western Tanzania (LCWT) initiative This program will help promote the conservation of chimpanzees and their habitats across western Tanzania, including the village forest reserves of the Gombe-Burundi Ridge. It specifically includes funding to increase monitoring effort by Village Forest Monitors in the remote and difficult to reach locations along the ridge. The program plans include conducting at least three additional surveys in the area, and the building of a field station in the area to facilitate patrols by Forest Monitors.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Deus&nbsp;C&nbsp;Mjungu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1743506/1743506_10520458_1546402896895_babychimpback--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1743506/1743506_10520458_1546402896895_babychimpback--rgov-800width.jpg" title="one of the sightings of chimps during the survey"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1743506/1743506_10520458_1546402896895_babychimpback--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="one of the sightings of chimps during the survey"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Baby chimpanzee on a tree</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ashahadu Bitata</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Deus&nbsp;C&nbsp;Mjungu</div> <div class="imageTitle">one of the sightings of chimps during the survey</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1743506/1743506_10520458_1546403592719_Old_nest_20171011--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1743506/1743506_10520458_1546403592719_Old_nest_20171011--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sighting of a old nest"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1743506/1743506_10520458_1546403592719_Old_nest_20171011--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sighting of a old nest"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">one of the nests seen during the survey. there were a total of 15 old nests in this location.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ashahadu Bitata</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Deus&nbsp;C&nbsp;Mjungu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sighting of a old nest</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1743506/1743506_10520458_1546403862086_Settlements_20171022--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1743506/1743506_10520458_1546403862086_Settlements_20171022--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Human settlements"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1743506/1743506_10520458_1546403862086_Settlements_20171022--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Human settlements"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">some of the houses which were seen with the village forest reserves.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Deus Mjungu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Deus&nbsp;C&nbsp;Mjungu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Human settlements</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[We observed a total of 501 nests, which ranged from one day old (fresh nests) to over one year old (old nests). We directly observed chimpanzees on four occasions. They were in parties that ranged from two individuals to seven individuals. This survey thus confirmed that a population of chimpanzees persists in village forest reserves of the Gombe-Burundi ridge.  We collected a total of 86 fecal samples, which ranged from very old to very fresh samples. Extracting genetic materials from these samples proved difficult, particularly for the old samples, which were dry and highly degraded. Nonetheless, 22 samples yielded analyzable quantities of genetic material from a minimum of seven distinct individuals. One of these individuals is a likely close relative (mother or sister) of a female that recently immigrated to Gombe, revealing a direct, recent connection between this population and Gombe. Four of the seven individuals tested positive for SIVcpz. Virus amplified from one individual is closely related to the virus infecting a female in Gombe that was first seen in Gombe in 1993, and is thus likely to have immigrated from the Gombe-Burundi Ridge population. Genetic analysis of samples from this survey thus detected both recent and historic connections between the chimpanzees of Gombe and the Gombe-Burundi Ridge population.  The survey also found substantial evidence of anthropogenic habitat destruction, which is occurring at alarming rate, and which threatens the existence of Gombe-Burundi Ridge chimpanzees Long-term study of the chimpanzees of Gombe National Park has provided key data and discoveries for several related fields, including evolutionary anthropology, behavioral ecology, disease ecology, and conservation biology. Because Gombe is a small park, with a small population of chimpanzees, the long-term survival of the chimpanzee population in Gombe depends on maintaining connectivity with chimpanzee populations outside the park. This project contributed towards that long-term goal by obtaining evidence that a substantial population of chimpanzees persists in the village forest reserves 10-20 km north of Gombe. Genetic evidence indicates that females from this population have transferred to Gombe, both historically and in recent years, indicating that Gombe is not isolated, but retains connections to at least one population outside the park. By raising awareness of the existence of this population of chimpanzees, and the threats facing these chimpanzees and their habitat, this project has increased the likelihood that steps will be taken to reduce those threats. It also provides a baseline that can now be used to inform the development, implementation and evaluation of future conservation strategies and actions. Insofar as these efforts prove successful, this project will represent a step towards ensuring the long-term viability of the Gombe chimpanzees and the research in multiple fields of study that focuses on these chimpanzees.    This project increased our understanding of the chimpanzees along the Gombe-Burundi Ridge, along with the challenges facing them and their habitats. This information contributed to the success of the Jane Goodall Institute?s application to the United States Agency for International Development, which funded a five-year, $20 million program called the Landscape Conservation in Western Tanzania (LCWT) initiative This program will help promote the conservation of chimpanzees and their habitats across western Tanzania, including the village forest reserves of the Gombe-Burundi Ridge. It specifically includes funding to increase monitoring effort by Village Forest Monitors in the remote and difficult to reach locations along the ridge. The program plans include conducting at least three additional surveys in the area, and the building of a field station in the area to facilitate patrols by Forest Monitors.            Last Modified: 01/01/2019       Submitted by: Deus C Mjungu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
