<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Community for Advancing Discovery Research Education (CADRE) 2018</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>985487.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>985487</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Ochsendorf</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rochsend@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922760</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project from the Community for Advancing Discovery Research in Education (CADRE) will provide assistance to Discovery Research K-12 (DRK-12) projects in areas such as research and development methods, implementation, and analysis procedures; synthesis of findings across the portfolio of projects; and national dissemination of the R&amp;D contributions of the DRK-12 program. This Design and Development project will strengthen the capacity, advance the research, and amplify the impact of DRK-12 projects and researchers working in the assessment, learning, and teaching strands. Through this effort, CADRE will advance the goals of the DRK-12 program in preK-12 formal STEM education by responding to the continuing need for communication, collaboration, and innovations among DRK-12 awardees and between awardees and the education system. The DRK-12 program seeks to significantly enhance the learning and teaching of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM)by preK-12 students and teachers through research and development of innovative resources, models and tools. Projects in the DRK-12 program build on fundamental research in STEM education and prior research and development efforts that provide theoretical and empirical justification for proposed projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CADRE's goals to strengthen the capacity, advance the research, and amplify the influence of over 300 active DRK-12 projects and associated researchers are designed to contribute to improvements in preK-12 STEM education. During this project, CADRE will continue its work in three main areas: (1) building the DRK-12 community, (2) connecting awardees in support of knowledge generation, and (3) connecting to the larger community of education research, policy, and practice. CADRE seeks to bring together (virtually and in-person) diverse audiences to contribute to and benefit from the work of DRK-12 projects, thereby further increasing engagement in evidence-based STEM education. CADRE will work to ensure that the knowledge and products produced by and with DRK-12 projects are broadly accessible to a varied group of stakeholders. CADRE will disseminate the research, models, resources, and technologies--both within the program and outside--to the broader education practitioner, research, and policymaking communities. In addition, CADRE, through its early career program, actively seeks to support next generation scholars and increase the capacity of a diverse group of researchers to participate in and contribute to improving education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1743807</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>McCulloch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine H McCulloch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cmcculloch@edc.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176182413</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000623235</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
<LastName>Busey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Ms,</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amy Busey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ABusey@edc.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128074212</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000737961</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Education Development Center</Name>
<CityName>Waltham</CityName>
<ZipCode>024538313</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176182227</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>43 Foundry Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076583830</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EDUCATION DEVELOPMENT CENTER, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>076583830</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Education Development Center, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Waltham</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024538313</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[43 Foundry St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>005Y</Code>
<Text>STEM + Computing (STEM+C) Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0417</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~985487</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="xxmsonormal">The Community for Discovery Research in Education (<a title="CADRE" href="http://cadrek12.org/">CADRE</a>), led by Education Development Center (EDC),&nbsp;is a resource network for STEM education researchers funded by the National Science Foundation's (NSF) Discovery Research PreK-12&nbsp;program. This program seeks to significantly enhance the learning and teaching of STEM (science, technology, engineering, and mathematics) and computer science by preK-12 students and teachers through research and development of STEM education innovations and approaches. CADRE has been serving the DRK-12 program and its awardees since 2008.</p> <p>During this project period (October 1, 2017-December 31, 2018), CADRE continued to address the need for collaboration among researchers, and synthesis and communication of their research to ensure that their products and research findings make their way into classrooms to improve learning and transform education. CADRE addressed this need by promoting conversations among researchers, gathering and helping to synthesize the research findings of DRK-12 projects, and highlighting and distributing their research products. CADRE also helped early career and experienced researchers to improve their capacity to advance research (e.g., managing their projects, sharing their research).&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p class="xxmsonormal"><strong>Select outcomes:</strong></p> <p class="xxmsonormal">CADRE advanced research by creating opportunities for researchers&nbsp;(1) to&nbsp;share,&nbsp;synthesize, and identify gaps in knowledge across projects; and&nbsp;(2)&nbsp;to learn about their colleagues' research approaches, methods, and findings. For example, CADRE convened over 300 awardees, NSF program officers, and guests for the 2018 DRK-12 PI Meeting. CADRE also convened topical groups that developed brief syntheses of their evidence-based recommendations for improving STEM education.</p> <p class="xxmsonormal">CADRE&nbsp;shared promising DRK-12 project approaches to and research-based resources for STEM education improvements with a broad group of education stakeholders through (1) the cadrek12.org and successfulstemeducation.org websites, (2) CADRE and STEM Smart newsletters, (3) social media, and (4) conference presentations.</p> <p class="xxmsonormal">CADRE increased early career researchers' capacity to advance their careers by leading the CADRE Fellows program. &nbsp;The program provided opportunities for 10 doctoral students from diverse backgrounds to gain exposure to NSF, network with other researchers, gain knowledge and&nbsp;skills to help advance their careers as STEM education researchers and developers (e.g., identifying funding opportunities and writing proposals),&nbsp;and learn about different work contexts and career tracks.&nbsp;In addition, CADRE offered a competitive opportunity for 10 postdocs to attend the 2018 DRK-12 PI Meeting, meet with awardees and NSF program officers, and participate in sessions.</p> <p class="xxmsonormal">CADRE developed and disseminated newsletters and resources about NSF funding opportunities, proposal writing, project management, research dissemination, and more, to increase participation in and&nbsp;potential influence and use of research by current and potential DRK-12 awardees?including those at institutions serving populations underserved in STEM fields.</p> <p class="xxmsonormal">CADRE met with other NSF resource networks and similar entities and shared information about the approaches employed that were proving effective in supporting collaboration, promoting the synthesis and use of knowledge, and contributing to workforce development at higher levels in STEM education (i.e., graduate students and beyond).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/13/2019<br>      Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;H&nbsp;Mcculloch</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The Community for Discovery Research in Education (CADRE), led by Education Development Center (EDC), is a resource network for STEM education researchers funded by the National Science Foundation's (NSF) Discovery Research PreK-12 program. This program seeks to significantly enhance the learning and teaching of STEM (science, technology, engineering, and mathematics) and computer science by preK-12 students and teachers through research and development of STEM education innovations and approaches. CADRE has been serving the DRK-12 program and its awardees since 2008.  During this project period (October 1, 2017-December 31, 2018), CADRE continued to address the need for collaboration among researchers, and synthesis and communication of their research to ensure that their products and research findings make their way into classrooms to improve learning and transform education. CADRE addressed this need by promoting conversations among researchers, gathering and helping to synthesize the research findings of DRK-12 projects, and highlighting and distributing their research products. CADRE also helped early career and experienced researchers to improve their capacity to advance research (e.g., managing their projects, sharing their research).          Select outcomes: CADRE advanced research by creating opportunities for researchers (1) to share, synthesize, and identify gaps in knowledge across projects; and (2) to learn about their colleagues' research approaches, methods, and findings. For example, CADRE convened over 300 awardees, NSF program officers, and guests for the 2018 DRK-12 PI Meeting. CADRE also convened topical groups that developed brief syntheses of their evidence-based recommendations for improving STEM education. CADRE shared promising DRK-12 project approaches to and research-based resources for STEM education improvements with a broad group of education stakeholders through (1) the cadrek12.org and successfulstemeducation.org websites, (2) CADRE and STEM Smart newsletters, (3) social media, and (4) conference presentations. CADRE increased early career researchers' capacity to advance their careers by leading the CADRE Fellows program.  The program provided opportunities for 10 doctoral students from diverse backgrounds to gain exposure to NSF, network with other researchers, gain knowledge and skills to help advance their careers as STEM education researchers and developers (e.g., identifying funding opportunities and writing proposals), and learn about different work contexts and career tracks. In addition, CADRE offered a competitive opportunity for 10 postdocs to attend the 2018 DRK-12 PI Meeting, meet with awardees and NSF program officers, and participate in sessions. CADRE developed and disseminated newsletters and resources about NSF funding opportunities, proposal writing, project management, research dissemination, and more, to increase participation in and potential influence and use of research by current and potential DRK-12 awardees?including those at institutions serving populations underserved in STEM fields. CADRE met with other NSF resource networks and similar entities and shared information about the approaches employed that were proving effective in supporting collaboration, promoting the synthesis and use of knowledge, and contributing to workforce development at higher levels in STEM education (i.e., graduate students and beyond).          Last Modified: 03/13/2019       Submitted by: Catherine H Mcculloch]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
