<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Exploring Mathematics Graduate Teaching Assistants'  Developmental Stages for Teaching</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>296258.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>296258</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Ferrara</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mferrara@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922635</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Mathematics plays a central role in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) disciplines, and student success in undergraduate mathematics courses is a crucial ingredient in meeting the Nation's need to prepare and sustain a globally competitive STEM workforce. However, mathematics courses often create barriers to student progress in obtaining degrees in STEM areas. To address this national problem, this project will focus on a research study to explore two critical issues in undergraduate mathematics education: (1) how future mathematics faculty members are prepared for teaching and (2) the format of mathematics teaching in undergraduate classrooms. These two issues are directly related to one another. How future mathematics faculty are prepared to teach mathematics is a determining factor in the quality and style of mathematics teaching in undergraduate classrooms. Unfortunately, all too often, this teaching does not have a positive impact on undergraduate students. Mathematics graduate teaching assistants (MGTAs) often receive minimal training for a career of teaching mathematics and, as a result, their teaching practices remain rooted in lecture-based instruction. Lecture-based mathematics teaching in undergraduate mathematics has been shown not to be the best form of instruction for the majority of students, indicating that there is critical need for research-based professional development programs for MGTAs. Yet, few studies have investigated MGTA needs for professional development at different points in their graduate programs. This study will fill this gap in the research by following MGTAs as they progress through their graduate programs. The findings will generate new knowledge to inform STEM departments across the country how to better prepare graduate students for teaching undergraduates, which, in turn, will lead to a better prepared United States STEM workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A fundamental goal of the project is to create a model of MGTAs' developmental stages for teaching that researchers and practitioners will be able to  use to design effective, long-term professional development programs that will result in mathematics instruction that improves student outcomes in undergraduate mathematics courses. To investigate MGTAs' developmental stages for teaching, surveys and interview protocols will be created to capture any changes in knowledge, beliefs, views of mathematics, and teaching. The surveys will have open-ended questions that inquire into MGTAs' thoughts about teaching and learning mathematics and what influences the way they think about teaching. Other items will address their epistemic beliefs and self-efficacy. An interview process will provide a deeper view of their teaching practices, their most recent teaching experiences, whether they feel that they are receiving adequate support, and what other support they feel they need. MGTAs will be surveyed and interviewed for the duration of their graduate programs to determine any changes to their views of teaching and their need of support for teaching. Their responses to the survey and interview questions will be analyzed using the stages of deductive thematic analysis. A long-term goal of this study is to use this new knowledge to design a research-based, scaffolded training program model that will attend to the stages mathematics graduate students go through as their teaching and thoughts about teaching evolve.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1744139</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Beisiegel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary D Beisiegel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mary.beisiegel@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417374933</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000665590</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0417</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~296258</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main objective of this study was to understand how mathematics graduate teaching assistants&nbsp;develop as teachers, what and how they learn about teaching, and changes in their thinking about teaching and learning longitudinally as they progress through their degree programs. We recruited 40 mathematics graduate teaching assistants from two institutions and interviewed and surveyed them for up to five years depending on whether they earned master&rsquo;s degrees or PhDs.&nbsp;</p> <p>Based on our analyses of the interviews and surveys, we found that mathematics graduate teaching assistants: (1) only receive training and mentoring for teaching during the first year of their graduate programs; (2) are rarely assigned to assist a specific course more than once; (3) do not have the opportunity to become comfortable enough with mathematical content so that they can then focus on their teaching practices; and (4) most often lecture to students rather than engage students in active learning. Thus, we recommend that graduate programs in mathematics: (1) offer explicit training and mentoring opportunities throughout the mathematics graduate teaching assistants&rsquo; programs; (2) develop course-assignment trajectories that provide mathematics graduate teaching assistants with opportunities to become comfortable with mathematical content and to think about student thinking and learning of mathematics across courses; (3) emphasize active learning and student engagement in mathematical activity in all courses offered by the department.</p> <p>A goal of this research study was to use the results to develop a multi-year training program for mathematics graduate teaching assistants, that addresses their development as teachers over time. Such a program has been developed and will be implemented and studied in three departments of mathematics beginning in 2021. This program has the potential to transform mathematics teaching at colleges and universities in ways that benefit diverse learners.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Mary&nbsp;D&nbsp;Beisiegel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main objective of this study was to understand how mathematics graduate teaching assistants develop as teachers, what and how they learn about teaching, and changes in their thinking about teaching and learning longitudinally as they progress through their degree programs. We recruited 40 mathematics graduate teaching assistants from two institutions and interviewed and surveyed them for up to five years depending on whether they earned master’s degrees or PhDs.   Based on our analyses of the interviews and surveys, we found that mathematics graduate teaching assistants: (1) only receive training and mentoring for teaching during the first year of their graduate programs; (2) are rarely assigned to assist a specific course more than once; (3) do not have the opportunity to become comfortable enough with mathematical content so that they can then focus on their teaching practices; and (4) most often lecture to students rather than engage students in active learning. Thus, we recommend that graduate programs in mathematics: (1) offer explicit training and mentoring opportunities throughout the mathematics graduate teaching assistants’ programs; (2) develop course-assignment trajectories that provide mathematics graduate teaching assistants with opportunities to become comfortable with mathematical content and to think about student thinking and learning of mathematics across courses; (3) emphasize active learning and student engagement in mathematical activity in all courses offered by the department.  A goal of this research study was to use the results to develop a multi-year training program for mathematics graduate teaching assistants, that addresses their development as teachers over time. Such a program has been developed and will be implemented and studied in three departments of mathematics beginning in 2021. This program has the potential to transform mathematics teaching at colleges and universities in ways that benefit diverse learners.          Last Modified: 12/29/2020       Submitted by: Mary D Beisiegel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
