<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF INCLUDES DDLP: SPICE (Supporting Pacific Indigenous Computing Excellence) Data Science Program for Native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mark Leddy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mleddy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924655</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of Texas at Austin's Texas Advanced Computing Center, Chaminade University of Honolulu (CUH), and the Georgia Institute of Technology will lead this NSF INCLUDES Design and Development Launch Pilot (DDLP) to establish a model for data science preparation of Native Hawaiian and Pacific Islander (NHPI) students at the high school and undergraduate levels. The project is premised on the promise of NHPI communities gaining access to, and the ability to work with, large data sets to tackle emerging problems in the Pacific. Such agency over "big data" sets that are relevant to Pacific issues, and contemporary skills in data science, analytics and visualization have the potential to be transformative for community improvement efforts. The effort has the potential to advance knowledge, instructional pedagogy and practices to improve NHPI high school and undergraduate students performance in and attraction to STEM education and careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project team will work to: 1) Increase interest and proficiency in data science and visualization among NHPI high school and undergraduate students through a summer immersion experience that bridges computation and culture; 2) Build data science capacity at an NHPI serving undergraduate institution (CUH) through creation of a certificate program; and 3) Develop and expand partnerships with other organizations with related goals working with NHPI populations.  The month-long summer training for 20 NHPI college students, and five NHPI high school students, takes place at CUH and focuses on data science, visualization, and virtual reality, including working on problem sets that require data science approaches and incorporate geographically, socially- and culturally-relevant research themes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1744526</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
<LastName>Gaither</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kelly P Gaither</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kelly@tacc.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124759418</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000356197</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rosalia</FirstName>
<LastName>Gomez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rosalia Gomez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rosie@tacc.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124716725</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000691382</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>NSF INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>029Z</Code>
<Text>Launch Pilots INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0417</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~299996</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Native Hawaiian and Pacific Islander (NHPI) underrepresentation in STEM fields, and specifically cutting-edge data science, limits self-determination, economic development and social justice goals for Pacific indigenous communities. NHPI communities are affected by poverty, health disparities, environmental degradation and erosion of traditional culture, and are broadly disenfranchised from STEM.&nbsp;For disadvantaged populations, that only recently gained basic access to science pipelines, the goalposts for effective preparation have shifted -- with data literacy being critical.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Unfortunately, the primarily undergraduate and community college institutions serving these populations are those least likely to offer data science curricula backed by high performance computing and expert faculty with a computational biology research agenda. Thus a &lsquo;big data, small school&rsquo; challenge is emerging in minority STEM education. To address this paradox, an effective inter-institutional partnership including Chaminade University of Honolulu -- CUH, &nbsp;the Texas Advanced Computing Center -- TACC, and Georgia Institute of Technology -- GIT was formed to integrate cultural norms and data science and deliver the results to NHPI students through a data science undergraduate curriculum at CUH and month-long summer immersion experiences (SIEs).</span></p> <p><span>Through the two SPICE SIEs held in-person summer 2019 and virtually summer 2020, 43 undergraduate students (90% NHPI) were introduced to data science and digital literacy in the context of applications that they were passionate about. Most of these 43 students had little to no training in computer programming and no interest in computational literacy. Following their immersion experience, over half of the students went on to pursue certificates or formal degrees in Data Science (DS) and many expressed interest in pursuing a graduate degree at the intersection of their original undergraduate degree discipline (e.g. Biology, Environmental Science, Forensic Science, etc) and DS.</span><span><span>&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><span>Both SPICE SIEs were high-contact, time-intensive experiences that resulted in relationships lasting well beyond the experiences themselves. Student outcomes, including final projects, demonstrated that working at the intersection of cultural norms and scientific principals produced highly creative products and most importantly, sparked significant student interest in pursuing additional programming in DS principals and computational literacy.&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/07/2021<br>      Modified by: Kelly&nbsp;P&nbsp;Gaither</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Native Hawaiian and Pacific Islander (NHPI) underrepresentation in STEM fields, and specifically cutting-edge data science, limits self-determination, economic development and social justice goals for Pacific indigenous communities. NHPI communities are affected by poverty, health disparities, environmental degradation and erosion of traditional culture, and are broadly disenfranchised from STEM. For disadvantaged populations, that only recently gained basic access to science pipelines, the goalposts for effective preparation have shifted -- with data literacy being critical.   Unfortunately, the primarily undergraduate and community college institutions serving these populations are those least likely to offer data science curricula backed by high performance computing and expert faculty with a computational biology research agenda. Thus a ‘big data, small school’ challenge is emerging in minority STEM education. To address this paradox, an effective inter-institutional partnership including Chaminade University of Honolulu -- CUH,  the Texas Advanced Computing Center -- TACC, and Georgia Institute of Technology -- GIT was formed to integrate cultural norms and data science and deliver the results to NHPI students through a data science undergraduate curriculum at CUH and month-long summer immersion experiences (SIEs).  Through the two SPICE SIEs held in-person summer 2019 and virtually summer 2020, 43 undergraduate students (90% NHPI) were introduced to data science and digital literacy in the context of applications that they were passionate about. Most of these 43 students had little to no training in computer programming and no interest in computational literacy. Following their immersion experience, over half of the students went on to pursue certificates or formal degrees in Data Science (DS) and many expressed interest in pursuing a graduate degree at the intersection of their original undergraduate degree discipline (e.g. Biology, Environmental Science, Forensic Science, etc) and DS.   Both SPICE SIEs were high-contact, time-intensive experiences that resulted in relationships lasting well beyond the experiences themselves. Student outcomes, including final projects, demonstrated that working at the intersection of cultural norms and scientific principals produced highly creative products and most importantly, sparked significant student interest in pursuing additional programming in DS principals and computational literacy.        Last Modified: 01/07/2021       Submitted by: Kelly P Gaither]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
