<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: Reducing Cultural Barriers to STEM for Native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders, a collaborative proposal.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>21008.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>21008</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sally O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>soconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924552</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will support a two-day workshop to be convened at Guam Community College, on July 17-18, 2017, to discuss ways to mitigate cultural barriers that challenge the full participation by Native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders (NHPI) in STEM. Participating in the workshop will be faculty and teachers from schools in the US Pacific Island territories of American Samoa, Guam, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, and the Compact-of-Free-Association countries (CoFA).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop follows the recommendations from a prior workshop, held in 2016, that discussed various barriers that prevent NHPI students from pursuing a STEM career. One of the main issues that surfaced at that workshop was the presence of strong cultural practices that could be seen as a barrier for young students to pursue a STEM career. Currently, there is an imminent risk presented by rising sea levels that have resulted in threats to homes, agriculture and continued residence in some of the islands. Therefore, there is a strong desire to grow native NH and PI talent who have the expertise to address the threats. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will result in active discussions of the issues facing NHPI, and the creation of plans to address the barriers to STEM participation. It is anticipated that when changes in the curricula and academic structure of some of the island schools are made, more students would be inclined to pursue STEM degrees. An outcome of this workshop will include a written document/report that will be made publicly available. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Increasing the number Native Hawaiian and Pacific Islanders in STEM fields will allow this group to actively engage in devising solutions to the many problems faced by the islanders due to changing climate. The proposed workshop will provide a group of faculty and staff at schools and colleges across the Pacific with potential solutions to be able to attract more talent into STEM. This project is supported by the Division of Biological Infrastructure in the NSF Directorate for Biological Sciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1744654</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonita</FirstName>
<LastName>Kerr</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Q</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonita Q Kerr</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jonita.kerr@guamcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6717971477</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000604949</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Guam Community College</Name>
<CityName>Mangilao</CityName>
<ZipCode>969130001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6717355516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One Sesame Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Guam</StateName>
<StateCode>GU</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG/>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>778900092</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GUAM COMMUNITY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Guam Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>Mangilao</CityName>
<StateCode>GU</StateCode>
<ZipCode>969131800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Sesame Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Guam</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF/>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~21008</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>For many Native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders, pursuing a degree or career in science, technology, engineering or math, the STEM fields, can be difficult to achieve. As some of the first populations to experience the effects of climate change, the lack of local capacity to plan for and deal with these effects needs to be addressed. The low numbers of Pacific Islanders in STEM fields can be attributed to the high cost of airfare, tuition and board, avoiding STEM courses due to inadequate preparation, lack of relevant science curricula, and cultural and family obligations that hinder success. Intrigued by the possibility of seeking solutions to the latter, this collaborative grant between a Principal Investigator (PI) from the Guam Community College and a PI from the University of Hawaii, funded a workshop entitled: <em>Reducing Cultural Barriers for Native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders</em>, held July 17-18, 2017, on Guam.</p> <p>The workshop included the two PIs, a professional facilitator and fifteen participants from Guam, the Commonwealth of the Northern Marianas, Pohnpei and Kosrae in the Federated States of Micronesia, the Republic of Palau, Republic of the Marshall Islands, American Samoa and Hawaii. Their occupations included secondary and post-secondary teachers, science researchers, non-governmental organization representatives, an electrical engineer, cultural practitioners, and a senator and a mayor who represented community leaders or elders. Thus, while this group was very diverse, they understood the limitations of their education systems such as poorly-trained teachers and the cost of sending children to attend school in other islands, and how pursuing an education could conflict with family, religious, and cultural obligations. Through breakout sessions and facilitated discussions the group converged on the issue that STEM curricula lacked relevance to life in the islands. Textbooks meant for students living in temperate climates do not resonate well with islanders in the tropics.</p> <p>At the conclusion of the workshop, the group agreed to form a network that would seek to address the issue of relevance. This outcome of choosing to form a network to identify and/or develop curricula that is possibly more appealing and interesting, and definitely more relevant, has the potential to increase the number of Native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders in STEM fields.</p> <p>During the months following the workshop, Humanities Gu&aring;han, a nonprofit organization,&nbsp;coordinated a summer 2018 pilot program for thirty middle-school aged students of Micronesian heritage. With assistance from Guam Nature Alliance partners, federal and local agencies, and cultural organizations, the students immersed in hands-on experiential environmental science activities for two weeks. Activities included hiking in the limestone forest and mangroves, kayaking up a river, snorkeling on a reef, visiting an ancient CHamoru village site, and learning about climate change and the lunar cycle. Whenever possible, emphasis was placed on cultural connections. The program culminated in a student sustainability conference in which the students presented community projects they had designed and executed. The projects were based on issues encountered during the immersion phase of the program. For example, one group coordinated a cleanup of a site popular with both residents and tourists, and created signs that provided historical information and promoted safe conduct in the area. The success of the program was evident in transformations observed in the students: shyness and reticence gave way to confidence and outgoing attitudes. <em>Taking Root</em> showed what could be possible with the right approach to teaching STEM topics and could be a model for similar programs in other islands.</p> <p>In October 2018, two meetings were held with workshop participants from American Samoa, Kosrae, Pohnpei and Republic of the Marshall Islands, as well as a GCC faculty member who is also a professional website developer. Discussion included the logistics of creating a website to support the network, choosing a name for the network, and introducing the <em>Taking Root </em>program as a model. Outcomes of these meetings included purchasing a subscription to <em>Wordpress, </em>a website-creating platform, as well as domain names for Oceania STEM, the name chosen by participants. A Swivl was also purchased to record and upload lessons to the website. Branding Oceania STEM involved creating a logo, motto, mission, and vision statements to guide the network. The website, <a href="https://oceaniastem.org/">https://oceaniastem.org/</a> was published and, while it is still a work in progress, Oceania STEM now has an Internet presence, as well as a Facebook page, @oceaniastem, and a Twitter account, Oceania STEM, to point visitors to the website.</p> <p>Oceania STEM aims to increase its partnerships and culturally, place-based relevant curricula to benefit both teachers and students, and thereby achieve its mission to increase Native Hawaiian and Pacific Islanders in STEM fields. As STEM education and delivery improves, entry into other fields such as health, law and civic planning could increase and further build capacity in the islands. Such outcomes would further the network's vision of achieving resilient and sustainable communities in Oceania. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/28/2019<br>      Modified by: Jonita&nbsp;Q&nbsp;Kerr</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For many Native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders, pursuing a degree or career in science, technology, engineering or math, the STEM fields, can be difficult to achieve. As some of the first populations to experience the effects of climate change, the lack of local capacity to plan for and deal with these effects needs to be addressed. The low numbers of Pacific Islanders in STEM fields can be attributed to the high cost of airfare, tuition and board, avoiding STEM courses due to inadequate preparation, lack of relevant science curricula, and cultural and family obligations that hinder success. Intrigued by the possibility of seeking solutions to the latter, this collaborative grant between a Principal Investigator (PI) from the Guam Community College and a PI from the University of Hawaii, funded a workshop entitled: Reducing Cultural Barriers for Native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders, held July 17-18, 2017, on Guam.  The workshop included the two PIs, a professional facilitator and fifteen participants from Guam, the Commonwealth of the Northern Marianas, Pohnpei and Kosrae in the Federated States of Micronesia, the Republic of Palau, Republic of the Marshall Islands, American Samoa and Hawaii. Their occupations included secondary and post-secondary teachers, science researchers, non-governmental organization representatives, an electrical engineer, cultural practitioners, and a senator and a mayor who represented community leaders or elders. Thus, while this group was very diverse, they understood the limitations of their education systems such as poorly-trained teachers and the cost of sending children to attend school in other islands, and how pursuing an education could conflict with family, religious, and cultural obligations. Through breakout sessions and facilitated discussions the group converged on the issue that STEM curricula lacked relevance to life in the islands. Textbooks meant for students living in temperate climates do not resonate well with islanders in the tropics.  At the conclusion of the workshop, the group agreed to form a network that would seek to address the issue of relevance. This outcome of choosing to form a network to identify and/or develop curricula that is possibly more appealing and interesting, and definitely more relevant, has the potential to increase the number of Native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders in STEM fields.  During the months following the workshop, Humanities Gu&aring;han, a nonprofit organization, coordinated a summer 2018 pilot program for thirty middle-school aged students of Micronesian heritage. With assistance from Guam Nature Alliance partners, federal and local agencies, and cultural organizations, the students immersed in hands-on experiential environmental science activities for two weeks. Activities included hiking in the limestone forest and mangroves, kayaking up a river, snorkeling on a reef, visiting an ancient CHamoru village site, and learning about climate change and the lunar cycle. Whenever possible, emphasis was placed on cultural connections. The program culminated in a student sustainability conference in which the students presented community projects they had designed and executed. The projects were based on issues encountered during the immersion phase of the program. For example, one group coordinated a cleanup of a site popular with both residents and tourists, and created signs that provided historical information and promoted safe conduct in the area. The success of the program was evident in transformations observed in the students: shyness and reticence gave way to confidence and outgoing attitudes. Taking Root showed what could be possible with the right approach to teaching STEM topics and could be a model for similar programs in other islands.  In October 2018, two meetings were held with workshop participants from American Samoa, Kosrae, Pohnpei and Republic of the Marshall Islands, as well as a GCC faculty member who is also a professional website developer. Discussion included the logistics of creating a website to support the network, choosing a name for the network, and introducing the Taking Root program as a model. Outcomes of these meetings included purchasing a subscription to Wordpress, a website-creating platform, as well as domain names for Oceania STEM, the name chosen by participants. A Swivl was also purchased to record and upload lessons to the website. Branding Oceania STEM involved creating a logo, motto, mission, and vision statements to guide the network. The website, https://oceaniastem.org/ was published and, while it is still a work in progress, Oceania STEM now has an Internet presence, as well as a Facebook page, @oceaniastem, and a Twitter account, Oceania STEM, to point visitors to the website.  Oceania STEM aims to increase its partnerships and culturally, place-based relevant curricula to benefit both teachers and students, and thereby achieve its mission to increase Native Hawaiian and Pacific Islanders in STEM fields. As STEM education and delivery improves, entry into other fields such as health, law and civic planning could increase and further build capacity in the islands. Such outcomes would further the network's vision of achieving resilient and sustainable communities in Oceania.               Last Modified: 10/28/2019       Submitted by: Jonita Q Kerr]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
