<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2017  Aspiring CPS PIs Meeting</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>88158.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>88158</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ralph Wachter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rwachter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cyber-physical systems (CPS) are engineered systems that are built from, and depend upon, the seamless integration of computational algorithms and physical components.  The CPS program seeks to develop the core system science needed to design and build complex CPS that people can use and with which they can interact, including some that must exhibit high-confidence or provably safe behaviors. The program also aims to foster a research community committed to advancing research and education in CPS and to transitioning applicable CPS science and technology into engineering practice.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This, the second Workshop for Aspiring PIs in Cyber-Physical Systems, is an invitation-only event, to be held 3-4 August 2017 at the National Science Foundation (NSF). The workshop will offer early-career researchers with interests in the NSF cyber-physical systems program an opportunity to engage program directors from NSF and participating agencies about the NSF CPS program, and to discuss with recent NSF CPS principal investigators about their experience in writing CPS proposals and serving on NSF CPS proposal review panels.  Anticipated benefits to CPS community include the introduction of more diverse ideas and more members. The talks and panel discussions will be captured via video, in order to disseminate the information from the workshop to a larger audience.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1744561</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frankie</FirstName>
<LastName>King</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frankie King</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>frankie.king@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153437460</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000614644</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PMB 407749 2301 Vanderbilt Place]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965717143</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004413456</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372122328</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1025 16th Avenue South, Ste 102]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~88158</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 2017 Cyber-Physical Systems (CPS) Principal Investigators&rsquo; (PI) Meeting marked the second of two such gatherings of 58 selected aspiring researchers who are interested in participating in NSF&rsquo;s CPS research program. The two-day workshop was held at NSF headquarters on August 3-4, 2017. Participation was by invitation only and was open to people with research interests in CPS who have not preciously been funded by NSF as part of the CPS program. Additionally, 42 CPS stakeholders comprising Government program directors, industry representatives, current CPS PIs, and other stakeholders were on hand to discuss new and ongoing programs in CPS research being pursued by U.S. government research sponsor agencies. This two-day forum allowed nearly 100</p> <p>The goal of the two-day workshop was to help aspiring PIs understand what NSF (and importantly, the review panels convened by NSF) will expect to see in a successful CPS proposal, and to articulate their ideas in a way that proposal reviewers can more easily understand how the proposed work will contribute to the CPS research agenda.</p> <p>The workshop attempted to address key impediments to submitting successful CPS proposals due to the competitive nature of the proposal selection process. For example, a proposal could have had a good idea, but could be considered by reviewers to be &ldquo;out of scope&rdquo; or &ldquo;not a good fit&rdquo; for the program to which it was submitted, or if does not make a clear enough case for the fit. The workshop also sought to clarify the scope of research sought by the CPS program by discussing the following topics:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Overview of the NSF Proposal review and funding process</li> <li>Developing a successful CPS proposal</li> <li>the roles of other Government agencies in supporting mission-specific aspects of the CPS solicitation, and the differences in scope between the CPS program and other CPS-related programs at the NSF such as:  <ul> <li><a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=505325&amp;org=CISE&amp;from=home" target="_blank">Smart and Autonomous Systems (S&amp;AS)</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=505364&amp;org=CISE&amp;from=home" target="_blank">Smart and Connected Communities (S&amp;CC)</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=504739&amp;org=CNS&amp;from=home" target="_blank">Smart and Connected Health (SCH)</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=504709&amp;org=CNS&amp;from=home" target="_blank">Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace (SaTC)</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=505241" target="_blank">Innovations at the Nexus of Food, Energy and Water Systems (INFEWS)</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=505277&amp;org=CNS&amp;from=home" target="_blank">Critical Resilient Interdependent Infrastructure Systems and Processes FY17 (CRISP)</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=503641&amp;org=CISE&amp;from=home" target="_blank">National Robotics Initiative 2.0: Ubiquitous Collaborative Robots (NRI-2.0)</a></li> </ul> </li> <li>Other topics included:  <ul> <li>The relationship between CPS research and Industry</li> <li>CSP career grants, testbeds, and other special grants</li> <li>The CPS review process explained</li> <li>Advice from CPS PIs and Program Directors on writing a strong CPS proposal</li> <li>Frequently made mistakes</li> <li>Collaboration and dissemination </li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>The workshop was structured as a series of informative talks and panel discussions, with time for open-ended discussions. The talks focused in part on questions submitted by the invited participants. The speakers and panelists were Program Directors from NSF and other participating Government agencies, and some currently funded CPS community members. The agenda allowed time for one-on-one discussions between aspiring PIs and program directors.</p> <p>The workshop was sponsored by the National Science Foundation through the CPS Virtual Organization at Vanderbilt University. &nbsp;Theodore P. ("Ted") Baker, a former NSF CPS Program Director and Professor Emeritus at the Florida State University, was the program chair.</p> <p>All public artifacts including the meeting program, speaker presentations, position papers, the meeting participant list, and the meeting organizers have been disseminated to communities of interest via the public website for the 2017 Aspiring CPS PI Meeting that can be found at&nbsp;<a href="https://cps-vo.org/group/aspiring-pimtg-17">https://cps-vo.org/group/aspiring-pimtg-17</a>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Frankie&nbsp;King</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 2017 Cyber-Physical Systems (CPS) Principal Investigators? (PI) Meeting marked the second of two such gatherings of 58 selected aspiring researchers who are interested in participating in NSF?s CPS research program. The two-day workshop was held at NSF headquarters on August 3-4, 2017. Participation was by invitation only and was open to people with research interests in CPS who have not preciously been funded by NSF as part of the CPS program. Additionally, 42 CPS stakeholders comprising Government program directors, industry representatives, current CPS PIs, and other stakeholders were on hand to discuss new and ongoing programs in CPS research being pursued by U.S. government research sponsor agencies. This two-day forum allowed nearly 100  The goal of the two-day workshop was to help aspiring PIs understand what NSF (and importantly, the review panels convened by NSF) will expect to see in a successful CPS proposal, and to articulate their ideas in a way that proposal reviewers can more easily understand how the proposed work will contribute to the CPS research agenda.  The workshop attempted to address key impediments to submitting successful CPS proposals due to the competitive nature of the proposal selection process. For example, a proposal could have had a good idea, but could be considered by reviewers to be "out of scope" or "not a good fit" for the program to which it was submitted, or if does not make a clear enough case for the fit. The workshop also sought to clarify the scope of research sought by the CPS program by discussing the following topics:     Overview of the NSF Proposal review and funding process Developing a successful CPS proposal the roles of other Government agencies in supporting mission-specific aspects of the CPS solicitation, and the differences in scope between the CPS program and other CPS-related programs at the NSF such as:   Smart and Autonomous Systems (S&amp;AS) Smart and Connected Communities (S&amp;CC) Smart and Connected Health (SCH), Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace (SaTC) Innovations at the Nexus of Food, Energy and Water Systems (INFEWS) Critical Resilient Interdependent Infrastructure Systems and Processes FY17 (CRISP) National Robotics Initiative 2.0: Ubiquitous Collaborative Robots (NRI-2.0)   Other topics included:   The relationship between CPS research and Industry CSP career grants, testbeds, and other special grants The CPS review process explained Advice from CPS PIs and Program Directors on writing a strong CPS proposal Frequently made mistakes Collaboration and dissemination      The workshop was structured as a series of informative talks and panel discussions, with time for open-ended discussions. The talks focused in part on questions submitted by the invited participants. The speakers and panelists were Program Directors from NSF and other participating Government agencies, and some currently funded CPS community members. The agenda allowed time for one-on-one discussions between aspiring PIs and program directors.  The workshop was sponsored by the National Science Foundation through the CPS Virtual Organization at Vanderbilt University.  Theodore P. ("Ted") Baker, a former NSF CPS Program Director and Professor Emeritus at the Florida State University, was the program chair.  All public artifacts including the meeting program, speaker presentations, position papers, the meeting participant list, and the meeting organizers have been disseminated to communities of interest via the public website for the 2017 Aspiring CPS PI Meeting that can be found at https://cps-vo.org/group/aspiring-pimtg-17.          Last Modified: 07/01/2019       Submitted by: Frankie King]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
