<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER:   SSDIM:   Leveraging Point Processes and Mean Field Games Theory for Simulating Data on Interdependent Critical Infrastructures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Walter Peacock</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wpeacock@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922634</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This EArly-concept Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER) project addresses modeling and inference problems in order to improve understanding of  interactions and interdependencies within interdependent critical infrastructures (ICIs). The key application areas are financial services, healthcare systems, communication technologies. This work will result in novel machine learning methodologies to generate data on infrastructure interdependencies. Findings will be widely disseminated in scholarly fora, with accompanying efforts in graduate-level training. Data and computer software produced in this project will be made publicly available via online data repositories. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project includes the development of new generative models and algorithms to simulate and synthesize extensive interdependent CI data for comprehensive study. This research focuses on modeling and simulation of interdependent critical infrastructure (ICI) data by leveraging point process models and mean field games (MFG) theory. In particular, multivariate Hawkes processes are used to model interactions and interdependencies of behaviors in a variety of domains. Additionally, an MFG framework is employed to capture the implicit optimization strategies that individuals perform, along with the cost functions that drive those strategies. This work addresses both mechanistic and human aspects of the ICIs, captured in point process models and their evolution. This work  advances the theory and computational methods for generative methods and algorithms for quantitative understanding and rigorous analysis of ICIs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/29/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1745382</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Duen Horng</FirstName>
<LastName>Chau</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Duen Horng Chau</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>polo@gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048944819</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000628477</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hongyuan</FirstName>
<LastName>Zha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hongyuan Zha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zha@cc.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043851491</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000490493</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/29/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaojing</FirstName>
<LastName>Ye</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaojing Ye</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xye@gsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4044136444</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000636991</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Intitute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>Q231</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This research is on the quantitative study of modeling and simulation of interdependent critical infrastructure (ICI) data by leveraging stochastic point process models and mean field games (MFG) theory. It includes both theoretical analysis and algorithmic developments of inference, simulation, and optimization of these processes based on rigorous mathematical concepts and advanced machine learning techniques. This research is motivated and has extensive applications in a number of important real-world problems on the interdependencies between ICIs, such as those between communication technologies, healthcare systems, and financial service sectors.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />Specifically, the research in this project established a rigorous mathematical foundation for ICI modeling and simulation via a unified framework integrating MFG theory and point process models, developed effective deep learning tools to parameterize high-dimensional functions used in modeling. Its results also include effective generative models to simulate data on human cognition and behavior within ICIs, and novel evaluation methods for the veracity of simulated data versus real data. A main approach developed in this project is to use multivariate Hawkes processes (MHP) model, which has proven to be particularly suitable for modeling interactions and interdependence of user behaviors, to study the viral signals (e.g., news, tweets, rumors) propagating on social networks and their impact to other critical infrastructures such as financial markets and health systems. More importantly, it also allows for control and intervention, critical for improving resiliency against disruptive processes caused by fake news and panics. Additionally, MFG theory is employed to capture the implicit optimization strategies that individuals perform, along with the reward functions that drive those strategies. The learned reward function can be used to model human motivation for certain financial decision, and the consequence interactions can be accurately estimated in the MHP framework. On the human aspect of the ICIs, this approach captures user susceptibility to neighboring influences, represented by triggering kernels point process models, and reward and value functions in MFG.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />In this project, the PIs also developed several mathematical models to accurately estimate the interactions between nodes using aggregate-state Fokker-Planck equations, temporal point processes and jump stochastic differential equations (JSDE). To predict the impact of viral signals, the aggregate-state Fokker-Planck equation provides a concise and computationally tractable approach to estimate the influence, defined by the expected number of affected nodes, at any given time. This approach dramatically reduces the computation complexity of exponential order in network size in the traditional Markov approach to a linear order at the cost a slight error from the exact solution. The dependency of this error on the transmission rates between nodes and network structure is derived, which shows that the error can be properly controlled. The JSDE approach yields an exact formulation of the random propagation, based on which an efficient sampling-based influence estimation algorithm is developed. Compared to the naive Monte Carlo sampling and previous mean-field approximation approaches, the JSDE-based estimation is highly accurate yet only requires low sampling complexity. More importantly, the JSDE approach inspired a novel, fast, and accurate influence prediction method based on deep residual neural network, which is a main part of the continuing research of this project.&nbsp;<br />In summary, the results produced in this project include novel theory and computational methods for generative methods and algorithms, with main applications in the understanding and quantitative analysis of ICIs. The point generative methods based on MFGs and deep learning techniques can be used to model the mechanism behind events and processes, and real-world data can be fed into these models to learn a statistical and generative representation of phenomenon. The output of the project also includes effective and adaptive generative algorithms, which can be used to produce simulated Internet and financial data, and to generate virtually unlimited synthetic data with matching statistics and properties for a variety of use cases. The results will advance our understanding and improve performance of ICIs.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />During the funding period of this project, the PIs have supervised three PhD students including one female student at Georgia State University, who have gained substantial experiences in mean field games, reinforcement learning, and deep learning for future career development in these fields. The results of this project have disseminated as more than 15 research papers published in a number of leading machine learning and computational mathematics conferences and journals. Data and computer software produced in this project have also been made publicly available via online data repositories, with links provided in the corresponding research papers.<br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/05/2020<br>      Modified by: Duen Horng&nbsp;Chau</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research is on the quantitative study of modeling and simulation of interdependent critical infrastructure (ICI) data by leveraging stochastic point process models and mean field games (MFG) theory. It includes both theoretical analysis and algorithmic developments of inference, simulation, and optimization of these processes based on rigorous mathematical concepts and advanced machine learning techniques. This research is motivated and has extensive applications in a number of important real-world problems on the interdependencies between ICIs, such as those between communication technologies, healthcare systems, and financial service sectors.    Specifically, the research in this project established a rigorous mathematical foundation for ICI modeling and simulation via a unified framework integrating MFG theory and point process models, developed effective deep learning tools to parameterize high-dimensional functions used in modeling. Its results also include effective generative models to simulate data on human cognition and behavior within ICIs, and novel evaluation methods for the veracity of simulated data versus real data. A main approach developed in this project is to use multivariate Hawkes processes (MHP) model, which has proven to be particularly suitable for modeling interactions and interdependence of user behaviors, to study the viral signals (e.g., news, tweets, rumors) propagating on social networks and their impact to other critical infrastructures such as financial markets and health systems. More importantly, it also allows for control and intervention, critical for improving resiliency against disruptive processes caused by fake news and panics. Additionally, MFG theory is employed to capture the implicit optimization strategies that individuals perform, along with the reward functions that drive those strategies. The learned reward function can be used to model human motivation for certain financial decision, and the consequence interactions can be accurately estimated in the MHP framework. On the human aspect of the ICIs, this approach captures user susceptibility to neighboring influences, represented by triggering kernels point process models, and reward and value functions in MFG.    In this project, the PIs also developed several mathematical models to accurately estimate the interactions between nodes using aggregate-state Fokker-Planck equations, temporal point processes and jump stochastic differential equations (JSDE). To predict the impact of viral signals, the aggregate-state Fokker-Planck equation provides a concise and computationally tractable approach to estimate the influence, defined by the expected number of affected nodes, at any given time. This approach dramatically reduces the computation complexity of exponential order in network size in the traditional Markov approach to a linear order at the cost a slight error from the exact solution. The dependency of this error on the transmission rates between nodes and network structure is derived, which shows that the error can be properly controlled. The JSDE approach yields an exact formulation of the random propagation, based on which an efficient sampling-based influence estimation algorithm is developed. Compared to the naive Monte Carlo sampling and previous mean-field approximation approaches, the JSDE-based estimation is highly accurate yet only requires low sampling complexity. More importantly, the JSDE approach inspired a novel, fast, and accurate influence prediction method based on deep residual neural network, which is a main part of the continuing research of this project.  In summary, the results produced in this project include novel theory and computational methods for generative methods and algorithms, with main applications in the understanding and quantitative analysis of ICIs. The point generative methods based on MFGs and deep learning techniques can be used to model the mechanism behind events and processes, and real-world data can be fed into these models to learn a statistical and generative representation of phenomenon. The output of the project also includes effective and adaptive generative algorithms, which can be used to produce simulated Internet and financial data, and to generate virtually unlimited synthetic data with matching statistics and properties for a variety of use cases. The results will advance our understanding and improve performance of ICIs.    During the funding period of this project, the PIs have supervised three PhD students including one female student at Georgia State University, who have gained substantial experiences in mean field games, reinforcement learning, and deep learning for future career development in these fields. The results of this project have disseminated as more than 15 research papers published in a number of leading machine learning and computational mathematics conferences and journals. Data and computer software produced in this project have also been made publicly available via online data repositories, with links provided in the corresponding research papers.         Last Modified: 10/05/2020       Submitted by: Duen Horng Chau]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
