<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Stochastic Vestibular Stimulation Wearable</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Kamei</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to increase the applications of wearable sensory modality (vision, vestibular, and/or proprioception) specific devices to encourage mobility and optimize movement for patients suffering from increased disequilibrium symptoms, such as vertigo or dizziness, and other fall risk comorbidity factors. This project will potentially enhance the delivery of rehabilitative care by clinical providers to their patients by simultaneously improving their patients' health outcomes and quantitatively demonstrating value in their treatment plans. Similarly, by serving as a channel to implement balance interventions to mitigate the high rates of falls among older adults, this project will support efforts by health care providers, senior advocacy groups, and hospital facility administrators to reduce the associated treatment costs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project enables the ameliorating effects of low random vestibular stimulation on balance coordination during stance and locomotion to be extended during an individual's daily routine in a non-research or clinical setting. The basis for the technique is a wearable device capable of delivering low electrical currents non-invasively to the individual's vestibular system through the mastoids. Sensory reweighting and integration are paramount to sustaining balance control in dynamic environments and deficits in those processes are frequently associated with balance impairments during gait and stance. Therefore, by leveraging the apparent postural responses induced in an individual, the technology has the potential to support a variety of motor adaption or retraining paradigms for balancing training and fall prevention.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1745513</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carole</FirstName>
<LastName>Tucker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carole Tucker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tuckerc@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2157074877</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000701802</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Agada</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Agada</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tuf30575@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000749738</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191223302</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Adults with impairments in their vestibular system often report levels of vertigo and dizziness that restrict their activities of daily living and participation in life roles, as well as reduce their quality of life. We have developed a wearable sensory-modulating device, fashioned as a pair of eyeglasses, that provides a specific form of electrical stimulation (i.e. stochastic) to the area behind the ears that enhances vestibular function. According to estimates, there were approximately 10 million individuals in the United States dealing with vestibular issues on a daily basis and as such, it was a problem that mandated a solution that our device could potentially address.</p> <p>The major objective of our project was to demonstrate the commercial viability of our wearable stochastic device, to create a commercialization plan for the technology, and expand on the necessary activities, resources, and partnerships required to navigate the FDA regulatory process and deliver the product in a profitable and sustainable manner. In this project, we conducted interviews with a total of 161 customers, potential end-users and/or buyers of our stochastic wearable technology, focused on discovering the alignment of their needs and our technologies offerings. Our plan was further enhanced with information gathered from an additional 61 key opinion leaders (e.g. neurologists, primary doctors, and other healthcare providers), Our interviews focused on gaining insights into market factors and other commercialization issues that would influence the profitability and sustainability of a business venture based around the technology. Our specific objective in conducting these interviews with potential end users or buyers was to create an archetype or psychographic segmentation map; to develop an understanding about market forces in the likely industry; to develop a positioning thesis for a product based on our stochastic wearable technology; and finally to uncover how an organization could be built to repeatably and on a larger scale deliver the product to our target customers in a sustainable manner.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Our end-user interviews confirmed that if a product was available and capable of reducing the severity of the debilitation the comes from their vestibular disorder, they would be willing to pay out of pocket to have access to that solution if required. Based on our interviews with key opinion experts and medical device vendors, we believe that a product based on our technology will be part of the neuromodulation or stimulation device market. Interview respondents did confirm that the device would most likely be a Class 2 medical device requiring FDA approval for sale in the United States. Additional information gleaned from interviews confirmed that there moderate competition in this market due to similar offerings from other transcranial stimulation vendors. However, a strong strategic advantage could be accessed through "focused" specialization around the vestibular system and balance impairment provided that the associated intellectual property rights were exclusively held by the company.&nbsp; A key outcome of the interviews was that the device would better be aligned to patient needs if it served a therapeutic need rather than solely a rehabilitative need. In order to sustain a business focused on delivering the wearable stochastic technology to the end-users, we learned that we would need to secure key partnerships with the vestibular patient advocacy groups and medical device engineering firms. Partnerships in this space would be essential because they both facilitate the customer acquisition and relationship processes and would enable the subsequent increase in production and manufacturing scale that would be required to capture a larger market share.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Carole&nbsp;Tucker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Adults with impairments in their vestibular system often report levels of vertigo and dizziness that restrict their activities of daily living and participation in life roles, as well as reduce their quality of life. We have developed a wearable sensory-modulating device, fashioned as a pair of eyeglasses, that provides a specific form of electrical stimulation (i.e. stochastic) to the area behind the ears that enhances vestibular function. According to estimates, there were approximately 10 million individuals in the United States dealing with vestibular issues on a daily basis and as such, it was a problem that mandated a solution that our device could potentially address.  The major objective of our project was to demonstrate the commercial viability of our wearable stochastic device, to create a commercialization plan for the technology, and expand on the necessary activities, resources, and partnerships required to navigate the FDA regulatory process and deliver the product in a profitable and sustainable manner. In this project, we conducted interviews with a total of 161 customers, potential end-users and/or buyers of our stochastic wearable technology, focused on discovering the alignment of their needs and our technologies offerings. Our plan was further enhanced with information gathered from an additional 61 key opinion leaders (e.g. neurologists, primary doctors, and other healthcare providers), Our interviews focused on gaining insights into market factors and other commercialization issues that would influence the profitability and sustainability of a business venture based around the technology. Our specific objective in conducting these interviews with potential end users or buyers was to create an archetype or psychographic segmentation map; to develop an understanding about market forces in the likely industry; to develop a positioning thesis for a product based on our stochastic wearable technology; and finally to uncover how an organization could be built to repeatably and on a larger scale deliver the product to our target customers in a sustainable manner.    Our end-user interviews confirmed that if a product was available and capable of reducing the severity of the debilitation the comes from their vestibular disorder, they would be willing to pay out of pocket to have access to that solution if required. Based on our interviews with key opinion experts and medical device vendors, we believe that a product based on our technology will be part of the neuromodulation or stimulation device market. Interview respondents did confirm that the device would most likely be a Class 2 medical device requiring FDA approval for sale in the United States. Additional information gleaned from interviews confirmed that there moderate competition in this market due to similar offerings from other transcranial stimulation vendors. However, a strong strategic advantage could be accessed through "focused" specialization around the vestibular system and balance impairment provided that the associated intellectual property rights were exclusively held by the company.  A key outcome of the interviews was that the device would better be aligned to patient needs if it served a therapeutic need rather than solely a rehabilitative need. In order to sustain a business focused on delivering the wearable stochastic technology to the end-users, we learned that we would need to secure key partnerships with the vestibular patient advocacy groups and medical device engineering firms. Partnerships in this space would be essential because they both facilitate the customer acquisition and relationship processes and would enable the subsequent increase in production and manufacturing scale that would be required to capture a larger market share.          Last Modified: 01/30/2019       Submitted by: Carole Tucker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
