<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the 25th IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Darleen Fisher</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlfisher@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ICNP 2017, the 25th annual edition of the IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols, is a conference covering all aspects of network protocols, including design, analysis, specification, verification, implementation, and performance. This award supports partial travel costs for graduate students enrolled in United States academic institutions to attend the conference. Depending on fund availability, postdoctoral researchers and faculty members from underrepresented groups that are employed in US institutions will also be considered for travel support. ICNP 2017 will be held in Toronto, Canada, from October 10th to 13th, 2017. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This travel grant aims to broaden ICNP participation by lowering the financial barrier of attendance for graduate students and postdoctoral researchers at institutions in the Unites States. Enabling students and postdocs to attend a high-quality conference at an early stage of a researcher's academic career is a wise investment in the future of the field. Providing opportunities for attendance to underrepresented students in particular will result in a greater diversity of ideas that will be discussed during the conference. One goal of this award is to encourage women and minorities to participate in a high-quality research event. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research in network protocols is advanced by the interactions of participants at conferences such as ICNP. The travel support will have a significant impact in at least three ways. First, graduate students who would have been unable otherwise to attend ICNP will be greatly benefited by listening to the speaker's talks and participating in resulting discussions. Second, even the ICNP participants that will not receive the grant will be indirectly benefited by the presence of the grant recipients. Since the award committee will make an effort to select a diverse group of students, the demographics of the conference will become more diverse as well. Finally, the research community as a whole will be positively impacted by the continuing success of the ICNP. The participation of scholars at early stages of their careers, some of which come from underrepresented groups, will advance training and the quality of the next generation of research leaders in the field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1745518</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Despoina</FirstName>
<LastName>Perouli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Despoina Perouli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>despoina.perouli@marquette.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4142883889</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000727026</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Marquette University</Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<ZipCode>532011881</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4142887200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 1881</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046929621</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MARQUETTE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006439962</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Marquette University]]></Name>
<CityName>Magnificent Mile</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>532011881</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 1881]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP) is one of the top conferences on the field of digital communications. In 2017, the 25th annual ICNP conference took place in Toronto, Canada, from October 10th to 13th. The project's major goal was to broaden the participation of graduate students studying in U.S. universities to the conference. This created a major professional development opportunity for the students, while it contributed to the conference's high quality and diversity.</p> <p>A student application for travel support consisted of three documents: a) student's vita, b) student's letter and c) advisor's letter. Both letters explain how the student's participation in ICNP would positively impact the student's research work and career. The student letter also highlighted any achievements (such as coursework and projects) that demonstrated the student?s knowledge and interest in topics related to ICNP. Four of the awarded students were authors of papers presented in ICNP 2017, while one student had submitted a research paper that was rejected. Applications were accepted from all students enrolled in US academic institutions, including those on student visas (F-1, J-1, etc.). The advisor's letter confirmed that the student was a PhD candidate in good standing and comment on the student?s academic accomplishments.</p> <p>The applications were reviewed by a committee that included the PI. A total of 18 students were selected to be partially supported. A significant number of them ended up refusing the award due to reported problems to receive a travel visa on time. Out of the 10 students that ended up receiving financial support, 3 of them were minority female students.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/12/2019<br>      Modified by: Despoina&nbsp;Perouli</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP) is one of the top conferences on the field of digital communications. In 2017, the 25th annual ICNP conference took place in Toronto, Canada, from October 10th to 13th. The project's major goal was to broaden the participation of graduate students studying in U.S. universities to the conference. This created a major professional development opportunity for the students, while it contributed to the conference's high quality and diversity.  A student application for travel support consisted of three documents: a) student's vita, b) student's letter and c) advisor's letter. Both letters explain how the student's participation in ICNP would positively impact the student's research work and career. The student letter also highlighted any achievements (such as coursework and projects) that demonstrated the student?s knowledge and interest in topics related to ICNP. Four of the awarded students were authors of papers presented in ICNP 2017, while one student had submitted a research paper that was rejected. Applications were accepted from all students enrolled in US academic institutions, including those on student visas (F-1, J-1, etc.). The advisor's letter confirmed that the student was a PhD candidate in good standing and comment on the student?s academic accomplishments.  The applications were reviewed by a committee that included the PI. A total of 18 students were selected to be partially supported. A significant number of them ended up refusing the award due to reported problems to receive a travel visa on time. Out of the 10 students that ended up receiving financial support, 3 of them were minority female students.       Last Modified: 04/12/2019       Submitted by: Despoina Perouli]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
