<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Reactive Polyolefins (x-PAOs) as Advanced Organic Phase Change Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project seeks to reduce the cost and complexity of incorporating energy-saving phase change materials (PCMs) into end-use products by developing a new class of form-stable PCM-modified resins that contain a unique reactive-polyolefin component. Importantly, the development of new PCMs for the passive thermal regulation of electric vehicle (EV) batteries has the potential to increase EV safety, range, and affordability, representing an addressable market currently valued at $87m and that is growing at 20% per year. Validation of these advantages should significantly benefit society by increasing electric vehicle performance and reducing the frequency of expensive battery replacement, thus increasing the adoption of energy efficient vehicles and reducing green-house gas emissions. This project can also result in an increase in the penetration of energy efficient PCM technology in additional markets worth a combined $370m, including building materials, textiles, electronics, and packaging, which can have a large positive economic impact on society. Finally, successful realization of the goals of this SBIR Phase I program will further enable scientific / technological understanding of PCMs that are based on organic materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is the validation of a new paradigm for a bottoms-up approach to the design, production, and optimization of structurally-well-characterized reactive polyolefins of tunable molecular weight and narrow polydispersity that possess superior performance and stability characteristics as organic phase change materials (PCMs) for waste heat management as compared to conventional paraffin-based PCMs that have remained virtually unchanged for the past half century. To achieve this goal, reactive polyolefins that are the best candidates for commercialization will be identified through optimization of molecular structure, stereochemical tacticity, and the temperature and kinetics of main-chain and side-chain phase transitions. Reaction variables will also be optimized to provide the highest yields of reactive polyolefins under industrially-relevant and scalable process conditions. The development of PCM-modified thermoset resins based on reactive polyolefins will provide access to commercial waste heat management applications that employ physical constructs obtained from casting or injection molding and should benefit from lower production costs, a wider range of applications, and greater long-term stability.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/26/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/26/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1746976</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Reeds</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan P Reeds</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jreeds@precisionpolyolefins.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056957</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000622246</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/26/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Precision Polyolefins, LLC</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207423371</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056957</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Suite 4506, Bldg 091</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>828832159</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRECISION POLYOLEFINS, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Precision Polyolefins, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207423371</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Suite 4506, Bldg 091]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The project outcomes have served to better establish a new class of synthetic polymer as phase change materials (PCMs) that can aid in the beneficial management of heat generated in a variety of applications, such as rechargeable battery packs used in electric vehicles, buiding construction materials, and self-temperature regulating textiles. The intellectual merit of the project is the validation of a new paradigm for chemically 'locking in' this new class of PCM within an environmentally robust, highly crosslinked polyurethane or epoxy composite. By employing a unique polymerization technology, the properties of these PCMs, which can be viewed as 'synthetic organic waxes', can also be highly optimized in ways not previously achievable with other naturally-occurring or synthetic waxes.&nbsp; It is likely that results obtained with this project will also have a positive impact on science and technology that is associated with other disciplines, such as physics, material science and engineering.&nbsp; Longer lifetimes and improved efficiencies for these composites can also be expected.&nbsp; The broader impacts of the project are that the commercialization of this new class of PCM can contribute to a better US economy, a better quality of life and a reduced impact on the environment and limited natural resources.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/25/2019<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;P&nbsp;Reeds</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project outcomes have served to better establish a new class of synthetic polymer as phase change materials (PCMs) that can aid in the beneficial management of heat generated in a variety of applications, such as rechargeable battery packs used in electric vehicles, buiding construction materials, and self-temperature regulating textiles. The intellectual merit of the project is the validation of a new paradigm for chemically 'locking in' this new class of PCM within an environmentally robust, highly crosslinked polyurethane or epoxy composite. By employing a unique polymerization technology, the properties of these PCMs, which can be viewed as 'synthetic organic waxes', can also be highly optimized in ways not previously achievable with other naturally-occurring or synthetic waxes.  It is likely that results obtained with this project will also have a positive impact on science and technology that is associated with other disciplines, such as physics, material science and engineering.  Longer lifetimes and improved efficiencies for these composites can also be expected.  The broader impacts of the project are that the commercialization of this new class of PCM can contribute to a better US economy, a better quality of life and a reduced impact on the environment and limited natural resources.       Last Modified: 04/25/2019       Submitted by: Jonathan P Reeds]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
