<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Student and Postdoc Travel Grant for the 2017 International Meshing Roundtable (2017 IMR)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19990.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19990</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tracy Kimbrel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tkimbrel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927924</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project supports student travel to participate in the 26th International Meshing Roundtable conference will be held on September 18-21, 2017 in Barcelona, Spain. Meshing is the decomposition of complex objects into simple parts for design, display, and analysis. As technologies change in computing and computer-aided design and manufacturing the demand for meshing seems only to increase. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The IMR conference includes four short courses, four invited speakers, and presentations of reviewed papers, research notes, and posters, and a professional development session particularly targeting students and postdocs. This award will support registration and some travel expenses for a dozen students (undergraduate to postdoctoral, coming from U.S. universities, national labs, or non-profit research organizations) to exchange ideas with experts from around the world, fostering collaboration and recognition that can help them launch their careers. (For selection criteria, see the conference web site http://www.imr.sandia.gov/26imr)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1746066</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Suzanne</FirstName>
<LastName>Shontz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Suzanne M Shontz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shontz@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7858648816</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000388719</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
<CityName>Lawrence</CityName>
<ZipCode>660457552</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KS02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076248616</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF KANSAS CENTER FOR RESEARCH, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007180078</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Kansas Center for Research Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Lawrence</CityName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2385 Irving Hill Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KS02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>Algorithmic Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7756</Code>
<Text>CARBON CYCLE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~19990</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Mesh generation refers to the discretization of a geometry; the discretization serves as an approximation of the geometry as required by geometry-based analysis techniques.&nbsp; Meshes have been used in computer simulations in engineering, science, and medicine.&nbsp; Specific applications include flight simulation, virtual surgery, clothing design, and computer animation.</p> <p>At the 26<sup>th</sup> and 27<sup>th</sup> International Meshing Roundtables held in Barcelona, Spain in 2017 and in Albuquerque, New Mexico in 2018, respectively, there were numerous presentations on recent research that have been conducted on mesh generation and related geometric topics.&nbsp; The talks took the form of presentations by invited speakers and contributed presentations in the form of refereed conference papers, research notes, and poster presentations.&nbsp; In addition, at each conference, there was a meshing contest and open spaces sessions, which gave attendees an opportunity to participate in self-organized discussions on any topic relevant to the IMR.&nbsp;</p> <p>The presentations focused on new algorithms for mesh generation and geometry, analysis of mesh generation and geometry algorithms, and novel applications in these areas. The titles of the presentations can be found on the 2017 and 2018 conference websites, i.e., <a href="https://imr.sandia.gov/26imr/index.html">https://imr.sandia.gov/26imr/index.html</a> and <a href="https://imr.sandia.gov/27imr/index.html">https://imr.sandia.gov/27imr/index.html</a> .</p> <p>In particular, the peer-reviewed papers that were presented at the 2017 conference were published in the following book:&nbsp; Steven Owen, Xevi Roca, and Scott A. Mitchell, editors, "Proceedings of the 26<sup>th</sup> &nbsp;International Meshing Roundtable", Procedia Engineering, vol. 203, p. 426, 2017.&nbsp; Similarly, those that were presented at the 2018 conference were published in the following book:&nbsp; Xevi Roca and Adrien Loseille, editors, ?Proceedings of the 27<sup>th</sup> International Meshing Roundtable?, Springer International Publishing, Lecture Notes in Computational Science and Engineering, vol. 127, p. 490, 2019.&nbsp;</p> <p>The titles of the research notes that were presented at the 2017 and 2018 conferences can be found on the conference websites given above.</p> <p>All of the research presented at the conference advances the knowledge of the international community in the areas of mesh generation and geometry techniques, analysis, and applications, and will impact the fields of computer science, mathematics, engineering, science, medicine, and other application areas where meshes and geometry may someday prove useful.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Our NSF grant was used to offer students and postdocs travel grants to attend the 2017 and 2018 conferences.&nbsp; This enabled students to present their research in the form of refereed conference papers, research notes, and posters. &nbsp;The conferences presented students and postdocs with the opportunity to gain invaluable feedback on their research endeavors.&nbsp; Some students were also funded to attend the conferences to present a short course or an open spaces session.&nbsp; All students learned about research in mesh generation and its applications.&nbsp;</p> <p>There were a few sessions at the conferences that, while open to all, were especially geared towards student and postdoc attendees.&nbsp; These sessions included pre-conference short courses which trained attendees in various new areas of mesh generation and its applications.&nbsp; In 2017, the short courses focused on topics ranging from high-order mesh generation to polyhedral meshing and from GPU programming of meshes to meshing for architectural geometry.&nbsp; Whereas in 2018, the topics ranged from mesh generation to isogeometric analysis and from parallel mesh generation to hexahedral mesh generation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/23/2019<br>      Modified by: Suzanne&nbsp;M&nbsp;Shontz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Mesh generation refers to the discretization of a geometry; the discretization serves as an approximation of the geometry as required by geometry-based analysis techniques.  Meshes have been used in computer simulations in engineering, science, and medicine.  Specific applications include flight simulation, virtual surgery, clothing design, and computer animation.  At the 26th and 27th International Meshing Roundtables held in Barcelona, Spain in 2017 and in Albuquerque, New Mexico in 2018, respectively, there were numerous presentations on recent research that have been conducted on mesh generation and related geometric topics.  The talks took the form of presentations by invited speakers and contributed presentations in the form of refereed conference papers, research notes, and poster presentations.  In addition, at each conference, there was a meshing contest and open spaces sessions, which gave attendees an opportunity to participate in self-organized discussions on any topic relevant to the IMR.   The presentations focused on new algorithms for mesh generation and geometry, analysis of mesh generation and geometry algorithms, and novel applications in these areas. The titles of the presentations can be found on the 2017 and 2018 conference websites, i.e., https://imr.sandia.gov/26imr/index.html and https://imr.sandia.gov/27imr/index.html .  In particular, the peer-reviewed papers that were presented at the 2017 conference were published in the following book:  Steven Owen, Xevi Roca, and Scott A. Mitchell, editors, "Proceedings of the 26th  International Meshing Roundtable", Procedia Engineering, vol. 203, p. 426, 2017.  Similarly, those that were presented at the 2018 conference were published in the following book:  Xevi Roca and Adrien Loseille, editors, ?Proceedings of the 27th International Meshing Roundtable?, Springer International Publishing, Lecture Notes in Computational Science and Engineering, vol. 127, p. 490, 2019.   The titles of the research notes that were presented at the 2017 and 2018 conferences can be found on the conference websites given above.  All of the research presented at the conference advances the knowledge of the international community in the areas of mesh generation and geometry techniques, analysis, and applications, and will impact the fields of computer science, mathematics, engineering, science, medicine, and other application areas where meshes and geometry may someday prove useful.       Our NSF grant was used to offer students and postdocs travel grants to attend the 2017 and 2018 conferences.  This enabled students to present their research in the form of refereed conference papers, research notes, and posters.  The conferences presented students and postdocs with the opportunity to gain invaluable feedback on their research endeavors.  Some students were also funded to attend the conferences to present a short course or an open spaces session.  All students learned about research in mesh generation and its applications.   There were a few sessions at the conferences that, while open to all, were especially geared towards student and postdoc attendees.  These sessions included pre-conference short courses which trained attendees in various new areas of mesh generation and its applications.  In 2017, the short courses focused on topics ranging from high-order mesh generation to polyhedral meshing and from GPU programming of meshes to meshing for architectural geometry.  Whereas in 2018, the topics ranged from mesh generation to isogeometric analysis and from parallel mesh generation to hexahedral mesh generation.       Last Modified: 07/23/2019       Submitted by: Suzanne M Shontz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
