<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  eLearning system that enables patient-centered, team-based care and reduces physician shortages in medically underserved areas</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to significantly reduce primary care physician shortages and improve quality of care for low income patients in the United States by developing a tool that analyzes clinical care team performance data at federally qualified health centers (FQHCs) to automatically deploy individually tailored eLearning support for staff members that enables patient centered team based care.  FQHCs are funded by the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services to serve 22 million low income patients living in more than 10,000 of the poorest communities across the Nation.  Well-implemented patient centered team-based care has the potential to significantly reduce physician shortages and burden of chronic disease which disproportionately affects low income communities. However, efforts to move and sustain FQHCs participation in this model have had limited success with only 66% attaining patient centered medical home (PCMH) recognition in 2016.  Various public initiatives, including the Health Resources and Service Administration Quality Improvement Award and Medicare Access and CHIP Reauthorization Act (MACRA), are providing additional financial incentives to move primary care practices towards PCMH Recognition. However, current approaches to practice transformation are cumbersome and difficult to sustain.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project seeks to disrupt continued health professional education at FQHCs by assessing the feasibility of developing a tool that leverages electronic health record data to identify gaps in patient centered team based care for diabetic patients and deploys tailored asynchronous individualized e-learning nudge type support to each member of the care team based on their performance.  The research objectives of this SBIR Phase 1 are to establish the feasibility of using EHR data through an API to trigger individual user and team level flags for variation from a specific set of PCMH standards and diabetes clinical protocols; to develop algorithms that generate an individualized learner user profile and teams level reports; to generate data to design algorithms that learn from user preferences, impacts on flags and patient outcomes; to design user interphase for reward and recognition and to evaluate end user acceptance of eLearning tools.  The research will be approached using user centric design, behavioral economics and adult learning principles to gather specific requirements and develop a minimum viable product focused on a subset of between five to 10 indicators.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1746007</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
<LastName>Levis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maria F Levis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maria.levis@impactivo.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7875651227</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000750284</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Impactivo LLC</Name>
<CityName>San Juan</CityName>
<ZipCode>009091827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7875651227</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1606 Ave. Ponce de Leon</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 703]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>967479705</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IMPACTIVO , LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Impactivo LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>San Juan</CityName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>009091827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1606 Ave. Ponce de Leon]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Impactivo, LLC. is a woman-owned, minority-owned small business with a mission to transform health systems.&nbsp; Impactivo received a National Science Foundation Phase I SBIR grant to establish the feasibility of developing a minimum viable product for a software capable of enabling team-based care. &nbsp;The software is being designed to advance knowledge and understanding of its field by taking continued health professional education beyond the current standard of one-size-fits-all approaches and pioneer the concept of precision learning in clinical settings.&nbsp; The technology is intended to support primary care teams in providing high value patient-centered care through recommended workflows and continued education based on gaps in care, identified from their electronic health record and patient reported data.</p> <p>Specifically, Phase I addressed the following technical barriers:</p> <ul> <li>Establishment of mechanisms for accessing electronic health record and patient reported data.</li> <li>Alignment of multiple care team member workflows to create data-based care gap flags attributable to patient care teams and individuals</li> <li>Lack of algorithms for matching and coding personalized instruction that addresses health professional's skill gaps, performance and preferences.</li> <li>Generation of data to improve personalized instruction and design a user-friendly interphase to reward care teams and reduce physician dissatisfaction with EHRs.</li> </ul> <p>Impactivo carried out a thorough client discovery process focused on federally qualified health centers which currently serve more than 27 million low income and/or underserved patients in the United States and validated market acceptance.&nbsp; In collaboration with our pilot site, their EHR vendor and our development team, we were able to identify and establish data parameters and the feasibility of using EHR data through an HL7 interphase.&nbsp; We also developed an Integration Layer that facilitates integration between our product and external systems and allows the system to receive data through standard HL7 messages.&nbsp; The Integration Layer has been tested in a development site with test data.&nbsp; Using this data, flags for variation from protocols can effectively be visualized.&nbsp; Impactivo also designed an initial set of algorithms that assign a risk level to each individual patient based on data elements associated with social determinants of health (SDoH) and clinical data.&nbsp; Our team also developed additional algorithms to validate the possibility of coordinating care based on socio-demographic and clinical supplementary data and to recommend individualized training.&nbsp; Impactivo also developed a questionnaire to assess and take action on SDoH through referrals and tracking.&nbsp; As a result of Phase 1, we now have a minimum viable product that established the feasibility and the team's capacity to develop the technology.</p> <p>The social benefits of our product include enhanced team-based care which produces improved patient clinical outcomes, promotes patient satisfaction, and enhances health worker skills and job performance. Six out of 10 people living in America are diagnosed with one or more chronic illnesses. These patients account for 90% of the nation?s $3.3 trillion in annual healthcare expenditures (CDC, 2018). Our product can enable and enhance team-based care, which is strongly linked to improved outcomes for patients with chronic diseases. When fully deployed this technology has the potential to provide a significant societal and economic impact.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/23/2019<br>      Modified by: Maria&nbsp;F&nbsp;Levis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Impactivo, LLC. is a woman-owned, minority-owned small business with a mission to transform health systems.  Impactivo received a National Science Foundation Phase I SBIR grant to establish the feasibility of developing a minimum viable product for a software capable of enabling team-based care.  The software is being designed to advance knowledge and understanding of its field by taking continued health professional education beyond the current standard of one-size-fits-all approaches and pioneer the concept of precision learning in clinical settings.  The technology is intended to support primary care teams in providing high value patient-centered care through recommended workflows and continued education based on gaps in care, identified from their electronic health record and patient reported data.  Specifically, Phase I addressed the following technical barriers:  Establishment of mechanisms for accessing electronic health record and patient reported data. Alignment of multiple care team member workflows to create data-based care gap flags attributable to patient care teams and individuals Lack of algorithms for matching and coding personalized instruction that addresses health professional's skill gaps, performance and preferences. Generation of data to improve personalized instruction and design a user-friendly interphase to reward care teams and reduce physician dissatisfaction with EHRs.   Impactivo carried out a thorough client discovery process focused on federally qualified health centers which currently serve more than 27 million low income and/or underserved patients in the United States and validated market acceptance.  In collaboration with our pilot site, their EHR vendor and our development team, we were able to identify and establish data parameters and the feasibility of using EHR data through an HL7 interphase.  We also developed an Integration Layer that facilitates integration between our product and external systems and allows the system to receive data through standard HL7 messages.  The Integration Layer has been tested in a development site with test data.  Using this data, flags for variation from protocols can effectively be visualized.  Impactivo also designed an initial set of algorithms that assign a risk level to each individual patient based on data elements associated with social determinants of health (SDoH) and clinical data.  Our team also developed additional algorithms to validate the possibility of coordinating care based on socio-demographic and clinical supplementary data and to recommend individualized training.  Impactivo also developed a questionnaire to assess and take action on SDoH through referrals and tracking.  As a result of Phase 1, we now have a minimum viable product that established the feasibility and the team's capacity to develop the technology.  The social benefits of our product include enhanced team-based care which produces improved patient clinical outcomes, promotes patient satisfaction, and enhances health worker skills and job performance. Six out of 10 people living in America are diagnosed with one or more chronic illnesses. These patients account for 90% of the nation?s $3.3 trillion in annual healthcare expenditures (CDC, 2018). Our product can enable and enhance team-based care, which is strongly linked to improved outcomes for patients with chronic diseases. When fully deployed this technology has the potential to provide a significant societal and economic impact.          Last Modified: 05/23/2019       Submitted by: Maria F Levis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
