<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: The Development of Axion Software for CUORE</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>41191.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>41191</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan Whitmore</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928908</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Multiple astronomical observations have established that about 85% of the matter in the universe is not made of known elementary particles. Deciphering the nature of this so-called Dark Matter is of fundamental importance to cosmology, astrophysics, and high-energy particle physics. One of the most exciting quests is the search for new particles beyond the Standard Model of Particle Physics, which describes all the known elementary particles and the interactions between them. Extensions of the model predict not only new particles with large masses but also some with very small masses. Such a candidate for the latter is the axion, which has been introduced to explain the smallness of the violation of the Charge-Parity (CP) symmetry in Quantum Chromodynamics, the theory describing the action of the strong force, for example, the interactions between protons and neutrons that make up atomic nuclei. The axion turns out to also be a prime candidate for a constituent of the dark matter in the universe. The conclusion that the strong CP problem is solved must await the experimental discovery of the axion. This award will provide funds to search for axions that are produced in the solar core by the decay of a particular excited nucleus (iron).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The discovery of the axion could explain a number of phenomena in cosmology. This award will also provide a stimulating environment for an experienced graduate student to work on a very challenging software project involving state of the art data from a particle astrophysics experiment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will involve a technique to search for axions that are produced by the ground-state decay of a Fe-57 nucleus thermally excited to the 14.4-keV, 3/2+ state. This deexcitation is an M1 nuclear ground state transition. Theoretically, nuclear M1 transitions have a weak axion branch. This work involves developing sophisticated software to search the data from the CUORE detector for the modulations characteristic of the periodic behavior consistent with the known Bragg condition patterns associated with the known position of the sun at every instant of every day. The CUORE detector is an array of 988 aligned TeO2 single crystal bolometers operated in Laboratori Nazionale del Gran Sasso (LNGS) in Assergi, Italy. A major challenge is to evaluate the uncertainties in the orientation of every crystal in the array, and to evaluate its impact on conclusions drawn from the analysis. These uncertainties must be incorporated into the data analysis to be sure that if there are axions from the sun satisfying the Bragg conditions, the experiment is sensitive to them, and, most importantly, that the analysis does not create generate a false signal.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1747860</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Avignone</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>III</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frank T Avignone</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>titus3@mac.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8037774121</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000150145</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Carolina at Columbia</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Awards Management</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1600 Hampton Street, Suite 414]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041387846</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH CAROLINA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041387846</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Carolina at Columbia]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbia</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[712 Main Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7235</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Undergro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~41191</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project involved developing the software for a method of detecting an elementary particle called the axion. This particle is a natural consequence of a theoretical fix of a serious flaw in the basic theory of nuclear physics called Quantum Chromo-dynamics (QCD). One manifestation of the flaw is that QCD predicts that the neutron, which is neutrally charged, has a very large electric dipole moment. In a classical picture, the neutron would have an electric-dipole moment because its positive and negative charges are separated by some mean distance. The dipole moment of the neutron predicted by QCD is ten billion times larger than the experimental upper limit set by the most sensitive experiment. In the late 1970s, Roberto Peccei and Helen Quinn of Stanford University developed a theoretical modification of QCD that cancelled the problematic term in the theory that creates the large neutron dipole moment.&nbsp;&nbsp;Their mechanism, however, creates a particle called a Goldstone boson, the axion. The confirmation of the Peccei-Quinn solution would require that the axion be detected and identified. The search for the axion has been an important endeavor pursued by many experimental groups around the world since the late 1970s. In the standard model of particle physics, the axion had properties that would have made it easily observable. Unfortunately, nature is not that kind and the particle is now referred to as the invisible axion because, in the more general models, its interaction with matter and with electromagnetic fields is predicted to be extremely weak. Nevertheless, its discovery would be so important that well-designed searches are certainly worth the effort.</p> <p>The Cryogenic Underground Observatory for Rare Events (CUORE) is an array of 988 bolometric (thermal) detectors operating underground in the Gran Sasso Laboratory in Assergi, Italy. The PI and his students have been involved in the construction and operation of CUORE and its prototypes for 20 years. The purpose of the present project was to determine whether CUORE would be an appropriate apparatus for searching for axions from the solar core. Axions could be created in our sun by several mechanisms. In the case of interest here, the axions would come from a nuclear transition in the isotope iron-57 in the solar core and would have a well-known energy. Earlier, our group invented a technique to search for the rapid variations of the detection probability due to the variation of the angles between the direct line of sight to the solar core and the crystal planes of the detectors. The 988 single crystal detectors are all oriented in the same direction. By recording the times of each detected event and correlating each detection time with the direct line of sight that the solar core makes with the crystal, one should be able to discriminate real events from continuous ubiquitous background. The purpose of the present research project was the determination of the uncertainties in the orientations of the crystal planes of each detector relative to true north on the celestial sphere and to incorporate these in the analysis software. This required the detailed examination of the engineering drawings and measuring the orientation of the basic stages of the CUORE cryostat. Douglas Adams, the student supported by this grant, traveled to Italy twice to perform the measurements and to make detailed analyses of all available dimensions and orientations of each crystal as well as all of the components of the cryostat.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Frank&nbsp;T&nbsp;Avignone</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project involved developing the software for a method of detecting an elementary particle called the axion. This particle is a natural consequence of a theoretical fix of a serious flaw in the basic theory of nuclear physics called Quantum Chromo-dynamics (QCD). One manifestation of the flaw is that QCD predicts that the neutron, which is neutrally charged, has a very large electric dipole moment. In a classical picture, the neutron would have an electric-dipole moment because its positive and negative charges are separated by some mean distance. The dipole moment of the neutron predicted by QCD is ten billion times larger than the experimental upper limit set by the most sensitive experiment. In the late 1970s, Roberto Peccei and Helen Quinn of Stanford University developed a theoretical modification of QCD that cancelled the problematic term in the theory that creates the large neutron dipole moment.  Their mechanism, however, creates a particle called a Goldstone boson, the axion. The confirmation of the Peccei-Quinn solution would require that the axion be detected and identified. The search for the axion has been an important endeavor pursued by many experimental groups around the world since the late 1970s. In the standard model of particle physics, the axion had properties that would have made it easily observable. Unfortunately, nature is not that kind and the particle is now referred to as the invisible axion because, in the more general models, its interaction with matter and with electromagnetic fields is predicted to be extremely weak. Nevertheless, its discovery would be so important that well-designed searches are certainly worth the effort.  The Cryogenic Underground Observatory for Rare Events (CUORE) is an array of 988 bolometric (thermal) detectors operating underground in the Gran Sasso Laboratory in Assergi, Italy. The PI and his students have been involved in the construction and operation of CUORE and its prototypes for 20 years. The purpose of the present project was to determine whether CUORE would be an appropriate apparatus for searching for axions from the solar core. Axions could be created in our sun by several mechanisms. In the case of interest here, the axions would come from a nuclear transition in the isotope iron-57 in the solar core and would have a well-known energy. Earlier, our group invented a technique to search for the rapid variations of the detection probability due to the variation of the angles between the direct line of sight to the solar core and the crystal planes of the detectors. The 988 single crystal detectors are all oriented in the same direction. By recording the times of each detected event and correlating each detection time with the direct line of sight that the solar core makes with the crystal, one should be able to discriminate real events from continuous ubiquitous background. The purpose of the present research project was the determination of the uncertainties in the orientations of the crystal planes of each detector relative to true north on the celestial sphere and to incorporate these in the analysis software. This required the detailed examination of the engineering drawings and measuring the orientation of the basic stages of the CUORE cryostat. Douglas Adams, the student supported by this grant, traveled to Italy twice to perform the measurements and to make detailed analyses of all available dimensions and orientations of each crystal as well as all of the components of the cryostat.          Last Modified: 12/07/2018       Submitted by: Frank T Avignone]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
