<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop on Indigenous Perspectives and Linguistic Practices Relevant to Wellness</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49581.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49581</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colleen M. Fitzgerald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Documenting the language of a given speech community includes recording the knowledge held by elders and traditional healers regarding physical, mental, and emotional wellbeing. Importantly, documenting these linguistic practices can increase the scientific understanding of factors important to health and wellbeing, including illness preventions and remedies, healing practices, and perspectives on how to live a healthy life. Native American and Alaska Native communities show a well-documented, major gap in wellbeing measures when comparing these communities and non-Native Americans. This award will fund a workshop that brings together community members and other researchers and experts from diverse backgrounds to explore these issues surrounding wellbeing and to present their findings. Better health outcomes for Alaska Native communities serve the national interest by reducing health inequities. Project activities will broaden participation by underrepresented groups of all ages in the social sciences, including involving high school and university students, some of whom will be trained in video documentation. The conference presentations will be available to the general public and other academics by sharing the recordings online. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Sharing Our Knowledge workshops have been held since 1993, bringing together Native and non-Native Tlingit researchers to present their work to a diverse audience. These workshops have been an important bridge between academics and indigenous community members. The Tlingit people have traditionally inhabited coastal Alaska and the contiguous interior of Yukon and British Columbia, and Tlingit is a severely threatened language, with 80 fluent first language speakers and many avid second language learners. The Native American Languages Act, passed by the U.S. Congress in 1990, enacted into policy the recognition of the unique status and importance of Native American languages. These workshops serve as a forum conducive to the production, sharing and documentation of Tlingit knowledge and language. The 10th Sharing Our Knowledge workshop will occur in 2017 and the focus on wellbeing will encompass research presentations on the physical, mental, emotional, spiritual, and economic wellbeing for individuals and communities. Workshop discussions include the multi-generational impacts on Tlingit health due to colonization and the documentation of the wellness teachings deeply embedded in the Tlingit language. Impressionistically speaking, for those who have witnessed the renaissance of Alaska Native traditions and languages, such cultural affinities seem to have improved the wellness of Alaska Natives. Workshop results will also add to the growing literature regarding the positive interactions between indigenous languages and cultures and wellbeing. The workshop will have broad impact, and will offer opportunities to cross traditional academic boundaries including health, biology, traditional ecological knowledge, archaeology, linguistics, museum studies, cultural anthropology, education, ethnohistory, art, music, and indigenous law. Project results will be archived and accessible at the Sealaska Heritage Institute Archive and at the Alaska State Library Historical Collections Archives.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1747878</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alice</FirstName>
<LastName>Taff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alice Taff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alicetaff@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9079572208</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000196655</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paula</FirstName>
<LastName>Martin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paula J Martin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pjmartin2@alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9077966494</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000752732</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alaska Southeast Juneau Campus</Name>
<CityName>Juneau</CityName>
<ZipCode>998010000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9077966494</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11066 Auke Lake Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AK00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>036674794</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ALASKA SOUTHEAST</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048679567</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alaska Southeast Juneau Campus]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>998018625</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AK00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ASSP-Arctic Social Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~49581</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit Outcomes</strong></p> <p>We accomplished our objectives to provide a forum for Alaska Native culture bearers, non-Native cultural experts, Tlingit, Tsimshian, and Haida speakers, and students. The conference, Sharing Our Knowledge (SOK), with a theme of, &ldquo;<em>Haa Shag&oacute;on, Yei Sh Natoosneixh</em>: Our History, We are Healing Ourselves,&rdquo;&nbsp;was held 10/15-19/2017, in Sitka, AK, and attracted 250 participants.&nbsp;57 were presenters. 42% of the presenters were Native. Half the presenters were from Alaska, the rest from California, Colorado, Maryland, New Hampshire, New York, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, Washington DC, Russia, and Canada. Scientists, clan leaders, culture bearers, scholars, writers, activists, film makers, musicians, educators, archivists, and artists shared insights on their traditions and research.The conference included three plenary sessions and 40 concurrent sessions. Of these, twelve were on museums-archives, six on healing trauma, five on clan history, four each on the Native American film industry, humor, Native fine arts, three each on language revitalization, Russian America, Russian Treaty of Cession effects, and National Parks, two on education, and one each on humor, cultural stereotyping, and Tlingit governance. All&nbsp;presenters&nbsp;referred to the healing&nbsp;potential&nbsp;of their particular focus.</p> <p>Special events included a two-hour boat cruise to view significant Tlingit cultural sites and learn their Tlingit place names. Sitka &#7732;waan (local Tlingit clans) welcomed guests at the "Warming of the Hands" ceremony. A gathering of Tlingit weavers gave demonstrations and taught each day.&nbsp; The Kiks.adi Clan held a ceremony to memorialized Tlingit ownership of the site where, 150 years previously, Russian and U.S. officials formalized the transfer of Russian America.&nbsp;A repatriation ceremony took place for the return of clan sacred items.&nbsp;A Tlingit clan leader conducted a tour of cemeteries holding the remains of Alaska Natives. Two films were screened. A luncheon focused on 150 years of Canadian/American control of Tlingit lands. A dinner honored the late Tlingit scholar and poet Nora Marks Dauenhauer. And a panel discussed the causes and consequences of the Alaska Treaty of Cession (aka the purchase of Alaska).</p> <p>For use by researchers, a video of each SOK 2017 session is viewable at&nbsp;<span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL5JmUC9niijgOtX10j4j-7E7Yg41bpF_Y">https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL5JmUC9niijgOtX10j4j-7E7Yg41bpF_Y</a>.</span>As of 4/1/19, there have been 2463 views on the Sharing Our Knowledge 2017 channel.</p> <p>So far, knowledge shared at SOK 2017 has been published in a book, a book chapter, a journal article, 3 conference presentations, and two websites.</p> <p>The videos and other conference materials in digital and paper format are discoverable, accessible and safely archived in Juneau, AK, at the Alaska State Library, Archives, and Museum and at Sealaska Heritage Institute (SHI) William L. Paul, Sr. Archive.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts Outcomes</strong></p> <p>The 2017 conference location and timing were strategically planned to take place immediately prior to Alaska Day, which celebrates the transfer of Russian America to the United States on October 18, 1867.&nbsp; The Tlingit people acknowledge only the transfer of a few small local sites ceded to the Russians by the Kiks.adi Clan, certainly not the whole of Alaska lands. SOK 2017 workshops and associated events provided Alaska Natives an opportunity to share their experiences and their legacy of the US occupancy of Alaska, leading to a general awareness that Alaska Day should be commemorative rather than celebratory. Among other presentations on his topic, a panel of four Russian scholars and four Alaska Native activists discussed the 1867 treaty by which Russia transferred its interests in Alaska to the United States. This session is documented for analysis of such things as content, floor time Russians vs. Alaska Natives.&nbsp;<span style="text-decoration: underline;">&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J9Sw1Kgt1sw&amp;feature=youtu.be" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J9Sw1Kgt1sw&amp;feature=youtu.b</a></span>. One immediate and direct result of SOK 2017 was that the original owners of Sitka lands, the Kiks.adi, were invited to the 2017 re-enactment for the first time since 1867, when the Kiks.adi were pointedly excluded.</p> <p>To help defray travel costs, NSF-DEL award 1747878 provided for travel vouchers to 67 elders, students, and presenters who had no other institutional funding. This meant more people could attend and share their perspectives.</p> <p>Five student volunteer videographers received videography training from Sarah Betcher (Farthest North Video), conference Video Coordinator. These volunteer videographers captured video, audio, and metadata of each session. Two graduate student volunteers were trained to input language metadata for six hours of audio in the sessions "Recording Healing in Southeast [AK] Languages." The audio and spreadsheet are archived with the other SOK 2017 materials.</p> <p>In addition to the details of the schedule, the SOK 2017 conference program includes extensive background and the founding documents for this gathering, which has endured for 25 years.</p> <p>The Sharing Our Knowledge website was updated with the 2017 photos, videos, and conference program, making the&nbsp;verbatim proceedings of the conference accessible to all through the&nbsp;internet.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.sharingourknowledge.org/">https://www.sharingourknowledge.org/</a></p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/08/2019<br>      Modified by: Alice&nbsp;Taff</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554498134723_WarmingHands--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554498134723_WarmingHands--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Warming of the Hands"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554498134723_WarmingHands--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Warming of the Hands"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This ceremony opens the conference as  travelers are welcomed by local Tlingit clans to their territory.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Peter Metcalfe</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alice&nbsp;Taff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Warming of the Hands</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554498523171_Atlatl--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554498523171_Atlatl--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tlingit Spearthrowers"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554498523171_Atlatl--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tlingit Spearthrowers"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Presenters from the Smithsonian engaged participants with the opportunity to try 3D printed replicas of Tlingit spearthrowers.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Peter Metcalfe</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alice&nbsp;Taff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tlingit Spearthrowers</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554500036283_TeslinCouncil--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554500036283_TeslinCouncil--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Teslin Tlingit Council"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554500036283_TeslinCouncil--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Teslin Tlingit Council"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Canadian Teslin Tlingit Council shared their process for introducing Tlingit culture into their organization.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Peter Metcalfe</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alice&nbsp;Taff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Teslin Tlingit Council</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554500423180_SpellBeeSOK--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554500423180_SpellBeeSOK--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tlingit Spelling Bee"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554500423180_SpellBeeSOK--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tlingit Spelling Bee"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The second biennial Tlingit spelling bee was won with the spelling of ch?ayoo al?ok, 'she's sipping tea'.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Peter Metcalfe</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alice&nbsp;Taff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tlingit Spelling Bee</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554501065686_DancingHat--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554501065686_DancingHat--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Dancing the Hat"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1747878/1747878_10500179_1554501065686_DancingHat--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Dancing the Hat"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Repatriation of a sacred clan hat is witnessed by those assembled as clan leader Herman Davis "dances" the hat among them.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Peter Metcalfe</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alice&nbsp;Taff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Dancing the Hat</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit Outcomes  We accomplished our objectives to provide a forum for Alaska Native culture bearers, non-Native cultural experts, Tlingit, Tsimshian, and Haida speakers, and students. The conference, Sharing Our Knowledge (SOK), with a theme of, "Haa Shag&oacute;on, Yei Sh Natoosneixh: Our History, We are Healing Ourselves," was held 10/15-19/2017, in Sitka, AK, and attracted 250 participants. 57 were presenters. 42% of the presenters were Native. Half the presenters were from Alaska, the rest from California, Colorado, Maryland, New Hampshire, New York, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, Washington DC, Russia, and Canada. Scientists, clan leaders, culture bearers, scholars, writers, activists, film makers, musicians, educators, archivists, and artists shared insights on their traditions and research.The conference included three plenary sessions and 40 concurrent sessions. Of these, twelve were on museums-archives, six on healing trauma, five on clan history, four each on the Native American film industry, humor, Native fine arts, three each on language revitalization, Russian America, Russian Treaty of Cession effects, and National Parks, two on education, and one each on humor, cultural stereotyping, and Tlingit governance. All presenters referred to the healing potential of their particular focus.  Special events included a two-hour boat cruise to view significant Tlingit cultural sites and learn their Tlingit place names. Sitka &#7732;waan (local Tlingit clans) welcomed guests at the "Warming of the Hands" ceremony. A gathering of Tlingit weavers gave demonstrations and taught each day.  The Kiks.adi Clan held a ceremony to memorialized Tlingit ownership of the site where, 150 years previously, Russian and U.S. officials formalized the transfer of Russian America. A repatriation ceremony took place for the return of clan sacred items. A Tlingit clan leader conducted a tour of cemeteries holding the remains of Alaska Natives. Two films were screened. A luncheon focused on 150 years of Canadian/American control of Tlingit lands. A dinner honored the late Tlingit scholar and poet Nora Marks Dauenhauer. And a panel discussed the causes and consequences of the Alaska Treaty of Cession (aka the purchase of Alaska).  For use by researchers, a video of each SOK 2017 session is viewable at https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL5JmUC9niijgOtX10j4j-7E7Yg41bpF_Y.As of 4/1/19, there have been 2463 views on the Sharing Our Knowledge 2017 channel.  So far, knowledge shared at SOK 2017 has been published in a book, a book chapter, a journal article, 3 conference presentations, and two websites.  The videos and other conference materials in digital and paper format are discoverable, accessible and safely archived in Juneau, AK, at the Alaska State Library, Archives, and Museum and at Sealaska Heritage Institute (SHI) William L. Paul, Sr. Archive.  Broader Impacts Outcomes  The 2017 conference location and timing were strategically planned to take place immediately prior to Alaska Day, which celebrates the transfer of Russian America to the United States on October 18, 1867.  The Tlingit people acknowledge only the transfer of a few small local sites ceded to the Russians by the Kiks.adi Clan, certainly not the whole of Alaska lands. SOK 2017 workshops and associated events provided Alaska Natives an opportunity to share their experiences and their legacy of the US occupancy of Alaska, leading to a general awareness that Alaska Day should be commemorative rather than celebratory. Among other presentations on his topic, a panel of four Russian scholars and four Alaska Native activists discussed the 1867 treaty by which Russia transferred its interests in Alaska to the United States. This session is documented for analysis of such things as content, floor time Russians vs. Alaska Natives.  https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J9Sw1Kgt1sw&amp;feature=youtu.b. One immediate and direct result of SOK 2017 was that the original owners of Sitka lands, the Kiks.adi, were invited to the 2017 re-enactment for the first time since 1867, when the Kiks.adi were pointedly excluded.  To help defray travel costs, NSF-DEL award 1747878 provided for travel vouchers to 67 elders, students, and presenters who had no other institutional funding. This meant more people could attend and share their perspectives.  Five student volunteer videographers received videography training from Sarah Betcher (Farthest North Video), conference Video Coordinator. These volunteer videographers captured video, audio, and metadata of each session. Two graduate student volunteers were trained to input language metadata for six hours of audio in the sessions "Recording Healing in Southeast [AK] Languages." The audio and spreadsheet are archived with the other SOK 2017 materials.  In addition to the details of the schedule, the SOK 2017 conference program includes extensive background and the founding documents for this gathering, which has endured for 25 years.  The Sharing Our Knowledge website was updated with the 2017 photos, videos, and conference program, making the verbatim proceedings of the conference accessible to all through the internet. https://www.sharingourknowledge.org/         Last Modified: 04/08/2019       Submitted by: Alice Taff]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
