<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Planning Grant:  Industry University Cooperative Research Center (IUCRC) for Bioanalytic Metrology (CBM), University of Notre Dame</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal entails planning for an Industry-University Collaborative Research Center for Bioanalytic Metrology, a joint effort of the University of Notre Dame, Indiana University, and Purdue University. Planning activities will bring together a national coalition of analytical instrument makers, pharmaceutical companies, clinical practitioners, academic researchers, and other stakeholders, and unite them in a mission to design and build new, industry-critical systems for chemical measurement and bioanalysis. These systems are needed to address a fundamental gap in U.S. research and development; namely, the ability to fully identify, characterize, and track biological molecules within human cells and understand their many complex interactions. If established, the technical spin-offs from the center will have direct and tangible benefits for drug discovery, molecular diagnostics, clinical biotechnology, and other areas. Moreover, the capabilities envisioned by the center are necessary for the implementation of other long-term objectives, such as precision medicine. In addition to this knowledge transfer, the center will also help train a new and diverse bioanalytical workforce. The outcomes of the planning exercise will form the basis of a proposal to the National Science Foundation to establish a Center for Bioanalytic Metrology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Genomics, proteomics, metabolomics and bioinformatics provide a holistic framework to study biological systems with applications ranging from fundamental studies of biological systems to the design and use of diagnostics and therapeutics for personalized medicine. To realize the promise of these technologies, however, we must increase the depth of analysis of proteins, metabolites and other biomolecular species beyond current limits, thus reducing the fraction of detected, but unidentified, species collectively known as the ?dark molecules of life.' This planning grant lays the groundwork for a Center for Bioanalytic Metrology (CBM), joining expertise at Notre Dame, Indiana, and Purdue. Planning activities will bring together analytical instrument makers, pharmaceutical companies, clinical practitioners, and leading academic research groups in analytical sciences and engineering. In addition to the technical objectives, the CBM will also: (a) enable technology and knowledge transfer to the industrial sector, (b) enhance graduate and undergraduate education activities specifically designed to increase diversity of the STEM workforce, and (c) provide valuable updates to chemistry, biology, computer science, and engineering curricula through the incorporation of research into existing undergraduate and graduate classes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1747764</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Bohn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul W Bohn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pbohn@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746311849</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000330608</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>824910376</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048994727</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName>Notre Dame</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565712</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[940 Grace Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The University of Notre Dame used support from NSF to plan for the establishment of the Center for Bioanalytic Metrology (CBM), an IUCRC with two overarching objectives: (1) to deliver best-in-class analytic metrology tools and expertise to enable the development of powerful new precompetitive technologies and capabilities across the pharmaceutical, biotechnology, food/nutrition/agriculture, and energy sectors; and (2) to be the critical proving ground for applications of new instrumentation to cutting-edge chemical and biochemical problems required to realize these pre-competitive technologies. CBM seeks to provide longer-term, larger-scale and more cost-effective solutions to precompetitive industry measurement science problems than can be achieved in-house or through contract research organizations. In addition, the center will provide industry members with compelling opportunities to invigorate human resources through access to hires of center-trained students, and opportunities for continuing education of existing staff. CBM is a partnership between Indiana University, the University of Notre Dame, and Purdue University&mdash;who together offer an exceptional confluence of geographically concentrated excellence in the biochemical measurement sciences. CBM is bringing together market-setting companies, spanning high technology sectors from pharma to energy, with major analytical instrument makers and some of their primary end-users in the same ecosystem. Thus, CBM is uniquely positioned to bridge the gap between the initial demonstration of new ideas&mdash;the traditional province of academia&mdash;and the delivery of practical pre-competitive technologies, which is the over-arching goal of the IUCRC program.</p> <p>NSF recognizes broader impacts arising from work which results in &ldquo;societally relevant outcomes&rdquo;, such as &ldquo;&hellip;development of a diverse, globally competitive <span style="text-decoration: underline;">STEM workforce</span>; increased <span style="text-decoration: underline;">partnerships</span> between academia, industry, and others; &hellip;increased <span style="text-decoration: underline;">economic competitiveness</span> of the US; and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">enhanced infrastructure for research and education</span>.&rdquo; The value being developed by the CBM addresses these four objectives specifically, and its impact will extend far beyond the member companies who benefit from the projects supported within the CBM. (1) The faculty and administration of the participating universities are developing deeper relationships with industry partners; (2) The CBM positively impacts US economic competitiveness across the pharma, biotech, food/nutrition/ag, and energy sectors; (3) The CBM fosters enhanced partnerships across the full spectrum of US industry by engaging small business, startups and the entrepreneur community; and (4) Students, including those from groups underrepresented in science and engineering, are receiving extensive, industry-relevant training that will fast-track their ability to pursue post-PhD job opportunities. In addition, the larger analytical community and the nation will benefit from professional workforce development that is a natural result of the IUCRC as well as the solutions to significant technological challenges that stand in the way of future progress in the pharmaceutical, biotechnology, food/nutrition/agriculture, and energy sectors.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/01/2020<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;W&nbsp;Bohn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The University of Notre Dame used support from NSF to plan for the establishment of the Center for Bioanalytic Metrology (CBM), an IUCRC with two overarching objectives: (1) to deliver best-in-class analytic metrology tools and expertise to enable the development of powerful new precompetitive technologies and capabilities across the pharmaceutical, biotechnology, food/nutrition/agriculture, and energy sectors; and (2) to be the critical proving ground for applications of new instrumentation to cutting-edge chemical and biochemical problems required to realize these pre-competitive technologies. CBM seeks to provide longer-term, larger-scale and more cost-effective solutions to precompetitive industry measurement science problems than can be achieved in-house or through contract research organizations. In addition, the center will provide industry members with compelling opportunities to invigorate human resources through access to hires of center-trained students, and opportunities for continuing education of existing staff. CBM is a partnership between Indiana University, the University of Notre Dame, and Purdue University&mdash;who together offer an exceptional confluence of geographically concentrated excellence in the biochemical measurement sciences. CBM is bringing together market-setting companies, spanning high technology sectors from pharma to energy, with major analytical instrument makers and some of their primary end-users in the same ecosystem. Thus, CBM is uniquely positioned to bridge the gap between the initial demonstration of new ideas&mdash;the traditional province of academia&mdash;and the delivery of practical pre-competitive technologies, which is the over-arching goal of the IUCRC program.  NSF recognizes broader impacts arising from work which results in "societally relevant outcomes", such as "&hellip;development of a diverse, globally competitive STEM workforce; increased partnerships between academia, industry, and others; &hellip;increased economic competitiveness of the US; and enhanced infrastructure for research and education." The value being developed by the CBM addresses these four objectives specifically, and its impact will extend far beyond the member companies who benefit from the projects supported within the CBM. (1) The faculty and administration of the participating universities are developing deeper relationships with industry partners; (2) The CBM positively impacts US economic competitiveness across the pharma, biotech, food/nutrition/ag, and energy sectors; (3) The CBM fosters enhanced partnerships across the full spectrum of US industry by engaging small business, startups and the entrepreneur community; and (4) Students, including those from groups underrepresented in science and engineering, are receiving extensive, industry-relevant training that will fast-track their ability to pursue post-PhD job opportunities. In addition, the larger analytical community and the nation will benefit from professional workforce development that is a natural result of the IUCRC as well as the solutions to significant technological challenges that stand in the way of future progress in the pharmaceutical, biotechnology, food/nutrition/agriculture, and energy sectors.          Last Modified: 02/01/2020       Submitted by: Paul W Bohn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
