<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Scalable Manufacture of Natural Fiber Welded Yarn</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224968.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224968</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This SBIR Phase I project aims to prove the technical feasibility and the economic viability of natural fiber welded and dyed yarns and fabrics. Natural fiber welding is process that swells and mobilizes polymers within natural fibers to create higher performance yarns and fabrics. At sufficiently fast rates, individual fibers are fused and bonded together without glues or resins while retaining a majority of the natural structure and order of natural polymers. This leads to improved mechanical properties while maintaining the benefits of a natural product. Moreover, during the welding process, functional materials and chemistries including dyes, antimicrobials, and flame retardants can be simultaneously locked within yarns and fabrics in new eco-friendly ways. This new ability has potential to displace, for example, present day resource intensive processes such as indigo dyeing for denim which is a water and chemical intensive process that requires significant equipment investment. Inclusion of indigo dye via natural fiber welding processes has tremendous potential to reduce the environmental impact of denim manufacture while saving costs and simultaneously improving the performance of resultant fabrics and with innovative new design effects. This type of disruptive innovation would bring in sustainable US-based manufacturing throughout the value chain of the massive multitrillion dollar per year textile industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An extremely promising and tunable class of solvents for natural fiber welding processes are called ionic liquids. This project explores several new types of ionic liquid-based solvent systems co-optimized with new automated hardware designs to cost effectively enact natural fiber welding processes with cotton and other natural fiber-containing yarn substrates. In so doing, ionic liquid-based process solvents are recovered in a closed-loop recycling process thereby enabling economic viability as well as creating an eco-friendly manufacturing platform. This project will focus on proving proof of concept with new combinations of ionic liquid(s) and co-solvent(s) to enable concurrent welding with indigo dyeing while developing high efficiency recycling methodologies. There are known methodologies to separate ionic liquids in dilute aqueous solutions but these have not yet been developed for situations where additional miscible co-solvents are present. The objective of this project is to demonstrate natural fiber welding processes that deliver indigo dye into cotton-based yarn substrates while achieving high rates of recycling with process solvents that contain co-solvent(s) and to enable scalable processes for potentially billions of pounds of denim products produced annually.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1747149</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Amstutz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron Amstutz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aaron.amstutz@naturalfiberwelding.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3096450916</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000752296</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Natural Fiber Welding, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Peoria</CityName>
<ZipCode>616061877</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3095735700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>801 W Main St.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080263157</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATURAL FIBER WELDING, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Natural Fiber Welding, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Peoria</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>616061877</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[801 W. Main St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~224968</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Natural textile fibers such as cotton, flax, wool, and silk exhibit desirable properties, many of which are unmatched by synthetic fibers.&nbsp; Synthetic fibers have the benefit of being made in continuous form while staple fibers such as cotton are less than 1.5&rdquo; long.&nbsp;&nbsp; Natural cotton staple fibers must be spun so that entanglement and friction between fibers produces a continuous yarn.&nbsp;&nbsp; Natural fiber welding (NFW) is a newly developed process whereby the friction that holds fibers together in a spun yarn is replaced and/or supplemented by tunable &ldquo;welding&rdquo; &ndash; which involves the partial dissolution of surface polymer to extend intramolecular hydrogen bonding networks between neighboring fibers.&nbsp; &nbsp;Yarns treated by natural fiber welding processes exhibit, for example, improved strength and abrasion resistance compared to un-processed (conventional spun) yarns.&nbsp; Natural Fiber Welding, Inc has engineered and demonstrated processes that work on fast timescales for materials such as cellulose (cotton &amp; flax) and keratin (wool &amp; silk) using efficacious ionic liquid-based solvents.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; For scaled implementation, ionic liquid solvents must be cost effectively captured and recycled.&nbsp; Efficient reuse of solvents means that NFW manufacturing can be &lsquo;closed loop&rsquo; yielding excellent unit economics while enabling natural fiber yarns to access morphologies and attributes that were previously only possible for petroleum-based synthetics.</p> <p>This project has demonstrated the ability to take yarn wash solutions that contained ionic liquids and recover the ionic liquids through a three-stage water removal process.&nbsp; In particular for this project, we found that direct contact evaporation through the use of &ldquo;microbubbles&rdquo; is an excellent means of removing the majority of the water.&nbsp;&nbsp; This approach is energy efficient and is gentle to avoid degrading the ionic liquid solvents even after many cycles of use.&nbsp; The yarn wash solutions were passed over the surface of a porous sintered stainless steel sparger plate in a thin layer (~ <sup>1</sup>/<sub>8</sub>&rdquo;) while hot air (~120&deg;C) was bubbled through the solution.&nbsp;&nbsp; The hot air bubbles quickly evaporate water (at the surface of the bubble) but, because they are so small, the solution itself doesn&rsquo;t heat up &ndash; in fact, because of evaporative cooling, the solution stays quite cool (~35&deg;C), while in residence on the sparger plate.&nbsp;&nbsp; During the project, we found that water content of the wash solutions could be dropped from &gt;90% down to ~25% in a single pass over the direct contact evaporator &ndash; all with very little heating to the solution itself.</p> <p>The project work has also showed that the final stages of water removal were best conducted in two separate passes through a wiped film evaporator.&nbsp;&nbsp; One pass was configured for water recovery (using the condensers); the other pass was configured for maximum ionic liquid dehydration.&nbsp;&nbsp; Using these two successive passes allowed for the best machine utilization in contrast to trying to remove the remaining water in a single pass under less-ideal conditions.</p> <p>Based on this project, we have found ionic liquid recovery methodologies for dilute aqueous solutions that are energy efficient, impart low-levels of thermal history to the ionic liquid solvent during bulk water removal, and require lower capital expenditure than competing methods.&nbsp;&nbsp; These methods support the goal of &gt;99% solvent recovery from the yarn wash solution and thus enable the cost-efficient scale-up of NFW manufacturing and meets major industry needs.&nbsp; For example, customer interviews reveal that garment manufacturers, brands, and apparel industry experts agree that there is a pressing need for the textile industry to greatly improve sustainability and material circularity.&nbsp; One of the primary technical solutions that has been lagging is a cost effective means to recycle and reuse natural fibers (e.g., both post-industrial and post-consumer cotton), while maintaining good strength and abrasion resistance.&nbsp; Yarns treated by NFW processes enable greatly increased recycled fiber content even while improving performance of conventional cotton yarns.&nbsp;&nbsp; In context, and based on the results of this project, natural fiber welding has great potential to be a disruptive technology that simultaneously enables improved performance, sustainability, and circularity across the multi-trillion dollar per year textile industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/16/2018<br>      Modified by: Aaron&nbsp;Amstutz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1747149/1747149_10526579_1539718668689_schematicofdirectcontactevaporator--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1747149/1747149_10526579_1539718668689_schematicofdirectcontactevaporator--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Schematic of Direct Contact Evaporator"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1747149/1747149_10526579_1539718668689_schematicofdirectcontactevaporator--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Schematic of Direct Contact Evaporator"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic of Direct Contact Evaporator</div> <div class="imageCredit">Aaron Amstutz</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Aaron&nbsp;Amstutz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Schematic of Direct Contact Evaporator</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1747149/1747149_10526579_1539718730017_directcontactevaporator--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1747149/1747149_10526579_1539718730017_directcontactevaporator--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Direct Contact Evaporator"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1747149/1747149_10526579_1539718730017_directcontactevaporator--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Direct Contact Evaporator"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Direct Contact Evaporator developed during this project</div> <div class="imageCredit">Aaron Amstutz</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Aaron&nbsp;Amstutz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Direct Contact Evaporator</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1747149/1747149_10526579_1539718810185_Wipedfilmevaporator--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1747149/1747149_10526579_1539718810185_Wipedfilmevaporator--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Wiped Film Evaporator"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1747149/1747149_10526579_1539718810185_Wipedfilmevaporator--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Wiped Film Evaporator"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Wiped Film Evaporator used for stage 2 and stage 3 of solution dehydration.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Aaron Amstutz</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Aaron&nbsp;Amstutz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Wiped Film Evaporator</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Natural textile fibers such as cotton, flax, wool, and silk exhibit desirable properties, many of which are unmatched by synthetic fibers.  Synthetic fibers have the benefit of being made in continuous form while staple fibers such as cotton are less than 1.5" long.   Natural cotton staple fibers must be spun so that entanglement and friction between fibers produces a continuous yarn.   Natural fiber welding (NFW) is a newly developed process whereby the friction that holds fibers together in a spun yarn is replaced and/or supplemented by tunable "welding" &ndash; which involves the partial dissolution of surface polymer to extend intramolecular hydrogen bonding networks between neighboring fibers.   Yarns treated by natural fiber welding processes exhibit, for example, improved strength and abrasion resistance compared to un-processed (conventional spun) yarns.  Natural Fiber Welding, Inc has engineered and demonstrated processes that work on fast timescales for materials such as cellulose (cotton &amp; flax) and keratin (wool &amp; silk) using efficacious ionic liquid-based solvents.    For scaled implementation, ionic liquid solvents must be cost effectively captured and recycled.  Efficient reuse of solvents means that NFW manufacturing can be ?closed loop? yielding excellent unit economics while enabling natural fiber yarns to access morphologies and attributes that were previously only possible for petroleum-based synthetics.  This project has demonstrated the ability to take yarn wash solutions that contained ionic liquids and recover the ionic liquids through a three-stage water removal process.  In particular for this project, we found that direct contact evaporation through the use of "microbubbles" is an excellent means of removing the majority of the water.   This approach is energy efficient and is gentle to avoid degrading the ionic liquid solvents even after many cycles of use.  The yarn wash solutions were passed over the surface of a porous sintered stainless steel sparger plate in a thin layer (~ 1/8") while hot air (~120&deg;C) was bubbled through the solution.   The hot air bubbles quickly evaporate water (at the surface of the bubble) but, because they are so small, the solution itself doesn?t heat up &ndash; in fact, because of evaporative cooling, the solution stays quite cool (~35&deg;C), while in residence on the sparger plate.   During the project, we found that water content of the wash solutions could be dropped from &gt;90% down to ~25% in a single pass over the direct contact evaporator &ndash; all with very little heating to the solution itself.  The project work has also showed that the final stages of water removal were best conducted in two separate passes through a wiped film evaporator.   One pass was configured for water recovery (using the condensers); the other pass was configured for maximum ionic liquid dehydration.   Using these two successive passes allowed for the best machine utilization in contrast to trying to remove the remaining water in a single pass under less-ideal conditions.  Based on this project, we have found ionic liquid recovery methodologies for dilute aqueous solutions that are energy efficient, impart low-levels of thermal history to the ionic liquid solvent during bulk water removal, and require lower capital expenditure than competing methods.   These methods support the goal of &gt;99% solvent recovery from the yarn wash solution and thus enable the cost-efficient scale-up of NFW manufacturing and meets major industry needs.  For example, customer interviews reveal that garment manufacturers, brands, and apparel industry experts agree that there is a pressing need for the textile industry to greatly improve sustainability and material circularity.  One of the primary technical solutions that has been lagging is a cost effective means to recycle and reuse natural fibers (e.g., both post-industrial and post-consumer cotton), while maintaining good strength and abrasion resistance.  Yarns treated by NFW processes enable greatly increased recycled fiber content even while improving performance of conventional cotton yarns.   In context, and based on the results of this project, natural fiber welding has great potential to be a disruptive technology that simultaneously enables improved performance, sustainability, and circularity across the multi-trillion dollar per year textile industry.             Last Modified: 10/16/2018       Submitted by: Aaron Amstutz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
