<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: EAGER: The early evolution of lamp shells and relatives (brachiopods) using an integrated approach combining genomics and fossils</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>120249.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>120249</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Schneider</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cjschnei@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927920</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Lamp shells and relatives (brachiopods) are marine animals that are one of the world's oldest forms of multicellular organisms. Although no longer numerous today, brachiopod species were a dominant component of marine ecosystems 540-250 million years ago.  Because of their mineralized shells, brachiopods have a high chance of being preserved as fossils, and have one of the most complete fossil records of any animal group. This project aims to solve a long-standing debate regarding how different brachiopod groups are related to each other and to other animals. Living brachiopods from North America, Croatia, Japan, New Zealand, and several other localities around the world will be sampled for genetic material that will be used to reconstruct evolutionary relationships among brachiopods. These genetic data will then be combined with data from their rich fossil record to test whether rates of evolution were higher during the Cambrian period than during more recent time periods. Several workshops will be organized to train a new generation of early career scientists in a diversity of genomic and paleontological methods. This project will also develop new instructional videos and accompanying lesson plans designed to teach high school science students how to build earth science content from a biological foundation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Brachiopods are amongst the first mineralized metazoans to appear in the fossil record during the Cambrian, yet agreement about the phylogenetic relationships among these early forms is still unknown. While the brachiopod fossil record will ultimately be key to determining character homology and polarity during the evolution of the distinctive brachiopod body plan, correctly reading this record has been difficult due to disagreement about relationships among the living clades. This project will use an integrated approach to understand the phylogeny of brachiopods and macroevolutionary patterns of early animal evolution. First, a widespread fieldwork campaign will collect brachiopod specimens suitable for high-quality RNA extraction and transcriptome sequencing. These data will form the basis for the heart of this study: the first phylogenomic study of brachiopods, which will result in a robust phylogenetic framework for the modern clades. Second, a comprehensive morphological database for living and fossil brachiopods will be constructed and calibrated using a molecular clock. These molecular and morphological data sources will be combined to test hypotheses of morphological and molecular evolution during the rapid diversification of form during the Cambrian radiation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1747731</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
<LastName>Sperling</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erik A Sperling</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>esper@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507232300</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000688515</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943054124</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[450 Serra Mall, Building 320]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7374</Code>
<Text>Systematics &amp; Biodiversity Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~120249</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>If one were able to walk along the seashore hundreds of millions of years ago, the beach would have been covered not by the shells of clams, but rather by brachiopods. This group (sometimes colloquially known as &lsquo;lamp shells&rsquo;) look superficially like clams in terms of having two bivalved shells, but they developed these shells independently. Some brachiopods make shells of calcium phosphate, like our bones, whereas others developed shells of calcium carbonate, or calcite, like clam shells. Determining how these shells and other characteristics of the brachiopod body plan evolved requires, first and foremost, understanding the evolutionary relationships within the group. Currently, it is not clear what other phylum brachiopods are most closely related to, whether phoronids are nested within brachiopods, or whether the brachiopods with calcium carbonate shells form a single evolutionary group. One of the best methods to generate such evolutionary histories (a phylogeny) is by comparing the genetic sequences from hundreds or thousands of individual genes (a &lsquo;phylogenomic&rsquo; approach). Although brachiopods were far more common in the geologic past than they are today, more than 300 brachiopod species are still living, and the goal of this project was to conduct the first phylogenomic analysis of living brachiopods.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Using specimens collected from the United States, Canada, Japan, Spain, Panama, and Antarctica, we sequenced the transcriptomes of brachiopods and their relatives and analyzed their relationships. This included the first transcriptomic data from many higher-level brachiopod groups such as the discinids. We found that brachiopods are a natural evolutionary group. Brachiopods are most closely related to Phoronida + Bryozoa. Within the brachiopods, the phosphatic-shelled brachiopods (lingulids and discinids) are nested within the brachiopods with calcitic shells (craniids and rhynchonelliforms). This implies either multiple transitions from phosphatic shells to calcitic shells, or a single transition from calcite to phosphate in the linguliform brachiopods. In either case, such mineralogical transitions in shell type are unknown in any other phylum. We further established the monophyly of many higher-level clades within Brachiopoda (for instance Lingulida) and determined higher level relationships within the articulate brachiopods (Terebratulidina sister to Thecideida + Terebratellidina).</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Beyond understanding evolutionary relationships, this project aimed to help train a new generation of evolutionary researchers. The history of evolution is written in two records&mdash;in stone in the fossil record, and in the genes of living organisms. Until recently, the study of these two records has been disconnected, and even contentious, yielding an incomplete view of the history of life. This project trained multiple early-career researchers (one post-doctoral scholar and two undergraduate students) to be comfortable and adept with both records. To further communication between paleontologists and modern biologists, we organized major symposia at both biology and geology conferences that included multiple researchers from both spheres, with a focus on a diverse speaker list and early-career researchers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/07/2021<br>      Modified by: Erik&nbsp;A&nbsp;Sperling</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ If one were able to walk along the seashore hundreds of millions of years ago, the beach would have been covered not by the shells of clams, but rather by brachiopods. This group (sometimes colloquially known as ‘lamp shells’) look superficially like clams in terms of having two bivalved shells, but they developed these shells independently. Some brachiopods make shells of calcium phosphate, like our bones, whereas others developed shells of calcium carbonate, or calcite, like clam shells. Determining how these shells and other characteristics of the brachiopod body plan evolved requires, first and foremost, understanding the evolutionary relationships within the group. Currently, it is not clear what other phylum brachiopods are most closely related to, whether phoronids are nested within brachiopods, or whether the brachiopods with calcium carbonate shells form a single evolutionary group. One of the best methods to generate such evolutionary histories (a phylogeny) is by comparing the genetic sequences from hundreds or thousands of individual genes (a ‘phylogenomic’ approach). Although brachiopods were far more common in the geologic past than they are today, more than 300 brachiopod species are still living, and the goal of this project was to conduct the first phylogenomic analysis of living brachiopods.              Using specimens collected from the United States, Canada, Japan, Spain, Panama, and Antarctica, we sequenced the transcriptomes of brachiopods and their relatives and analyzed their relationships. This included the first transcriptomic data from many higher-level brachiopod groups such as the discinids. We found that brachiopods are a natural evolutionary group. Brachiopods are most closely related to Phoronida + Bryozoa. Within the brachiopods, the phosphatic-shelled brachiopods (lingulids and discinids) are nested within the brachiopods with calcitic shells (craniids and rhynchonelliforms). This implies either multiple transitions from phosphatic shells to calcitic shells, or a single transition from calcite to phosphate in the linguliform brachiopods. In either case, such mineralogical transitions in shell type are unknown in any other phylum. We further established the monophyly of many higher-level clades within Brachiopoda (for instance Lingulida) and determined higher level relationships within the articulate brachiopods (Terebratulidina sister to Thecideida + Terebratellidina).              Beyond understanding evolutionary relationships, this project aimed to help train a new generation of evolutionary researchers. The history of evolution is written in two records&mdash;in stone in the fossil record, and in the genes of living organisms. Until recently, the study of these two records has been disconnected, and even contentious, yielding an incomplete view of the history of life. This project trained multiple early-career researchers (one post-doctoral scholar and two undergraduate students) to be comfortable and adept with both records. To further communication between paleontologists and modern biologists, we organized major symposia at both biology and geology conferences that included multiple researchers from both spheres, with a focus on a diverse speaker list and early-career researchers.          Last Modified: 01/07/2021       Submitted by: Erik A Sperling]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
