<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>USENIX ATC'17 student travel grants</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marilyn McClure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmcclure@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal requests funding to assist 20 US-based graduate students to attend the 2017 USENIX Annual Technical Conference (USENIX ATC 2017). USENIX ATC is the premier forum for advanced professionals from academic and industrial backgrounds to meet and discuss the latest research in systems software. USENIX ATC 2017 will be held in Santa Clara, CA, from July 12-14, 2017. The conference will consist of three days of the ATC 3-day technical program. Co-located workshops and symposiums include HotStorage 2017, HotCloud 2017, and SOUPS 2017. Other activities include industry talks, a poster session, Birds-of-a-Feather (BoF) sessions and more. In addition to attending the conference events, students receiving assistance may serve as scribes for the conference sessions to write summaries for a later issue of ;login: magazine, will be invited to attend the student Birds-of-a-Feather session to interact with senior members of the research community specifically interested in meeting students in a casual and informal atmosphere, and will be strongly encouraged to present posters and works-in-progress as part of the selection process.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference focuses on the computer systems, and brings together professionals from academic and industrial backgrounds.  It provides students with the opportunity to interact with more senior researchers in the field and exposes students to leading-edge work in the field.  The conference emphasizes innovative novel research. Attendance offers many opportunities for students to meet, interact, and exchange ideas in an informal atmosphere. Participation in USENIX ATC 2017 and similar conferences is a valuable and important part of the graduate school experience. The support requested in this proposal will enable the participation of students who would otherwise be unable to attend ATC.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1748280</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dilma</FirstName>
<LastName>Da Silva</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dilma Da Silva</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dilma@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9794587617</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000695299</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>847205572</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Sta</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433112</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Tamu 3112 - Office 305B]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>USENIX ATC gathers researchers from across the networking and systems community -- including computer networking, distributed systems, and operating systems -- to foster cross-disciplinary approaches and to address shared research challenges. The students supported by this award benefited from this cross-disciplinary emphasis.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Participation in ATC 2017 and similar conferences is a valuable and important part of the graduate school experience. It provides students with the opportunity to interact with more senior researchers in the field and exposes students to leading-edge work in the field. It also enables students to expand their networking of contacts, a valuable asset both during their research activities &ndash; as they have access to expertise not available in their home institutions &ndash; but also later on, when they enter the job market. The support requested in this proposal made possible the participation of 19 students who would otherwise be unable to attend.</p> <p>USENIX received 58 grant applications from students and awarded 44 grants. The NSF funds of $20,000 covered 19 of these grants, and all those awardees were enrolled at U.S. universities. USENIX appreciates the continued financial support from the NSF, which, for the conference, allowed us to grant awards to many more qualified applicants than we would have been able to otherwise. There were 312 total attendees at USENIX ATC &lsquo;17. Of these, the majority were from the U.S. Non-U.S. attendees came from Australia, Austria, Belgium, Brazil, Canada, China, France, Germany, Greece, Hong Kong, India, Israel, Japan, Netherlands, Portugal, Singapore, South Korea, Switzerland, Taiwan, and the United Kingdom.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/04/2018<br>      Modified by: Dilma&nbsp;Da Silva</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1748280/1748280_10510374_1528088045695_ATC17_GrantRecipients--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1748280/1748280_10510374_1528088045695_ATC17_GrantRecipients--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Group Picture - Travel Grant Recipients"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1748280/1748280_10510374_1528088045695_ATC17_GrantRecipients--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Group Picture - Travel Grant Recipients"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Group Picture - NSF Travel Grant Recipients for participation at the USENIX ATC'17 conference.</div> <div class="imageCredit">USENIX ASSOCIATION</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dilma&nbsp;Da Silva</div> <div class="imageTitle">Group Picture - Travel Grant Recipients</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:  USENIX ATC gathers researchers from across the networking and systems community -- including computer networking, distributed systems, and operating systems -- to foster cross-disciplinary approaches and to address shared research challenges. The students supported by this award benefited from this cross-disciplinary emphasis.     Broader Impacts:     Participation in ATC 2017 and similar conferences is a valuable and important part of the graduate school experience. It provides students with the opportunity to interact with more senior researchers in the field and exposes students to leading-edge work in the field. It also enables students to expand their networking of contacts, a valuable asset both during their research activities &ndash; as they have access to expertise not available in their home institutions &ndash; but also later on, when they enter the job market. The support requested in this proposal made possible the participation of 19 students who would otherwise be unable to attend.  USENIX received 58 grant applications from students and awarded 44 grants. The NSF funds of $20,000 covered 19 of these grants, and all those awardees were enrolled at U.S. universities. USENIX appreciates the continued financial support from the NSF, which, for the conference, allowed us to grant awards to many more qualified applicants than we would have been able to otherwise. There were 312 total attendees at USENIX ATC ?17. Of these, the majority were from the U.S. Non-U.S. attendees came from Australia, Austria, Belgium, Brazil, Canada, China, France, Germany, Greece, Hong Kong, India, Israel, Japan, Netherlands, Portugal, Singapore, South Korea, Switzerland, Taiwan, and the United Kingdom.          Last Modified: 06/04/2018       Submitted by: Dilma Da Silva]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
