<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Computational systems to deliver proper injectable treatments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>cindy walkerpeach</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is that it will potentially reduce fatal errors associated with compounded sterile preparations (CSP).  This will save lives and save money by preventing dose errors and wastage of costly medications and accessories when CSP's are incorrectly made. This I-Corps project will also explore similar problems that can also have life threatening consequences. The project will help to discern how various types of errors encountered in industrial processes can be minimized by integrating technology and human intervention at various workplaces. The product will help to gain understanding about how machines and people interact so as to design better workflow practices related to the CSP preparation and other relevant health care/industrial processes. The design of the technology allows usage in virtual simulation centers and other educational settings to train technical personnel, students, and professionals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project involves a computational decision support system (CDSS) product that was developed to address severe shortcomings in compounded sterile preparations (CSP).  Current procedures can result in fatal errors, inappropriate techniques, and noncompliance issues.  The first feature of the CDSS is an audio-visual interface for the compounding technician to identify and pick the correct materials and accessories to prepare a CSP. The second feature of the CDSS tracks, monitors, and evaluates the methods used by a technician compounding the injectable medication through image and video processing. The third feature of the CDSS checks and confirms the volume of a liquid injection contained in a syringe. The CDSS product can digitally document all the steps during this process enabling real time feedback during compounding so that errors can be corrected immediately. The technology also records the techniques used during compounding to ensure that proper procedures were followed according to regulatory guidelines. The CDSS thus provides timely warnings and real time feedback during preparation of a CSP and documents all aspects of the process that can be fully integrated with quality assurance (QA) programs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1749053</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jerry</FirstName>
<LastName>Nesamony</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jerry Nesamony</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jerry.nesamony@utoledo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4193831938</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000569824</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Toledo Health Science Campus</Name>
<CityName>Toledo</CityName>
<ZipCode>436142595</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4193834252</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3000 Arlington Ave.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>807418939</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TOLEDO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>051623734</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Toledo Health Science Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Toledo</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>436142595</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3000 Arlington Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project explored commercialization of a new computational decision support system (CDSS) developed for implementation in intravenous fluids (IV fluids also referred to as compounded sterile preparations or CSP's) compounding clean rooms in hospitals, pharmacies, and similar healthcare settings. As part of this project our NSF ICORPS team performed 212 interviews. These interviews were done with personnel involved in the IV fluids preparation and dispensing process and included regulatory personnel, regional and local leadership within large, medium, and small hospitals and hospital systems across the US such as VP's, COO's, Directors, and Managers, pharmacists, nurses, and pharmacy technicians. Our team also met and interviewed software engineers, technical support personnel, and marketing personnel at companies that have developed and launched products to address concerns, problems and issues in the area of CSP's.&nbsp;The interviews performed during this project&nbsp;created a thorough understanding about the needs of the industry, the most common and important problems and issues in the industry, and provided insights into the approaches that will best address the issues of the industry at this time.</p> <p>The project led us to conclude that the CDSS developed in the PI's lab is much needed in the industry and that it has the potential to be fully developed into a beta prototype. Based on our findings from the ICORPS project we performed preliminary prototype development. It is our conviction that our technology will reduce fatal errors related to CSP's thereby saving lives. The product will also help to document the CSP preparation process to meet regulatory requirements in the industry.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/22/2019<br>      Modified by: Jerry&nbsp;Nesamony</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project explored commercialization of a new computational decision support system (CDSS) developed for implementation in intravenous fluids (IV fluids also referred to as compounded sterile preparations or CSP's) compounding clean rooms in hospitals, pharmacies, and similar healthcare settings. As part of this project our NSF ICORPS team performed 212 interviews. These interviews were done with personnel involved in the IV fluids preparation and dispensing process and included regulatory personnel, regional and local leadership within large, medium, and small hospitals and hospital systems across the US such as VP's, COO's, Directors, and Managers, pharmacists, nurses, and pharmacy technicians. Our team also met and interviewed software engineers, technical support personnel, and marketing personnel at companies that have developed and launched products to address concerns, problems and issues in the area of CSP's. The interviews performed during this project created a thorough understanding about the needs of the industry, the most common and important problems and issues in the industry, and provided insights into the approaches that will best address the issues of the industry at this time.  The project led us to conclude that the CDSS developed in the PI's lab is much needed in the industry and that it has the potential to be fully developed into a beta prototype. Based on our findings from the ICORPS project we performed preliminary prototype development. It is our conviction that our technology will reduce fatal errors related to CSP's thereby saving lives. The product will also help to document the CSP preparation process to meet regulatory requirements in the industry.       Last Modified: 01/22/2019       Submitted by: Jerry Nesamony]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
