<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER:  Advancing High-Efficiency Nanoscale Antiferromagnetic Spintronics with Two-Dimensional Half Metals</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lawrence Goldberg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lgoldber@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928339</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Antiferromagnets hold promise in spintronics, due to the unique advantages over ferromagnets, such as high phase transition temperatures and null stray field. These characteristics make antiferromagnet appealing for high-density integrated devices, because each magnetic bit is robust against thermal and environmental magnetic field perturbation, and adjacent bits does not interfere mutually. However, zero-magnetization, an intrinsic attribute of antiferromagnet, usually is considered to be a primary factor limiting its applications. Despite of zero-magnetization, the Fermi surface electrons can be 100% spin-polarized, highly desirable for high-efficiency spintronic devices. Through rational material design of antiferromagnetic half metals, a novel type of spin field effect transistor can be realized. The work will fundamentally advance the nanoscale spintronics and the applications in information processing and storage. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project supports the study of a novel type of two-dimensional materials, antiferromagnetic half metals, and the development of spin field effect transistors. The study can fundamentally impact the state of the art spintronics and the related applications in information processing and storage. This work would also provide an excellent platform for education activities. Such an interdisciplinary research brings together researchers from material scientists, physicists, and electronic engineers. It requires concerted efforts to design and synthesize the promising antiferromagnetic materials, fabricate nanoscale transistors, and measure and optimize the device performance.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1753380</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiang Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xzhang@me.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106434978</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000309344</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947201740</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5130 Etcheverry Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7681</Code>
<Text>ENG NNI Special Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">Outcome summary: Combining device physics with material physics and processing,<span class="s1"> </span>this research was devoted to the exploration of a novel type of two-dimensional (2D) materials, antiferromagnetic half metals, which hold promise for future spintronics. The researchers in the team worked closely and successfully resulted in the development of platform of two-dimensional magnetic van der Waals crystals for the design and control of antiferromagnets bestowed with new spin properties. For example, we have designed the bilayer A-type antiferromagnetic materials leading to 100% spin-polarized carriers possible. We have achieved efficient electric control of single spin at quantum level enabling high-performance single photon detectors. We have achieved the switchable valley polarization and multiferroic properties in 2D materials enabling<span class="s2"> </span>efficient spintronic devices. The study leads to the fundamental advancement of nanoscale spintronics and the applications for next-generation information processing, storage and communications.</p> <p class="p1">Intellectual Merit: Developing miniatured spintronic structures and devices requires the precise knowledge and delicate control of magnetic properties of materials in reduced dimensions. Two-dimensional magnetic van der Waals crystals, owing to the high crystallinity and atomic thinness and flatness, innately eliminate the challenges associated with the conventional thin-film preparation process, in which extrinsic defect or surface states and spurious magnetic anisotropies would be otherwise inevitable. Given the fact that the abundance of antiferromagnetic crystals with generally higher magnetic order temperatures than ferromagnetic crystals, as well as the robustness against environmental magnetic field perturbation and null stray fields, two-dimensional antiferromagnets would be significant in both fundamental physics and technological applications.<span class="s1"> </span>The exploration of high spin material and interlayer magnetoelectric effect at 2D level opens a door to low-dimensional magnetoelectric and spintronic physics and applications.<span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1">Broader Impacts: The outcomes of this project result from a balanced synergy between researchers from material scientists, physicists, and electric engineers. The concerted efforts in design, synthesis, fabrication, and measurement was organized to benefit from the skillsets of the different stakeholders, and the constant interaction between coworkers ensured a mutual knowledge transfer. The study can fundamentally impact the state of the art spintronics and the related applications in information processing and storage. The formation of undergraduate and graduate students was central in this project, and postdoc were largely involved into this educational aspect. Last, to ensure the sustainability of the project and its continuity, the experimental and theoretical platforms developed have been conceived to be transfer to further investigations in novel 2D magnetic materials. <span>&nbsp; &nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/04/2020<br>      Modified by: Xiang&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Outcome summary: Combining device physics with material physics and processing, this research was devoted to the exploration of a novel type of two-dimensional (2D) materials, antiferromagnetic half metals, which hold promise for future spintronics. The researchers in the team worked closely and successfully resulted in the development of platform of two-dimensional magnetic van der Waals crystals for the design and control of antiferromagnets bestowed with new spin properties. For example, we have designed the bilayer A-type antiferromagnetic materials leading to 100% spin-polarized carriers possible. We have achieved efficient electric control of single spin at quantum level enabling high-performance single photon detectors. We have achieved the switchable valley polarization and multiferroic properties in 2D materials enabling efficient spintronic devices. The study leads to the fundamental advancement of nanoscale spintronics and the applications for next-generation information processing, storage and communications. Intellectual Merit: Developing miniatured spintronic structures and devices requires the precise knowledge and delicate control of magnetic properties of materials in reduced dimensions. Two-dimensional magnetic van der Waals crystals, owing to the high crystallinity and atomic thinness and flatness, innately eliminate the challenges associated with the conventional thin-film preparation process, in which extrinsic defect or surface states and spurious magnetic anisotropies would be otherwise inevitable. Given the fact that the abundance of antiferromagnetic crystals with generally higher magnetic order temperatures than ferromagnetic crystals, as well as the robustness against environmental magnetic field perturbation and null stray fields, two-dimensional antiferromagnets would be significant in both fundamental physics and technological applications. The exploration of high spin material and interlayer magnetoelectric effect at 2D level opens a door to low-dimensional magnetoelectric and spintronic physics and applications.  Broader Impacts: The outcomes of this project result from a balanced synergy between researchers from material scientists, physicists, and electric engineers. The concerted efforts in design, synthesis, fabrication, and measurement was organized to benefit from the skillsets of the different stakeholders, and the constant interaction between coworkers ensured a mutual knowledge transfer. The study can fundamentally impact the state of the art spintronics and the related applications in information processing and storage. The formation of undergraduate and graduate students was central in this project, and postdoc were largely involved into this educational aspect. Last, to ensure the sustainability of the project and its continuity, the experimental and theoretical platforms developed have been conceived to be transfer to further investigations in novel 2D magnetic materials.              Last Modified: 06/04/2020       Submitted by: Xiang Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
