<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>TWC: Small: Collaborative: Secure Data Charging Architecture for Mobile Devices in 3G/4G Cellular Networks: Vulnerabilities and Solutions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/25/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>78585.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>78585</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Phillip Regalia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pregalia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922981</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Wireless cellular networks serve as an essential cyber-infrastructure for mobile users. Unlike the Internet, cellular networks have adopted usage-based charging, rather than the simpler flat-rate charging. Data-plan subscribers have to pay their data bills based on the consumed traffic volume in 3G/4G networks. Although this metered charging system has been operational and generally successful for years, the security study of such a system remains largely unaddressed. The objective of this research is to investigate the insecurity aspects of large-scale cellular network infrastructures, identify their security loopholes, sketch novel attacks that exploit such loopholes, devise defenses that protect from such attacks, and validate the attacks and the defenses via real experiments in operational carriers. The proposed study helps us to better understand how various forms of vulnerabilities exhibit in the cellular system, open new venue for secure system design and operations, and refine the networking design that makes both the infrastructure and the user devices more resilient against malicious threats.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By addressing the key security issues of mobile data charging, the proposed research helps to protect the multi-trillion dollar network operations. It not only secures revenues of global cellular operators, but also protects the monetary rights of billions of mobile users. The proposed solutions will help to renovate the existing network infrastructure, and shape the upcoming 5G cellular technology in its standardization. It will also train a new generation of engineers and students in this field. The PIs will interact closely with industry for possible technology transfer.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/03/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/03/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1753500</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chunyi</FirstName>
<LastName>Peng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chunyi Peng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chunyi@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142920055</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000652380</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072107</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[305 N. University Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~78585</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project has investigated security issues in mobile data charging, which is an essential component in operational cellular networks. Throughout this project, we have successfully identified security loopholes in large-scale cellular network infrastructure, sketched novel attacks that exploit such loopholes, devised defenses that protect from such attacks, and validated the attacks and the defenses via real experiments in operational carriers. Our study not only helps us to better understand how various forms of vulnerabilities exhibit in the cellular network system, open new venue for secure system design and operations, but also refine the networking design that makes both the infrastructure and the user devices more resilient against malicious threats.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We summarize our main outcomes in two aspects.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> In this project, we have made three key technical contributions. First, we have systematically disclosed security loopholes from both the technology and the practice. We have shown that all components in mobile data charging, i.e., authentication, authorization, and (volume) accounting (AAA), might be breached in technology and operation. All currently deployed defense measures failed to protect. Second, we have disclosed diversified root causes and developed novel design guidelines to secure mobile data charging. We have shown that both cellular networks and the Internet design fundamentals share the blame. Open-looped operation and lack of cross-layer secure binding result in the disclosed loopholes on the cellular side, while the IP-push data delivery and</p> <p>lack of source address verification further aggravates them on the Internet side. Given these lessons, we further devise three security guidelines of cross-layer security binding, coordinated control-plane and data-plane security operations, and infrastructure-assisted end-user feedback. Third, we have extended our study from volume-based charging models to other charging models for Internet of Things (IoTs) and voice calls. Our results have resulted in six papers: CCS&rsquo;14, CCS&rsquo;15, CCS&rsquo;16, CNS&rsquo;18, MobiCom&rsquo;18 and INFOCOM&rsquo;19.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:&nbsp; </strong>The results of this project help to both secure the multi-trillion revenue of global operators and protect the rights of billions of mobile users. The immediate adoption of our research results by US carriers has quickly fixed these vulnerabilities and protected US carriers and their mobile users from real threats (e.g., free data access attacks and overcharging attacks) and have addressed big social concerns on time. The insights gained from this project may shed lights on securing other mobile Internet systems. They together offer a transformative approach to trustworthy data charging system in cellular networks, which would not only renovate the essential cellular infrastructure, but also reshape the role of end devices in the mobile Internet. Last but not least, this project helps training a new generation of students and workforce in cybersecurity, information and communication technology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/26/2019<br>      Modified by: Chunyi&nbsp;Peng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project has investigated security issues in mobile data charging, which is an essential component in operational cellular networks. Throughout this project, we have successfully identified security loopholes in large-scale cellular network infrastructure, sketched novel attacks that exploit such loopholes, devised defenses that protect from such attacks, and validated the attacks and the defenses via real experiments in operational carriers. Our study not only helps us to better understand how various forms of vulnerabilities exhibit in the cellular network system, open new venue for secure system design and operations, but also refine the networking design that makes both the infrastructure and the user devices more resilient against malicious threats.     We summarize our main outcomes in two aspects.  Intellectual Merit: In this project, we have made three key technical contributions. First, we have systematically disclosed security loopholes from both the technology and the practice. We have shown that all components in mobile data charging, i.e., authentication, authorization, and (volume) accounting (AAA), might be breached in technology and operation. All currently deployed defense measures failed to protect. Second, we have disclosed diversified root causes and developed novel design guidelines to secure mobile data charging. We have shown that both cellular networks and the Internet design fundamentals share the blame. Open-looped operation and lack of cross-layer secure binding result in the disclosed loopholes on the cellular side, while the IP-push data delivery and  lack of source address verification further aggravates them on the Internet side. Given these lessons, we further devise three security guidelines of cross-layer security binding, coordinated control-plane and data-plane security operations, and infrastructure-assisted end-user feedback. Third, we have extended our study from volume-based charging models to other charging models for Internet of Things (IoTs) and voice calls. Our results have resulted in six papers: CCS?14, CCS?15, CCS?16, CNS?18, MobiCom?18 and INFOCOM?19.  Broader Impacts:  The results of this project help to both secure the multi-trillion revenue of global operators and protect the rights of billions of mobile users. The immediate adoption of our research results by US carriers has quickly fixed these vulnerabilities and protected US carriers and their mobile users from real threats (e.g., free data access attacks and overcharging attacks) and have addressed big social concerns on time. The insights gained from this project may shed lights on securing other mobile Internet systems. They together offer a transformative approach to trustworthy data charging system in cellular networks, which would not only renovate the essential cellular infrastructure, but also reshape the role of end devices in the mobile Internet. Last but not least, this project helps training a new generation of students and workforce in cybersecurity, information and communication technology.          Last Modified: 02/26/2019       Submitted by: Chunyi Peng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
