<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Gauge Theory on Manifolds with Special Holonomy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/13/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>152000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>152000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Gauge theory is a subject that originated at the interface of mathematics and high energy physics.  In special cases, gauge theory is believed to underlie the mathematical description of the universe; for example, the standard model for particle physics is a gauge theory in four dimensions.  The subject also has deep links with many areas of mathematics, including partial differential equations, representation theory, algebraic geometry, differential geometry and topology. However, most research in gauge theory and almost all applications so far have focused on dimensions two, three and four.   In this project, the PI intends to push the boundary of our understanding of gauge theory in higher dimensions.  The PI's results are expected to have wide implications for geometric analysis, because the fundamental system of equations that define gauge theory (the Yang-Mills equations) poses additional challenges, in terms of controlling the solutions, that are not present in lower dimensions.  The PI's work will also have impact through integrated research and training, as the PI plans to involve undergraduates in research opportunities related to his project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI's research project consists of three parts.  The first part of the project will extend this dictionary between gauge theory and complex algebraic geometry to the context of Hermitian-Yang Mills connections with singularities, and specifically understand the fine structure at the singularities in terms of the complex algebraic geometry of the corresponding reflexive sheaves. In the second part of this project, the PI will develop a deformation theory for a certain class of Yang-Mills connections called G2-instantons with one-dimensional singular set, and use this to construct concrete examples of singular G2-instantons from algebro-geometric input. The third part of the PI's research project will further explore the role that generalized Seiberg-Witten equations (specifically the ones discovered in joint work of Andriy Haydys and the PI) play in gauge theory in higher dimensions.  As alluded to above, the main obstacle to progress in gauge theory in higher dimension is our lack of understanding of the non-compactness issues arising from the fact that the Yang-Mills equations become super-critical starting in dimension five and leading to the formation of non-removable singularities and bubbling phenomena.  &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1754967</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Walpuski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Walpuski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>walpuski@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173559684</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000732882</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Landing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~49623</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~102377</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project resulted in 10 research articles. &nbsp;These are concerned with questions regarding (possibly singular) solutions to geometric differential equations inspired by physics and (putative) "counting Invariants" constructed out of these. More precisely, the work did address, in particular, the following questions:</p> <p>1. &nbsp;The Hermitian Yang-Mills equation and the extended Bogomolny equations are a kind of Maxwell equation defined on geometric objects defined in "complex space". &nbsp;These "complex objects" have close ties with algebra (more precisely: algebraic geometry). &nbsp;One can ask: does the algebra dictate the kind of singularities which appear? &nbsp;The PI's works with Jacob and with He establishes certain cases in which answer is affirmative.</p> <p>2. &nbsp;There are further versions of&nbsp;Maxwell's equation on spaces which arise not from the complex numbers, but from the octionions (the final step in the chain: reals, complex numbers, quaternions, octonions). &nbsp;These have been discovered by physicists in the 1980s. &nbsp;Since the work of Donaldson and Thomas in 1998, mathematicians were wondering if these equations can be used to construct "counting invariants". &nbsp;Similar invariants have surfaced since the 1980s and revolutionized many areas of geometry. &nbsp;In the PI's work prior to this grant, a connection between this question and certain monopole equations was discovered. &nbsp;The PIs work with Doan and Zhang is concerned with deepening this understanding. &nbsp;As a result:</p> <p>(a) We have a better understanding of how the monopole equations behave in families.</p> <p>(b) We know how to construct singular solutions by trying to count monopoles (possibly foreshadowing an analogous behaviour for the octonionic Maxwell equation).</p> <p>(c) We better understand how these monopoles can degenerate (the basis of the link to the octonionic Maxwell equation).</p> <p>(d) We have a detailed proposal for a counting theory involving monopoles and geometric subspaces (a degenerate form of solutions of the octonionic Maxwell equation).</p> <p>3. &nbsp;The final line of inquiry undertaken within this project regards pseudo-holomorphic curves/maps. &nbsp;These are (parametrized) one-dimensional geometric subobjects of complex spaces (and generalizations thereof). &nbsp;Pseudo-holomorphic curves play a central role in geometry since their introduction in 1985. &nbsp;The specific question the PI tried to understand was: how topologically complicated can pseudo-holomorphic curves be? &nbsp;More precisely: how large can the genus be? &nbsp;In work with Doan the PI was able to derive genus bounds in generic cases. &nbsp;In work with Doan and Ionel the PI obtained a genus bound for all cases, however, the bound is not on all pseudo-holomorphic curves but only those with so-called non-vanishing BPS contribution. &nbsp;This work proves the Gopakumar-Vafa finiteness conjecture.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/19/2021<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Walpuski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project resulted in 10 research articles.  These are concerned with questions regarding (possibly singular) solutions to geometric differential equations inspired by physics and (putative) "counting Invariants" constructed out of these. More precisely, the work did address, in particular, the following questions:  1.  The Hermitian Yang-Mills equation and the extended Bogomolny equations are a kind of Maxwell equation defined on geometric objects defined in "complex space".  These "complex objects" have close ties with algebra (more precisely: algebraic geometry).  One can ask: does the algebra dictate the kind of singularities which appear?  The PI's works with Jacob and with He establishes certain cases in which answer is affirmative.  2.  There are further versions of Maxwell's equation on spaces which arise not from the complex numbers, but from the octionions (the final step in the chain: reals, complex numbers, quaternions, octonions).  These have been discovered by physicists in the 1980s.  Since the work of Donaldson and Thomas in 1998, mathematicians were wondering if these equations can be used to construct "counting invariants".  Similar invariants have surfaced since the 1980s and revolutionized many areas of geometry.  In the PI's work prior to this grant, a connection between this question and certain monopole equations was discovered.  The PIs work with Doan and Zhang is concerned with deepening this understanding.  As a result:  (a) We have a better understanding of how the monopole equations behave in families.  (b) We know how to construct singular solutions by trying to count monopoles (possibly foreshadowing an analogous behaviour for the octonionic Maxwell equation).  (c) We better understand how these monopoles can degenerate (the basis of the link to the octonionic Maxwell equation).  (d) We have a detailed proposal for a counting theory involving monopoles and geometric subspaces (a degenerate form of solutions of the octonionic Maxwell equation).  3.  The final line of inquiry undertaken within this project regards pseudo-holomorphic curves/maps.  These are (parametrized) one-dimensional geometric subobjects of complex spaces (and generalizations thereof).  Pseudo-holomorphic curves play a central role in geometry since their introduction in 1985.  The specific question the PI tried to understand was: how topologically complicated can pseudo-holomorphic curves be?  More precisely: how large can the genus be?  In work with Doan the PI was able to derive genus bounds in generic cases.  In work with Doan and Ionel the PI obtained a genus bound for all cases, however, the bound is not on all pseudo-holomorphic curves but only those with so-called non-vanishing BPS contribution.  This work proves the Gopakumar-Vafa finiteness conjecture.       Last Modified: 07/19/2021       Submitted by: Thomas Walpuski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
