<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research in Economics: Social Comparisons in Peer Effects</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kgyimahb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927466</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding the sources of social conformity is important because it is a very common phenomenon that affects social and economic outcomes.  Economic models of conforming to social norms assume that people conform either because of material incentives or to avoid punishment.  This research project will use economic theory and laboratory experiments to study why people conform to social norms when there are no material incentives to do so or punishment for deviating from those norms. The theory is based on the idea that individuals want to judge themselves in a positive way but lack a direct way of evaluating themselves.  As a result, individuals look at the actions of their peers to form the positive image of themselves, allowing them to form a better image of themselves.  Comparing one?s behavior to their peer?s lead to a better understanding of social conformity that does not require material incentives or punishment.  The researchers will then conduct laboratory experiments to test this theory.  The results of this research project will provide an input into the formulation of policies to enhance social cohesion.  The project will support a doctoral dissertation research and therefore contributes to growth of US's economic research capital and global leadership in economics research.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Economic theories of social conformity based on sanctions, social signaling, or adherence to social norms cannot explain why there is conformity among those whose actions are not likely to be seen by others, nor do they address the environment in which peer effects may be strong.  This research project seeks to deepen understanding of why social conformity arises in the absence of material incentives with a unified theory and two experiments. The theory posits that individuals have an intrinsic desire to judge and evaluate themselves positively.  Lacking objective means of self-evaluation, individuals rely on social comparisons to better understand what their choices reveal about themselves.  By deriving behavioral conformity from self-image, the model establishes a scope for peer effects without observable incentives or the pressures of social stigma.  Two experiments are then conducted to test the predictions of this model.  The first experiment tests whether individuals follow a pattern of peer effects that is uniquely consistent with self-image evaluation.  The second experiment tests whether a noisier signal mitigates peer effects by garbling the information peer-behavior provides.  The effects of social interaction on individual decisions is quite broad and a better understanding of how self-evaluation through social comparisons drives social conformity will provide explanation of empirical observations of this phenomenon as well as provide policy makers with information as to when peer effects are likely to be strong.  The results of this research project have many broader impacts, not only from application to fields of economics, but also in areas of public policy, business, and education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/16/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/16/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1757246</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Sprenger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles Sprenger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>csprenger@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585349000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000556563</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/16/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seung-Keun</FirstName>
<LastName>Martinez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Seung-Keun Martinez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sem012@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8588227457</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000755297</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/16/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SAN DIEGO]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930508</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Dr. #0508]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>ECONOMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~24000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The economic scope of peer effects is vast. For example, previous work has documented that an individual's participation in retirement savings programs, effort at work, decision to invest in financial instruments, and participation in paternal leave are all directly related to the observed decisions of his peers, and that students' academic achievements covary with whom they share a classroom or dormitory. While material incentives for coordination and social learning can explain some instances of social conformity, researchers have documented myriad examples of the influence of social interactions not predicted by neo-classical theories.<br /><br />Intellectual Merit:<br />In this project we sought to further our understanding of why social conformity arises absent material incentives with two experiments unified by a single theory. We posited that individuals have an intrinsic desire to hold a high self esteem. That is, each person would like to perceive himself positively -- e.g. diligent, intelligent, charitable, et cetera. However, lacking a direct or objective means of self evaluation, individuals rely on social comparisons to better understand what their choices reveal about their own characters. The primary contributions of this theory are two-fold. First, by deriving behavioral conformity from self-esteem concerns we formally establish scope for peer effects without observable incentives or the pressures of social stigma. Second, our theory offers novel predictions on the environmental conditions that mediate when social conformity arises.</p> <p><br />We used these novel predictions to experimentally study the role of self signaling in social conformity. Since many theories of conformity predict the same basic pattern of behavior, empirically distinguishing between competing theories is notoriously difficult. Further, any attempt to disentangle self and social signaling faces significant challenges. Unless subjects are unaware that they are being observed, self and and social signaling motivations are often conflated. Our experiment attempted to circumvent these challenges by using novel social information interventions to manipulate participants' self-signaling inferences to produce patterns of behavior not predicted by previous theories on conformity.<br /><br />Broader Impact:<br />The importance of social interactions in individual decision making is undeniable. Not only do is it an essential part of how individuals learn to behave in uncertain environments, but we also observe behavioral conformity in the work place and in the classroom. A careful investigation of how self evaluation through social comparisons may drive social conformity could not only contribute to our understanding of the existing empirical and theoretical literature, but also provide researchers and policy makers with greater predictive power over when such peer effects are likely to take hold. Therefore, this project&nbsp; may broadly impact how policy makers predict when peer effects are likely to aid or undermine work-place and school practices. <br /><br />This project provides economic researchers a formal framework with which to evaluate or design social information interventions. It demonstrates that the promise of future social comparisons, not just the revelation of past social comparisons, may be a effective tool to encourage or curtail specific behaviors. Our project further provides an intuitive characterization of relative peers. That is, an individual decision maker's perception of how his extrinsic constraints compare to the extrinsic constraints of others will determine to whom he will conform on image-relevant decisions. This suggests that further studies on peer effects should carefully consider how individuals determine those who face similar extrinsic incentives and constraints. Understanding this could lead to more precise and effective social information interventions.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/21/2019<br>      Modified by: Charles&nbsp;Sprenger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The economic scope of peer effects is vast. For example, previous work has documented that an individual's participation in retirement savings programs, effort at work, decision to invest in financial instruments, and participation in paternal leave are all directly related to the observed decisions of his peers, and that students' academic achievements covary with whom they share a classroom or dormitory. While material incentives for coordination and social learning can explain some instances of social conformity, researchers have documented myriad examples of the influence of social interactions not predicted by neo-classical theories.  Intellectual Merit: In this project we sought to further our understanding of why social conformity arises absent material incentives with two experiments unified by a single theory. We posited that individuals have an intrinsic desire to hold a high self esteem. That is, each person would like to perceive himself positively -- e.g. diligent, intelligent, charitable, et cetera. However, lacking a direct or objective means of self evaluation, individuals rely on social comparisons to better understand what their choices reveal about their own characters. The primary contributions of this theory are two-fold. First, by deriving behavioral conformity from self-esteem concerns we formally establish scope for peer effects without observable incentives or the pressures of social stigma. Second, our theory offers novel predictions on the environmental conditions that mediate when social conformity arises.   We used these novel predictions to experimentally study the role of self signaling in social conformity. Since many theories of conformity predict the same basic pattern of behavior, empirically distinguishing between competing theories is notoriously difficult. Further, any attempt to disentangle self and social signaling faces significant challenges. Unless subjects are unaware that they are being observed, self and and social signaling motivations are often conflated. Our experiment attempted to circumvent these challenges by using novel social information interventions to manipulate participants' self-signaling inferences to produce patterns of behavior not predicted by previous theories on conformity.  Broader Impact: The importance of social interactions in individual decision making is undeniable. Not only do is it an essential part of how individuals learn to behave in uncertain environments, but we also observe behavioral conformity in the work place and in the classroom. A careful investigation of how self evaluation through social comparisons may drive social conformity could not only contribute to our understanding of the existing empirical and theoretical literature, but also provide researchers and policy makers with greater predictive power over when such peer effects are likely to take hold. Therefore, this project  may broadly impact how policy makers predict when peer effects are likely to aid or undermine work-place and school practices.   This project provides economic researchers a formal framework with which to evaluate or design social information interventions. It demonstrates that the promise of future social comparisons, not just the revelation of past social comparisons, may be a effective tool to encourage or curtail specific behaviors. Our project further provides an intuitive characterization of relative peers. That is, an individual decision maker's perception of how his extrinsic constraints compare to the extrinsic constraints of others will determine to whom he will conform on image-relevant decisions. This suggests that further studies on peer effects should carefully consider how individuals determine those who face similar extrinsic incentives and constraints. Understanding this could lead to more precise and effective social information interventions.       Last Modified: 08/21/2019       Submitted by: Charles Sprenger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
