<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Support for the 2018 Gordon Research Conference on Environmental Sciences: Water  To held June 24-29, 2018 in Holderness, NH</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>40000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karl Rockne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>krockne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925356</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The conference will survey national and international priority research in the field of water quality. The science will focus on solutions to urgent societal challenges for water safety and ecosystem health. Scientific advances will include cutting edge research in separation technologies, water treatment, and systems engineering for the production of food, energy, and material resources, preventing exposures to hazardous chemicals, and remediation technologies. This proposal advances US national interests and societal benefits by facilitating communication of scientific progress towards improving water quality. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will survey priority and emerging issues across all aspects of the field of environmental water research focusing on challenges and the development of new technologies to meet these challenges. A focus will be on developments in separation technologies, water treatment, and systems engineering for the production of food, energy, and material resources. Other topics include mitigation strategies for climate change, exposures to hazardous chemicals, and remediation technologies. These topics will be explored in sessions that focus on the broad themes of: 1) Sustainable water and materials, 2) Chemical exposures and outcomes, 3) New technologies for water, 4) Community-engaged science and public policy. These are relevant to the program objectives of the Environmental Engineering program, as well as Environmental Chemistry program in MPS, and NSF initiatives in INFEWS, among others. This proposal advances the broader mission of NSF through direct societal benefits by facilitating communication of scientific progress towards improving water availability and quality, and protection of ecosystem health. Solutions to the problems require ideas and interactions among multiple disciplines to allow proper action and development of environmental policy. The conference will advance discovery while promoting teaching, training, and learning by offering a platform for graduate student and postdoctoral researchers to present their research and participate fully in the conference activities. The conference also provides a forum for interactions between senior scientists and students and broad participation of scientists from groups underrepresented in science and engineering. Assessment of the broader impacts will be performed via survey of participants at the conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/05/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1757459</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Arnold</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William A Arnold</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>arnol032@tc.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126258582</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000312042</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/05/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heileen</FirstName>
<LastName>Hsu-Kim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Heileen Hsu-Kim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hsukim@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196605109</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000211522</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/05/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075712877</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004Z</Code>
<Text>Innovations at the Nexus of Food-Energy-</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 2018 Gordon Research Conference on Environmental Sciences: Water featured a program of leading researchers whose work strives to improve aquatic resources and protect public health. Traditionally this Gordon Conference has featured the frontiers of water quality research, with an emphasis on contaminant fate and impacts. However, as the field has evolved and matured, water quality scientists and engineers are wondering: <em>How can we be more proactive? How is global change impacting water quality and resources? What is our role in a globalized society?</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>With these challenges in the environmental aquatic sciences, researchers are required to work at the intersections of traditional disciplines, especially as we strive to enrich our understanding of fundamental processes and develop solutions. For example, the production of food, energy, and material resources for the modern world relies upon new developments in separation technologies, water treatment, and systems engineering to meet the demand. The protection of water resources, particularly in areas vulnerable to global change, requires an understanding of chemical and biological phenomena from molecular to global scales. Exposures to hazardous chemicals can be mitigated by knowledge of human-environment interactions, and recent developments in new technologies could lead to opportunities to reduce exposures and remediate contaminated settings. The 2018 Environmental Science: Water GRC featured a program of thought-provoking research in the areas of sustainable water and material resources, molecular processes in aquatic systems, chemical exposures and health outcomes, and new technologies for water.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/08/2018<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;A&nbsp;Arnold</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 2018 Gordon Research Conference on Environmental Sciences: Water featured a program of leading researchers whose work strives to improve aquatic resources and protect public health. Traditionally this Gordon Conference has featured the frontiers of water quality research, with an emphasis on contaminant fate and impacts. However, as the field has evolved and matured, water quality scientists and engineers are wondering: How can we be more proactive? How is global change impacting water quality and resources? What is our role in a globalized society?     With these challenges in the environmental aquatic sciences, researchers are required to work at the intersections of traditional disciplines, especially as we strive to enrich our understanding of fundamental processes and develop solutions. For example, the production of food, energy, and material resources for the modern world relies upon new developments in separation technologies, water treatment, and systems engineering to meet the demand. The protection of water resources, particularly in areas vulnerable to global change, requires an understanding of chemical and biological phenomena from molecular to global scales. Exposures to hazardous chemicals can be mitigated by knowledge of human-environment interactions, and recent developments in new technologies could lead to opportunities to reduce exposures and remediate contaminated settings. The 2018 Environmental Science: Water GRC featured a program of thought-provoking research in the areas of sustainable water and material resources, molecular processes in aquatic systems, chemical exposures and health outcomes, and new technologies for water.          Last Modified: 11/08/2018       Submitted by: William A Arnold]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
