<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Preparing Equity-Minded Mathematics and Science Teachers to Work with Diverse Communities of Learners</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1199858.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1199858</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen Bergin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kbergin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925171</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Track 1 Scholarships and Stipends Noyce project at the College of William and Mary (WM) aims to meet a national need for talented STEM teachers who are prepared and committed to teaching diverse communities of students in high-need schools.  The project includes collaborations with six high needs school districts: Gloucester and New Kent Counties (rural); York and Williamsburg-James City Counties (suburban); and Newport News and Hampton (urban).  A major project goal is developing a new model to: (1) interest outstanding mathematics majors in teaching; (2) help students sustain an enduring commitment to STEM teaching; and (3) develop students' ability to connect effectively with diverse communities.  The project will work with the WM Office of Community Engagement to engage first- and second-year mathematics and science students in teaching activities and reflection.  Working with WM community engagement staff, prospective teachers will explore issues of fair access to skills in mathematics and science for all students.  These activities will expand preliminary research on factors that enhance the motivation of prospective teachers for STEM teaching.  Once recruited into the Noyce Program, Noyce scholars will take two project-specific courses.  The "How Students Learn" course will focus on how to teach learning skills and self-management.  The other course, a Practicum in High Need Schools, will use early visits to high-need schools to help Noyce Scholars understand how skilled STEM teachers can effectively support student success.  The project will also offer opportunities for experiences and courses in special education and teaching English language learners.  The project will supplement cultural competency preparation in the curriculum with activities focused on equity-mindedness and working with diverse communities.  Following placement of new STEM teachers in schools, a mentoring program will engage teachers in skill-building and problem-solving in their first years of teaching.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project intends to recruit and prepare 33 new teachers who are licensed in STEM disciplines.  STEM majors will be recruited from two pools: (1) Undergraduate STEM majors, including transfer students, who will gain licensure as undergraduates or through a fifth-year master's program; and (2) Post-baccalaureates in STEM fields who will complete a master's program in mathematics or science education.  Recruitment will focus on regional institutions, including those with high proportions of underrepresented minority students.  Prospective mathematics and science teachers will be supported in gaining certification in science teaching for grades 6-12, and in mathematics teaching for grades K-8 or 6-12.  Partners include six high-need school districts.  The project intends to continue to develop existing partnerships with high-need schools to prepare more cooperating teachers to supervise and mentor Noyce Scholars during student teaching. A key objective is to integrate the project's data in a published model that can inform other programs to improve recruitment and preparation of STEM teachers.  Through preparation of new STEM teachers and development of a model to initiate and sustain commitments to teaching in high-need schools, the project has the potential to support societal goals of effective preparation of teachers for diverse communities of learners.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1758419</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>R</FirstName>
<LastName>Macdonald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>R H Macdonald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rhmacd@wm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7572212443</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000418539</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Heideman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul D Heideman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pdheid@wm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7572212239</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000389472</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marguerite</FirstName>
<LastName>Mason</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marguerite M Mason</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mmmaso@wm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7572212327</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000305620</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Meredith</FirstName>
<LastName>Kier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Meredith Kier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mwkier@wm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7572212332</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000696900</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melody</FirstName>
<LastName>Porter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melody Porter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcporter@wm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7572213966</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000756247</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>College of William and Mary</Name>
<CityName>Williamsburg</CityName>
<ZipCode>231878795</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7572213966</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 8795]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>074762238</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLLEGE OF WILLIAM &amp; MARY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>074762238</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[College of William and Mary]]></Name>
<CityName>Williamsburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>231878795</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0418</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~1146725</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~53133</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
