<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBP: Conference: Broadening Participation and Building Bridges</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>39500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>39500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jacqueline Vadjunec</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support the conduct of the 2018 Race, Ethnicity, and Place (REP) conference.  REP is a biennial meeting that has brought together diverse groups of scholars to facilitate research on race and ethnicity in geography and has provided a critical gathering place of support and collaboration for underrepresented scholars.  REP will catalyze new activities focusing on geographic, racial, and ethnic dimensions of social science research.  More so than any other conference or community-wide activity in geography, REP explicitly brings together scholars who are members of underrepresented groups as well as scholars whose research involves the study of socioeconomic, cultural, and other dynamics within communities populated by people who are underrepresented in STEM fields.  REP also will involve scholars from sociology, anthropology, and other related fields.  REP will focus on building collaborative relationships among participating scholars to foster a broader range of activities that engage more students and other early-career professionals in STEM research.  As such, REP will provide a test-bed for advancing scholarship on race, ethnicity, and place that requires participants to engage in discussions about different epistemological approaches and issues that can hinder or advance scholarship on this topic.  Explicit efforts will be made to engage more scholars from underrepresented groups and to help them form stronger research networks to help enhance and improve their future capabilities.  Through explicit attention to building bridges across research approaches and by providing active, ongoing intergenerational mentoring, REP will encourage more effective research on racial and ethnic dimensions of social science research in geography and related fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Diversifying the involvement of individuals engaged in all types of work and activity remains a major challenge in higher education.  To directly address this challenge in geography and related fields, the 2018 REP conference will be held in mid-October at the Mexican American Cultural Center (MAC) in Austin, Texas.  The conference will integrate new participants through active recruitment and engagement; by designing strategic panels and keynotes to attract a broader audience, and by offering a post-conference mentoring and professional-development workshop for early-career faculty and advanced graduate students from underrepresented groups.  Special emphasis will be given to examining complex issues of race and ethnicity through cross-disciplinary collaborations that integrate a range of theoretical, ontological, epistemological, and methodological approaches across multiple scales of analysis.  This award will support early career researchers from underrepresented groups to participate in the 2018 REP Conference and thus integrate new generations of scholars into the meetings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/12/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/12/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1759657</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Torres</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebecca Torres</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rebecca.torres@austin.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124716424</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000546158</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Blue</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah Blue</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sblue@txstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5122452314</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000756766</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas State University - San Marcos</Name>
<CityName>San Marcos</CityName>
<ZipCode>786664616</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5122452314</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 University Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>074602368</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>101405814</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas State University - San Marcos]]></Name>
<CityName>San Marcos</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>786664684</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 University Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>35</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX35</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8050</Code>
<Text>Science of Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~39500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">The Race, Ethnicity, and Place (REP) Conference has served over fifteen years as an important focal point for academic research on issues of race and ethnicity as well as a critical gathering place of support and solidarity for underrepresented scholars in geography and other related disciplines. The objective of NSF support was to innovate and expand the scope of REP through: (1) broadening participation in the conference, (2) bridging cross-disciplinary divides in the study of race and ethnicity, and (3) promoting greater racial and ethnic diversity within the discipline of geography.</p> <p class="Default">The 9<sup>th</sup> bi-annual Race, Ethnicity, and Place Conference took place October 23-25, 2018 at the Emma S. Barrientos Mexican American Cultural Center in downtown Austin. The conference was a collaboration between the Texas State University, the University of Texas at Austin, the City of Austin and the National Science Foundation (NSF).</p> <p class="Default">The conference brought together over 235 participants, over half of whom were from groups historically underrepresented in academia. They were from twenty-six states and eight countries. The host institutions had very strong representation: 38 presenters from University of Texas at Austin and 40 presenters from Texas State. The conference began with a pre-conference Early Career Mentorship Workshop themed ?Surviving and Thriving in the Academy? that consisted of 27 early career scholars and 14 senior scholar mentors. The workshop included panels focused on achieving success at writing, research, and publishing, small breakout groups, a talk on finding and applying for grants by NSF Program Director, Dr. Tom Baerwald, and sessions on applying for tenure-track jobs and achieving tenure and promotion.</p> <p class="Default">The two other days of the conference involved 50 separate paper and panel sessions on topics as diverse as gentrification and community resilience, natural disaster recovery, diversity, inclusion and ethnic studies initiatives on college campuses, immigration and refugees, health disparities, human-environment interactions, criminalization and human rights, and cultural and ethnic identity. The conference also featured panels that allowed for in-depth discussion on topics such as teaching race and ethnicity, advancing women in geography, methodological and theoretical diversity in the discipline of geography, international field work, supporting historically black serving institutions, and more. Powerful keynote speakers concluded the conference days, with community leaders speaking on the controversy around confederate statue removal and name changes in Austin and across the U.S. South, the power of Latinx stories, and the history of farm worker organizing. All speakers spoke to the conference theme of ?Engaged Scholarship: Fostering Civil and Human Rights?.</p> <p class="Default">To achieve these objectives, we integrated new participants, designed strategic panels and keynotes, and offered a pre-conference mentoring and professional development workshop for early career faculty and advanced PhD students from underrepresented groups. The pre-conference mentorship workshop support and networking for diverse scholars created a productive forum for scholarly exchange and promoted diversity in the discipline of geography and related fields.</p> <p>Complex issues of race and ethnicity need cross-disciplinary collaboration that combines various theoretical, ontological, epistemological, and methodological approaches addressing the topic at multiple scales of analysis. The 2018 REP conference, together with the pre-conference workshop, broadened participation of scholars and put into conversation distinct research approaches to the study of race and ethnicity that rarely engage or intersect intellectually. This served as a catalyst for more synergetic research, and ultimately a deeper understanding of issues of race, ethnicity and diversity. Furthermore, promoting the increased diversity of scholars, particularly from underrepresent groups, will encourage the proliferation and quality of scholarship on these topics.&nbsp;</p> <p>Diversity remains a deep challenge in geography. The 2018 REP conference was part of the transformation in the discipline, joining a growing wave of efforts in recent years. Through building increased participation into the REP Conference and enhancing mentorship opportunities and early career resources for underrepresented scholars of color, the NSF funds supported a long-standing goal of increasing diversity in geography. The new sessions, speakers, and pre-conference mentoring workshop all served as a model for promoting diversity recruiting, support, retention, promotion, and success in the discipline and beyond. NSF funds expanded the opportunities to establish and sustain peer support networks among faculty and students through the REP Conference. These targeted efforts at increasing and strengthening resources available to underrepresented scholars supported faculty to be better mentors and provided guidance to departments in developing more effective diversity plans and actions in their home universities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/24/2019<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;Blue</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1759657/1759657_10534010_1574617134598_slide--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1759657/1759657_10534010_1574617134598_slide--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REP IX Conference Poster"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1759657/1759657_10534010_1574617134598_slide--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REP IX Conference Poster"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">IX Race, Ethnicity, and Place Conference Poster 2018</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ma?l LeNoc, Texas State University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sarah&nbsp;Blue</div> <div class="imageTitle">REP IX Conference Poster</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The Race, Ethnicity, and Place (REP) Conference has served over fifteen years as an important focal point for academic research on issues of race and ethnicity as well as a critical gathering place of support and solidarity for underrepresented scholars in geography and other related disciplines. The objective of NSF support was to innovate and expand the scope of REP through: (1) broadening participation in the conference, (2) bridging cross-disciplinary divides in the study of race and ethnicity, and (3) promoting greater racial and ethnic diversity within the discipline of geography. The 9th bi-annual Race, Ethnicity, and Place Conference took place October 23-25, 2018 at the Emma S. Barrientos Mexican American Cultural Center in downtown Austin. The conference was a collaboration between the Texas State University, the University of Texas at Austin, the City of Austin and the National Science Foundation (NSF). The conference brought together over 235 participants, over half of whom were from groups historically underrepresented in academia. They were from twenty-six states and eight countries. The host institutions had very strong representation: 38 presenters from University of Texas at Austin and 40 presenters from Texas State. The conference began with a pre-conference Early Career Mentorship Workshop themed ?Surviving and Thriving in the Academy? that consisted of 27 early career scholars and 14 senior scholar mentors. The workshop included panels focused on achieving success at writing, research, and publishing, small breakout groups, a talk on finding and applying for grants by NSF Program Director, Dr. Tom Baerwald, and sessions on applying for tenure-track jobs and achieving tenure and promotion. The two other days of the conference involved 50 separate paper and panel sessions on topics as diverse as gentrification and community resilience, natural disaster recovery, diversity, inclusion and ethnic studies initiatives on college campuses, immigration and refugees, health disparities, human-environment interactions, criminalization and human rights, and cultural and ethnic identity. The conference also featured panels that allowed for in-depth discussion on topics such as teaching race and ethnicity, advancing women in geography, methodological and theoretical diversity in the discipline of geography, international field work, supporting historically black serving institutions, and more. Powerful keynote speakers concluded the conference days, with community leaders speaking on the controversy around confederate statue removal and name changes in Austin and across the U.S. South, the power of Latinx stories, and the history of farm worker organizing. All speakers spoke to the conference theme of ?Engaged Scholarship: Fostering Civil and Human Rights?. To achieve these objectives, we integrated new participants, designed strategic panels and keynotes, and offered a pre-conference mentoring and professional development workshop for early career faculty and advanced PhD students from underrepresented groups. The pre-conference mentorship workshop support and networking for diverse scholars created a productive forum for scholarly exchange and promoted diversity in the discipline of geography and related fields.  Complex issues of race and ethnicity need cross-disciplinary collaboration that combines various theoretical, ontological, epistemological, and methodological approaches addressing the topic at multiple scales of analysis. The 2018 REP conference, together with the pre-conference workshop, broadened participation of scholars and put into conversation distinct research approaches to the study of race and ethnicity that rarely engage or intersect intellectually. This served as a catalyst for more synergetic research, and ultimately a deeper understanding of issues of race, ethnicity and diversity. Furthermore, promoting the increased diversity of scholars, particularly from underrepresent groups, will encourage the proliferation and quality of scholarship on these topics.   Diversity remains a deep challenge in geography. The 2018 REP conference was part of the transformation in the discipline, joining a growing wave of efforts in recent years. Through building increased participation into the REP Conference and enhancing mentorship opportunities and early career resources for underrepresented scholars of color, the NSF funds supported a long-standing goal of increasing diversity in geography. The new sessions, speakers, and pre-conference mentoring workshop all served as a model for promoting diversity recruiting, support, retention, promotion, and success in the discipline and beyond. NSF funds expanded the opportunities to establish and sustain peer support networks among faculty and students through the REP Conference. These targeted efforts at increasing and strengthening resources available to underrepresented scholars supported faculty to be better mentors and provided guidance to departments in developing more effective diversity plans and actions in their home universities.          Last Modified: 11/24/2019       Submitted by: Sarah Blue]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
