<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Low-cost Smart RF Sensor for Autonomous Floodwater Level Monitoring</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>41690.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>41690</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anthony Kuh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to experimentally investigate the efficacy and reliability of low-cost portable wireless radar sensors for floodwater monitoring in realistic environment by collecting real-time on-site data of receding floodwater at multiple locations after hurricane Harvey and Irma. The proposed automatic water monitoring solution is based on portable radio frequency sensors that can be quickly deployed and integrated into a wireless sensor framework. Compared with traditional water gauging technologies that are typically based on acoustic sensors, pressure sensors, or older float and shaft angle decoders, the proposed solution does not require contact with water and thus offers larger measurement range and robustness against biological buildup and corrosion. Compared with existing microwave technologies being investigated for water monitoring, the proposed solution features much lower cost and smaller hardware size taking advantage of advanced semiconductor technology, high-linearity demodulation, adaptive DC-tuning architecture, and embedded signal processing. Furthermore, the proposed system can operate with battery power and thus does not require continuous connection to powerlines, which could be vulnerable in the event of hurricanes. Field tests of monitoring receding water after hurricane flood and comparison with results from conventional measurements will validate the proposed approach. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If proven to be successful based on measurement in realistic environment, the proposed technology can be widely deployed as a sensor network in many urban, suburban, and rural communities to help government and homeowners automatically and accurately obtain real-time flood level information across a large region, without sending volunteers to dangerous areas for manual check. In addition to benefiting the national infrastructure, it will be valuable to many households for local flood monitoring and home protection. Furthermore, the big data collected from a network of such sensors will serve as a valuable resource for the understanding of the history, pathways, and extent of floodwater. It may enable strong interdisciplinary collaborative effort between researchers from electrical and coastal engineering and may result in transdisciplinary tools in sensor technology and coastal science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1760497</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Changzhi</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Changzhi Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>changzhi.li@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8067423533</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000545895</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas Tech University</Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8067423884</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>349 Administration Bldg</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041367053</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS TECH UNIVERSITY SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041367053</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas Tech University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>071Y</Code>
<Text>Hurricane Harvey 2017</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~41690</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project first experimentally investigated the feasibility of using low-cost portable wireless radar sensors for floodwater monitoring in realistic environment by collecting real-time onsite data of receding floodwater after hurricane Harvey. It further conducted design optimization, comparison and performance evaluation in controlled experiments for radar operating in different modes to achieve reliable water level monitoring.</p> <p>A 20-hour onsite experiment was first conducted on the Buffalo Bayou in Houston after hurricane Harvey hit Houston and caused severe damages. A DC-coupled 5.8-GHz interferometry radar was used to monitor the receding floodwater. A large set of data was collected and shared with interested researchers to study various algorithms in processing interferometry radar data for water level monitoring.</p> <p>Based on the field experiment in Houston, the research team identified several areas in hardware design and signal processing that could be further investigated to enhance the detection accuracy and robustness against environment noise. Therefore, a revised version of 5.8-GHz interferometry radar for water level monitoring was developed and tested at Texas Tech University. The capability of the interferometry radar system was evaluated through a series of experiments that typically lasted for a few hours. In these experiments, the radar was used to observe the water level in a barrel, which had water filled in and drained out at various speeds. The experimental results demonstrated that the developed portable radar system can achieve cm-level accuracy in tracking the change of water surface.</p> <p>To remove the error accumulated in interferometry mode operation, frequency-modulated continuous wave (FMCW) radar for water level monitoring is also studied. An FMCW radar was developed and mounted on top of the water barrel to observe the absolute distance between the water surface and the radar. The experimental result showed the measured absolute distance matched with the ground truth measured by a tape meter. Because the interferometry mode requires less resource in hardware control and signal processing, the team came up with a hybrid-mode operation solution. A hybrid-mode portable radar was developed and tested. The hybrid-mode aims to use interferometry detection for most of the time to track the water surface displacement, and periodically turn on the FMCW mode for calibration remove any error accumulated in interferometry detection.</p> <p>To resolve the challenge of clutter noise caused by environment, an advanced intermodulation radar system was also designed and tested. The intermodulation radar transmits two tones simultaneously and selectively detects the third-order intermodulation reflected by the target. Experimental results showed that the designed intermodulation radar can effectively detect small motion of nonlinear target while rejecting undesired reflections from environmental clutters that do not exhibit nonlinear properties. Such technology can be potentially used for background and clutter noise rejection in motion sensing applications. It has the potential to be used in water-level monitoring systems to reject undesired reflections and only track the motion of the water.</p> <p>During the project period, one PhD student was trained professionally on circuit design, radar signal processing, and testing. Two papers were published. Radar prototype devices were developed and shared with researchers in the Civil and Coastal Engineering Department at the University of Florida and installed on the Hudson river in New York to study low-cost radar-based wireless sensor network for water level monitoring. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The developed technology may be densely deployed to monitor regional water level at a low cost. It can be widely used as a sensor network in many urban, suburban, and rural areas to help government and homeowners automatically and accurately obtain real-time flood level information, avoiding sending people to dangerous areas for manual check. Furthermore, the big data collected from a network of such sensors may serve as a valuable resource for the understanding of the history, pathways, and extent of floodwater.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Changzhi&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project first experimentally investigated the feasibility of using low-cost portable wireless radar sensors for floodwater monitoring in realistic environment by collecting real-time onsite data of receding floodwater after hurricane Harvey. It further conducted design optimization, comparison and performance evaluation in controlled experiments for radar operating in different modes to achieve reliable water level monitoring.  A 20-hour onsite experiment was first conducted on the Buffalo Bayou in Houston after hurricane Harvey hit Houston and caused severe damages. A DC-coupled 5.8-GHz interferometry radar was used to monitor the receding floodwater. A large set of data was collected and shared with interested researchers to study various algorithms in processing interferometry radar data for water level monitoring.  Based on the field experiment in Houston, the research team identified several areas in hardware design and signal processing that could be further investigated to enhance the detection accuracy and robustness against environment noise. Therefore, a revised version of 5.8-GHz interferometry radar for water level monitoring was developed and tested at Texas Tech University. The capability of the interferometry radar system was evaluated through a series of experiments that typically lasted for a few hours. In these experiments, the radar was used to observe the water level in a barrel, which had water filled in and drained out at various speeds. The experimental results demonstrated that the developed portable radar system can achieve cm-level accuracy in tracking the change of water surface.  To remove the error accumulated in interferometry mode operation, frequency-modulated continuous wave (FMCW) radar for water level monitoring is also studied. An FMCW radar was developed and mounted on top of the water barrel to observe the absolute distance between the water surface and the radar. The experimental result showed the measured absolute distance matched with the ground truth measured by a tape meter. Because the interferometry mode requires less resource in hardware control and signal processing, the team came up with a hybrid-mode operation solution. A hybrid-mode portable radar was developed and tested. The hybrid-mode aims to use interferometry detection for most of the time to track the water surface displacement, and periodically turn on the FMCW mode for calibration remove any error accumulated in interferometry detection.  To resolve the challenge of clutter noise caused by environment, an advanced intermodulation radar system was also designed and tested. The intermodulation radar transmits two tones simultaneously and selectively detects the third-order intermodulation reflected by the target. Experimental results showed that the designed intermodulation radar can effectively detect small motion of nonlinear target while rejecting undesired reflections from environmental clutters that do not exhibit nonlinear properties. Such technology can be potentially used for background and clutter noise rejection in motion sensing applications. It has the potential to be used in water-level monitoring systems to reject undesired reflections and only track the motion of the water.  During the project period, one PhD student was trained professionally on circuit design, radar signal processing, and testing. Two papers were published. Radar prototype devices were developed and shared with researchers in the Civil and Coastal Engineering Department at the University of Florida and installed on the Hudson river in New York to study low-cost radar-based wireless sensor network for water level monitoring.     The developed technology may be densely deployed to monitor regional water level at a low cost. It can be widely used as a sensor network in many urban, suburban, and rural areas to help government and homeowners automatically and accurately obtain real-time flood level information, avoiding sending people to dangerous areas for manual check. Furthermore, the big data collected from a network of such sensors may serve as a valuable resource for the understanding of the history, pathways, and extent of floodwater.       Last Modified: 04/01/2019       Submitted by: Changzhi Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
