<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Rapid detection of pathogens using microfluidic dielectrophoresis and dielectric spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pamela McCauley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to advance microbiologists' ability to detect, characterize, and control microscopic organisms such as bacteria, fungi, and viruses. Collectively, the planet's microbiome makes up more than 80% of all living mass and it significantly impacts human health and activities. Some microorganisms are beneficial, providing useful industrial functions or therapeutic value; others can cause severe disease and disrupt industrial processes. Currently, microbiologists grow microorganisms in their laboratories to characterize molecular and cellular mechanisms related to replication, pathogenicity, therapeutic and industrial properties, and interactions with the host and the environment. These goals have proven successful in the generation of diagnostic tools, new therapies, and improving industrial processes. However, a vast proportion of microorganisms remain unable to be efficiently cultivated. Particularly in clinical diagnostics, the ability to detect pathogens accurately and in a timely manner has a direct impact in patient health. This project seeks to address this bottleneck by accelerating the time to detect and isolate microbes from clinical and industrial samples. It is anticipated that reducing the time required to analyze samples from days to a few hours will lead to significant improvements in clinical outcomes and industrial microbiology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project focuses on developing a miniaturized and disposable device that automatically performs sample processing and analysis to isolate and characterize bacteria. It features state-of-the-art microelectronic arrays embedded in microfluidic channels. The array generates electrical force fields having specific frequencies to selectively isolate microorganisms from background debris and other undesired cells present in clinical and industrial samples. Laboratory prototypes have demonstrated proof-of-principle for the isolation and detection subsystems. In the next phase of the technical development, these components will be integrated into a single device. This project will inform the specific design criteria and requirements for this next prototype through customer discovery work.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/01/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/01/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1760015</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nadim</FirstName>
<LastName>Ajami</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nadim Ajami</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nadimajami@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8325450132</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000757225</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Baylor College of Medicine</Name>
<CityName>HOUSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>770303411</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137981297</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ONE BAYLOR PLAZA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MS-310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>051113330</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BAYLOR COLLEGE OF MEDICINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>051113330</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Baylor College of Medicine]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770303411</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Baylor Plaza]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>With support from the National Science Foundation Innovation Corps award, our group conducted 350 customer interviews with hospital administrators, laboratory directors, technicians, and infectious diseases doctors in 25 different cities around the country to understand how blood stream infections are diagnosed and managed. We learned that a critical bottleneck in this process is the delay associated with pathogen detection and isolation. The gold-standard method is blood culture followed by biochemical characterization and antimicrobial susceptibility testing.&nbsp; Detecting the presence of microbes and providing antimicrobial susceptibility results takes 36-120 hours because microorganisms are required to grow to high concentrations (10<sup>7</sup>-10<sup>8</sup> cells/mL) and later isolated in culture before characterization can occur. The lengthy culture time is due to the low concentration (1-10 cells/mL) of microorganisms at early stages of infections, or because of slow replication. Molecular diagnostic products like multiplex PCR &ldquo;syndromic&rdquo; panels offer fast turnaround-time but still require a positive blood culture, which can take 24 - 120 hours. Currently, there are two FDA-cleared tests that are direct-from-sample (DFS) offering results in 6 hours, the T2 Biosystems&rsquo; T2Bacteria and T2Candida Panels. The limited number of targets results in an incomplete diagnosis with little impact on clinical outcomes. An effective solution must offer a gain in time-to-results, cover most common etiologies, and provide clinically actionable results.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/14/2020<br>      Modified by: Nadim&nbsp;Ajami</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ With support from the National Science Foundation Innovation Corps award, our group conducted 350 customer interviews with hospital administrators, laboratory directors, technicians, and infectious diseases doctors in 25 different cities around the country to understand how blood stream infections are diagnosed and managed. We learned that a critical bottleneck in this process is the delay associated with pathogen detection and isolation. The gold-standard method is blood culture followed by biochemical characterization and antimicrobial susceptibility testing.  Detecting the presence of microbes and providing antimicrobial susceptibility results takes 36-120 hours because microorganisms are required to grow to high concentrations (107-108 cells/mL) and later isolated in culture before characterization can occur. The lengthy culture time is due to the low concentration (1-10 cells/mL) of microorganisms at early stages of infections, or because of slow replication. Molecular diagnostic products like multiplex PCR "syndromic" panels offer fast turnaround-time but still require a positive blood culture, which can take 24 - 120 hours. Currently, there are two FDA-cleared tests that are direct-from-sample (DFS) offering results in 6 hours, the T2 Biosystems’ T2Bacteria and T2Candida Panels. The limited number of targets results in an incomplete diagnosis with little impact on clinical outcomes. An effective solution must offer a gain in time-to-results, cover most common etiologies, and provide clinically actionable results.       Last Modified: 05/14/2020       Submitted by: Nadim Ajami]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
