<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Mechanobiology of Fiber Geometry-RhoGTPase Crosstalk at the Leading Edge of Cells Crawling on Fibers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>172044.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>172044</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laurel Kuxhaus</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lkuxhaus@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924465</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cells move in a complex three-dimensional environment composed of fibrous proteins.  A first step for a cell in choosing a direction to move is to sense its environment by tugging at the fibers.  This starts what is called 'cell contractility.'  How contractility is achieved on fibers of varying diameters distributed randomly or in specific patterns, in normal or diseased tissues, is mostly unknown. Understanding the first sensory interactions between a cell and a contacted fiber is important to how cells invade a fibrous tissue, such as when cancer cells leave a tumor, or in directed migration of cells on fibers towards a wound site. Most of what we know about cell migration stems from classical studies conducted on 2D flat substrates or, more recently, using complex gels.  Neither approach allows the studying of cell-fiber interactions.  This research will address the need to quantify cell-fiber interactions to understand cell migration during wound healing and disease. In this collaborative research, by combining state-of-art technologies in nanofiber manufacturing, cell signaling biosensors, and cell mechanics, we will be able to see inside the cell and determine the decision mechanisms that help cells migrate along fibers.   The PI will work with faculty at a local community college to train them in the laboratory so that they can develop educational materials.  This will create research opportunities for community college students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will define the mechanobiological state of a cell as it interacts with fibers. Specifically, we will reveal RhoGTPase signaling (RhoA, Rac1, and CdC42) as cells form protrusions and migrate on fibers. The interplay, localization, and summation of these molecules at specific regions of the cell define the mode of migration, which has been shown to be different in 2 and 3D. To determine the activity maps of these proteins in cells on fibers, we will design fiber networks of varying diameters (nanometers-microns) distributed in aligned and random configurations signifying pro- and anti-invasive conditions. In doing so, we will be able to pinpoint spatial and temporal activation maps of RhoGTPase's as cells tug and exert forces on fibers. The mechanobiological force quantitation-biosensor activation will develop new knowledge in the plasticity of cell migration to changing fibrous environments, as would be encountered in vivo. Linking adhesion receptor-based signaling spanning a wide range of spatial (nanometers-microns) and temporal (seconds-hours) scales with migration and force modulation will provide new knowledge in invasion-driven cell migration, thus opening new directions in drug discovery and development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1762468</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Klaus Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Hahn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Klaus Michael Hahn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>khahn@med.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9193231737</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000627404</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>608195277</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName>Chapel Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275997365</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Genetic Medicine Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7479</Code>
<Text>BMMB-Biomech &amp; Mechanobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>028E</Code>
<Text>BIOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>070Z</Code>
<Text>MB-Mechanobiology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~172044</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The cell must respond to many external stimuli, integrating and balancing multiple inputs to determine proper behavior. This is important to maintain health, and goes awry in disease. Unlike manmade computers, the parts of the cell circuitry that determine cell behavior are constantly rearranging themselves, adopting new configurations as the cell encounters different environments. This element of cell decision making, the rearrangement and transient, localized activation of proteins, cannot be understood by isolating cell components. It is necessary to visualize and when possible even control the localized workings of proteins in living cells. Our role was to develop and apply approaches to make this possible. &nbsp;We collaborated with others who had set up a system that mimicked the tumor environment, including fibers that metastatic cells use to find blood vessels. We supplied them with tools and trained them in applying known techniques to study the internal workings of metastatic versus cancer cells manipulating and negotiating the fibers. For protein visualization we used biosensors our lab had previously developed to 'see' conformational changes of Rho family GTPases. These are small proteins that act as the final on/off switches actually controlling cell movements. They respond to the upstream integrating network to activate or inactivate parts of the the cytoskeleton.&nbsp;We also focused on ubiquitous proteins that control these GTPases ("Guanine exchange factors" of GEFs and "GTPase activating proteins" or GAPs), applying known strategies and building new analogs that could be controlled by light.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our hope is that the new tools will also be used by other researchers studying diverse biological behaviors.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/13/2021<br>      Modified by: Klaus Michael&nbsp;Hahn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The cell must respond to many external stimuli, integrating and balancing multiple inputs to determine proper behavior. This is important to maintain health, and goes awry in disease. Unlike manmade computers, the parts of the cell circuitry that determine cell behavior are constantly rearranging themselves, adopting new configurations as the cell encounters different environments. This element of cell decision making, the rearrangement and transient, localized activation of proteins, cannot be understood by isolating cell components. It is necessary to visualize and when possible even control the localized workings of proteins in living cells. Our role was to develop and apply approaches to make this possible.  We collaborated with others who had set up a system that mimicked the tumor environment, including fibers that metastatic cells use to find blood vessels. We supplied them with tools and trained them in applying known techniques to study the internal workings of metastatic versus cancer cells manipulating and negotiating the fibers. For protein visualization we used biosensors our lab had previously developed to 'see' conformational changes of Rho family GTPases. These are small proteins that act as the final on/off switches actually controlling cell movements. They respond to the upstream integrating network to activate or inactivate parts of the the cytoskeleton. We also focused on ubiquitous proteins that control these GTPases ("Guanine exchange factors" of GEFs and "GTPase activating proteins" or GAPs), applying known strategies and building new analogs that could be controlled by light.  Our hope is that the new tools will also be used by other researchers studying diverse biological behaviors.          Last Modified: 06/13/2021       Submitted by: Klaus Michael Hahn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
