<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Impact of Interactions between Metal Oxides to Redox Reactivity of Iron and Manganese Oxides</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/21/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>6000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>89130</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karl Rockne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>krockne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925356</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1236517&lt;br/&gt;Zhang&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the fate of emerging contaminants in the environment is critical for assessing their potential risks to ecological systems.  Yet, quantitative estimates of contaminant fate in complex environmental systems cannot be accurately obtained through experimentation and modeling with simple model systems.  For this reason, this project will investigate complex model systems containing binary oxide mixtures to resemble soil-water environments: iron (Fe) or manganese (Mn) oxides as the redox active oxides and aluminum, silicon or other iron oxides as the second oxides.  The main objective is to determine how the presence of a second metal oxide affects the redox activity of Fe/Mn oxides.  Specifically, two model systems will be examined for their redox reactivity with respect to eight organic contaminants: an oxidizing environment containing either manganese dioxide or goethite as the dominant oxidant and a reducing environment containing soluble ferrous ions in the presence of goethite as the dominant reductant.  Experimental and modeling work will be carried out to study the reaction kinetics of the target contaminants in the above systems.  Potential particle interactions will be evaluated based on surface complexation, surface precipitation, heteroaggregation, and competitive adsorption.  This study is the first to examine how the interactions between two different types of metal oxides affect the redox activity of iron and manganese oxides.  This research will generate knowledge that is critical for predicting the fate of emerging contaminants in redox active soil-water environments.  The intellectual merit of this project is based on: 1) a fundamental understanding of the nature of interactions within binary oxide mixtures and how these interactions are affected by solution chemistry including pH, oxide composition, and ionic strength; 2) a mechanistic understanding of how a second metal oxide affects the redox behavior of Fe/Mn oxides under oxic and anoxic conditions; and 3) quantitative modeling of the relative contribution of each type of interaction between metal oxides to the overall inhibitory effect of a second metal oxide on the redox activity of Fe/Mn oxides.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study will create a new body of knowledge available to aquatic chemists, environmental engineers, geochemists and microbiologists working with metal oxides in terms of either the activity of soil-water environments or contaminant removal.  By developing complex model systems, results of this project can enable a more accurate risk analysis which could eventually be used by public health and environmental agencies for contaminant regulation and environmental clean-up.  This project will also contribute to training, mentoring and overall development of graduate, undergraduate and high school students.  Other planned outreach activities include participation of underrepresented minority and female students (particularly from the Society of Women Engineers), one-week summer workshops for female high school students, broad dissemination to over 30 industrial partners at the annual industrial advisory board meetings for the NSF Water and Environmental Technology (WET) Center, integration into the environmental curriculum at the Temple University, and presentation at Temple seminars that serve 1000+ Temple members and 3000+ working professionals from the great Philadelphia area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/18/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/18/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1762691</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Huichun</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Huichun Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hjz13@case.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2163684510</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000758215</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/18/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
<CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[10900 Euclid Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077758407</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CASE WESTERN RESERVE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>077758407</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Case Western Reserve University]]></Name>
<CityName>Clevleand</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>021E</Code>
<Text>Water management</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~83130</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Calibri;">As the amount of emerging contaminants (ECs), such as pharmaceutical and personal care products and endocrine disrupting chemicals, discharged into the environment continues to grow, possible environmental and health risks will become increasingly important issues in the near future. Currently, there is a lack of quantitative data on the transformation of ECs in the aquatic environment. The environment is too complex to understand based on the exiting data on mostly simple model systems containing one reactant. This hinders researchers and regulatory agencies? ability to develop environmental fate models to assess ECs fate in and possible risks to water supply and environmental systems.</span></span></p> <p><span style="color: #000000;"> </span></p> <p><strong><span><span style="font-family: Calibri;">Intellectual Merit</span></span></strong></p> <p><span style="color: #000000;"> </span></p> <p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Calibri;"><span>To bridge the gap between environmental systems and simple model systems, we examined the reactivity of ECs in two complex model systems: (i) oxic systems containing manganese oxides, a second metal oxide including Al, Fe, Si, and Ti oxides, and natural organic matter (NOM) and (ii) anoxic systems containing iron(III) oxides, a second metal oxide, ferrous ion, and small organic ligands. In additional to monitoring ECs degradation in the systems, </span><span>the study relied on diverse methods including solution phase analysis, particle morphology and surface composition analysis, and colloidal (particle size, surface area and surface charge) measurements coupled with analytical determinations</span><span>.</span></span></span></p> <p><span style="color: #000000;"> </span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri;">Our major findings include: (i) for the oxic systems, the second oxides mostly inhibited Mn oxide reactivity, and the inhibition mechanisms varied from particle aggregation (between the same and different types of particles), surface complexation of soluble ions with the Mn oxide, to competitive adsorption of different surfaces toward the EC; (ii) for the anoxic systems, TiO2 enhanced contaminant degradation in the mixed systems mostly due to facilitated interparticle electron transfer, while SiO2 inhibited contaminant degradation by dissolving soluble Si ions, (iii) NOM and/or small ligands affected the Mn/Fe oxide reactivity by interfering with particle aggregation in the oxic systems while with the adsorption of ferrous ion by the iron(III) oxides in the anoxic systems.</span></p> <p><span style="color: #000000;"> </span></p> <p><strong><span><span style="font-family: Calibri;">Broader Impacts</span></span></strong></p> <p><span style="color: #000000;"> </span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri;">The development and examination of complex model systems has created new information regarding the fate of ECs in environmental systems, and thus moved a major step forward in incorporating redox transformation into environmental fate models. As a result, more realistic risk assessments can be conducted for many ECs. This project has supported the training of three Ph. D. students, seven undergraduate student researchers, and seven high school interns. We have broadly disseminated the findings at a number of professional meetings and in the peer-reviewed literature. In addition, we had planned various outreach activities, including professional development opportunities for members of Society of Women Engineers, annual workshops for 200+ high school girls and 13 African American boys to </span><span style="font-family: Calibri;">increase awareness of and interest in advances in engineering, and projects for four college senior design teams.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Huichun&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1762691/1762691_10194452_1543632610898_Image_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1762691/1762691_10194452_1543632610898_Image_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Interactions in the mixtures of MnO2, Fe(III) oxides, and NOM"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1762691/1762691_10194452_1543632610898_Image_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Interactions in the mixtures of MnO2, Fe(III) oxides, and NOM"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The reactivity of MnO2 was inhibited at lower NOM concentrations but enhanced at higher NOM concentrations. NOM mainly affected the extents of homo- versus hetero-aggregation in the mixed oxides.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Saru Taujale</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Huichun&nbsp;Zhang</div> <div class="imageTitle">Interactions in the mixtures of MnO2, Fe(III) oxides, and NOM</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As the amount of emerging contaminants (ECs), such as pharmaceutical and personal care products and endocrine disrupting chemicals, discharged into the environment continues to grow, possible environmental and health risks will become increasingly important issues in the near future. Currently, there is a lack of quantitative data on the transformation of ECs in the aquatic environment. The environment is too complex to understand based on the exiting data on mostly simple model systems containing one reactant. This hinders researchers and regulatory agencies? ability to develop environmental fate models to assess ECs fate in and possible risks to water supply and environmental systems.     Intellectual Merit     To bridge the gap between environmental systems and simple model systems, we examined the reactivity of ECs in two complex model systems: (i) oxic systems containing manganese oxides, a second metal oxide including Al, Fe, Si, and Ti oxides, and natural organic matter (NOM) and (ii) anoxic systems containing iron(III) oxides, a second metal oxide, ferrous ion, and small organic ligands. In additional to monitoring ECs degradation in the systems, the study relied on diverse methods including solution phase analysis, particle morphology and surface composition analysis, and colloidal (particle size, surface area and surface charge) measurements coupled with analytical determinations.     Our major findings include: (i) for the oxic systems, the second oxides mostly inhibited Mn oxide reactivity, and the inhibition mechanisms varied from particle aggregation (between the same and different types of particles), surface complexation of soluble ions with the Mn oxide, to competitive adsorption of different surfaces toward the EC; (ii) for the anoxic systems, TiO2 enhanced contaminant degradation in the mixed systems mostly due to facilitated interparticle electron transfer, while SiO2 inhibited contaminant degradation by dissolving soluble Si ions, (iii) NOM and/or small ligands affected the Mn/Fe oxide reactivity by interfering with particle aggregation in the oxic systems while with the adsorption of ferrous ion by the iron(III) oxides in the anoxic systems.     Broader Impacts     The development and examination of complex model systems has created new information regarding the fate of ECs in environmental systems, and thus moved a major step forward in incorporating redox transformation into environmental fate models. As a result, more realistic risk assessments can be conducted for many ECs. This project has supported the training of three Ph. D. students, seven undergraduate student researchers, and seven high school interns. We have broadly disseminated the findings at a number of professional meetings and in the peer-reviewed literature. In addition, we had planned various outreach activities, including professional development opportunities for members of Society of Women Engineers, annual workshops for 200+ high school girls and 13 African American boys to increase awareness of and interest in advances in engineering, and projects for four college senior design teams.           Last Modified: 12/01/2018       Submitted by: Huichun Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
