<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IOS RAPID: Does adaptation to urbanization promote resilience during a natural disaster? A test of brown anole (Anolis sagrei) behavior and stress after Hurricane Irma.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>45210.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>45210</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jodie Jawor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjawor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927887</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Resilience is the capacity for individuals to cope with stressful challenges and recover successfully from any adverse effects of said challenges. Such challenges are met with a physiological response that involves the secretion of stress hormones into the blood and their accumulation in the brain resulting in the expression of adaptive behaviors, such as fight or flight. Individuals frequently exposed to stress in day-to-day life are predicted to recover more rapidly both behaviorally and physiologically, e.g., they are more resilient. Scientists have recently documented that anole lizards in urban Orlando have a lessened stress response when compared to rural counterparts, possibly as a means to cope with the challenges of urbanization, which could increase their resilience to stressful events. Hurricane Irma provides an unprecedented opportunity to test this "urban resilience" hypothesis by comparing how urban and rural populations perceived, responded and recovered from this natural disaster. Using data collected prior to hurricane landfall, this work will investigate stress hormones and their accumulation in the brain, and stress-related behaviors in both urban and rural lizard populations as they recover from the hurricane's impact. Understanding resilience in this context is valuable to conservation managers concerned about how natural disasters impact wildlife and potentially facilitate non-native animal invasions, such as the famed South Florida python invasion following Hurricane Andrew in 1992, which typically begin in cities. Conceptually this study can also inform how low resilience leaves individuals susceptible to the prolonged effects of extreme stress, such as occurs with post-traumatic stress disorder.  This work will involve undergraduate students in data collection and analysis and provide opportunities for presentation of findings at national and international conferences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Enduring natural disasters requires resilience, the ability to successfully cope with and recover from the adverse effects of extreme challenges. Prominent in resilience is the ability to successfully manage the stress response, a hormonal cascade initiating in the brain and ultimately involving the secretion of glucocorticoids from the adrenal gland. Glucocorticoids alter metabolism and behavior to permit survival during stress and frequent activation of this response can attenuate their secretion to avoid the cost of excessive accumulation which could negatively impact neural function. Preliminary data show urban populations of the invasive brown anole (Anolis sagrei) have an attenuated stress response compared to rural ones suggesting urban lizards may exhibit greater resilience. An unprecedented opportunity to test this "urban resilience" hypothesis occurred when Hurricane Irma made landfall. This research will provide undergraduate student opportunities to conduct research on circulating and neural glucocorticoid levels and stress-related behaviors in urban and rural lizard populations sampled immediately before and after Hurricane Irma to determine the time taken to return to "baseline" conditions prior to landfall. Understanding resilience in this context informs conservation managers interested in how hurricanes can promote accidental invasions of exotic species, such as happened with Burmese pythons after Hurricane Andrew in 1992. Such invasions usually start in cities, where potential invaders must simultaneously cope with both city and disaster associated stressors, yet this interaction has never been explored. Data from this study can be used to inform disorders characterized by low resistance to extreme stress, such as post-traumatic stress disorder.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/14/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/14/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1762109</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bobby</FirstName>
<LastName>Fokidis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bobby Fokidis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>HFOKIDIS@rollins.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4076462452</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000661900</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rollins College</Name>
<CityName>Winter Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>327894499</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4076461943</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 Holt Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004076667</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ROLLINS COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004076667</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rollins College]]></Name>
<CityName>Winter Park</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>327894499</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 Holt Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>074Y</Code>
<Text>Hurricane Irma 2017</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~45210</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Resilience describes the ability of an individual to successfully adapt and recover from a severe challenge. &nbsp;High resilience would be strongly favored by natural selection, whereas low resilience can be deleterious to survival and reproduction. A vital component of resilience is the ability to enact, regulate and recover from the hormonal &ldquo;stress response&rdquo;. During a stress response, the adrenal gland secretes glucocorticoid (GC) hormones that reallocate energy, suppress inflammation and inhibit reproduction to order to improve the odds of immediate survival. These GCs also neurochemically prepare the brain for potential exposure to stress in the future. Thus, patterns of GC secretion are used to determine if an environmental disturbance is stressful. To successfully recovery from stress, an intact negative feedback is required to returns GC levels to that preceding the disturbance. A long-standing paradigm in stress biology suggests that repeated exposure to small and largely nonconsequential stressors will prime the hormonal stress response to become more efficient and thus improve overall resilience. To date, few (if any) studies have tested this paradigm in a natural setting.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>On September 10, 2017, Hurricane Irma, the largest and strongest hurricane ever recorded in the Atlantic basin, made landfall in Florida and provided a unique opportunity to test this paradigm using a natural experiment. Hurricane Irma interrupted a study on the behavior and physiology of the highly invasive lizard, the brown anole (<em>Anolis sagrei</em>). Our previous research uncovered that anoles within urban Orlando have a lessened stress response when compared to rural lizards. This difference may indicate an adaptation for coping with the challenges of urbanization, and this could increase their resilience to stressful events. Hurricane Irma provides an unprecedented opportunity to test this "urban resilience" hypothesis by comparing how urban and rural populations perceived, responded and recovered from this natural disaster.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The research supported by this award enabled us to collect data at both sites at different timepoints both immediately prior to and after the hurricane. We investigated changes in GC concentrations in the blood and their accumulation in the brain, as well as behaviors associated with stress. Immediately following the hurricane, both urban and rural anoles showed drastic increases in circulating GC levels, but urban anoles recovered within days, whereas forest anoles maintained high GC levels up to a month after. These GC changes were accompanied by increases in aggressive territoriality between anoles and also predator avoidance behaviors that relate to anxiety. Again, rural anoles took longer than urban lizards to reach the levels of these behaviors that were exhibited prior to the hurricane. Within the brain, Hurricane Irma also increased GC concentrations, particularly in two stress-sensitive brain areas: 1) the amygdala which regulates emotion and fear responses, and 2) the dorsal cortex, the reptile equivalent of the mammalian hippocampus, which is involved in memory. Prolonged exposure to GCs in these areas can impair their function, and low resilience can leave individuals susceptible to the effects of extreme stress, as is observed in post-traumatic stress disorder or PTSD. These GC accumulations were again more pronounced in the rural anole population than the urban one. Experiments conducted in the field revealed that the population variation in GC levels can be traced to differences in the effectiveness of the negative feedback that &ldquo;shuts off&rdquo; the stress response.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Research supported by this award found evidence supporting the urban resilience hypothesis and this is valuable to conservation managers concerned about how natural disasters impact wildlife. Particularly, natural disasters often facilitate non-native animal invasions, such as the famed South Florida python invasion following Hurricane Andrew in 1992. As these invasions typically begin in cities and understanding resilience can allow us to make better predictions about the range expansion of invasive species, such as the brown anole. This award also supported undergraduate student training in the PI&rsquo;s research lab, with students involved in data collection and analysis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/11/2018<br>      Modified by: Bobby&nbsp;Fokidis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Resilience describes the ability of an individual to successfully adapt and recover from a severe challenge.  High resilience would be strongly favored by natural selection, whereas low resilience can be deleterious to survival and reproduction. A vital component of resilience is the ability to enact, regulate and recover from the hormonal "stress response". During a stress response, the adrenal gland secretes glucocorticoid (GC) hormones that reallocate energy, suppress inflammation and inhibit reproduction to order to improve the odds of immediate survival. These GCs also neurochemically prepare the brain for potential exposure to stress in the future. Thus, patterns of GC secretion are used to determine if an environmental disturbance is stressful. To successfully recovery from stress, an intact negative feedback is required to returns GC levels to that preceding the disturbance. A long-standing paradigm in stress biology suggests that repeated exposure to small and largely nonconsequential stressors will prime the hormonal stress response to become more efficient and thus improve overall resilience. To date, few (if any) studies have tested this paradigm in a natural setting.     On September 10, 2017, Hurricane Irma, the largest and strongest hurricane ever recorded in the Atlantic basin, made landfall in Florida and provided a unique opportunity to test this paradigm using a natural experiment. Hurricane Irma interrupted a study on the behavior and physiology of the highly invasive lizard, the brown anole (Anolis sagrei). Our previous research uncovered that anoles within urban Orlando have a lessened stress response when compared to rural lizards. This difference may indicate an adaptation for coping with the challenges of urbanization, and this could increase their resilience to stressful events. Hurricane Irma provides an unprecedented opportunity to test this "urban resilience" hypothesis by comparing how urban and rural populations perceived, responded and recovered from this natural disaster.     The research supported by this award enabled us to collect data at both sites at different timepoints both immediately prior to and after the hurricane. We investigated changes in GC concentrations in the blood and their accumulation in the brain, as well as behaviors associated with stress. Immediately following the hurricane, both urban and rural anoles showed drastic increases in circulating GC levels, but urban anoles recovered within days, whereas forest anoles maintained high GC levels up to a month after. These GC changes were accompanied by increases in aggressive territoriality between anoles and also predator avoidance behaviors that relate to anxiety. Again, rural anoles took longer than urban lizards to reach the levels of these behaviors that were exhibited prior to the hurricane. Within the brain, Hurricane Irma also increased GC concentrations, particularly in two stress-sensitive brain areas: 1) the amygdala which regulates emotion and fear responses, and 2) the dorsal cortex, the reptile equivalent of the mammalian hippocampus, which is involved in memory. Prolonged exposure to GCs in these areas can impair their function, and low resilience can leave individuals susceptible to the effects of extreme stress, as is observed in post-traumatic stress disorder or PTSD. These GC accumulations were again more pronounced in the rural anole population than the urban one. Experiments conducted in the field revealed that the population variation in GC levels can be traced to differences in the effectiveness of the negative feedback that "shuts off" the stress response.     Research supported by this award found evidence supporting the urban resilience hypothesis and this is valuable to conservation managers concerned about how natural disasters impact wildlife. Particularly, natural disasters often facilitate non-native animal invasions, such as the famed South Florida python invasion following Hurricane Andrew in 1992. As these invasions typically begin in cities and understanding resilience can allow us to make better predictions about the range expansion of invasive species, such as the brown anole. This award also supported undergraduate student training in the PI?s research lab, with students involved in data collection and analysis.          Last Modified: 12/11/2018       Submitted by: Bobby Fokidis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
