<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Equivariant Cohomology: Positivity, Differential Equations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>125000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>125000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The singularities of a function in one variable are the points where the derivative of the function vanishes. The relationship between singularities and global aspects of the function, such as minima and maxima, is only the tip of the iceberg. Rimanyi studies singularities of functions between higher dimensional spaces, and their relations with global aspects of the spaces. A key notion of his research is the equivariant cohomology class represented by a geometrically relevant variety. Natural infinite series of these classes often display remarkable properties. The PI proposes a new approach to prove a positivity result for an interesting set of equivariant classes, the so-called quiver polynomials. He also plans to study the positivity of another class: the Thom polynomials of Morin singularities, in connection with the Green-Griffiths conjecture on the holomorphic maps to projective varieties. His new approach is based on the flexibility of Iterated Residue descriptions of equivariant classes. Another area the PI proposes to study is the very promising interplay between equivariant cohomology, differential equations, and physics. Namely, equivariant classes often satisfy physically inspired differential equations. Based on earlier works with Varchenko, Rimanyi proposes to find the topological aspects of quantum Knizhnik-Zamolodchikov differential equations, and study why equivariant cohomology classes satisfy them. As an application quantum Selberg type integrals with topological ingredients are expected.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the physical sciences, one very challenging problem is the understanding of sudden changes caused by smooth alterations of parameters. Rimanyi is working on the mathematical aspects of these physical phenomena. An essential aspect of his proposal is its educational component. Rimanyi proposes to continue a Geometry Learning Seminar for the graduate students at UNC, providing a critical source of communication between faculty and interested graduate students. By continuing to involve some bright Chapel Hill high school students in mathematics research, the proposer is creating new opportunities and new channels of communication between different institutions. He also proposes to broaden participation of undergraduates in the mathematical life of the department by advising students as they begin their honors theses. He will continue running a weekly problem solving/competition preparation seminar for undergraduates---where the students get not only math olympiad type training, but experience research firsthand. He continues to advice master and PhD student. Rimanyi proposes to set up an online Thom polynomial portal, where scattered results of Thom polynomials would be collected and organized for the benefit of scientists.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1200685</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Rimanyi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard Rimanyi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rimanyi@email.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9199621294</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000277047</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>608195277</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName>Chapel Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275993250</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[120 East Cameron Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~125000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main theme of the research carried out under this grant was the connection between two branches of mathematics, namely Schubert calculus and quantum integrable systems. Schubert calculus is concerned with the enumerative geometry of linear spaces, and quantum integrable models provide remarkable actions of some (Bethe) algebras on some vector spaces inspired by physics.</p> <p>With co-author A. Varchenko (and occasionally with other co-authors) the PI found several results, and published several papers along the following lines: there is an explicit correspondence (isomorphism) between objects on the two sides. On both sides there are objects that are simple and difficult to study. On the Schubert calculus side the simple objects are ``fixed point classes&rsquo;&rsquo; and the difficult ones<strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">&nbsp;</span></em></strong> are ``Schubert classes&rsquo;&rsquo;.&nbsp; On the Bethe algebra side the simple object is the ``coordinate basis&rsquo;&rsquo; and the difficult ones are the ``Bethe vectors&rsquo;&rsquo;. Remarkably, the correspondence we found matches the simple objects of one side to the difficult objects of the other side.</p> <p>Numerous applications are immediate: we found explicit expressions for Bethe vectors and<strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">&nbsp;</span></em></strong> calculated the so-called Chern-MacPherson deformations of Schubert classes. We found interpolation descriptions of polynomials relevant in enumerative geometry. Some of these are suggested to be the atom of the so far hardly existing CSM theory of degenracy loci.</p> <p>In mathematical physics literature it is well known that the Bethe algebra we studied have three different flavors: the rational, the trigonometric, and the elliptic. Our correspondence clearly matches the rational one with cohomological Schubert calculus. We proved that the trigonometric version<strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">&nbsp;</span></em></strong> matches with the so-called K-theoretic Schubert calculus. Using the patterns we found in these two cases we created our own version of elliptic Schubert calculus<strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span></em></strong>by extending the correspondence to the elliptic flavor.</p> <p>During this research we found stabilization properties of polynomials that encode enumerative geometry information. A consequence of these stabilizations is that the polynomials can be organized into one (formal iterated residue) generating sequence. We explored the extent and consequences of such residue calculus for the theory of quivers and moduli spaces of curves.</p> <p>A related subject is the dimension count of algebras whose structure is governed by the notions described above. The PI calculated these dimension counts in several different ways; comparing these methods proved remarkable identities among a particularly important function called the quantum dilogarithm series.</p> <p>An important part of the work done is its broader impact. The PI is active in training PhD students. His graduate students, R. Kaliszewski (now postdoc at Drexel) and J. Allman (now tenure-track at Annapolis), studied stabilization and positivity properties of cohomological and K-theoretic quiver polynomials, essentially related to the research topics described above. Their training and mentoring as researchers was greatly improved by the active research environment provided by the current grant. The PI started the training of a third PhD student, S. Pramtapaan, along the lines of this research, and S.P. has<strong><em></em></strong> already completed a Master&rsquo;s thesis.The PI has started collaborations with graduate students at other schools, leading for example to a paper with a graduate student co-author at Urbana-Champaign.</p> <p>The PI is also active in disseminating research results on two levels. Locally, he contributes to the <strong><em></em></strong>annual weekend conferences held at UNC on Geometric Representation Theory. He was also involved in the organization of the Triangle Lectures in<strong><em></em></strong> Combinatorics in 2011 and 2014. Internationally the PI is involved in connecting researchers in Europe with those in the USA. He gave mini-courses to PhD students at the University of Geneva<strong><em></em></strong>, as well as at the winter school at Les Diablerets to students from several Swiss universities. He co-organized a workshop on Global Singularity Theory and Enumerative Geometry in Lausanne Switzerland in 2016.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;Rimanyi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main theme of the research carried out under this grant was the connection between two branches of mathematics, namely Schubert calculus and quantum integrable systems. Schubert calculus is concerned with the enumerative geometry of linear spaces, and quantum integrable models provide remarkable actions of some (Bethe) algebras on some vector spaces inspired by physics.  With co-author A. Varchenko (and occasionally with other co-authors) the PI found several results, and published several papers along the following lines: there is an explicit correspondence (isomorphism) between objects on the two sides. On both sides there are objects that are simple and difficult to study. On the Schubert calculus side the simple objects are ``fixed point classes?? and the difficult ones  are ``Schubert classes??.  On the Bethe algebra side the simple object is the ``coordinate basis?? and the difficult ones are the ``Bethe vectors??. Remarkably, the correspondence we found matches the simple objects of one side to the difficult objects of the other side.  Numerous applications are immediate: we found explicit expressions for Bethe vectors and  calculated the so-called Chern-MacPherson deformations of Schubert classes. We found interpolation descriptions of polynomials relevant in enumerative geometry. Some of these are suggested to be the atom of the so far hardly existing CSM theory of degenracy loci.  In mathematical physics literature it is well known that the Bethe algebra we studied have three different flavors: the rational, the trigonometric, and the elliptic. Our correspondence clearly matches the rational one with cohomological Schubert calculus. We proved that the trigonometric version  matches with the so-called K-theoretic Schubert calculus. Using the patterns we found in these two cases we created our own version of elliptic Schubert calculus by extending the correspondence to the elliptic flavor.  During this research we found stabilization properties of polynomials that encode enumerative geometry information. A consequence of these stabilizations is that the polynomials can be organized into one (formal iterated residue) generating sequence. We explored the extent and consequences of such residue calculus for the theory of quivers and moduli spaces of curves.  A related subject is the dimension count of algebras whose structure is governed by the notions described above. The PI calculated these dimension counts in several different ways; comparing these methods proved remarkable identities among a particularly important function called the quantum dilogarithm series.  An important part of the work done is its broader impact. The PI is active in training PhD students. His graduate students, R. Kaliszewski (now postdoc at Drexel) and J. Allman (now tenure-track at Annapolis), studied stabilization and positivity properties of cohomological and K-theoretic quiver polynomials, essentially related to the research topics described above. Their training and mentoring as researchers was greatly improved by the active research environment provided by the current grant. The PI started the training of a third PhD student, S. Pramtapaan, along the lines of this research, and S.P. has already completed a Master?s thesis.The PI has started collaborations with graduate students at other schools, leading for example to a paper with a graduate student co-author at Urbana-Champaign.  The PI is also active in disseminating research results on two levels. Locally, he contributes to the annual weekend conferences held at UNC on Geometric Representation Theory. He was also involved in the organization of the Triangle Lectures in Combinatorics in 2011 and 2014. Internationally the PI is involved in connecting researchers in Europe with those in the USA. He gave mini-courses to PhD students at the University of Geneva, as well as at the winter school at Les Diablerets to students from several Swiss universities. He co-organized a workshop on Global Singularity Theory and Enumerative Geometry in Lausanne Switzerland in 2016.       Last Modified: 10/30/2016       Submitted by: Richard Rimanyi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
