<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>New Modeling and Solution Paradigms for Transportation Problems with Applications to Railroads</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>233134.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>233134</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Georgia-Ann Klutke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gaklutke@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922443</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>To provide services, industries and the government rely heavily on their ability to efficiently transport goods. In their simplest form, transportation problems can be solved efficiently using traditional optimization algorithms. However, practical applications often exhibit a variety of additional combinatorial requirements that necessitate involved modeling, often in the form of integer programs. This modeling is often seen as unnatural by practitioners and results in models that are difficult to solve with state-of-the-art commercial software. The research objective of this award is to develop a new modeling and solution paradigm for such transportation problems. In this paradigm, a few key constructs are identified that allow the user to succinctly impose often-occurring combinatorial constraints without the need to formulate them using integer programming. These constructs can then be exploited to design more efficient exact and heuristic solution methodologies that take advantage of the structure of the network and of the combinatorial requirements.  The research will also seek to demonstrate the advantages of this paradigm on practical problems emanating from bulk delivery in railroads. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this research will result in an integrated modeling and solution paradigm that will provide faster solutions to larger transportation problems and that will bring within the range of tractability many practically relevant problems that are currently intractable. It will lead to solutions where transportation costs and miles are reduced and will therefore improve the efficiency of industries relying on transportation. Results will be disseminated timely via conferences, publications and a dedicated internet page that will contain relevant models, stylized applications and prototype implementations. Undergraduate and graduate students will also benefit from this award through the development of course material and involvement in research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/17/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1200616</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jean-Philippe</FirstName>
<LastName>Richard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jean-Philippe Richard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jrichar@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126267912</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000494212</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/17/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326116595</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1787</Code>
<Text>SERVICE ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>076E</Code>
<Text>SERVICE ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>078E</Code>
<Text>ENTERPRISE DESIGN &amp; LOGISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~233134</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Efficiently transporting goods is a fundamental part of providing services to industries&nbsp;and the government. Many transportation problems are naturally expressed as discrete optimization problems over networks. In their simplest form, these problems can be solved efficiently using&nbsp;traditional network flow algorithms. However, practical applications typically also exhibit a variety&nbsp;of additional combinatorial requirements that necessitate more involved modeling, often in the form&nbsp;of integer programs (IPs). This&nbsp;modeling however (i) is often seen as unnatural by practitioners, (ii) requires a certain amount of&nbsp;experience to yield reasonably strong IP formulations, (iii) may necessitate a very large number of&nbsp;additional variables, and (iv) results in formulations whose natural network structure is lost. This project&nbsp;laid the foundation for new, simpler modeling tools and more&nbsp;dedicated solution methodologies for network-based transportation optimization with combinatorial requirements.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We studied how to express the no-split-no-merge requirement. This requirement naturally arises in the formulation of railroad transportation problems, as train compositions cannot be altered at most railroad yards since adding/removing cars from a train requires appropriate manpower/equipment.  In mathematical terms, the no-split-no-merge requirement stipulates that each positive flow entering an unsplittable node must leave this node unaltered, i.e., it cannot be split or merged with other flows. We studied the requirement in the initial space of variables, developed cut generation procedures for its convex hull, and discovered a large family of facet-defining inequalities that can be separated in polynomial time.  These results apply not only to single nodes but to aggregations of nodes as well. We found numerically that adding such inequalities yield strong relaxation bounds (when applied to node pairs, and node triplets). These bounds are in fact much stronger than those that can be obtained using commercial software, and its arsenal of cuts, on IP formulations of the model. We also developed problem formulations that use cardinality constraints, where variables represent flows on indivisible paths. Even when cardinality constraints are relaxed through linear constraints, the obtained relaxations are strong. These ideas also apply to generalizations of the no-split-no-merge requirement where a flow entering a node, must leave this node on a pre-specified path. Further, we studied a generalization of a mixing set that appears in several logistics application, including those of railroads. We developed family of facet-defining by lifting mixing inequalities. These lifted inequalities were obtained by discovering some restricted subadditivity properties of the associated lifting functions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Two female graduate research assistants have been involved in this research. Further, this research has allowed various students to gain technical skills in optimization, integer programming and transportation. By its very nature, this research seeks to benefit the transportation community by providing simpler and more efficient tools for transportation problems. If applied,&nbsp;these results&nbsp;would positively influence industries that rely on network-based transportation. This research&nbsp;provides the necessary groundwork for the development of better exact solution methodologies for transportation problems with combinatorial constraints that leverage the widespread success of branch-and-cut techniques. We envision that, because their expressive power, the constructs we propose would also help structure and simplify model design for network-based transportation problems that appear in railroads and other industries.&nbsp;This would in turn&nbsp;help improve the efficiency of distribution systems in a variety of applications, far beyond the transportation of freight in railroads.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/14/2017<br>      Modified by: Jean-Philippe&nbsp;Richard</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Efficiently transporting goods is a fundamental part of providing services to industries and the government. Many transportation problems are naturally expressed as discrete optimization problems over networks. In their simplest form, these problems can be solved efficiently using traditional network flow algorithms. However, practical applications typically also exhibit a variety of additional combinatorial requirements that necessitate more involved modeling, often in the form of integer programs (IPs). This modeling however (i) is often seen as unnatural by practitioners, (ii) requires a certain amount of experience to yield reasonably strong IP formulations, (iii) may necessitate a very large number of additional variables, and (iv) results in formulations whose natural network structure is lost. This project laid the foundation for new, simpler modeling tools and more dedicated solution methodologies for network-based transportation optimization with combinatorial requirements.      We studied how to express the no-split-no-merge requirement. This requirement naturally arises in the formulation of railroad transportation problems, as train compositions cannot be altered at most railroad yards since adding/removing cars from a train requires appropriate manpower/equipment.  In mathematical terms, the no-split-no-merge requirement stipulates that each positive flow entering an unsplittable node must leave this node unaltered, i.e., it cannot be split or merged with other flows. We studied the requirement in the initial space of variables, developed cut generation procedures for its convex hull, and discovered a large family of facet-defining inequalities that can be separated in polynomial time.  These results apply not only to single nodes but to aggregations of nodes as well. We found numerically that adding such inequalities yield strong relaxation bounds (when applied to node pairs, and node triplets). These bounds are in fact much stronger than those that can be obtained using commercial software, and its arsenal of cuts, on IP formulations of the model. We also developed problem formulations that use cardinality constraints, where variables represent flows on indivisible paths. Even when cardinality constraints are relaxed through linear constraints, the obtained relaxations are strong. These ideas also apply to generalizations of the no-split-no-merge requirement where a flow entering a node, must leave this node on a pre-specified path. Further, we studied a generalization of a mixing set that appears in several logistics application, including those of railroads. We developed family of facet-defining by lifting mixing inequalities. These lifted inequalities were obtained by discovering some restricted subadditivity properties of the associated lifting functions.     Two female graduate research assistants have been involved in this research. Further, this research has allowed various students to gain technical skills in optimization, integer programming and transportation. By its very nature, this research seeks to benefit the transportation community by providing simpler and more efficient tools for transportation problems. If applied, these results would positively influence industries that rely on network-based transportation. This research provides the necessary groundwork for the development of better exact solution methodologies for transportation problems with combinatorial constraints that leverage the widespread success of branch-and-cut techniques. We envision that, because their expressive power, the constructs we propose would also help structure and simplify model design for network-based transportation problems that appear in railroads and other industries. This would in turn help improve the efficiency of distribution systems in a variety of applications, far beyond the transportation of freight in railroads.       Last Modified: 06/14/2017       Submitted by: Jean-Philippe Richard]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
