<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ACOUSTO-OPTO-MECHANICAL SYSTEMS in PIEZOELECTRIC ALUMINUM NITRIDE NANOFILMS FOR RADIO FREQUENCY PHOTONICS</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>331300.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>345300</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jenshan Lin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to use on-chip acoustics and photonics to produce miniaturized components that offer a very competitive approach for the synthesis of low power radio receivers. The approach consists in developing devices made out of piezoelectric aluminum nitride (AlN) thin films, in which acousto-optic (modulation of optical signals via elastic waves) and opto-mechanical (modulation of mechanical vibrations via radiation pressure) effects are exploited in confined nanoscale resonant structures. The proposed radio frequency (RF)-photonic receiver relies on an AlN piezoelectric micromechanical filter to select the incoming RF signal (electromechanical effect) and modulate the photonic signal (acousto-optic effect). It also uses the intrinsic non-linearity of the self-sustained opto-mechanical oscillator (opto-mechanical effect) to down convert the signal to baseband. &lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this proposal consists in addressing the engineering challenges that limit the realization of compact RF-photonics receivers based on exploiting electromechanical, acousto-optic and opto-mechanical effects in AlN films.  Scientifically, elasto-optic effects in thin AlN films and noise mechanisms in nanoscale opto-mechanical devices will be understood.  &lt;br/&gt;Beyond directly impacting wireless communications, the proposed acousto-opto-mechanical platform will benefit the broader field of photonics by enabling visible and deep ultraviolet components that could be employed for medical applications. Simultaneously, the high mechanical displacement sensitivity attained via acousto-optic modulators can be transferred to inertial and pressure sensors to enhance their resolution. More broadly, the knowledge generated by these research activities will set the pathway for the synthesis of low power distributed communication links and will enable new generations of sensor networks.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1201659</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gianluca</FirstName>
<LastName>Piazza</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gianluca Piazza</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>piazza@ece.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122687762</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491421</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WQED Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie-Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133890</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~107350</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~116600</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~113350</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project has focused on the realization of a fully integrated platform to enable the modulation of whispering gallery mode resonators with piezoelectrically actuated laterally vibrating MEMS devices for the first time. This method of electrically controlling optomechanical structures through the strong electromechanical coupling afforded by piezoelectric actuation should enable new possibilities for future integrated RF-Photonic modulators. As a result, it can be considered a building block towards the realization of a future RF-Photonic front-end that combines the filtering and frequency reference capabilities of MEMS resonators with photonic integrated circuits. With regard to the current demonstration, there are numerous ways to improve the modulation response. These include the reduction of coupling losses and increasing optical quality factors as well as structural re-designs to match the mechanical modes and reduce damping losses. Nevertheless, the fabrication and design process that has been demonstrated should be able to accommodate all these changes, and also enable scaling to higher frequencies of operation. In summary, this project has made the following original contributions in aluminum nitride:</p> <ul> <li>Demonstration of low loss, wide 1 dB bandwidth <em>C</em>-band      optical grating couplers</li> <li>High-<em>Q<sub>L</sub></em> (&gt;10<sup>4</sup>) 2D      traveling wave evanescently coupled integrated photonic resonators</li> <li>Development of a robust, CMOS-compatible fabrication      process for concurrent production of acoustic and photonic resonators to      enable optomechanics</li> <li>Piezoelectrically actuated acousto-optic modulator at      653 MHz</li> <li>Opto-acoustic oscillator based on piezoelectric      modulation </li> <li>Elasto-optic modulator around 800 MHz</li> <li>Approach towards enabling super high frequency (SHF)      operation of photonic <br /> modulators and reference oscillators in an integrated platform based on a      new class of piezoelectric optomechanical devices</li> </ul> <p>The project has enabled the training of two PhD students and two REU students. It has also resulted in material that was included in the PI&rsquo;s lectures. To educate the broader community and train young engineers, the PI has organized tutorials on the general topic of opto-mechanics at IEEE conferences.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/14/2017<br>      Modified by: Gianluca&nbsp;Piazza</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1201659/1201659_10162667_1500063899166_Project_Outcomes_Figure_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1201659/1201659_10162667_1500063899166_Project_Outcomes_Figure_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Aluminum Nitride Acousto-Optic Modulator"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1201659/1201659_10162667_1500063899166_Project_Outcomes_Figure_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Aluminum Nitride Acousto-Optic Modulator"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SEM images of acousto-optic modulator device. Contour-Mode-Resonator and Whispering-Gallery-Mode (WGM) rings (zoomed in at top right) are highlighted in red, gratings (zoomed in at bottom right) and rib waveguides are highlighted in green.Figure inset highlights 75 nm WGM ring-waveguide gap.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sid Ghosh</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gianluca&nbsp;Piazza</div> <div class="imageTitle">Aluminum Nitride Acousto-Optic Modulator</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project has focused on the realization of a fully integrated platform to enable the modulation of whispering gallery mode resonators with piezoelectrically actuated laterally vibrating MEMS devices for the first time. This method of electrically controlling optomechanical structures through the strong electromechanical coupling afforded by piezoelectric actuation should enable new possibilities for future integrated RF-Photonic modulators. As a result, it can be considered a building block towards the realization of a future RF-Photonic front-end that combines the filtering and frequency reference capabilities of MEMS resonators with photonic integrated circuits. With regard to the current demonstration, there are numerous ways to improve the modulation response. These include the reduction of coupling losses and increasing optical quality factors as well as structural re-designs to match the mechanical modes and reduce damping losses. Nevertheless, the fabrication and design process that has been demonstrated should be able to accommodate all these changes, and also enable scaling to higher frequencies of operation. In summary, this project has made the following original contributions in aluminum nitride:  Demonstration of low loss, wide 1 dB bandwidth C-band      optical grating couplers High-QL (&gt;104) 2D      traveling wave evanescently coupled integrated photonic resonators Development of a robust, CMOS-compatible fabrication      process for concurrent production of acoustic and photonic resonators to      enable optomechanics Piezoelectrically actuated acousto-optic modulator at      653 MHz Opto-acoustic oscillator based on piezoelectric      modulation  Elasto-optic modulator around 800 MHz Approach towards enabling super high frequency (SHF)      operation of photonic   modulators and reference oscillators in an integrated platform based on a      new class of piezoelectric optomechanical devices   The project has enabled the training of two PhD students and two REU students. It has also resulted in material that was included in the PI?s lectures. To educate the broader community and train young engineers, the PI has organized tutorials on the general topic of opto-mechanics at IEEE conferences.       Last Modified: 07/14/2017       Submitted by: Gianluca Piazza]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
