<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PDE Problems in Geometry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>207866.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>207866</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed research is concerned with problems in the field of geometric flows, in particular the Ricci flow and the mean curvature flow. Specifically, we plan to study the evolution of symplectomorphisms under the mean curvature flow. In particular, we want to find condition that guarantee that the mean curvature flow evolves a given symplectomorphism to a biholomorphic isometry. The PI also plans to study self-similar solutions to the Ricci flow. The PI has recently obtained a uniqueness result for the Bryant soliton under a noncollapsing assumption.  It seems interesting to try to construct self-similar solutions which are collapsed, but not rotationally symmetric. Finally, the PI plans to study the gap between the first and second eigenvalue of a Schroedinger operator, building on recent work of Andrews and Clutterbuck.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main goal of this project is to approach problems in differential geometry using tools from analysis, especially partial differential equations. This approach has been successful in the past, and has led to the solution of several major open in the problems in the field, including Min-Oo's Conjecture, the Compactness Conjecture for the Yamabe problem, and the Differentiable Sphere Theorem. The Lagrangian mean curvature flow offers potential applications to mathematical physics, due to its connection with the Strominger-Yau-Zaslow conjecture.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1201924</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Simon</FirstName>
<LastName>Brendle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Simon Brendle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sab2280@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128544112</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000092351</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052125</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~66893</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~69262</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~71711</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main goal of this project has been to understand the formation of singularities in geometric flows. The most important examples of geometric flows are the flow by mean curvature, and Richard Hamilton's Ricci flow. These flows have the interesting property that curvature tends to dissipate in a way similar to heat diffusion. However, it is also possible that the flow may develop a singularity where the curvature becomes infinite. Understanding these singularities is a central problem in geometry. For Ricci flow in dimension 3, Hamilton and Perelman were able to classify the singularities and extend the flow beyond singularities by means of a 'surgery procedure'; this lies at the heart of Perelman's proof of the Poincare Conjecture.</p> <p>As part of this project, the PI and Gerhard Huisken considered similar questions for mean curvature flow. Of particular interest is the case of two-dimensional surfaces in 3-dimensional Euclidean space (or, more generally, in a 3-dimensional manifold). In this situation, we were able to control the flow in a precise way. This made it possible to extend the flow beyond singularities by means of a surgery procedure in the spirit of Hamilton and Perelman. Moreover, we were able to carry out a similar surgery construction for certain fully nonlinear curvature flows in higher dimensions. This required a new approach, as the existing techniques did not carry over to the fully nonlinear setting.</p> <p>In another direction, we were able to confirm a well-known conjecture in the field concerning self-similar solutions to mean curvature flow. Specifically, we were able to classify all self-similar shrinking solutions to mean curvature flow in 3-dimensional Euclidean which are embedded (i.e. free of self-intersections) and of genus 0 (i.e. which have no handles).</p> <p>Finally, the PI and Nicos Kapouleas worked on Page's proposed construction of new Einstein metrics in dimension 4. We showed that the proposed construction does not produce an Einstein metric; instead it leads to a new example of a solution to the Ricci flow which turns out to have interesting properties.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/11/2016<br>      Modified by: Simon&nbsp;Brendle</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main goal of this project has been to understand the formation of singularities in geometric flows. The most important examples of geometric flows are the flow by mean curvature, and Richard Hamilton's Ricci flow. These flows have the interesting property that curvature tends to dissipate in a way similar to heat diffusion. However, it is also possible that the flow may develop a singularity where the curvature becomes infinite. Understanding these singularities is a central problem in geometry. For Ricci flow in dimension 3, Hamilton and Perelman were able to classify the singularities and extend the flow beyond singularities by means of a 'surgery procedure'; this lies at the heart of Perelman's proof of the Poincare Conjecture.  As part of this project, the PI and Gerhard Huisken considered similar questions for mean curvature flow. Of particular interest is the case of two-dimensional surfaces in 3-dimensional Euclidean space (or, more generally, in a 3-dimensional manifold). In this situation, we were able to control the flow in a precise way. This made it possible to extend the flow beyond singularities by means of a surgery procedure in the spirit of Hamilton and Perelman. Moreover, we were able to carry out a similar surgery construction for certain fully nonlinear curvature flows in higher dimensions. This required a new approach, as the existing techniques did not carry over to the fully nonlinear setting.  In another direction, we were able to confirm a well-known conjecture in the field concerning self-similar solutions to mean curvature flow. Specifically, we were able to classify all self-similar shrinking solutions to mean curvature flow in 3-dimensional Euclidean which are embedded (i.e. free of self-intersections) and of genus 0 (i.e. which have no handles).  Finally, the PI and Nicos Kapouleas worked on Page's proposed construction of new Einstein metrics in dimension 4. We showed that the proposed construction does not produce an Einstein metric; instead it leads to a new example of a solution to the Ricci flow which turns out to have interesting properties.          Last Modified: 04/11/2016       Submitted by: Simon Brendle]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
