<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Carolina Dynamics Symposium 2012</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>8190.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>8190</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Taylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding to help defray the expenses of participants, especially women, graduate students, postdocs, and junior faculty, in the "Carolina Dynamics Symposium 2012" that will be held during the Spring of 2012 on the campus of Clemson University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference will cover a variety of topics in analysis, e.g., dynamical systems, mathematical physics, mathematical control theory.  The conference topics are central to analysis and are active and important subjects of current research. The format of the meeting is such that young people will have ample opportunities to speak and be otherwise engaged in the various conference activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/02/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/02/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1201546</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Schmoll</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin J Schmoll</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schmoll@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8646561284</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000219745</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/02/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Predrag</FirstName>
<LastName>Punosevac</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Predrag Punosevac</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>predragp@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122688939</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000601682</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/02/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clemson University</Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296345701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLEMSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clemson University]]></Name>
<CityName>Clemson</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 Brackett, Box 345702]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~8190</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 10th edition of Carolina Dynamics Symposium took place Friday 13th <br />to Sunday 15th of April, 2012 at Clemson University.<br />NSF-funding allowed us to invite four plenary speakers:<br />Sheldon Newhouse (Michigan State), a central figure of dynamical systems<br />theory in the US, with many ties to the Carolina Dynamics Group as<br />former faculty and chair at UNC-Chapel-Hill. Newhouse gave<br />the colloquium talk on Friday, describing problems and theory behind <br />computer based proofs.<br />The other invited speakers were Robert Connelly (Cornell), Serge Tabachnikov (Penn State) and Yuliy Baryshnikov (Urbana/Bell Labs).<br />All three made outstanding contributions to the field robotics and control theory and gave an outline of their results during our Sunday session.<br /><br />Control theory and robotics are relatively young research disciplines, closely connected to dynamical systems theory, and of high value for engineering and science applications. Promoting these research topics, reaching a broad audience ranging from engineers, physicists all the way to theoretical mathematicians was one of the organizers objectives. <br /><br />Most participants from North-Carolina and Georgia arrived <br />Saturday morning for talks of Tabachnikov,&nbsp; Douglas Shafer<br />(UNC Charlotte) and Newhouse.<br />Because of high demand to present research, Saturday afternoon<br />was divided in sections:<br /><br />Differential Equations and Applications,<br />Ergodic Theory,<br />Mathematical Biology and Neuroscience and<br />Billiard Dynamical Systems.<br /><br />Keeping the tradition, Carolina Dynamics Symposium once again<br />heavily supported young researchers: 9 of the 12 sectional talks were delivered by students and post-docs.<br />&nbsp;<br /><br />Among the 45 registered participants were 8 woman,<br />7 undergraduate students, 13 graduate students&nbsp; and<br />2 post-docs, who were all funded.&nbsp;&nbsp; <br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/01/2012<br>      Modified by: Martin&nbsp;J&nbsp;Schmoll</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 10th edition of Carolina Dynamics Symposium took place Friday 13th  to Sunday 15th of April, 2012 at Clemson University. NSF-funding allowed us to invite four plenary speakers: Sheldon Newhouse (Michigan State), a central figure of dynamical systems theory in the US, with many ties to the Carolina Dynamics Group as former faculty and chair at UNC-Chapel-Hill. Newhouse gave the colloquium talk on Friday, describing problems and theory behind  computer based proofs. The other invited speakers were Robert Connelly (Cornell), Serge Tabachnikov (Penn State) and Yuliy Baryshnikov (Urbana/Bell Labs). All three made outstanding contributions to the field robotics and control theory and gave an outline of their results during our Sunday session.  Control theory and robotics are relatively young research disciplines, closely connected to dynamical systems theory, and of high value for engineering and science applications. Promoting these research topics, reaching a broad audience ranging from engineers, physicists all the way to theoretical mathematicians was one of the organizers objectives.   Most participants from North-Carolina and Georgia arrived  Saturday morning for talks of Tabachnikov,  Douglas Shafer (UNC Charlotte) and Newhouse. Because of high demand to present research, Saturday afternoon was divided in sections:  Differential Equations and Applications, Ergodic Theory, Mathematical Biology and Neuroscience and Billiard Dynamical Systems.  Keeping the tradition, Carolina Dynamics Symposium once again heavily supported young researchers: 9 of the 12 sectional talks were delivered by students and post-docs.    Among the 45 registered participants were 8 woman, 7 undergraduate students, 13 graduate students  and 2 post-docs, who were all funded.            Last Modified: 11/01/2012       Submitted by: Martin J Schmoll]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
