<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Problems in Function Theory with Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>187267.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>187267</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Taylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI proposes to study several problems in geometric function theory that have as common underlying theme "conformal invariants" such as the hyperbolic and Kobayashi metric, harmonic measure, Green's functions, and modulus of path families. One such problem consists in studying dimensionality properties of p-Harmonic measure on domains beyond simply-connected ones. A second question deals with generalizations of the Chang-Marshall theorem in space, namely with exponential integrability properties for the trace of analytic functions, and their quasiregular counterparts in higher dimensions, when restricted to the boundary. A third problems studies iteration of analytic functions in one and several dimensions with a focus on the interplay between complex dynamics and the hyperbolic geometry of the unit disk in the complex plane and of the unit ball in higher dimensions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will also draw on the properties of conformal invariants mentioned above to obtain concrete applications in the study of large networks. This is an area that has become more salient with the advent of the internet and the need to analyze large databases (so-called massive data-sets). One example that most people are familiar with is search-engines. The way internet searches work is through random processes that continually sample the web and periodically return averages and other statistics. The simplest such process is called a random crawler or walker and the mathematics that governs its behavior is derived from the study of conformal invariants in geometric function theory. The PI is conducting research that is expected to bring new tools to the task of comparing the behavior of such random processes to the geometry of the data-set. Because of the large applicability of such results the PI will also study the problem of epidemic outbreaks. In this context the PI has already obtained initial funding from the Center for Engagement and Community Development at Kansas State University for a joint project with Professor Scoglio in the Department of Electrical and Computing Engineering and Professor Schumm in the Department of Family Studies. Our team collected data in the city of Chanute, Kansas, and has already built a "contact" network, which is now being analyzed using the conformal invariants mentioned above. The ultimate goal is to provide the city of Chanute with a concrete set of directions that could help its city officials mitigate and manage an epidemic outbreak, especially one of zoonotic nature, originating on a farm.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1201427</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pietro</FirstName>
<LastName>Poggi-Corradini</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pietro Poggi-Corradini</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pietro@math.ksu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7855320569</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000432237</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Caterina</FirstName>
<LastName>Scoglio</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Caterina Scoglio</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>caterina@ksu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7855324646</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000259356</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kansas State University</Name>
<CityName>Manhattan</CityName>
<ZipCode>665061100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7855326804</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2 FAIRCHILD HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1601 VATTIER STREET]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>929773554</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KANSAS STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041146432</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Kansas State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Manhattan</CityName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>665061103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2 Fairchild Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~187267</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <div>Conformal modulus of path families is a powerful tool in function theory, first developed in complex analysis by Arne Beurling and Lars Ahlfors in the 1940's. The successes of modulus and its generalization to p-modulus are too many to list, but for instance it was used to study such disparate objects as hitting probabilities of Brownian motion, hyperbolic manifolds, fractals, the famous Mandelbrot set, etc.</div> <div>The main thrust of our research project was to define, analyze, and apply the concept of p-modulus to networks, namely in a discrete setting. The idea to work with modulus on graphs is not novel, however, we set out to do a systematic study and also we insisted on pursuing interdisciplinary applications to various problems such as: controlling epidemic spreading on networks, &nbsp;quantifying the robustness of a network, and routing information across a network under the risk that pieces of information could be intercepted by third parties.</div> <div>Our team was able to publish 10 papers on these topics. We included in our research project &nbsp;7 undergraduate students, 11 graduate students, as well as 1 postdoc and 1 assistant tenure-track professor. &nbsp;We also organized 3 mathematics conferences and we delivered at least 20 talks at conferences and universities around the world.</div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our efforts have been recognized and have lead to the formation of an interdisciplinary research group at Kansas State University called NODE (Network Optimization, Design and Exploration). Kansas State University is in the process of building a lab and office space for our group. We also have invested a lot of effort in the training mission at the university. For instance, we developed a new year-long graduate course on the "The mathematics of networks and data" and we are now in the process of turning it into an online class as part of the new graduate certificate in Data Analytics offered by KState.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Pietro&nbsp;Poggi-Corradini</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Conformal modulus of path families is a powerful tool in function theory, first developed in complex analysis by Arne Beurling and Lars Ahlfors in the 1940's. The successes of modulus and its generalization to p-modulus are too many to list, but for instance it was used to study such disparate objects as hitting probabilities of Brownian motion, hyperbolic manifolds, fractals, the famous Mandelbrot set, etc. The main thrust of our research project was to define, analyze, and apply the concept of p-modulus to networks, namely in a discrete setting. The idea to work with modulus on graphs is not novel, however, we set out to do a systematic study and also we insisted on pursuing interdisciplinary applications to various problems such as: controlling epidemic spreading on networks,  quantifying the robustness of a network, and routing information across a network under the risk that pieces of information could be intercepted by third parties. Our team was able to publish 10 papers on these topics. We included in our research project  7 undergraduate students, 11 graduate students, as well as 1 postdoc and 1 assistant tenure-track professor.  We also organized 3 mathematics conferences and we delivered at least 20 talks at conferences and universities around the world.     Our efforts have been recognized and have lead to the formation of an interdisciplinary research group at Kansas State University called NODE (Network Optimization, Design and Exploration). Kansas State University is in the process of building a lab and office space for our group. We also have invested a lot of effort in the training mission at the university. For instance, we developed a new year-long graduate course on the "The mathematics of networks and data" and we are now in the process of turning it into an online class as part of the new graduate certificate in Data Analytics offered by KState.           Last Modified: 07/30/2016       Submitted by: Pietro Poggi-Corradini]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
