<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Virginia-North Carolina Alliance for Minority Participation: Mid-level LSAMP</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>3500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>3500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leroy Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Virginia - North Carolina Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (VA-NC Alliance) will broaden the participation of underrepresented minority populations (UREP) in the science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) disciplines. The VA-NC Alliance consists of eight colleges and universities in Virginia and North Carolina: four historically black colleges and universities including Bennett College for Women, Elizabeth City State University, Johnson C. Smith University, and Saint Augustine?s College; and four doctorate-granting/research-extensive universities including George Mason University, the University of Virginia, Virginia Commonwealth University, and Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, which will continue to lead the consortium. The Alliance will be expanded with the addition of Piedmont Virginia Community College. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The VA-NC Alliance integrates students into their academic institutions and provides disciplinary socialization opportunities; in addition, partner schools collaborate to retain students across the critical junctures between secondary schools, two-year institutions, four-year colleges or universities, and graduate programs. The VA-NC Alliance?s goal is to substantially increase the number of STEM baccalaureate degrees earned annually by UREP students. Alliance students are equipped with the knowledge, skills, and experiences to transition successfully to graduate school. As a secondary goal, the Alliance will increase the number of UREP STEM students entering graduate school. The Alliance offers a broad array of activities including research experiences, symposia, workshops, and graduate school preparation retreats which are open to all students and faculty at partner schools. The synergy created by sharing resources across institutional lines in order to achieve a common goal is exemplified by the VA-NC Alliance Summer Research Program, which brings select students from partner schools to one campus to engage research projects with faculty. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The VA-NC Alliance project will create new knowledge, innovations and models for broadening the participation of underrepresented groups in STEM disciplines and the STEM workforce. Results of these efforts will be disseminated.  Project evaluation and monitoring activities will yield evidence-based knowledge concerning the effectiveness of the various broadening participation models and innovations.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The VA-NC Alliance will yield broader impacts by increasing the quantity and quality of UREP STEM graduates well prepared to succeed at the graduate level, and contribute to the STEM workforce. In order to address the challenges of the 21st century, particularly in the science and technology sectors, the increased diversification of the United States labor force is critical to enhancing the nation?s competitiveness. By tapping into a workforce underrepresented in the STEM fields, the VA-NC Alliance will ensure that diverse perspectives are applied to complex and global problems, benefitting its geographic region and the nation as a whole.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1202181</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Archie</FirstName>
<LastName>Holmes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Archie L Holmes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>archieholmes@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4349247770</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000380660</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carolyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Vallas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carolyn Vallas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cv5d@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4349240614</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000472165</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marcus</FirstName>
<LastName>Martin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marcus L Martin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mlm8n@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4342432079</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000245652</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
<LastName>Columbus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Linda M Columbus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>columbus@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4342432123</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000086743</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O.  BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065391526</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RECTOR &amp; VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065391526</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Virginia Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlottesville</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 400195]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9133</Code>
<Text>Alliances-Minority Participat.</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1400000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~700000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~1400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Virginia-North Carolina Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (VA-NC Alliance) received funding from the National Science Foundation (NSF) for $3.5 million dollars starting September 15, 2012 and ending August 31, 2017.&nbsp; The VA-NC Alliance was approved for a one-year no-cost extension, extending the grant until August 31, 2018.&nbsp; During this Mid-level Phase, the Alliance was comprised of the following schools: Bennett College, Elizabeth City State University (ECSU), George Mason University (GMU), Johnson C. Smith University (JCSU), Saint Augustine's University (SAU), University of Virginia (UVA), Virginia Commonwealth University (VCU), Virginia Tech (VT), and its first community college partner: Piedmont Virginia Community College (PVCC). The VA-NC Alliance partner schools worked together towards the primary goals of increasing by 60 percent the number of underrepresented minority (URM) students enrolled in and graduating from the science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) fields.</p> <p>The VA-NC Alliance's enrollment and degree data illustrate its <strong>broader impact</strong> of increasing the quality and quantity of underrepresented students in STEM fields. From it baseline to academic year 2016-2017, the Mid-level Phase of the VA-NC Alliance reported a 54 percent increase in the number of URM STEM students enrolled at its partner schools and a 109 percent increase in the number of URM STEM students who graduated (see attached graphs).&nbsp; Over the five years for which data are available during the Mid-level phase, 5,499 URM STEM students earned degrees at VA-NC Alliance partner schools. These students will have been well-prepared to succeed in graduate school and the STEM workforce, helping to meet the needs of the U.S. labor force.</p> <p>During its Mid-level Phase, the VA-NC Alliance provided professional development activities, financial support, community building opportunities, and academic programming for its students, including: transition programs, annual undergraduate research symposia, research experiences, tutoring, mentoring, and other activities designed to reinforce students' academic success. Many incoming freshman students began their participation with the VA-NC Alliance through bridge programs including traditional summer residential programs as well as online options. At GMU and VCU, students engaged in hybrid bridge programs with both online instruction and a short residential experience to become acclimated to their campuses. PVCC implemented a bridge program for local high school students. At JCSU, students received academic support from faculty during its Saturday Academy program.</p> <p>Engaging its students in undergraduate research remained a top priority of the consortium, and the VA-NC Alliance Summer Research Program continued to be one of the partnership's signature activities. During the Mid-level Phase and one-year no-cost-extension, the VA-NC Alliance hosted annual cohorts of summer researchers at UVA with research tracks in astronomy, biology, chemistry, computer science, data science, engineering, environmental science, neuroscience, and physics. The summer research program strengthened connections between the partner schools, UVA STEM departments, and the National Radio Astronomy Observatory in Charlottesville, Virginia, leveraging UVA and local resources. At both Bennett College and ECSU, Alliance scholars were required to engage in STEM research under the guidance of a faculty member. The Alliance management team promoted participation in research experiences and sent regular email bulletins about opportunities to its partner schools and posted these on the LSAMP.VIRGINIA.EDU website. Several Alliance students participated in international research experiences including: the Organization for Tropical Studies REU in Costa Rica; the European Molecular Biology Laboratory REU in Grenoble, France; and the REU in Austria at Graz University of Technology.</p> <p>VA-NC Alliance students had numerous opportunities to present their research during the Mid-level Phase and one-year no-cost-extension. The VA-NC Alliance hosted its Annual Undergraduate Research Symposia, rotating venues between Virginia and North Carolina partner schools.&nbsp; On average more than 100 participants registered for each of these symposia and at least 30 percent of students gave oral or poster presentations. Saint Augustine's University hosted the Tenth Anniversary of the VA-NC Alliance Undergraduate Research Symposium in the spring of 2017 and featured invited speakers from the NSF, the United States Congress, and other honored guests. For the 2017 symposium, the VA-NC Alliance created an award category specifically for community college students' presentations, and welcomed participation from a regional Bridge to the Baccalaureate program, the NC STEM Alliance. In addition to the Alliance's annual symposium, students presented their research at national conferences<em>. </em>The substantive knowledge contributed by students to the STEM fields demonstrated the <strong>intellectual merit</strong> of the VA-NC Alliance.</p> <p>VA-NC Alliance institutions hosted graduate school preparation retreats for students from partner schools, including but not limited to: the Alliance Graduate School Preparation Retreat at VT; GEM GradLab hosted by the GEM Consortium, the University of Maryland, Baltimore County, and UVA; and a graduate school preparation event hosted by the Commonwealth Center for Advanced Manufacturing in Richmond, VA in collaboration with UVA and VT. In addition, the VA-NC Alliance website shared information about application fee waivers and currently funded Bridge to the Doctorate programs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Marcus&nbsp;L&nbsp;Martin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342060070_Korey_horizontalmicroscope--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342060070_Korey_horizontalmicroscope--rgov-800width.jpg" title="VA-NC Alliance Student Conducting Research"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342060070_Korey_horizontalmicroscope--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="VA-NC Alliance Student Conducting Research"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Johnson C. Smith University student Korey Smith conducting research at the University of Virginia</div> <div class="imageCredit">Cole Geddy</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Marcus&nbsp;L&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">VA-NC Alliance Student Conducting Research</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342320950_midleveldegreegraph_110118--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342320950_midleveldegreegraph_110118--rgov-800width.jpg" title="VA-NC Alliance Mid-level Degree Graph"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342320950_midleveldegreegraph_110118--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="VA-NC Alliance Mid-level Degree Graph"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Mid-level Phase of the VA-NC Alliance was very successful with a 109 percent increase in the number of URM STEM students who earned undergraduate degrees from partner institutions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kristin Morgan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Marcus&nbsp;L&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">VA-NC Alliance Mid-level Degree Graph</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342492318_midlevelenrollmentgraph_110118--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342492318_midlevelenrollmentgraph_110118--rgov-800width.jpg" title="VA-NC Alliance Enrollment Graph"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342492318_midlevelenrollmentgraph_110118--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="VA-NC Alliance Enrollment Graph"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Mid-level Phase of the VA-NC Alliance was very successful with a 54 percent increase in the number of URM STEM students enrolled at its partner schools.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kristin Morgan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Marcus&nbsp;L&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">VA-NC Alliance Enrollment Graph</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342708048_Sarai_Alvarez_-_Laura_Barnes_01HR_DAresized--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342708048_Sarai_Alvarez_-_Laura_Barnes_01HR_DAresized--rgov-800width.jpg" title="VA-NC Alliance Summer Researcher Discussing Project with Faculty Mentor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342708048_Sarai_Alvarez_-_Laura_Barnes_01HR_DAresized--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="VA-NC Alliance Summer Researcher Discussing Project with Faculty Mentor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">VA-NC Alliance summer researcher Sarai Alvarez from George Mason University discussing her project with University of Virginia professor Laura Barnes</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dan Addison</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Marcus&nbsp;L&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">VA-NC Alliance Summer Researcher Discussing Project with Faculty Mentor</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342887649_GBTsmallgroup2017--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342887649_GBTsmallgroup2017--rgov-800width.jpg" title="VA-NC Alliance Summer Researchers at the Green Bank Observatory"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543342887649_GBTsmallgroup2017--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="VA-NC Alliance Summer Researchers at the Green Bank Observatory"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Some of the 2017 summer researchers visiting the Green Bank Observatory in Green Bank, West Virginia (affiliated with the National Radio Astronomy Observatory)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Devante Cunningham</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Marcus&nbsp;L&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">VA-NC Alliance Summer Researchers at the Green Bank Observatory</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543343098242_MiahPerchpresenting--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543343098242_MiahPerchpresenting--rgov-800width.jpg" title="VA-NC Alliance Student Presents Capstone Research Project"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1202181/1202181_10212457_1543343098242_MiahPerchpresenting--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="VA-NC Alliance Student Presents Capstone Research Project"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Piedmont Virginia Community College student Miah Perch presents her capstone research project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kristin Morgan</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Marcus&nbsp;L&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">VA-NC Alliance Student Presents Capstone Research Project</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Virginia-North Carolina Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (VA-NC Alliance) received funding from the National Science Foundation (NSF) for $3.5 million dollars starting September 15, 2012 and ending August 31, 2017.  The VA-NC Alliance was approved for a one-year no-cost extension, extending the grant until August 31, 2018.  During this Mid-level Phase, the Alliance was comprised of the following schools: Bennett College, Elizabeth City State University (ECSU), George Mason University (GMU), Johnson C. Smith University (JCSU), Saint Augustine's University (SAU), University of Virginia (UVA), Virginia Commonwealth University (VCU), Virginia Tech (VT), and its first community college partner: Piedmont Virginia Community College (PVCC). The VA-NC Alliance partner schools worked together towards the primary goals of increasing by 60 percent the number of underrepresented minority (URM) students enrolled in and graduating from the science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) fields.  The VA-NC Alliance's enrollment and degree data illustrate its broader impact of increasing the quality and quantity of underrepresented students in STEM fields. From it baseline to academic year 2016-2017, the Mid-level Phase of the VA-NC Alliance reported a 54 percent increase in the number of URM STEM students enrolled at its partner schools and a 109 percent increase in the number of URM STEM students who graduated (see attached graphs).  Over the five years for which data are available during the Mid-level phase, 5,499 URM STEM students earned degrees at VA-NC Alliance partner schools. These students will have been well-prepared to succeed in graduate school and the STEM workforce, helping to meet the needs of the U.S. labor force.  During its Mid-level Phase, the VA-NC Alliance provided professional development activities, financial support, community building opportunities, and academic programming for its students, including: transition programs, annual undergraduate research symposia, research experiences, tutoring, mentoring, and other activities designed to reinforce students' academic success. Many incoming freshman students began their participation with the VA-NC Alliance through bridge programs including traditional summer residential programs as well as online options. At GMU and VCU, students engaged in hybrid bridge programs with both online instruction and a short residential experience to become acclimated to their campuses. PVCC implemented a bridge program for local high school students. At JCSU, students received academic support from faculty during its Saturday Academy program.  Engaging its students in undergraduate research remained a top priority of the consortium, and the VA-NC Alliance Summer Research Program continued to be one of the partnership's signature activities. During the Mid-level Phase and one-year no-cost-extension, the VA-NC Alliance hosted annual cohorts of summer researchers at UVA with research tracks in astronomy, biology, chemistry, computer science, data science, engineering, environmental science, neuroscience, and physics. The summer research program strengthened connections between the partner schools, UVA STEM departments, and the National Radio Astronomy Observatory in Charlottesville, Virginia, leveraging UVA and local resources. At both Bennett College and ECSU, Alliance scholars were required to engage in STEM research under the guidance of a faculty member. The Alliance management team promoted participation in research experiences and sent regular email bulletins about opportunities to its partner schools and posted these on the LSAMP.VIRGINIA.EDU website. Several Alliance students participated in international research experiences including: the Organization for Tropical Studies REU in Costa Rica; the European Molecular Biology Laboratory REU in Grenoble, France; and the REU in Austria at Graz University of Technology.  VA-NC Alliance students had numerous opportunities to present their research during the Mid-level Phase and one-year no-cost-extension. The VA-NC Alliance hosted its Annual Undergraduate Research Symposia, rotating venues between Virginia and North Carolina partner schools.  On average more than 100 participants registered for each of these symposia and at least 30 percent of students gave oral or poster presentations. Saint Augustine's University hosted the Tenth Anniversary of the VA-NC Alliance Undergraduate Research Symposium in the spring of 2017 and featured invited speakers from the NSF, the United States Congress, and other honored guests. For the 2017 symposium, the VA-NC Alliance created an award category specifically for community college students' presentations, and welcomed participation from a regional Bridge to the Baccalaureate program, the NC STEM Alliance. In addition to the Alliance's annual symposium, students presented their research at national conferences. The substantive knowledge contributed by students to the STEM fields demonstrated the intellectual merit of the VA-NC Alliance.  VA-NC Alliance institutions hosted graduate school preparation retreats for students from partner schools, including but not limited to: the Alliance Graduate School Preparation Retreat at VT; GEM GradLab hosted by the GEM Consortium, the University of Maryland, Baltimore County, and UVA; and a graduate school preparation event hosted by the Commonwealth Center for Advanced Manufacturing in Richmond, VA in collaboration with UVA and VT. In addition, the VA-NC Alliance website shared information about application fee waivers and currently funded Bridge to the Doctorate programs.          Last Modified: 11/27/2018       Submitted by: Marcus L Martin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
