<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Topics in Computable Structure Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>133557.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>133557</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Harizanov and her students and their collaborators investigate algorithmic properties of general and concrete mathematical structures arising in algebra, model theory, and topology. This requires intricate interplay of computability theory with algebra, topology, and geometry. Harizanov?s goal is to understand the computability theoretic properties of countable structures and their isomorphisms, and of natural relations on the domains of the structures. She studies the connections between definability and computability. The Turing degree spectra of structures can be related to the degree spectra of relations via spectrally universal structures, which are often obtained as Fraisse limits. Harizanov?s project includes model-theoretic complexity of computable structures measured by their Scott rank.  It also includes classification problems such as the isomorphism problem and the embedding problem for natural classes of algebraic structures. Harizanov studies the left orders and bi-orders of various torsion-free groups, including free groups, surface and braid groups, and how the topological properties of the spaces of orders relate to the computability-theoretic properties of orders. The project involves important new directions in computable structure theory, including the study of Turing degrees of the isomorphism types of geometric objects, such as varieties and schemes, and of structures with a nonassociative binary operation of importance in low-dimensional topology, such as quandles. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Computable structure theory is a very active research area that has blossomed in the last few decades. It is of importance in theoretical mathematics and computer science and in the philosophy of mathematics. Some mathematical constructions are essentially nonalgorithmic, while the others are algorithmic, or can be replaced by algorithmic ones yielding the same results.  Computability theory has developed powerful and unique techniques to further analyze and classify nonalgorithmic mathematical objects. Such methods involve syntactic descriptions using computable infinitary language, as well as Turing and other degree theoretic measures of relative computational complexity of sets and problems they encode.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1202328</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Valentina</FirstName>
<LastName>Harizanov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Valentina Harizanov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>harizanv@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2029946595</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000334683</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1922 F Street NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[4th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2115 G Street NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1268</Code>
<Text>FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~133557</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project falls in the realm of computable model theory, a branch of mathematical logic that applies ideas and methods of computability theory to examine the computational difficulty of problems in model theory. Classical computability theory formalized the intuitive notion of a decision procedure or algorithm, and provided the theoretical basis for digital computers.&nbsp; It also demonstrated the limitations of algorithms and showed that most mathematical objects, such as functions (transformations), relations, and structures, are not computable.&nbsp; Important results of modern computability theory include measuring relative computational difficulty of non-computable objects, for example, using the Turing degree of an object. Model theory provides a rigorous mathematical framework for the notions of structure and truth.&nbsp; A model, a concept used in all of the sciences, describes a portion of reality by using a formal language to express properties under study.</p> <p>Harizanov&rsquo;s goal is to understand how structural properties interact with and affect algorithmic properties. She and collaborators established a number of results that advanced the understanding of complexity of countable mathematical models, of their structure preserving transformations, and relations, as well as of classes of structures. More specifically, they investigated the complexity of structure preserving transformations using the Turing degree hierarchy, and focusing on computable and limit-computable transformations and the classification of computable structures for which such transformations must exist. Examples were obtained in natural classes of structures where computable or limit-computable transformations do not come from definability using corresponding computable infinitary formulae. Harizanov and collaborators also determined the exact complexity of the problems dealing with the existence of computable and structure preserving transformations between models having extra decidability properties as described using specific fragments of the formal language. Harizanov and collaborators investigated Turing degree spectra of relations and how they relate to and differ from the degree spectra of structures. In particular, they obtained degree spectra of structures, as well as of relations, which contain specific sets of degrees that come from Turing&rsquo;s iterated halting problem hierarchy. Harizanov and collaborators classified classes of structures using a computability-theoretic notion of reducibility. This led to some surprising results in comparison with those in classical mathematics.</p> <p>Harizanov was active in organizing national and international conferences and special sessions. She ran the logic seminar and quantum computing events at GW. She presented papers related to the project at major national and international conferences and in the Washington area. For example, she was a plenary speaker at the meeting of the MD-DC-VA section of the Mathematical Association of America in fall 2014. Harizanov contributed to the training of undergraduate and graduate students through teaching innovative courses and direct mentoring of research projects and dissertations. In addition to research papers, Harizanov co-authored a chapter in the volume Turing&rsquo;s Legacy: Developments from Turing Ideas in Logic published by the Cambridge University Press in 2014, and co-edited a book Logic and Algebraic Structures in Quantum Computing published by the Cambridge University Press in 2016.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/15/2016<br>      Modified by: Valentina&nbsp;Harizanov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project falls in the realm of computable model theory, a branch of mathematical logic that applies ideas and methods of computability theory to examine the computational difficulty of problems in model theory. Classical computability theory formalized the intuitive notion of a decision procedure or algorithm, and provided the theoretical basis for digital computers.  It also demonstrated the limitations of algorithms and showed that most mathematical objects, such as functions (transformations), relations, and structures, are not computable.  Important results of modern computability theory include measuring relative computational difficulty of non-computable objects, for example, using the Turing degree of an object. Model theory provides a rigorous mathematical framework for the notions of structure and truth.  A model, a concept used in all of the sciences, describes a portion of reality by using a formal language to express properties under study.  Harizanov?s goal is to understand how structural properties interact with and affect algorithmic properties. She and collaborators established a number of results that advanced the understanding of complexity of countable mathematical models, of their structure preserving transformations, and relations, as well as of classes of structures. More specifically, they investigated the complexity of structure preserving transformations using the Turing degree hierarchy, and focusing on computable and limit-computable transformations and the classification of computable structures for which such transformations must exist. Examples were obtained in natural classes of structures where computable or limit-computable transformations do not come from definability using corresponding computable infinitary formulae. Harizanov and collaborators also determined the exact complexity of the problems dealing with the existence of computable and structure preserving transformations between models having extra decidability properties as described using specific fragments of the formal language. Harizanov and collaborators investigated Turing degree spectra of relations and how they relate to and differ from the degree spectra of structures. In particular, they obtained degree spectra of structures, as well as of relations, which contain specific sets of degrees that come from Turing?s iterated halting problem hierarchy. Harizanov and collaborators classified classes of structures using a computability-theoretic notion of reducibility. This led to some surprising results in comparison with those in classical mathematics.  Harizanov was active in organizing national and international conferences and special sessions. She ran the logic seminar and quantum computing events at GW. She presented papers related to the project at major national and international conferences and in the Washington area. For example, she was a plenary speaker at the meeting of the MD-DC-VA section of the Mathematical Association of America in fall 2014. Harizanov contributed to the training of undergraduate and graduate students through teaching innovative courses and direct mentoring of research projects and dissertations. In addition to research papers, Harizanov co-authored a chapter in the volume Turing?s Legacy: Developments from Turing Ideas in Logic published by the Cambridge University Press in 2014, and co-edited a book Logic and Algebraic Structures in Quantum Computing published by the Cambridge University Press in 2016.       Last Modified: 10/15/2016       Submitted by: Valentina Harizanov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
