<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CSBR: Natural History Collections: Compactorization of the vascular plant herbarium of NC State Univ to alleviate space constraints and allow research- and training-driven growth</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>148338.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>148338</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The North Carolina State University vascular plant herbarium (NCSC) is specialized in the flora of North Carolina and the southeastern US, continuing its mission to document and understand plant diversity and to transfer the taxonomic expertise developed to various users that depend on the generated knowledge.  This project focuses on the: (1) compactorization of NCSC to alleviate specimen damage from current space constraints and allow for continued research- and training-driven growth, and the (2) imaging and databasing of a component of the collection, providing a training opportunity for undergraduates and engagement of the public through a citizen science approach.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The resulting publically available database of specimen label information, species distribution maps, and images has many practical applications, including increased capacity for survey and documentation, climate studies, and precision natural resource management.  Also, because of NCSC's initiative to require silica-gel collections in addition to standard vouchers in floristic research, NCSC holdings will be significantly informative to studies at various levels of organization from molecules to ecosystems.  In addition, to close the gap between modern collections-based research and K-12 education, NCSC is partnering with NC 4-H and high school teachers to develop lessons on genetic diversity, classification, and adaptive evolution. For additional information, see the NCSC website: http://herbarium.ncsu.edu/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/02/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1203409</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Krings</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander Krings</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Alexander_Krings@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195152700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000256637</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/02/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957612</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1197</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH COLLECTION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~148338</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>For over 110 years, the North Carolina State University vascular plant herbarium (NCSC) has specialized in the flora of North Carolina and the southeastern United States (SEUS). The holdings of NCSC include significant historical collections unique to the development of taxonomy, ecology, and general plant science in the SEUS, as well as outstanding recent and historical collections from North Carolina state parks and natural areas. NCSC remains one of the few research-extensive institutions in the Southeast to maintain an intensive floristic training program and the only research-extensive institution in North Carolina emphasizing floristics at the master&rsquo;s level. NCSC integrates the strengths of NCSU&mdash;teaching, research, extension, and engagement&mdash;through its mission: (1) To document and understand plant diversity, and (2) to transfer the taxonomic expertise developed to various users that depend on the generated knowledge. NCSC is active in understanding and documenting plant diversity both locally, nationally, and internationally. Efforts by NCSC-affiliated researchers to transfer taxonomic expertise through graduate-level training and primary research seek to contribute to easing the &ldquo;taxonomic impediment&rdquo; to the sound management of biodiversity that has been identified by governments through the Convention on Biological Diversity. However, NCSC outgrew its space over a decade ago and the collection showed significant signs of stress from the compounded effect of heavy usage and specimens overcrowding cabinets. Overcrowding is a major issue affecting the long-term security of the collection, as well as its growth.&nbsp; Without adequate space, NCSC could not continue to accession specimens from floristic efforts, thus limiting knowledge growth and transfer.&nbsp; To overcome these issues, this project focused on (1) the compactorization of these collections and (2) imaging and databasing the component of the collection (40,000 specimens) for which such support was not concurrently being sought under a different grant panel. The awarded funds were used to support (1) the purchase and installation of a mobile aisle storage system, (2) twenty-six additional herbarium cabinets to fill out the mobile carriages, and (3) part-time, temporary student technicians to facilitate imaging, databasing, and the associated release of the inherent biodiversity data to the scientific community at large through online data portals. &nbsp;The project will impact undergraduate and graduate training, as well as outreach to all groups&mdash;including those historically underrepresented in science&mdash;through secondary education. &nbsp;As a component of the project, NCSC partnered with the 4-H program in the state to develop six curriculum lessons that incorporated NC Essential Standards for Science for High School Biology.&nbsp; At the conclusion of the period of the grant, all objectives outlined above were met. &nbsp;A mobile aisle system was successfully installed, alleviating space constraints and positioning NCSC for future growth. Images and label data were captured for the targeted 40,000-specimen set and made available to researchers and the public worldwide through the SERNEC Symbiota portal (sernecportal.org), as well as iDigBio (idigbio.org). Six curriculum activites were developed through the process described above and made available to educators (https://projects.ncsu.edu/cals/plantbiology/ncsc/4H/).&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Alexander&nbsp;Krings</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1203409/1203409_10170020_1496170858260_NCSC_compactors--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1203409/1203409_10170020_1496170858260_NCSC_compactors--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Compactors at NCSC"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1203409/1203409_10170020_1496170858260_NCSC_compactors--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Compactors at NCSC"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Mobile system ("compactors") at the North Carolina State University Vascular Plant Herbarium.</div> <div class="imageCredit">A. Krings</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alexander&nbsp;Krings</div> <div class="imageTitle">Compactors at NCSC</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For over 110 years, the North Carolina State University vascular plant herbarium (NCSC) has specialized in the flora of North Carolina and the southeastern United States (SEUS). The holdings of NCSC include significant historical collections unique to the development of taxonomy, ecology, and general plant science in the SEUS, as well as outstanding recent and historical collections from North Carolina state parks and natural areas. NCSC remains one of the few research-extensive institutions in the Southeast to maintain an intensive floristic training program and the only research-extensive institution in North Carolina emphasizing floristics at the master?s level. NCSC integrates the strengths of NCSU&mdash;teaching, research, extension, and engagement&mdash;through its mission: (1) To document and understand plant diversity, and (2) to transfer the taxonomic expertise developed to various users that depend on the generated knowledge. NCSC is active in understanding and documenting plant diversity both locally, nationally, and internationally. Efforts by NCSC-affiliated researchers to transfer taxonomic expertise through graduate-level training and primary research seek to contribute to easing the "taxonomic impediment" to the sound management of biodiversity that has been identified by governments through the Convention on Biological Diversity. However, NCSC outgrew its space over a decade ago and the collection showed significant signs of stress from the compounded effect of heavy usage and specimens overcrowding cabinets. Overcrowding is a major issue affecting the long-term security of the collection, as well as its growth.  Without adequate space, NCSC could not continue to accession specimens from floristic efforts, thus limiting knowledge growth and transfer.  To overcome these issues, this project focused on (1) the compactorization of these collections and (2) imaging and databasing the component of the collection (40,000 specimens) for which such support was not concurrently being sought under a different grant panel. The awarded funds were used to support (1) the purchase and installation of a mobile aisle storage system, (2) twenty-six additional herbarium cabinets to fill out the mobile carriages, and (3) part-time, temporary student technicians to facilitate imaging, databasing, and the associated release of the inherent biodiversity data to the scientific community at large through online data portals.  The project will impact undergraduate and graduate training, as well as outreach to all groups&mdash;including those historically underrepresented in science&mdash;through secondary education.  As a component of the project, NCSC partnered with the 4-H program in the state to develop six curriculum lessons that incorporated NC Essential Standards for Science for High School Biology.  At the conclusion of the period of the grant, all objectives outlined above were met.  A mobile aisle system was successfully installed, alleviating space constraints and positioning NCSC for future growth. Images and label data were captured for the targeted 40,000-specimen set and made available to researchers and the public worldwide through the SERNEC Symbiota portal (sernecportal.org), as well as iDigBio (idigbio.org). Six curriculum activites were developed through the process described above and made available to educators (https://projects.ncsu.edu/cals/plantbiology/ncsc/4H/).           Last Modified: 05/30/2017       Submitted by: Alexander Krings]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
