<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A combined proxy and model investigation of Late Holocene paleoclimate in the Horn of Africa</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10098.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10098</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Candace Major</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cmajor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927597</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project seeks to investigate the mechanisms causing drought events in the Horn of Africa over the last 4,500 years using a combination of proxy measurements and modeling. Researchers from the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute and Columbia University's Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory will collaborate to generate the first known paleoclimate record for the region. The project will use proxy data from a sediment core collected in the Gulf of Aden to determine regional sea surface temperatures (Mg/Ca, TEX86) and hydroclimate (carbon and hydrogen isotopes from plant leaf waxes) at a resolution of ~20 years. The regional sea surface temperature data will be used to drive Community Earth System Model (CESM) simulations of key drought and pluvial events. Model output will be compared with the proxy hydroclimate record to assess the Horn of Africa's sensitivity to regional SSTs versus more remote (global) climate drivers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Drought history in the Horn of Africa is closely tied to political instability, making its population particularly vulnerable to climate change. The investigators will engage policy makers focused on this issue through a workshop held in collaboration with the Woodrow Wilson Center's Environmental Change and Security Program. The project will support three early-career researchers, two of which are female with no prior NSF support, as well as training of an undergraduate student.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1203295</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>DeMenocal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter DeMenocal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pdemenocal@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6462566278</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000163155</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>Palisades</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>109641000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[61 Route 9W]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1304</Code>
<Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~10098</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project focused on advancing our understanding of past controls on the hydroclimate of the Horn of Africa region. The paleoclimate history of this region is very poorly understood due to the paucity of suitable records, yet this is a geopolitical 'hotspot' where current and future claimte changes impact a large and vulnerable population.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our results have been summarized in three publications. In Tierney and deMenocal, 2013, we document the abrupt, century-scale, onset and collapse of the African Humid Period based on plant wax dD and d13C analyses on the Gulf of Aden core studied with this project funding. Tierney, Pausata and deMenocal., 2015, we document that the deglacial indian monsoon failure was linked to a increased stratification of the western Indian Ocean. And in Tierney, Ummenhofer, and deMenocal (2015) we show for the first time that the current multidecadal drought in the Horn of Africa is a consequence of the climatic impacts of human carbon emissions. The drought is captured by increasing plant wax dD values and is conicident with declining d13C resulting from the Suess effect from fossil fuel combustion. We further show that this drying trend was not projected in most of the IPCC climate models due to an adequate representation of the complex rainfall dynamics in the Horn of Africa region.&nbsp;</p> <p>1.<span> </span>Tierney, J. E., Ummenhofer, C. C. &amp; deMenocal, P. B. Past and future rainfall in the Horn of Africa. <em>Science Advances</em> <strong>1,</strong> e1500682&ndash;e1500682 (2015).</p> <p>2.<span> </span>Tierney, J. E., Pausata, F. S. R. &amp; deMenocal, P. Deglacial Indian monsoon failure and North Atlantic stadials linked by Indian Ocean surface&nbsp;cooling. <em>Nature Geoscience</em> (2015). doi:10.1038/ngeo2603</p> <p>3.<span> </span>Tierney, J. E. &amp; deMenocal, P. B. Abrupt Shifts in Horn of Africa Hydroclimate Since the Last Glacial Maximum. <em>Science</em> <strong>342,</strong> 843&ndash;846 (2013).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/23/2015<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;Demenocal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project focused on advancing our understanding of past controls on the hydroclimate of the Horn of Africa region. The paleoclimate history of this region is very poorly understood due to the paucity of suitable records, yet this is a geopolitical 'hotspot' where current and future claimte changes impact a large and vulnerable population.   Our results have been summarized in three publications. In Tierney and deMenocal, 2013, we document the abrupt, century-scale, onset and collapse of the African Humid Period based on plant wax dD and d13C analyses on the Gulf of Aden core studied with this project funding. Tierney, Pausata and deMenocal., 2015, we document that the deglacial indian monsoon failure was linked to a increased stratification of the western Indian Ocean. And in Tierney, Ummenhofer, and deMenocal (2015) we show for the first time that the current multidecadal drought in the Horn of Africa is a consequence of the climatic impacts of human carbon emissions. The drought is captured by increasing plant wax dD values and is conicident with declining d13C resulting from the Suess effect from fossil fuel combustion. We further show that this drying trend was not projected in most of the IPCC climate models due to an adequate representation of the complex rainfall dynamics in the Horn of Africa region.   1. Tierney, J. E., Ummenhofer, C. C. &amp; deMenocal, P. B. Past and future rainfall in the Horn of Africa. Science Advances 1, e1500682&ndash;e1500682 (2015).  2. Tierney, J. E., Pausata, F. S. R. &amp; deMenocal, P. Deglacial Indian monsoon failure and North Atlantic stadials linked by Indian Ocean surface cooling. Nature Geoscience (2015). doi:10.1038/ngeo2603  3. Tierney, J. E. &amp; deMenocal, P. B. Abrupt Shifts in Horn of Africa Hydroclimate Since the Last Glacial Maximum. Science 342, 843&ndash;846 (2013).             Last Modified: 12/23/2015       Submitted by: Peter Demenocal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
