<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Continuation of Development and Application of AO-FVCOM to Improve Understanding of Arctic Changes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>357698.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>357698</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anjuli Bamzai</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abamzai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928688</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PIs have successfully developed a high-resolution unstructured-grid, finitevolume&lt;br/&gt;coupled ice-ocean model for the Arctic Ocean (AO-FVCOM). AO-FVCOM has been&lt;br/&gt;validated via comparison to observed data under climatological conditions. Now they seek support to work on the following three tasks: &lt;br/&gt;1) Calibrate and validate AO-FVCOM using observational data collected in the Canada Arctic Basin and its marginal Chukchi and Beaufort Sea. This region is chosen for intense study because it has the most pronounced loss of sea ice extent and thickness in recent years and its unprecedented coverage by multiyear national and international field and modeling studies. &lt;br/&gt;2) Apply the new calibrated and validated AV-FVCOM to investigate the following scientific topics: &lt;br/&gt;a) improve understanding of the circulation of the Alaskan Coastal Current and Pacific and Atlantic waters in the study region, &lt;br/&gt;b) revisit scientific questions and methodological problems associated with shelf-basin exchange (SBE) processes in the region, and &lt;br/&gt;c) apply AO-FVCOM to investigate transformations and transports of fresh water (both liquid and solid) from freshwater sources (Bering Strait, rivers, central Beaufort Gyre, precipitation) towards the North Atlantic Ocean via Fram and Canadian Archipelago Straits. &lt;br/&gt;3) Train a Ph.D. student in advanced Arctic Ocean modeling.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Successful completion of this project will provide an additional protocol for modeling Arctic Ocean processes.  It will also advance understanding of the circulation and mixing processes in the Arctic Ocean, processes which will grow in socio-economic importance with increasing ice loss and development activities in this part of the globe.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1203393</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chang-Sheng</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chang-Sheng Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>c1chen@umassd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5089106388</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000103960</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts, Dartmouth</Name>
<CityName>North Dartmouth</CityName>
<ZipCode>027472300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5089998953</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>285 Old Westport Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>799477427</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[School for Marine Science and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>New Bedford</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>027441221</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[706 South Rodney French Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5219</Code>
<Text>ARCSS-Arctic System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~357698</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Arctic climate has changed significantly in the past three decades. The summer sea-ice concentration, for instance, has decreased considerably since the 1970s. The observed change in sea ice is undoubtedly due to interactions between the atmosphere and ocean. Among these three components, the ocean remains the least observed and also likely the least understood. More observations, improvements in numerical models and a better theoretic framework/model are all needed in the Arctic physical oceanography. A state-of-art Arctic Ocean model requires: (1) flexible and high resolution horizontal and vertical grids to represent the complex coastline, steep continental slopes and strong upper ocean stratification; (2) mass conservation to accurately simulate mass, heat and salt transformations and transports; (3) proper parameterization of vertical and lateral mixing, (4) advanced data assimilation methods to integrate observations with simulation results; (5) modular design to facilitate selection and/or addition of essential model components needed in both process-oriented and hindcast/forecast applications; and (6) the ability to resolve regional Arctic features. Some examples of these regional features include (i) the sharp Arctic halocline which creates the stratification necessary to insulate perennial sea ice from the Pacific and Atlantic Water layers; (ii) the strong seasonal variability of sea surface height associated with large changes in atmospheric pressure; (iii) ice-tide interactions providing effective heat exchange between ocean and atmosphere; (iv) fast ice formation and break-up with very well pronounced specific atmosphere-ice-ocean interactions at the fast ice &ndash; pack ice edges; and (v) very strong and sometimes extreme river runoff. This model should also be an open-source ocean community model that can be accessed or used by scientists for particular applications and independent model comparison/validation studies.</p> <p>We have successfully developed a global-Arctic nested, high-resolution unstructured-grid, finite-volume coupled ice-ocean model for the Arctic Ocean (AO-FVCOM). AO-FVCOM is significantly different from existing Arctic Ocean structured-grid models due to the geometric flexibility inherent in the unstructured-grid approach and the local mass, momentum, heat, and salt conservation and computational efficiency inherent in the finite-volume approach. The geometric flexibility of this model enables detailed examination of multi-scale shelf-basin interactions in the Arctic, particularly over the shelfbreak and in the region connected to the Canadian Archipelago.</p> <p>This model has been validated via comparisons with 38-year (1978-2015) observational data collected in the Canada Arctic Basin and its marginal Chukchi and Beaufort Sea. The 38-year hindcast simulations has provided a valuable model database for long-term ocean and climate change studies, while the process-oriented experiments have advanced our understanding of the nonlinear interactions between tides, sea ice, wind stress, heat flux, atmospheric loading, and time-dependent river discharge and boundary inflow on ocean circulation, water structure and sea ice in the Arctic Ocean. AO-FVCOM development has provided an exciting new tool to study the linkages between Arctic and North Atlantic Oceans (especially through the Canadian Archipelago) and allow direct numerical simulation of the high-latitude buoyancy-driven coastal boundary current that drives the shelf and upper slope circulation from Labrador south to Cape Hatteras.</p> <p>Project results have been broadly disseminated to the general oceanographic community, undergraduate and graduate education communities and to the public through web-based servers using existing infrastructure at University of Massachusetts-Dartmouth.&nbsp; The sea-ice module has been implemented to FVCOM to create the ocean model software package, which has been used for different regions by academic universities, government agencies and private companies in the world.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Chang-Sheng&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1203393/1203393_10191889_1509324087349_Particle_trajectories--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1203393/1203393_10191889_1509324087349_Particle_trajectories--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Particle trajectories in the Arctic"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1203393/1203393_10191889_1509324087349_Particle_trajectories--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Particle trajectories in the Arctic"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Trajectories of particles released in the Arctic and Pan-Arctic region.</div> <div class="imageCredit">UMASSD</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Chang-Sheng&nbsp;Chen</div> <div class="imageTitle">Particle trajectories in the Arctic</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1203393/1203393_10191889_1509324591478_AO-FVCOM_sea_ice--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1203393/1203393_10191889_1509324591478_AO-FVCOM_sea_ice--rgov-800width.jpg" title="AO-FVCOM simulated sea ice during the ice formation period"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1203393/1203393_10191889_1509324591478_AO-FVCOM_sea_ice--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="AO-FVCOM simulated sea ice during the ice formation period"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A snapshot of the sea ice formation  by the AO-FVCOM.</div> <div class="imageCredit">UMASSD</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Chang-Sheng&nbsp;Chen</div> <div class="imageTitle">AO-FVCOM simulated sea ice during the ice formation period</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Arctic climate has changed significantly in the past three decades. The summer sea-ice concentration, for instance, has decreased considerably since the 1970s. The observed change in sea ice is undoubtedly due to interactions between the atmosphere and ocean. Among these three components, the ocean remains the least observed and also likely the least understood. More observations, improvements in numerical models and a better theoretic framework/model are all needed in the Arctic physical oceanography. A state-of-art Arctic Ocean model requires: (1) flexible and high resolution horizontal and vertical grids to represent the complex coastline, steep continental slopes and strong upper ocean stratification; (2) mass conservation to accurately simulate mass, heat and salt transformations and transports; (3) proper parameterization of vertical and lateral mixing, (4) advanced data assimilation methods to integrate observations with simulation results; (5) modular design to facilitate selection and/or addition of essential model components needed in both process-oriented and hindcast/forecast applications; and (6) the ability to resolve regional Arctic features. Some examples of these regional features include (i) the sharp Arctic halocline which creates the stratification necessary to insulate perennial sea ice from the Pacific and Atlantic Water layers; (ii) the strong seasonal variability of sea surface height associated with large changes in atmospheric pressure; (iii) ice-tide interactions providing effective heat exchange between ocean and atmosphere; (iv) fast ice formation and break-up with very well pronounced specific atmosphere-ice-ocean interactions at the fast ice &ndash; pack ice edges; and (v) very strong and sometimes extreme river runoff. This model should also be an open-source ocean community model that can be accessed or used by scientists for particular applications and independent model comparison/validation studies.  We have successfully developed a global-Arctic nested, high-resolution unstructured-grid, finite-volume coupled ice-ocean model for the Arctic Ocean (AO-FVCOM). AO-FVCOM is significantly different from existing Arctic Ocean structured-grid models due to the geometric flexibility inherent in the unstructured-grid approach and the local mass, momentum, heat, and salt conservation and computational efficiency inherent in the finite-volume approach. The geometric flexibility of this model enables detailed examination of multi-scale shelf-basin interactions in the Arctic, particularly over the shelfbreak and in the region connected to the Canadian Archipelago.  This model has been validated via comparisons with 38-year (1978-2015) observational data collected in the Canada Arctic Basin and its marginal Chukchi and Beaufort Sea. The 38-year hindcast simulations has provided a valuable model database for long-term ocean and climate change studies, while the process-oriented experiments have advanced our understanding of the nonlinear interactions between tides, sea ice, wind stress, heat flux, atmospheric loading, and time-dependent river discharge and boundary inflow on ocean circulation, water structure and sea ice in the Arctic Ocean. AO-FVCOM development has provided an exciting new tool to study the linkages between Arctic and North Atlantic Oceans (especially through the Canadian Archipelago) and allow direct numerical simulation of the high-latitude buoyancy-driven coastal boundary current that drives the shelf and upper slope circulation from Labrador south to Cape Hatteras.  Project results have been broadly disseminated to the general oceanographic community, undergraduate and graduate education communities and to the public through web-based servers using existing infrastructure at University of Massachusetts-Dartmouth.  The sea-ice module has been implemented to FVCOM to create the ocean model software package, which has been used for different regions by academic universities, government agencies and private companies in the world.           Last Modified: 10/29/2017       Submitted by: Chang-Sheng Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
