<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Testing the Northern Route for Younger Dryas Meltwater</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>401457.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>401457</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cynthia Suchman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>csuchman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922092</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PIs propose a three-year project to investigate the origin of the Younger Dryas cooling. New evidence suggests that glacial Lake Agassiz released fresh water to the Arctic through the Mackenzie River and they propose that this signal should be detectable along the western margin of the Canadian Archipelago in the oxygen isotope ratio in the shells of planktonic foraminifera. The project involves a three-week expedition to survey the seafloor and subbottom layers and collect sediment cores from the eastern Beaufort Sea, a region that is remote and has not been well explored. Besides the sediment processing and micropaleontology that are part of generating the isotope data that reflect sea surface salinity, two complementary shore-based projects are proposed. The first is to integrate the new geophysical data on the continental margin with the climate history of the open sea, sediment transport, relative sea level change, and terrestrial climate, as they have done previously for the Chukchi Sea. The second is to compare the geochemical data with results from a high resolution General Circulation Model that is configured to reveal the path and the mixing of the melt water. Although the paleoceanographic data will be spatially limited, model runs will show the low salinity distribution in the Arctic as well as in the Nordic seas where the freshening may have affected deep ocean overturning and caused the Younger Dryas cooling.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Younger Dryas was a period of climatic cooling that began about 13,000 years ago and lasted more than 1000 year.  It reversed a period of climatic warming, even though insolation continued to increase.  This study will attempt to determine the mechanism that allowed such a reversal in temperature trend to occur and, thus, inform discussions of whether similar changes are probable in the future.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1203944</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Neal</FirstName>
<LastName>Driscoll</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Neal W Driscoll</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ndriscoll@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8588225026</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000098980</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Univ of California-San Diego]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>175104595</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UCSD - Scripps Inst of Oceanography]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930244</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5280</Code>
<Text>ANS-Arctic Natural Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~401457</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Following the Fresh Water<em> Evidence of ancient abrupt climate change found in Arctic </em></strong></p> <p>A team of researchers from Scripps Institution of Oceanography at the University of California San Diego and Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution found evidence for a massive flood of fresh water in the western Arctic, thought to be the cause of an ancient cold snap that began around 13,000 years ago. The find could put to rest a question that has been open among scientists for more than 100 years.&nbsp; The existence of the cold snap, called the Younger Dryas, had been known for decades but the physical cause for its origin had eluded researchers who traveled to points throughout the Atlantic Ocean, the eastern United States, and Canada looking for it.</p> <p>&nbsp;In 2013, Driscoll, Keigwin and colleagues set sail to the eastern Beaufort Sea in search of evidence for the flood offshore of the Mackenzie River, which forms the border between Canada&rsquo;s Yukon and Northwest territories.&nbsp; From aboard the U.S. Coast Guard Cutter <em>Healy</em>, the team gathered sediment cores bearing foraminifera from along the continental slope north of the Mackenzie River. The researchers found a record of the event encased in seafloor sediment over 200 kilometers (~135 miles) from the mouth of the river. Preserved in the shells of microscopic organisms known as foraminifera were isotopes of oxygen with a ratio that is consistent with a large incursion of glacially derived freshwater.</p> <p>The signature of oxygen isotopes recorded in foraminifera shells preserved in the sediment allowed the researchers to fingerprint the source of the glacial lake discharge down the Mackenzie River 13,000 years ago. Radiocarbon dating on the shells provided the age constraints. How exciting when the pieces of a more than 100-year puzzle come together.</p> <p>The abrupt climate change triggered by the freshwater inundation ended more than 2,000 years of warming, The Younger Dryas triggered dramatic changes to regional climates. The freshwater from glaciers made its way from the Arctic to the north Atlantic Ocean. There it disrupted a circulation pattern that stretches from Greenland to the Southern Ocean. That pattern, the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC), transports warm equatorial waters poleward and releases heat to the atmosphere.</p> <p>That disruption caused substantial cooling in Europe, The Younger Dryas in fact takes its name from a flower (<em>Dryas octopetala</em>) that flourished in the continent&rsquo;s cold conditions at the time. The Younger Dryas cooling lasted only a small amount of time, as such it is only a short blip in a longer warming period that has lasted 20,000 years; but to scientists, it&rsquo;s an important example of how feedbacks affect the climate system. Overall trends of warming or cooling on Earth are not linear but are punctuated by reversals and accelerations such as this one. Such events help scientists interpret current trends, distinguishing global climate signals from regional signals.</p> <p>Next steps in future research will be for scientists to answer remaining questions about the quantity of fresh water delivered to the North Atlantic preceding the Younger Dryas event and over how long of a period of time. Events like this are really important, and we have to understand them better; the findings from this research will stimulate more research on how much fresh water is really necessary to cause a change in the system and weakening of the AMOC. It certainly calls further attention to the warming we're observing in the Arctic today, and the accelerated melting of Greenland ice. Earlier this year, a paper by researchers at the University College London and WHOI found evidence&nbsp;that the AMOC hasn&rsquo;t been running at peak strength since the mid-1800s and is currently at its weakest point in the past 1,600&nbsp;years.&nbsp;Continued weakening could disrupt weather patterns from the U.S. and Europe to the African Sahel.This research provides some constraints on patterns and magnitudes of cooling in response to weakening the vigor of the AMOC.</p> <p>All of the geophysical data acquired during this project are stored at the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory's data repository&nbsp; (https://www.ldeo.columbia.edu/research/databases-repositories).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/18/2018<br>      Modified by: Neal&nbsp;W&nbsp;Driscoll</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Following the Fresh Water Evidence of ancient abrupt climate change found in Arctic   A team of researchers from Scripps Institution of Oceanography at the University of California San Diego and Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution found evidence for a massive flood of fresh water in the western Arctic, thought to be the cause of an ancient cold snap that began around 13,000 years ago. The find could put to rest a question that has been open among scientists for more than 100 years.  The existence of the cold snap, called the Younger Dryas, had been known for decades but the physical cause for its origin had eluded researchers who traveled to points throughout the Atlantic Ocean, the eastern United States, and Canada looking for it.   In 2013, Driscoll, Keigwin and colleagues set sail to the eastern Beaufort Sea in search of evidence for the flood offshore of the Mackenzie River, which forms the border between Canada?s Yukon and Northwest territories.  From aboard the U.S. Coast Guard Cutter Healy, the team gathered sediment cores bearing foraminifera from along the continental slope north of the Mackenzie River. The researchers found a record of the event encased in seafloor sediment over 200 kilometers (~135 miles) from the mouth of the river. Preserved in the shells of microscopic organisms known as foraminifera were isotopes of oxygen with a ratio that is consistent with a large incursion of glacially derived freshwater.  The signature of oxygen isotopes recorded in foraminifera shells preserved in the sediment allowed the researchers to fingerprint the source of the glacial lake discharge down the Mackenzie River 13,000 years ago. Radiocarbon dating on the shells provided the age constraints. How exciting when the pieces of a more than 100-year puzzle come together.  The abrupt climate change triggered by the freshwater inundation ended more than 2,000 years of warming, The Younger Dryas triggered dramatic changes to regional climates. The freshwater from glaciers made its way from the Arctic to the north Atlantic Ocean. There it disrupted a circulation pattern that stretches from Greenland to the Southern Ocean. That pattern, the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC), transports warm equatorial waters poleward and releases heat to the atmosphere.  That disruption caused substantial cooling in Europe, The Younger Dryas in fact takes its name from a flower (Dryas octopetala) that flourished in the continent?s cold conditions at the time. The Younger Dryas cooling lasted only a small amount of time, as such it is only a short blip in a longer warming period that has lasted 20,000 years; but to scientists, it?s an important example of how feedbacks affect the climate system. Overall trends of warming or cooling on Earth are not linear but are punctuated by reversals and accelerations such as this one. Such events help scientists interpret current trends, distinguishing global climate signals from regional signals.  Next steps in future research will be for scientists to answer remaining questions about the quantity of fresh water delivered to the North Atlantic preceding the Younger Dryas event and over how long of a period of time. Events like this are really important, and we have to understand them better; the findings from this research will stimulate more research on how much fresh water is really necessary to cause a change in the system and weakening of the AMOC. It certainly calls further attention to the warming we're observing in the Arctic today, and the accelerated melting of Greenland ice. Earlier this year, a paper by researchers at the University College London and WHOI found evidence that the AMOC hasn?t been running at peak strength since the mid-1800s and is currently at its weakest point in the past 1,600 years. Continued weakening could disrupt weather patterns from the U.S. and Europe to the African Sahel.This research provides some constraints on patterns and magnitudes of cooling in response to weakening the vigor of the AMOC.  All of the geophysical data acquired during this project are stored at the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory's data repository  (https://www.ldeo.columbia.edu/research/databases-repositories).                   Last Modified: 08/18/2018       Submitted by: Neal W Driscoll]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
