<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Implementation and Expansion of Science-Based Service Technology in HEVs</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199312.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199312</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Herbert H. Richtol</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Lewis and Clark Community College (L&amp;C) is conducting a number of activities which focus on hybrid electric vehicle (HEV) technology. The project develops HEV-infused professional development programs in all eight major areas of automotive technology for community college and high school instructors of automotive technology and to emergency responders. The project also expands its outreach to high schools in the region of southwestern Illinois with the broadened implementation of its Automotive Academy and continues a focused recruitment of underrepresented groups in the region through expansion of its program called Females under the Hood. Updating the HEV-infused curriculum to include a variety of HEV car models and to transition to plug-in hybrid models is also part of the project. The project is revising and updating its articulation program with Southern Illinois University-Carbondale (SIUC). Existing partnerships with local automotive repair businesses which deal with HEVs are sustained and strengthened. The project increases understanding about instruction in HEV technology with dissemination of the results of the curriculum development activities and targets underrepresented groups and females.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1204362</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Reynolds</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher Reynolds</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cereynolds@lc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6184684915</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000561905</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Gilbert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Gilbert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dwgilb@siu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6184667000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000563332</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Holmes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth Holmes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kholmes@lc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6184667000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000563333</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lewis and Clark Community College</Name>
<CityName>Godfrey</CityName>
<ZipCode>620352426</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6184667000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5800 Godfrey Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071996722</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LEWIS &amp; CLARK COMMUNITY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071996722</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lewis and Clark Community College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>620352426</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~199312</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was a continuation of funding the previous year (Summer 2012) from Macomb Community College, located in Warren, MI and designated as a NSF Center, supporting the individuals responsible for the development of curricula that support and contribute to the body of knowledge surrounding Hybrid Electric Vechicle (HEV) technology training for automobile service technicians.</p> <p>Its overall intent was to provide students and educators in the automotive service industry access to theoretical and practical ideas and solutions for the betterment of the automobile service industry. This is in response to the limited detail provided in curriculum developed by the original equipment manufacturers (OEM's) for manufacturer specific technician training.</p> <p>Upon direct NSF funding, our program began to implement HEV technologies contextually into the curriculum rather than building a stand-alone course. While we did not collect data to directly measure this practice and its effectiveness, we were provided many positive comments from peer-representatives of other institutions for doing so. It provided a 'gentler' introduction to HEV technology, and created purposeful room for stakeholder interest.</p> <p>This project provided 3-years of student engagement and interest in HEV technologies, contextualized mathematics, funding for Principal Investigator training, specialized test equipment, and free instructor training (formative process using funded video equipment, specialized test equipment, and video editing on YouTube - past and present). The implementation of the YouTube channel will continue to provide the general public, and vested audiences, direct and precise information regarding the servicing of HEV's.</p> <p>This grant also provided the college community (individual divisions) with great pride and academic presence when competing for other grants. While we are not currently actively pursuing additional NSF funds as a program, we are actively working on Title III/ WIA and TAACCCT funding, which is currently supporting the development of a stand-alone advanced course, and Society of Automotive Engineers (SAE) endorsed HEV Specialists to teach the course sections.</p> <p>We did have difficulty (zero success) in recruiting targeted minorities from specific locations in the secondary school system (out-of-district, but agreed upon by college presidents and grant staff). District management, funding, and morale suffered greatly, and did not allow effective communications between our facility and the secondary target. Our program intends to continue pursuing this district in hopes of developing a post-secondary pathway for the successes of the district's student body.</p> <p>Overall, these funds provided the world (via YouTube) and students of our program with direct access to proven platforms that support HEV diagnosis and repair.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/27/2015<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;Reynolds</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was a continuation of funding the previous year (Summer 2012) from Macomb Community College, located in Warren, MI and designated as a NSF Center, supporting the individuals responsible for the development of curricula that support and contribute to the body of knowledge surrounding Hybrid Electric Vechicle (HEV) technology training for automobile service technicians.  Its overall intent was to provide students and educators in the automotive service industry access to theoretical and practical ideas and solutions for the betterment of the automobile service industry. This is in response to the limited detail provided in curriculum developed by the original equipment manufacturers (OEM's) for manufacturer specific technician training.  Upon direct NSF funding, our program began to implement HEV technologies contextually into the curriculum rather than building a stand-alone course. While we did not collect data to directly measure this practice and its effectiveness, we were provided many positive comments from peer-representatives of other institutions for doing so. It provided a 'gentler' introduction to HEV technology, and created purposeful room for stakeholder interest.  This project provided 3-years of student engagement and interest in HEV technologies, contextualized mathematics, funding for Principal Investigator training, specialized test equipment, and free instructor training (formative process using funded video equipment, specialized test equipment, and video editing on YouTube - past and present). The implementation of the YouTube channel will continue to provide the general public, and vested audiences, direct and precise information regarding the servicing of HEV's.  This grant also provided the college community (individual divisions) with great pride and academic presence when competing for other grants. While we are not currently actively pursuing additional NSF funds as a program, we are actively working on Title III/ WIA and TAACCCT funding, which is currently supporting the development of a stand-alone advanced course, and Society of Automotive Engineers (SAE) endorsed HEV Specialists to teach the course sections.  We did have difficulty (zero success) in recruiting targeted minorities from specific locations in the secondary school system (out-of-district, but agreed upon by college presidents and grant staff). District management, funding, and morale suffered greatly, and did not allow effective communications between our facility and the secondary target. Our program intends to continue pursuing this district in hopes of developing a post-secondary pathway for the successes of the district's student body.  Overall, these funds provided the world (via YouTube) and students of our program with direct access to proven platforms that support HEV diagnosis and repair.             Last Modified: 07/27/2015       Submitted by: Christopher Reynolds]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
