<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WSC-Category 2 Collaborative: Robust decision-making for South Florida water resources by ecosystem service valuation, hydro-economic optimization, and conflict resolution modeling</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300514.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300514</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Torgersen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Water management in south Florida is characterized by the need to balance multiple objectives. Among the objectives are the maintenance of high groundwater levels to limit seawater intrusion and flood control measures that are also used to mitigate  dry-season water shortages. In addition, south Florida's current population of 6 million is projected to grow to 10 million over the next 20 years, and urban water demand must be reliably managed. In this exceptionally vulnerable region, sea level rise and salt water intrusion have already impacted drinking water supplies and threaten the integrity of low-lying and highly-valued built and natural environments as diverse as Miami Beach and the Everglades. Long-term adaptive strategies are needed to ensure sustainable water resources for expanding populations, agriculture, and wetlands that serve multiple functions, including support of Florida's fishing industry. Development of such strategies has been hampered by conflicting stakeholder interests and technical, economic, and political challenges. This project will conduct highly interdisciplinary research, utilizing the expertise of multiple institutions, to investigate the hydrologic, economic, ecologic, and human behavioral dimensions of sustainable water management and land use planning under various climate change, economic, population, and sea level rise scenarios. The research will employ hydro-economic optimization approaches based on robust decision making to develop management strategies that ensure the resilience of water supplies for the built and natural systems, while also accounting for the broad-sector value of water use. Optimization criteria will incorporate the results of project research linking water management, ecological function, and the economic value of ecosystem services. New experimental approaches will be implemented to better understand the impacts of scenario information type and uncertainty on both selection of decision criteria and evaluation of model predictions among individuals and groups of local stakeholders. These experiments are designed to improve understanding of the roles of cognitive and perceptual biases in decision-making when stakeholders examine hydro-economic projections coupled with scenario forecasts. Comparative behavioral analyses of stakeholder evaluations and institutional decision-making will provide unique insights into how information type, information content, and cognitive biases combine to influence risk perception, and how the perceived risks to individual and collective well-being influence scenario selection. Finally, with agency and stakeholder involvement, the project will collaboratively develop recommendations for adaptive water management plans that foster long-term support from the stakeholders. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Low-lying coastal regions subject to sea level rise, climate change, and diverse water demands, including growing populations, will benefit from the development of innovative, pragmatic approaches to optimizing the social-ecological benefits of water resources allocation. The research will include novel approaches for dynamically incorporating economics into stakeholder evaluations of adaptive land use and water management strategies. Local, state, and federal agencies responsible for managing south Florida's water resources will benefit from analyses of adaptive schemes that explicitly incorporate uncertainty estimates of potential outcomes. The multiple societies that exist in south Florida, whose options for managing public water resources are limited by climatic, physical, and/or legal constraints, require this type of integrated assessment to promote cooperative decision-making while preparing for uncertain hydro-climatic conditions and socioeconomic futures.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1204666</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Mann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Mann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mem45@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148674075</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000099802</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
<LastName>Fuentes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jose D Fuentes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jdfuentes@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148631585</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000477024</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~300514</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project investigated the historical and the future patterns and trends in the climate variables of air temperature and precipitation in south Florida. The research developed unique statistical downscaling &nbsp;approaches to make future projections of seasonal precipitation characteristics in south Florida. The approach was applied separately to September?November, December?February, March?May, and June?August. Climate model outputs were considered in the analyses to include the 30-year windows of daily mean precipitation for historical (1976?2005), near future (2021?2050), and far future (2071?2100) periods for three climate scenarios representing different greenhouse gas emissions (RCP2.6, RCP4.5, and RCP8.5). &nbsp;The ensemble averages of raw outputs from nineteen climate models poorly replicated historical rainfall totals. Results revealed that current climate models still need further developments and improvements to properly capture the unique climatic conditions of the Florida peninsula whose spatial rainfall distribution is largely dominated by features such as breezes and tropical storms. Nonetheless, the developed downscaling technique of rainfall totals in south Florida more accurately reproduced the observed precipitation values during the historical period. The validated downscaling approach, applied to the considered future climate scenarios, indicated that the resulting projections yield an overall drying in all seasons over all of south Florida. The magnitude of the drying depends on the timeframe (near future versus far future) and the future greenhouse gas emission scenarios. Accordingly, anticipated frequency of wet days will likely decrease and the average length of dry spells will increase in response to future climate projections for south Florida. Compared to current conditions, south Florida will likely experience a ten percent reduction in rainfall in the near future. Given the great demand for water in south Florida, involving agricultural and urban planner stakeholders, the results from this project offer some guidance on the planning of multifaceted relationships between human activities and the regional water system. The results can also serve as guides for the development of water sustainability and adaptive approaches to benefit the people of south Florida in the face of rapid climate change.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/14/2019<br>      Modified by: Jose&nbsp;D&nbsp;Fuentes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1204666/1204666_10225979_1555266295714_Graphical_Abstract--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1204666/1204666_10225979_1555266295714_Graphical_Abstract--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ImageForWSC1ProjectOutcomes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1204666/1204666_10225979_1555266295714_Graphical_Abstract--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ImageForWSC1ProjectOutcomes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Projected Changes in Seasonal Precipitation Climatology (in %; Based on Historical data) for future periods in Florida (Near Future: 2021-2050; Far Future: 2071-2100)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jose D Fuentes</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jose&nbsp;D&nbsp;Fuentes</div> <div class="imageTitle">ImageForWSC1ProjectOutcomes</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project investigated the historical and the future patterns and trends in the climate variables of air temperature and precipitation in south Florida. The research developed unique statistical downscaling  approaches to make future projections of seasonal precipitation characteristics in south Florida. The approach was applied separately to September?November, December?February, March?May, and June?August. Climate model outputs were considered in the analyses to include the 30-year windows of daily mean precipitation for historical (1976?2005), near future (2021?2050), and far future (2071?2100) periods for three climate scenarios representing different greenhouse gas emissions (RCP2.6, RCP4.5, and RCP8.5).  The ensemble averages of raw outputs from nineteen climate models poorly replicated historical rainfall totals. Results revealed that current climate models still need further developments and improvements to properly capture the unique climatic conditions of the Florida peninsula whose spatial rainfall distribution is largely dominated by features such as breezes and tropical storms. Nonetheless, the developed downscaling technique of rainfall totals in south Florida more accurately reproduced the observed precipitation values during the historical period. The validated downscaling approach, applied to the considered future climate scenarios, indicated that the resulting projections yield an overall drying in all seasons over all of south Florida. The magnitude of the drying depends on the timeframe (near future versus far future) and the future greenhouse gas emission scenarios. Accordingly, anticipated frequency of wet days will likely decrease and the average length of dry spells will increase in response to future climate projections for south Florida. Compared to current conditions, south Florida will likely experience a ten percent reduction in rainfall in the near future. Given the great demand for water in south Florida, involving agricultural and urban planner stakeholders, the results from this project offer some guidance on the planning of multifaceted relationships between human activities and the regional water system. The results can also serve as guides for the development of water sustainability and adaptive approaches to benefit the people of south Florida in the face of rapid climate change.          Last Modified: 04/14/2019       Submitted by: Jose D Fuentes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
