<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Interactions Between Air Temperature, Permafrost and Hydrology in the High Latitudes of Eurasia</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>168138.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>168138</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Neil R. Swanberg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal builds off of work conducted under the Freshwater Integration program and seeks to address two interrelated hypotheses aimed at improved understanding of the Arctic system at various time and space scales.  The first hypothesis will explore the seasonal relationship between air temperature, river ice thickness, and winter runoff, while the second will investigate the contribution of thawing permafrost to river discharge.  Research will focus on several river basins and feeder streams within the Russian Arctic and sub-Arctic where hydrometeorological measurements have been collected since 1950 and climate data are available from a number of global data archives.  These data sets will be augmented by new field data collected by the PI team, focusing on permafrost, isotopic, hydrochemical, and higher time and spatial resolution hydrologic sampling.  This suite of measurements will be used to test the hypotheses using watershed scale models and the Geophysical Institute Permafrost Lab model coupled to the Water Balance and Discharge Transformation Model (WBMplus).  Graduate students and an undergraduate will receive training in fieldwork and modeling, and the grant will support an early career principal investigator.  Results and methodology will also be incorporated into courses taught at the awardee institutions as well as through minority high school outreach programs.  During fieldwork, an ongoing collaboration with residents near Igarka will be maintained and materials provided for their local permafrost museum.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1204110</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nikolay</FirstName>
<LastName>Shiklomanov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nikolay I Shiklomanov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shiklom@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2029946255</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000544344</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dmitry</FirstName>
<LastName>Streletskiy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dmitry A Streletskiy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>strelets@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2029949168</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000580055</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1922 F Street NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[4th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520042</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1922 F Street, NW #217]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5219</Code>
<Text>ARCSS-Arctic System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~168138</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Eurasian pan-Arctic is one of the regions requiring more immediate attention in association with global warming.<em> </em>To investigate the role of climate change on permafrost degradation and hydrology, extensive field work was conducted in a series of small watersheds located in the discontinuous permafrost zone of the lower Yenisei River near Igarka, and in the continuous permafrost zone of the Kolyma River near Cherskii. Climatic, hydrologic and permafrost characteristics were monitored at both locations over a three year period and extended using historical data. Stable isotope composition of rain, snow, water from lakes and rivers, and various types of ground ice was used to determine various inputs and runoff pathways to a river flow in several watersheds. The results who that water flow of smaller creeks follows precipitation closely, while flow of larger rivers is affected by evaporation effects related to water storage in thermokarst lakes. Ground ice of the epigenetic permafrost near Igarka has a similar isotopic composition as that of Holocene permafrost and contemporary late summer precipitation. Ground ice of the syngenetic Pleistocene permafrost (Ice Complex) near Cherskii has a significantly lighter isotopic composition than pore water of the active and transient layers. Increases in air temperature resulted in thickening of the active-layer and melting of ice that reach the transient layer in continuous permafrost. In areas where the transient layer severely reduced as a result of intense forest fires and other landscape disturbances, ground ice from permafrost is also involved in hydrological processes. Progressive decrease in the seasonal freezing layer thickness and a lower permafrost table promoted more groundwater storage and redistribution of summer precipitation towards winter baseflow in discontinuous permafrost region. The major contribution of permafrost at both locations is not through the melting of ground ice, but through changes in soil properties affecting the water flow. Project results were presented at numerous national and international scientific venues and were published in high-impact journals. Members of local communities were engaged through a series of newspapers interviews, collaborations with local museum and schools. Graduate and undergraduate students from the US, Russia, Norway, UK gained valuable experiences by participation in various project activities, many were trained as part of the International Permafrost School annual visits to observation sites near Igarka. Through its outreach and educational activities, the project has contributed to the increasing public awareness about climate- and human-induced changes in permafrost and hydrology, which can potentially constitute an important threat to human livelihood and well-being in the Arctic regions. Collected observations are indispensable for broader hydrological, climatological and isotopic regional and global modeling studies and in the future will provide a baseline of the historic changes in the region.&nbsp;<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Dmitry&nbsp;A&nbsp;Streletskiy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Eurasian pan-Arctic is one of the regions requiring more immediate attention in association with global warming. To investigate the role of climate change on permafrost degradation and hydrology, extensive field work was conducted in a series of small watersheds located in the discontinuous permafrost zone of the lower Yenisei River near Igarka, and in the continuous permafrost zone of the Kolyma River near Cherskii. Climatic, hydrologic and permafrost characteristics were monitored at both locations over a three year period and extended using historical data. Stable isotope composition of rain, snow, water from lakes and rivers, and various types of ground ice was used to determine various inputs and runoff pathways to a river flow in several watersheds. The results who that water flow of smaller creeks follows precipitation closely, while flow of larger rivers is affected by evaporation effects related to water storage in thermokarst lakes. Ground ice of the epigenetic permafrost near Igarka has a similar isotopic composition as that of Holocene permafrost and contemporary late summer precipitation. Ground ice of the syngenetic Pleistocene permafrost (Ice Complex) near Cherskii has a significantly lighter isotopic composition than pore water of the active and transient layers. Increases in air temperature resulted in thickening of the active-layer and melting of ice that reach the transient layer in continuous permafrost. In areas where the transient layer severely reduced as a result of intense forest fires and other landscape disturbances, ground ice from permafrost is also involved in hydrological processes. Progressive decrease in the seasonal freezing layer thickness and a lower permafrost table promoted more groundwater storage and redistribution of summer precipitation towards winter baseflow in discontinuous permafrost region. The major contribution of permafrost at both locations is not through the melting of ground ice, but through changes in soil properties affecting the water flow. Project results were presented at numerous national and international scientific venues and were published in high-impact journals. Members of local communities were engaged through a series of newspapers interviews, collaborations with local museum and schools. Graduate and undergraduate students from the US, Russia, Norway, UK gained valuable experiences by participation in various project activities, many were trained as part of the International Permafrost School annual visits to observation sites near Igarka. Through its outreach and educational activities, the project has contributed to the increasing public awareness about climate- and human-induced changes in permafrost and hydrology, which can potentially constitute an important threat to human livelihood and well-being in the Arctic regions. Collected observations are indispensable for broader hydrological, climatological and isotopic regional and global modeling studies and in the future will provide a baseline of the historic changes in the region.            Last Modified: 11/30/2016       Submitted by: Dmitry A Streletskiy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
