<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WSC-Category 2 Collaborative: WATER QUALITY AND SUPPLY IMPACTS FROM CLIMATE-INDUCED INSECT TREE MORTALITY AND RESOURCE MANAGEMENT IN THE ROCKY MOUNTAIN WEST</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>648929.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>648929</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Torgersen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>It is estimated that over 4 million acres of forests in Colorado and Wyoming are dying due to the ongoing mountain pine beetle (MPB) infestation. The visual impact of dying and dead forests is stunning, but the invisible changes to the water cycle in vital watersheds in the Rocky Mountain west, including the Platte and Colorado River headwaters, may be a longer-lasting legacy of the MPB. The objective of this work is to determine potential water resource changes resulting from the MPB epidemic by defining and quantifying feedbacks between changes in climate, forested ecosystems altered by MPB impacts, biogeochemical processes and resource management practices.  Beetle-killed trees will alter hydrologic and biogeochemical processes that govern water quantity and quality in forested headwater catchments. When coupled with natural resources management practices, these changes can potentially affect the ability to fulfill downstream water user demands and challenge ecological and human health needs.  This project will directly address the social and physical science factors that govern water resource availability and quality under ecological and climate change. Concern about beetle-killed forest and watershed management is driving municipalities to implement water rate increases, and there is confusion about how to most effectively improve watershed health as it relates to this issue.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Our interdisciplinary research team will merge field observations, laboratory experiments, integrated hydrologic models, and high-performance computing to increase our understanding and predictive capabilities for a critical problem facing society: changes to water availability and quality from an unprecedented change to our forests. This work will be complimented by place-based collaborative learning for impacted communities and workshops with water treatment municipalities. These workshops will be two-way and will serve to both  understand concerns and experiences with MPB impacts as well as communicate results. Integration of stakeholder perceptions and management responses will further inform and enrich our scientific analysis of water supply and contribute to the uniqueness of our research vision. In addition to stakeholder outreach and scenario planning, modules will be developed that convey key water resource issues to K-12 teachers and students as well as provide training, research and educational opportunities for undergraduate, graduate students and postdoctoral scholars. Not only will this work provide an improved scientific basis for managing watershed ecosystems in the Platte and Colorado River basins, thus helping to ensure safe and reliable water resources to more than 30 million residential users and 1.8 million acres of irrigated agriculture, it will also improve our scientific and social understanding of the water supply and quantity challenges for MPB-impacted areas across the Rocky Mountain West.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1204460</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Stednick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John D Stednick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jds@nrel.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704917248</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000429462</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/14/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
<LastName>Clement</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jessica Clement</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jessica.clement@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704916355</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000562655</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/24/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stuart</FirstName>
<LastName>Cottrell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stuart Cottrell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cottrell@warnercnr.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704916355</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000573585</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stuart</FirstName>
<LastName>Cottrell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stuart Cottrell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cottrell@warnercnr.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704916355</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000573585</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/14/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>785979618</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>948905492</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7977</Code>
<Text>CR-Water Sustainability &amp; Clim</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~648929</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Widespread tree mortality in forested watersheds affected by the mountain pine beetle (MPB) epidemic across western North America raised public concerns about the effects of this climate-induced disturbance on drinking water resources. Effective communication is essential for constructively responding to such disturbances. In this grant in collaboration with the Colorado School of Mines, we developed and conducted social science research to assess drinking water providers, professionals working with drinking water providers in northern Colorado and southern Wyoming, and land manger knowledge levels, information needs, concerns, and suggested communication strategies.</p> <p>During the span of the grant, we developed stakeholder interviews both online and face-to-face and focus group workshops labeled as Beetle Cafes (see Fig. 1 of results). The objective of the studies were an enhanced scientific and social understanding of the water supply and quantity challenges for MPB-affected areas ecosystems in the Platte and Colorado River basins. In addition, we examined public perceptions of bark beetle effects on natural resources among the general public near three national forests in Colorado with findings pertinent to foster collaboration among scientists and land manager efforts for managing bark beetle impacts from a social ecological systems perspective.</p> <p>A few examples of key findings from our research include improved understanding of the challenges, concerns, and experience of drinking water providers, forest managers, and community watershed health collaborative groups. Knowledge levels were relatively low about MPB effects on drinking water with 50% of the various stakeholders reporting little to no knowledge of the effects of MPB on drinking water quality. One of the bigger concerns among drink water providers was fire in beetle kill forests in their associated watersheds as well as costs of water treatment for increased total organic carbon. Recommendations were to include dissemination of non-academic research summaries, exchange of information through existing media and community resources, demonstration projects, and information clearinghouses.</p> <p>Among the most significant communication achievements of the grant has been the development of key messages for placed- based science education and public educational programs about the effects of mountain pine beetle infestation on water quality and natural resources. This was accomplished via several means such as conference presentations, a university honors seminar course conducted collaboratively with the Colorado School of Mines entitled &ldquo;Naked Trees, Killer Beetles, and Dirty Water&rdquo; (see <a href="https://warnercnr.colostate.edu/announcements/naked-trees-killer-beetles-dirty-water/">https://warnercnr.colostate.edu/announcements/naked-trees-killer-beetles-dirty-water/</a> ) for 40 plus undergraduate students at Colorado State University over two years that culminated in outreach videos, educational outreach at Outdoor School with 6<sup>th</sup> grade kids in Jefferson County Colorado and 9<sup>th</sup> grade biology classes for two years at Rocky Mountain High School in Fort Collins Colorado. A final K-12 Teachers Workshop focused on creation of curriculum resources for the classroom developed collaboratively among university students, K-12 teachers and the research project scientists at Colorado School of Mines and Colorado State University.</p> <p>Our research has developed new concepts for the study of bark beetle disturbances and social perspectives on high severity outbreaks in collaboration with NSF funded RCN (Mountain Social Ecological Observatory Network (MtnSEON)) see https://webpages.uidaho.edu/mtnseon/. This led to further understanding of factors that influence adaptive capacity for increasing resilience to bark beetles using mountain pine beetle (<em><span style="font-family: Times;">Dendroctonus ponderosae</span></em>) in the western U.S. as a model as well as identification of priority research questions on insect forest disturbances through socio-environmental collaboration.</p> <p>A conceptual framework was developed to provide land managers and policymakers a useful tool for identifying limitations in adaptive capacity in social ecological systems (SES) in hopes of addressing future bark beetle infestation events in the USA and abroad.&nbsp; We aim for this effort to be useful to motivate future research in the assessment of adaptive capacity and to foster collaboration among scientists and land manager efforts to manage for bark beetle impacts to SES.</p> <!--   @font-face  {font-family:Times;  panose-1:2 0 5 0 0 0 0 0 0 0;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:3 0 0 0 1 0;} @font-face  {font-family:"&#65325;&#65331; &#26126;&#26397;";  mso-font-charset:78;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1791491579 18 0 131231 0;} @font-face  {font-family:"Cambria Math";  panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1107305727 0 0 415 0;} @font-face  {font-family:Cambria;  panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1073743103 0 0 415 0;}   p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal  {mso-style-unhide:no;  mso-style-qformat:yes;  mso-style-parent:";  margin:0in;  margin-bottom:.0001pt;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:"&#65325;&#65331; &#26126;&#26397;";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-hansi-font-family:Cambria;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;} a:link, span.MsoHyperlink  {mso-style-priority:99;  color:blue;  mso-themecolor:hyperlink;  text-decoration:underline;  text-underline:single;} a:visited, span.MsoHyperlinkFollowed  {mso-style-noshow:yes;  mso-style-priority:99;  color:purple;  mso-themecolor:followedhyperlink;  text-decoration:underline;  text-underline:single;} p  {mso-style-noshow:yes;  mso-style-priority:99;  mso-margin-top-alt:auto;  margin-right:0in;  mso-margin-bottom-alt:auto;  margin-left:0in;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:10.0pt;  font-family:Times;  mso-fareast-font-family:"&#65325;&#65331; &#26126;&#26397;";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";} .MsoChpDefault  {mso-style-type:export-only;  mso-default-props:yes;  font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:"&#65325;&#65331; &#26126;&#26397;";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-hansi-font-family:Cambria;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;} @page WordSection1  {size:8.5in 11.0in;  margin:1.0in 1.25in 1.0in 1.25in;  mso-header-margin:.5in;  mso-footer-margin:.5in;  mso-paper-source:0;} div.WordSection1  {page:WordSection1;} --><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/22/2018<br>      Modified by: Stuart&nbsp;Cottrell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1204460/1204460_10203547_1540147908324_MountainPineBeetleCafe_Graphic--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1204460/1204460_10203547_1540147908324_MountainPineBeetleCafe_Graphic--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Beetle Cafe Results"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1204460/1204460_10203547_1540147908324_MountainPineBeetleCafe_Graphic--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Beetle Cafe Results"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1 Beetle Cafe Workshop Results - graphic illustrations</div> <div class="imageCredit">Karina Mullin and Stuart Cottrell</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stuart&nbsp;Cottrell</div> <div class="imageTitle">Beetle Cafe Results</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Widespread tree mortality in forested watersheds affected by the mountain pine beetle (MPB) epidemic across western North America raised public concerns about the effects of this climate-induced disturbance on drinking water resources. Effective communication is essential for constructively responding to such disturbances. In this grant in collaboration with the Colorado School of Mines, we developed and conducted social science research to assess drinking water providers, professionals working with drinking water providers in northern Colorado and southern Wyoming, and land manger knowledge levels, information needs, concerns, and suggested communication strategies.  During the span of the grant, we developed stakeholder interviews both online and face-to-face and focus group workshops labeled as Beetle Cafes (see Fig. 1 of results). The objective of the studies were an enhanced scientific and social understanding of the water supply and quantity challenges for MPB-affected areas ecosystems in the Platte and Colorado River basins. In addition, we examined public perceptions of bark beetle effects on natural resources among the general public near three national forests in Colorado with findings pertinent to foster collaboration among scientists and land manager efforts for managing bark beetle impacts from a social ecological systems perspective.  A few examples of key findings from our research include improved understanding of the challenges, concerns, and experience of drinking water providers, forest managers, and community watershed health collaborative groups. Knowledge levels were relatively low about MPB effects on drinking water with 50% of the various stakeholders reporting little to no knowledge of the effects of MPB on drinking water quality. One of the bigger concerns among drink water providers was fire in beetle kill forests in their associated watersheds as well as costs of water treatment for increased total organic carbon. Recommendations were to include dissemination of non-academic research summaries, exchange of information through existing media and community resources, demonstration projects, and information clearinghouses.  Among the most significant communication achievements of the grant has been the development of key messages for placed- based science education and public educational programs about the effects of mountain pine beetle infestation on water quality and natural resources. This was accomplished via several means such as conference presentations, a university honors seminar course conducted collaboratively with the Colorado School of Mines entitled "Naked Trees, Killer Beetles, and Dirty Water" (see https://warnercnr.colostate.edu/announcements/naked-trees-killer-beetles-dirty-water/ ) for 40 plus undergraduate students at Colorado State University over two years that culminated in outreach videos, educational outreach at Outdoor School with 6th grade kids in Jefferson County Colorado and 9th grade biology classes for two years at Rocky Mountain High School in Fort Collins Colorado. A final K-12 Teachers Workshop focused on creation of curriculum resources for the classroom developed collaboratively among university students, K-12 teachers and the research project scientists at Colorado School of Mines and Colorado State University.  Our research has developed new concepts for the study of bark beetle disturbances and social perspectives on high severity outbreaks in collaboration with NSF funded RCN (Mountain Social Ecological Observatory Network (MtnSEON)) see https://webpages.uidaho.edu/mtnseon/. This led to further understanding of factors that influence adaptive capacity for increasing resilience to bark beetles using mountain pine beetle (Dendroctonus ponderosae) in the western U.S. as a model as well as identification of priority research questions on insect forest disturbances through socio-environmental collaboration.  A conceptual framework was developed to provide land managers and policymakers a useful tool for identifying limitations in adaptive capacity in social ecological systems (SES) in hopes of addressing future bark beetle infestation events in the USA and abroad.  We aim for this effort to be useful to motivate future research in the assessment of adaptive capacity and to foster collaboration among scientists and land manager efforts to manage for bark beetle impacts to SES.        Last Modified: 10/22/2018       Submitted by: Stuart Cottrell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
