<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Design of impedance matched infrared antennas using optical vector near-field mapping</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/23/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>390000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Objective:&lt;br/&gt;We seek to increase sensitivity of antenna-coupled infrared detectors by an order of magnitude. We will gain understanding of relevant design parameters, and subsequently design impedance-matched antenna-sensor combinations. We utilize our newly developed high-spatial-resolution, three-dimensional probe techniques to measure electric fields in the vicinity of the infrared antennas. This enables us, for the first time, to determine the infrared-frequency impedance as a function of position. Combined with an iterative design-fabrication-test approach, this will enable development of infrared impedance-matching components.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit:&lt;br/&gt;We scale up the concept of a radiofrequency network analyzer by nine orders of magnitude in frequency. This proven advance yields experimental tools needed to extend the performance of antenna-coupled sensors by a similar scale in frequency, making the entire field of passive low-&lt;br/&gt;5&lt;br/&gt;frequency electronics operational in the infrared range. Infrared antennas have been proposed for a wide range of applications, including nanoscale chemical and photon sensors, nearfield microscopy, and optical rectennas for energy-harvesting. Such devices would transform the field of optics, enabling sensing devices of nano-scale dimensions with order-of-magnitude enhancement in sensitivity, responsivity, and reliability compared to conventional optical techniques.&lt;br/&gt;Broader impact:&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research greatly extends the frequency range of classical electronics, while serving as the foundation for a dynamic and engaging learning environment at each of the PIs? institutions. All three PIs have an established track record of mentorship of underrepresented students, and all three participate in programs for science and engineering outreach to K-12 students and research participation of undergraduate students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/22/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/22/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1204993</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Glenn</FirstName>
<LastName>Boreman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Glenn Boreman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gboreman@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046878132</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000182267</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/22/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9201 University City Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066300096</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHARLOTTE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Charlotte]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlotte</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9201 University City Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>098E</Code>
<Text>Antennas and Electromagnetics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~390000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project allowed measurement, for the first time at infrared frequencies, of the feedpoint impedance of an optical antenna.&nbsp; Near field scanning optical microscopy was used to measure magnitude and phase of electric fields in the vicinity of infrared antenna and transmission line structures.&nbsp; Through the excitation of stable standing waves on transmission line coupled antennas, we achieved a systematic way to determine the impedance values of optical antennas through near-field imaging and analysis. &nbsp;Optical antennas have been studied as a means to manipulate nanoscale fields, local field enhancements, radiative rates, and emissive directional control.&nbsp; However, a fundamental function of antennas, the transfer of power between a coupled load and far-field radiation, has seen limited development in optical antennas owing largely to the inherent challenges of extracting impedance parameters from fabricated designs. As the transitional element between radiating fields and loads, the impedance is the requisite information for describing, and designing optimally, both emissive (transmitting) and absorptive (receiving) optical antennas.&nbsp; This quantification of optical antenna impedance using near-field measurements provides the long sought enabling step for a systematic approach to improve collection efficiencies and control of the overall antenna response.&nbsp; Both open and short-circuit resonances, as well as multi-element antennas, have been investigated to present a blueprint for maximizing collection efficiency and flexibly controlling optical antenna impedance through design as a means of achieving maximum power transfer through impedance matching. This work provides a requisite step towards extending all theoretical concepts of optical and infrared nanoantennas into practical applications by demonstrating the measurement of well-controlled input impedance in optical nanoantennas.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/11/2016<br>      Modified by: Glenn&nbsp;Boreman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project allowed measurement, for the first time at infrared frequencies, of the feedpoint impedance of an optical antenna.  Near field scanning optical microscopy was used to measure magnitude and phase of electric fields in the vicinity of infrared antenna and transmission line structures.  Through the excitation of stable standing waves on transmission line coupled antennas, we achieved a systematic way to determine the impedance values of optical antennas through near-field imaging and analysis.  Optical antennas have been studied as a means to manipulate nanoscale fields, local field enhancements, radiative rates, and emissive directional control.  However, a fundamental function of antennas, the transfer of power between a coupled load and far-field radiation, has seen limited development in optical antennas owing largely to the inherent challenges of extracting impedance parameters from fabricated designs. As the transitional element between radiating fields and loads, the impedance is the requisite information for describing, and designing optimally, both emissive (transmitting) and absorptive (receiving) optical antennas.  This quantification of optical antenna impedance using near-field measurements provides the long sought enabling step for a systematic approach to improve collection efficiencies and control of the overall antenna response.  Both open and short-circuit resonances, as well as multi-element antennas, have been investigated to present a blueprint for maximizing collection efficiency and flexibly controlling optical antenna impedance through design as a means of achieving maximum power transfer through impedance matching. This work provides a requisite step towards extending all theoretical concepts of optical and infrared nanoantennas into practical applications by demonstrating the measurement of well-controlled input impedance in optical nanoantennas.          Last Modified: 01/11/2016       Submitted by: Glenn Boreman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
