<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WSC-Category 2 Collaborative: Robust decision-making for South Florida water resources by ecosystem service valuation, hydro-economic optimization, and conflict resolution modeling</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>430497.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>430497</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Torgersen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Water management in south Florida is characterized by the need to balance multiple objectives. Among the objectives are the maintenance of high groundwater levels to limit seawater intrusion and flood control measures that are also used to mitigate  dry-season water shortages. In addition, south Florida's current population of 6 million is projected to grow to 10 million over the next 20 years, and urban water demand must be reliably managed. In this exceptionally vulnerable region, sea level rise and salt water intrusion have already impacted drinking water supplies and threaten the integrity of low-lying and highly-valued built and natural environments as diverse as Miami Beach and the Everglades. Long-term adaptive strategies are needed to ensure sustainable water resources for expanding populations, agriculture, and wetlands that serve multiple functions, including support of Florida's fishing industry. Development of such strategies has been hampered by conflicting stakeholder interests and technical, economic, and political challenges. This project will conduct highly interdisciplinary research, utilizing the expertise of multiple institutions, to investigate the hydrologic, economic, ecologic, and human behavioral dimensions of sustainable water management and land use planning under various climate change, economic, population, and sea level rise scenarios. The research will employ hydro-economic optimization approaches based on robust decision making to develop management strategies that ensure the resilience of water supplies for the built and natural systems, while also accounting for the broad-sector value of water use. Optimization criteria will incorporate the results of project research linking water management, ecological function, and the economic value of ecosystem services. New experimental approaches will be implemented to better understand the impacts of scenario information type and uncertainty on both selection of decision criteria and evaluation of model predictions among individuals and groups of local stakeholders. These experiments are designed to improve understanding of the roles of cognitive and perceptual biases in decision-making when stakeholders examine hydro-economic projections coupled with scenario forecasts. Comparative behavioral analyses of stakeholder evaluations and institutional decision-making will provide unique insights into how information type, information content, and cognitive biases combine to influence risk perception, and how the perceived risks to individual and collective well-being influence scenario selection. Finally, with agency and stakeholder involvement, the project will collaboratively develop recommendations for adaptive water management plans that foster long-term support from the stakeholders. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Low-lying coastal regions subject to sea level rise, climate change, and diverse water demands, including growing populations, will benefit from the development of innovative, pragmatic approaches to optimizing the social-ecological benefits of water resources allocation. The research will include novel approaches for dynamically incorporating economics into stakeholder evaluations of adaptive land use and water management strategies. Local, state, and federal agencies responsible for managing south Florida's water resources will benefit from analyses of adaptive schemes that explicitly incorporate uncertainty estimates of potential outcomes. The multiple societies that exist in south Florida, whose options for managing public water resources are limited by climatic, physical, and/or legal constraints, require this type of integrated assessment to promote cooperative decision-making while preparing for uncertain hydro-climatic conditions and socioeconomic futures.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1204474</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Watkins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David W Watkins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dwatkins@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064871640</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000225921</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan Technological University</Name>
<CityName>Houghton</CityName>
<ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9064871885</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 Townsend Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065453268</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN TECHNOLOGICAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065453268</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan Technological University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~430497</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project integrated the expertise of investigators from multiple institutions to conduct interdisciplinary research to understand hydrologic, economic, ecologic, and human behavioral dimensions of sustainable water management.&nbsp; The research used hydro-economic optimization approaches to explore management strategies that account for the value of water for the built environment, agriculture, and natural eco-systems under various climate change, economic, population, sea level rise, and land use planning scenarios. This required better understanding of future climate and the effects of too much and too little water on cities, agriculture, and ecosystem services. Flooding, water scarcity, and seawater intrusion affect Southeast Florida cities, while water scarcity and high water tables impact agriculture. Ecosystem services including carbon storage and fisheries are also water-dependent.</p> <p>The economic values of agricultural and urban water supplies, urban flood damage, and environmental flows that sustain carbon storage and fisheries were developed from numerous data sources. Following testing of the optimization approach, it was used to examine tradeoffs between water supply, flood mitigation, and maintenance of ecosystem functions under existing conditions and different possible future conditions, including more or less rainfall, higher temperatures, and sea level rise. Under existing conditions, due to large differences in rainfall from year-to-year and due to water storage constraints in Lake Okeechobee, there are significant tradeoffs between maintaining reliable water supplies for urban and agricultural sectors, and maintaining ecosystems. Under an increased rainfall scenario, system-wide expected economic losses decrease significantly, except for the risk of urban flooding. Under scenarios of reduced rainfall and increased evapotranspiration, the system&rsquo;s ability to meet water demands significantly degrades, thus intensifying tradeoffs. Results also point to vulnerability of the Everglades Agricultural Area to climate change, even in the absence of Everglades ecosystem restoration targets. Sea level rise limits the ability to move water through the system without increasing flood risk.</p> <p>Managing environmental flows in a future of changes in freshwater availability due to climate change and the increasing water demands of people requires understanding of how ecological systems respond to changing flows. We found that freshwater flows can have a major influence on the ecology of economically-valuable coastal fish and fisheries that depend on estuaries, including their diversity, abundance, use of space, movements, and distributions. Changing flows affect salinity, nutrient flows, and other important factors such as dissolved oxygen, as well as causing changes to habitat quality and quantity.</p> <p>Coastal wetlands are also important sites of organic carbon storage.&nbsp; For a few thousand years, coastal wetlands have expanded under stable sea level, and have provided ecosystem services of high ecological and socio-economic significance including carbon storage and fisheries.&nbsp; Whether coastal mangrove forests will survive under accelerating sea level rise depends on their ability to gain and maintain soil elevation and/or migrate landward. We found that carbon accumulation drives soil elevation in southwestern Florida mangroves. The sustainability of these wetlands depends on the balance between soil organic matter production and preservation. Our results showed reductions in carbon storage where more sea water is invading coastal mangroves. Soil elevation was keeping up with sea level rise rates over the last 50 to 100 years, but has not kept pace with the faster sea level rise in the last decade.</p> <p>Outreach to South Florida stakeholder groups occurred in several different forms. First, there was direct engagement with key stakeholder groups. Direct engagement with agricultural stakeholders revealed the complex and multifaceted relationship between agricultural activities and the regional water system that is expected to become more complex due to potential climate change impacts. Insights were also gathered from examining local citizens&rsquo; policy preferences for Everglades restoration and sea level rise adaptation. New social science experimental approaches were implemented to better understand the impacts of information type and uncertainty on risk perception and decision making, particularly in the context of sea level rise impacts on communities. These insights can support adaptive management strategies in South Florida and elsewhere.</p> <p>The project fostered ongoing agency and stakeholder collaborations and contributed to managers&rsquo; understanding of the integrated water-human-climate system of South Florida. These connections will enhance the relevance of research findings for regional policy.</p> <p>Outreach activities also included lectures, websites, webinars, citizen science activities, and presentations at conferences, workshops, and schools.</p> <p>Finally, the project looked at the process of conducting interdisciplinary team science itself and published the results for the benefit of researchers doing similar work and for the benefit of all people facing complex challenges that require multi- and inter-disciplinary perspectives.</p> <p>The project published nearly 40 peer-reviewed journal articles through 2018. Master&rsquo;s theses and Ph.D. dissertations have also been published. The project supported the research and professional development of a high school intern, more than 15 undergraduate students, 21 graduate students, and 8 postdoctoral researchers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2019<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;W&nbsp;Watkins</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project integrated the expertise of investigators from multiple institutions to conduct interdisciplinary research to understand hydrologic, economic, ecologic, and human behavioral dimensions of sustainable water management.  The research used hydro-economic optimization approaches to explore management strategies that account for the value of water for the built environment, agriculture, and natural eco-systems under various climate change, economic, population, sea level rise, and land use planning scenarios. This required better understanding of future climate and the effects of too much and too little water on cities, agriculture, and ecosystem services. Flooding, water scarcity, and seawater intrusion affect Southeast Florida cities, while water scarcity and high water tables impact agriculture. Ecosystem services including carbon storage and fisheries are also water-dependent.  The economic values of agricultural and urban water supplies, urban flood damage, and environmental flows that sustain carbon storage and fisheries were developed from numerous data sources. Following testing of the optimization approach, it was used to examine tradeoffs between water supply, flood mitigation, and maintenance of ecosystem functions under existing conditions and different possible future conditions, including more or less rainfall, higher temperatures, and sea level rise. Under existing conditions, due to large differences in rainfall from year-to-year and due to water storage constraints in Lake Okeechobee, there are significant tradeoffs between maintaining reliable water supplies for urban and agricultural sectors, and maintaining ecosystems. Under an increased rainfall scenario, system-wide expected economic losses decrease significantly, except for the risk of urban flooding. Under scenarios of reduced rainfall and increased evapotranspiration, the system?s ability to meet water demands significantly degrades, thus intensifying tradeoffs. Results also point to vulnerability of the Everglades Agricultural Area to climate change, even in the absence of Everglades ecosystem restoration targets. Sea level rise limits the ability to move water through the system without increasing flood risk.  Managing environmental flows in a future of changes in freshwater availability due to climate change and the increasing water demands of people requires understanding of how ecological systems respond to changing flows. We found that freshwater flows can have a major influence on the ecology of economically-valuable coastal fish and fisheries that depend on estuaries, including their diversity, abundance, use of space, movements, and distributions. Changing flows affect salinity, nutrient flows, and other important factors such as dissolved oxygen, as well as causing changes to habitat quality and quantity.  Coastal wetlands are also important sites of organic carbon storage.  For a few thousand years, coastal wetlands have expanded under stable sea level, and have provided ecosystem services of high ecological and socio-economic significance including carbon storage and fisheries.  Whether coastal mangrove forests will survive under accelerating sea level rise depends on their ability to gain and maintain soil elevation and/or migrate landward. We found that carbon accumulation drives soil elevation in southwestern Florida mangroves. The sustainability of these wetlands depends on the balance between soil organic matter production and preservation. Our results showed reductions in carbon storage where more sea water is invading coastal mangroves. Soil elevation was keeping up with sea level rise rates over the last 50 to 100 years, but has not kept pace with the faster sea level rise in the last decade.  Outreach to South Florida stakeholder groups occurred in several different forms. First, there was direct engagement with key stakeholder groups. Direct engagement with agricultural stakeholders revealed the complex and multifaceted relationship between agricultural activities and the regional water system that is expected to become more complex due to potential climate change impacts. Insights were also gathered from examining local citizens? policy preferences for Everglades restoration and sea level rise adaptation. New social science experimental approaches were implemented to better understand the impacts of information type and uncertainty on risk perception and decision making, particularly in the context of sea level rise impacts on communities. These insights can support adaptive management strategies in South Florida and elsewhere.  The project fostered ongoing agency and stakeholder collaborations and contributed to managers? understanding of the integrated water-human-climate system of South Florida. These connections will enhance the relevance of research findings for regional policy.  Outreach activities also included lectures, websites, webinars, citizen science activities, and presentations at conferences, workshops, and schools.  Finally, the project looked at the process of conducting interdisciplinary team science itself and published the results for the benefit of researchers doing similar work and for the benefit of all people facing complex challenges that require multi- and inter-disciplinary perspectives.  The project published nearly 40 peer-reviewed journal articles through 2018. Master?s theses and Ph.D. dissertations have also been published. The project supported the research and professional development of a high school intern, more than 15 undergraduate students, 21 graduate students, and 8 postdoctoral researchers.          Last Modified: 03/31/2019       Submitted by: David W Watkins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
