<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research in Classical and Quantum Gravity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1320000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1320000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmarrone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927372</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant will support continued research at the University of California, Santa Barbara into a quantum theory of gravity and its application to cosmology. James Hartle will investigate the principles which determine the quantum state of the universe and the generalizations of quantum mechanics necessary to understand it. Gary Horowitz will investigate the gravitational aspects of string theory, a promising candidate for a quantum theory of gravity. Don Marolf will explore interacting quantum matter around black holes and in cosmology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work in centered in the ongoing quest of physics for a unified theory of nature's fundamental forces and the origin of the universe. These are subjects not only of great interest to scientists but also the general public. By engaging the interest of students and the public, the principal investigators hope to encourage general appreciation for science.  In addition, the project will develop human resources for science and technology by training graduate students and postdoctoral scholars in advanced techniques.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1205500</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>Horowitz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gary T Horowitz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gary@physics.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058932742</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000235626</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Hartle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James B Hartle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hartle@physics.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058932725</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000227639</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Marolf</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald Marolf</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marolf@physics.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058935205</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000396005</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1244</Code>
<Text>Gravity Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~440000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~440000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~440000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>One of the most remarkable developments to emerge from string theory is gauge/gravity duality which relates a theory of gravity with certain boundary conditions (known as anti-de Sitter or AdS) to a nongravitational theory. Using this duality, problems that are hard to solve in one theory can be mapped to tractable problems in another. Horowitz applied this duality in both directions to improve our understanding of quantum gravity and strongly coupled systems. First he showed with Santos that several properties of high temperature superconductors can be reproduced by a simple gravitational model. They also found an analytic gravity solution describing a conductor that includes nonlinear effects such as Joule heating. Applying the duality in the other direction, Horowitz &nbsp;worked with his student, Engelhardt, and Hertog to gain insight into cosmological singularities like the Big Bang by mapping them to a simpler problem in a theory without gravity.</p> <p>Horowitz and Marolf also developed our understanding of gravity in Anti-de Sitter (AdS) space in several ways. &nbsp;First, working with Santos and Dias, they argued that known instabilities of empty AdS turn off when enough energy is added to significantly deform the geometry. &nbsp;In particular, even though the distant regions of the space are deformed only infinitesimally, no instability remains in those regions. &nbsp;Second, Marolf worked with Fischetti and Santos to find a time-independent solution in which entropy is constantly created. &nbsp;This differs significantly from the previously-known time-independent solutions which were all in thermodynamic equilibrium.</p> <p>Another highlight of Marolf's results from this grant was a series of papers (with Polchinski and others) demonstrating the extreme nature of the so-called black hole information problem. &nbsp;This problem is the tension between i) the ever-increasing quantum entanglement of a black hole with its surroundings that results from the Hawking radiation process and ii) the apparently finite number of quantum states associated with a black hole. &nbsp;They argued that resolving this tension will require dramatic new physics at the black hole horizon, and they conjectured that in sufficiently old black holes the smooth horizon predicted by general relativity is transformed to a surface (dubbed a ``firewall'') where spacetime itself breaks down and infalling observers are destroyed.</p> <p><span>At the big bang the largest physical system &mdash; the universe &mdash; was at the smallest physical size. Quantum mechanics is therefore important for the origin of the universe.&nbsp; Hartle, often in collaboration with Thomas Hertog, continued a program to understand the quantum origin of the universe. In particular he explored the predictions of a quantum state of the universe for the cosmological observations that we see today 14 billion years after the big bang. Among the issues addressed were : How to formulate predictions for observations when the observer is inside the system not outside it.&nbsp; How to use models of the string landscape to make quantitative predictions for the dark energy and early density fluctuations that eventually formed galaxies, starts, planets etc. The origin of classical physics in a quantum universe was studied along with what to do when the approximation of classical physics breaks down. This work is part of an ongoing program to understand quantitatively how today&rsquo;s universe emerged from its quantum origin.&nbsp;</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/02/2016<br>      Modified by: Gary&nbsp;T&nbsp;Horowitz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ One of the most remarkable developments to emerge from string theory is gauge/gravity duality which relates a theory of gravity with certain boundary conditions (known as anti-de Sitter or AdS) to a nongravitational theory. Using this duality, problems that are hard to solve in one theory can be mapped to tractable problems in another. Horowitz applied this duality in both directions to improve our understanding of quantum gravity and strongly coupled systems. First he showed with Santos that several properties of high temperature superconductors can be reproduced by a simple gravitational model. They also found an analytic gravity solution describing a conductor that includes nonlinear effects such as Joule heating. Applying the duality in the other direction, Horowitz  worked with his student, Engelhardt, and Hertog to gain insight into cosmological singularities like the Big Bang by mapping them to a simpler problem in a theory without gravity.  Horowitz and Marolf also developed our understanding of gravity in Anti-de Sitter (AdS) space in several ways.  First, working with Santos and Dias, they argued that known instabilities of empty AdS turn off when enough energy is added to significantly deform the geometry.  In particular, even though the distant regions of the space are deformed only infinitesimally, no instability remains in those regions.  Second, Marolf worked with Fischetti and Santos to find a time-independent solution in which entropy is constantly created.  This differs significantly from the previously-known time-independent solutions which were all in thermodynamic equilibrium.  Another highlight of Marolf's results from this grant was a series of papers (with Polchinski and others) demonstrating the extreme nature of the so-called black hole information problem.  This problem is the tension between i) the ever-increasing quantum entanglement of a black hole with its surroundings that results from the Hawking radiation process and ii) the apparently finite number of quantum states associated with a black hole.  They argued that resolving this tension will require dramatic new physics at the black hole horizon, and they conjectured that in sufficiently old black holes the smooth horizon predicted by general relativity is transformed to a surface (dubbed a ``firewall'') where spacetime itself breaks down and infalling observers are destroyed.  At the big bang the largest physical system &mdash; the universe &mdash; was at the smallest physical size. Quantum mechanics is therefore important for the origin of the universe.  Hartle, often in collaboration with Thomas Hertog, continued a program to understand the quantum origin of the universe. In particular he explored the predictions of a quantum state of the universe for the cosmological observations that we see today 14 billion years after the big bang. Among the issues addressed were : How to formulate predictions for observations when the observer is inside the system not outside it.  How to use models of the string landscape to make quantitative predictions for the dark energy and early density fluctuations that eventually formed galaxies, starts, planets etc. The origin of classical physics in a quantum universe was studied along with what to do when the approximation of classical physics breaks down. This work is part of an ongoing program to understand quantitatively how todayÆs universe emerged from its quantum origin.             Last Modified: 06/02/2016       Submitted by: Gary T Horowitz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
