<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Emergent Quantum Phenomena in Layered Ruthenates and Iron Chalcogenides</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>334999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>334999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdurakie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924892</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>****Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;Emergent quantum phenomena in correlated electron materials not only show promise for use in advanced applications in energy and information technologies, but also challenge current knowledge in condensed matter physics. This project will focus on two correlated material systems, i.e. layered ruthenates and iron chalcogenides. Both material systems provide remarkable opportunities for observing novel quantum phenomena due to complex interplay between the charge, spin, lattice and orbital degrees of freedom. For ruthenates, the project aims at searching for a novel quantum phase related to the quantum Griffiths phenomena and elucidating the mechanism for various unusual magnetic phase transitions. For iron chalcogenides, the goal is to seek emergent magnetic phenomena and unconventional superconductivity. This project will bring together a wide range of expertise including crystal growth, property characterization, neutron scattering and optical spectroscopy to enable comprehensive understanding of emergent quantum phenomena of correlated electrons. This project will be integrated with education activities through the following efforts: a) involving graduate and undergraduate students in the research, b) developing senior design projects for students majoring in Engineering Physics, and c) guiding students from a local high school in an independent research project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****Non-Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt; Materials with strong electron-electron correlation are commonly believed to hold the key for developing the next generation of electronics. The objective of this project is to search for novel quantum phenomena and investigate their underlying physics in two correlated material systems, i.e. layered ruthenates and iron chalcogenides. Both material systems have been found to show various exciting properties, such as metal-insulator transitions and unconventional forms of superconductivity and magnetic ordering. One of the remarkable characteristics of these materials is that their properties are sensitive to external stimuli and their properties can be tuned by magnetic field, pressure and chemical substitution; this provides wonderful opportunities to study the novel physics associated with complex phase transitions of correlated electrons. This project will bring together a wide range of expertise to enable comprehensive understanding of emergent quantum phenomena of correlated electrons. This project will be integrated with education activities through the following efforts: a) involving graduate and undergraduate students in the research, b) developing senior design projects for students majoring in Engineering Physics, and c) guiding students from a local high school in an independent research project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1205469</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhiqiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Mao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhiqiang Mao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zim1@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148657258</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000286901</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/24/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tulane University</Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<ZipCode>701185698</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5048654000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6823 ST CHARLES AVENUE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADMINISTRATORS OF THE TULANE EDUCATIONAL FUND, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tulane University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>701185665</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6823 St. Charles Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~124999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~110000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Functional properties such as superconductivity and metal-insulator transition in novel quantum materials not only hold the promise for advanced applications in information and energy technologies, but also challenge current knowledge in physics. The research supported by the NSF through grant DMR-1205469 aims to search for emergent phenomena in quantum materials such as strongly correlated oxides and transition metal chalcogenides, and investigate their underlying physics. The research work supported by this award has led to 30 publications in peered-reviewed journals; many of them appear in prestigious journals such as <em>Nature Physics</em> (1), <em>Nature Materials</em> (1), <em>Nature Communications </em>(2), <em>Physical Review letters</em> (<em>4</em>), <em>Scientific Report (3)</em>, <em>Physical Review B</em> (<em>13</em>). The results published in these papers have remarkably advanced the understanding of novel functional properties of several quantum material systems as summarized below. &nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p><strong>-- Understanding of the interplay between magnetism and superconductivity in iron chalcogenides</strong></p> <p>High temperature superconductors of compounds containing Fe has been a focused research area in condensed matter physics in recent years. The PI&rsquo;s earlier work demonstrated a unique scenario of the interplay between superconductivity and magnetism in the iron chalcogenide system [Nature materials <strong>9</strong>, 718-720 (2010)]. In the project supported by the current award, the PI was focused on the study of the coupling between electronic and magnetic properties in Fe<sub>1+<em>y</em></sub>(Te<sub>1-x</sub>Se<sub>x</sub>), the goal of which is to further understand the complex interplay between magnetism and superconductivity. The PI has mapped out a more complete electronic phase diagram and studied the evolution of several physical quantities in the phase diagram, including Sommerfeld coefficient and Hall coefficient. The results resulting from this study reveal the mechanism for the superconductivity suppression in the underdoped region: magnetic fluctuations at a wave vector of (pi,0) cause incoherent magnetic scattering which reduces the charge carriers&rsquo; mobility and results in charge carrier localization [<em>PRB </em><strong>88,</strong> 094505(13)].</p> <p><strong>--Novel Exotic phenomena in strongly correlated ruthenates</strong>:</p> <p>The PI&rsquo;s work on correlated oxides (<em>i.e. </em>ruthetaes) has also been fruitful. First, the PI discovered a novel quantum phase characterized by slow dynamics of rare regions arising from the effect of disorder near a quantum phase transition (QPT). This finding advances the understanding of QPTs in disordered systems [<em>PRB</em> <strong>86</strong>, 014434 (2012)]. Second, the PI found a new type of magnetic phase transitions tuned by small concentration (&lt;=3%) chemical doping. For Sr2RuO4 which is the first example of spin-triplet superconductor, the PI found that &lt;2% Co doping can trigger a short-range ferromagnetic order, while 3%Mn doping can establish a long-range antiferromagnetic order, indicating that the superconductivity of Sr2RuO4 lies directly on the borderline of two distinct magnetic states. This highlights the important role of competing magnetic fluctuations in determining superconducting properties of Sr<sub>2</sub>RuO<sub>4</sub> [<em>Scientific Report</em> <strong>3</strong>:2950 (13)]. For Ca3Ru2O7, the PI&rsquo;s group, together with his collaborator Ke at MSU, found its quai-2D metal ground state can be tuned to a Mott insulating state with the nearest neighbor G-type antiferromagetic order [PRB 87, 085125(13); Scientific Report 6, 19462 (2016)]. They also found such a Mott insulating state can be tuned back to a metallic state with an A-type-like antiferromagnetic order by magnetic fields [PRL 116, 216401(2016)].</p> <p><strong>--Enhanced electron coherence in atomically thin Nb<sub>3</sub>SiTe<sub>6</sub></strong></p> <p>The PI has also explored low-dimensional physics using quantum transport properties found in one of his synthesized materials, Nb<sub>3</sub>SiTe<sub>6</sub>. One important issue he addressed is the quantum confinement effect on electron-phonon (<em>e-ph</em>) interaction. This work was done through collaboration with several other groups, including Wei at Tulane, Natelson at Rice and Adams at LSU. They find that the <em>e-ph</em> interaction is indeed modified by a phonon dimensionality crossover and suppressed in the two-dimensional limit [<em>Nature Physics 11, 471 (2015<strong>)</strong></em>].</p> <p><strong>Accomplishments related to the Broader Impact activities</strong></p> <p>Mao has made significant efforts to integrate his research with education activities. First, research training is an important part of his research projects. Nine graduate students and six postdocs have been involved as participants in his research projects. Three of them graduated with Ph.D. during the current award period. Mao also offered research opportunities to five undergraduate students over the past four years. One successful example he likes to mention is that one honor student directed by him published his honor thesis in <em>Scientific Report</em> and was awarded a NSF graduate fellowship. Secondly, Mao also actively participated in outreach activities. He participated in organizing Materials Summer Camp at Tulane in 2013-2016: The Science of Electronic and Bio Materials. Mao offered two lectures on superconductivity and magnetism for each camp; hands-on labs were also provided during the camp. In addition, Mao also participated in several other outreach activities. For instance, during the summer of 2015, Mao helped with executing the STEM demonstrations with the high school students from Savannah, GA.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Zhiqiang&nbsp;Mao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Functional properties such as superconductivity and metal-insulator transition in novel quantum materials not only hold the promise for advanced applications in information and energy technologies, but also challenge current knowledge in physics. The research supported by the NSF through grant DMR-1205469 aims to search for emergent phenomena in quantum materials such as strongly correlated oxides and transition metal chalcogenides, and investigate their underlying physics. The research work supported by this award has led to 30 publications in peered-reviewed journals; many of them appear in prestigious journals such as Nature Physics (1), Nature Materials (1), Nature Communications (2), Physical Review letters (4), Scientific Report (3), Physical Review B (13). The results published in these papers have remarkably advanced the understanding of novel functional properties of several quantum material systems as summarized below.      -- Understanding of the interplay between magnetism and superconductivity in iron chalcogenides  High temperature superconductors of compounds containing Fe has been a focused research area in condensed matter physics in recent years. The PI?s earlier work demonstrated a unique scenario of the interplay between superconductivity and magnetism in the iron chalcogenide system [Nature materials 9, 718-720 (2010)]. In the project supported by the current award, the PI was focused on the study of the coupling between electronic and magnetic properties in Fe1+y(Te1-xSex), the goal of which is to further understand the complex interplay between magnetism and superconductivity. The PI has mapped out a more complete electronic phase diagram and studied the evolution of several physical quantities in the phase diagram, including Sommerfeld coefficient and Hall coefficient. The results resulting from this study reveal the mechanism for the superconductivity suppression in the underdoped region: magnetic fluctuations at a wave vector of (pi,0) cause incoherent magnetic scattering which reduces the charge carriers? mobility and results in charge carrier localization [PRB 88, 094505(13)].  --Novel Exotic phenomena in strongly correlated ruthenates:  The PI?s work on correlated oxides (i.e. ruthetaes) has also been fruitful. First, the PI discovered a novel quantum phase characterized by slow dynamics of rare regions arising from the effect of disorder near a quantum phase transition (QPT). This finding advances the understanding of QPTs in disordered systems [PRB 86, 014434 (2012)]. Second, the PI found a new type of magnetic phase transitions tuned by small concentration (&lt;=3%) chemical doping. For Sr2RuO4 which is the first example of spin-triplet superconductor, the PI found that &lt;2% Co doping can trigger a short-range ferromagnetic order, while 3%Mn doping can establish a long-range antiferromagnetic order, indicating that the superconductivity of Sr2RuO4 lies directly on the borderline of two distinct magnetic states. This highlights the important role of competing magnetic fluctuations in determining superconducting properties of Sr2RuO4 [Scientific Report 3:2950 (13)]. For Ca3Ru2O7, the PI?s group, together with his collaborator Ke at MSU, found its quai-2D metal ground state can be tuned to a Mott insulating state with the nearest neighbor G-type antiferromagetic order [PRB 87, 085125(13); Scientific Report 6, 19462 (2016)]. They also found such a Mott insulating state can be tuned back to a metallic state with an A-type-like antiferromagnetic order by magnetic fields [PRL 116, 216401(2016)].  --Enhanced electron coherence in atomically thin Nb3SiTe6  The PI has also explored low-dimensional physics using quantum transport properties found in one of his synthesized materials, Nb3SiTe6. One important issue he addressed is the quantum confinement effect on electron-phonon (e-ph) interaction. This work was done through collaboration with several other groups, including Wei at Tulane, Natelson at Rice and Adams at LSU. They find that the e-ph interaction is indeed modified by a phonon dimensionality crossover and suppressed in the two-dimensional limit [Nature Physics 11, 471 (2015)].  Accomplishments related to the Broader Impact activities  Mao has made significant efforts to integrate his research with education activities. First, research training is an important part of his research projects. Nine graduate students and six postdocs have been involved as participants in his research projects. Three of them graduated with Ph.D. during the current award period. Mao also offered research opportunities to five undergraduate students over the past four years. One successful example he likes to mention is that one honor student directed by him published his honor thesis in Scientific Report and was awarded a NSF graduate fellowship. Secondly, Mao also actively participated in outreach activities. He participated in organizing Materials Summer Camp at Tulane in 2013-2016: The Science of Electronic and Bio Materials. Mao offered two lectures on superconductivity and magnetism for each camp; hands-on labs were also provided during the camp. In addition, Mao also participated in several other outreach activities. For instance, during the summer of 2015, Mao helped with executing the STEM demonstrations with the high school students from Savannah, GA.                Last Modified: 08/30/2016       Submitted by: Zhiqiang Mao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
