<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Operations of VERITAS in the Epoch 2011 to 2014</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1425000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1425000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jean Allen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcallen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Very Energetic Radiation Imaging Telescope Array System (VERITAS) began full-scale operations in September 2007 and completed a telescope upgrade in the summer of 2012.  This award funds ongoing maintenance and operation of both the telescopes and the array facility over a 3-year period.  VERITAS seeks to both identify new sources of Very High Energy (VHE: E &gt;100 Gigaelectron-volt) gamma rays, and to perform in-depth studies of the known sources to better understand their underlying fundamental processes.  The primary targets of VERITAS Galactic observations are supernova remnants, pulsars, binary systems, and known VHE sources whose classification is currently unknown. The extragalactic targets observed by VERITAS include active galactic nuclei, radio galaxies, starburst galaxies, galaxy clusters and gamma-ray bursts.  In addition, Local Group galaxies, dwarf galaxies and globular clusters are targets of VERITAS observations focused on the indirect detection of cold dark matter.  VERITAS is currently the most-sensitive VHE gamma-ray observatory in the world.  After 6-years of operation, the experiment is well-understood and promised performance metrics of the experiment (e.g. total data yield and data quality) are achieved or surpassed.  Continued operations of VERITAS for this funding cycle are expected to result in new gamma-ray science.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact and Outreach:  The VERITAS collaboration is involved in public engagement as an important element of its research program.  The Adler Planetarium and the Fred Lawrence Whipple Observatory Visitors Center at the VERITAS site coordinate activities, websites and public displays to promote VERITAS science to the public, other educators, museum professionals and the wider community.  VERITAS scientists provide education and public outreach experiences in the form of multimedia products, public presentations and activities such as classroom visits, an annual public lecture series, "star parties" at the observatory, and tours of the experiment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1205389</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wystan</FirstName>
<LastName>Benbow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wystan R Benbow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wbenbow@cfa.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174967597</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508621</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Smithsonian Institution Astrophysical Observatory</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021381516</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174967923</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>60 Garden St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Stop 23]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003261823</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>161906193</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Smithsonian Institution Astrophysical Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Amado</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>856456369</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[670 Mt. Hopkins Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1643</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Cosmic P</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~435000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~440000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~550000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; VERITAS is the world&rsquo;s most-sensitive very-high-energy (VHE; E  &gt; 100 GeV) gamma-ray observatory, and is located in southern  Arizona.&nbsp; This award from the NSF partially supported the operations of  the VERITAS telescope array and the array facility for the purposes of  astrophysical research from 2013-2017.&nbsp; The support covered the  project&rsquo;s seventh through tenth season of operation.&nbsp; VERITAS remains  operational, the experiment is in excellent condition and support is  identified to operate the facility through at least 2019.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A  recent external review concluded the VERITAS collaboration &ldquo;pioneered  the field of ground-based gamma-ray astronomy and is one of three  leading experiments at this time.&nbsp; It is a key experiment in a triad,  with Fermi and HAWC, allowing the US to decisively lead the field of  gamma-ray astronomy&rdquo;.&nbsp;&nbsp; The scientific operation of VERITAS was highly  successful during the award.&nbsp; The VERITAS collaboration has reported the  detection of 60 astrophysical sources of VHE gamma rays, belonging to  ~8 different source classes.&nbsp; The VERITAS catalog increased by ~20%  during the award period, and overall it now represents about one-third  of the entire VHE catalog.&nbsp;&nbsp; All VERITAS results are published in  high-impact factor, peer-reviewed journals.&nbsp; The VERITAS collaboration  has published 99 refereed journal articles and has produced 56 PhD  theses. Forty-three of these articles appeared, and twenty-three of  these theses were completed, during the award period.&nbsp; This publication  rate compares favorably to other VHE experiments.&nbsp; While the science  program addressed a number of important topics in astrophysics, one  particular science highlight involves the unexpected detection of VHE  gamma-rays from a galaxy located more than halfway across the universe.&nbsp;  This unique detection was the first detection of large-scale VHE  emission from an extragalactic source, and enabled strong single-source  constraints for cosmology.&nbsp; Significant science remains to be completed  by VERITAS, including our legacy observing program.&nbsp; Observing time at  VERITAS remains oversubscribed and approximately 50 VERITAS journal  articles are in preparation, with five near submission. The training  mission of VERITAS also remains strong as 40% of the collaboration  members are students.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; During the award period, VERITAS operations  also could only be described as highly successful.&nbsp; External reviews  held during the award period commented on &ldquo;impressive levels of  operational efficiency and expanded uptime of the telescopes&rdquo; and noted  &ldquo;the project is extremely well managed&rdquo;.&nbsp; Another report noted VERITAS  &ldquo;is a mature experiment with a well-developed maintenance and operation  plan that has constantly delivered a stream of quality science data with  high efficiency&rdquo;.&nbsp; Specifically, an average of 1310 h of data were  taken over the four seasons covered by this award, exceeding the project  requirements of more than 900 h per year.&nbsp; In addition, all performance  metrics for these data were met and often exceeded and no event  rendered any significant quantity of data unusable.&nbsp; Significant  cost-cutting measures were also developed and tested, enabling future  VERITAS operations to proceed with more than 20% reduced budget.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;  &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;Throughout this award the VERITAS collaboration continued its  strong commitment to enabling public understanding of science as an  outcome of its research.&nbsp; At the VERITAS site itself, the F.L. Whipple  Observatory (FLWO) Visitor&rsquo;s Center continued to coordinate many ongoing  activities to promote VERITAS science to the public and the wider  community.&nbsp; Here displays, exhibits and videos presented astronomy and  astrophysics relevant to VERITAS.&nbsp; VERITAS Project Office (VPO)  scientists also delivered public lectures and participated in the  extensive community outreach program at FLWO.&nbsp; This included providing  formal &amp; informal tours of the VERITAS site for journalists,  authors, astronomy clubs, and youth groups.&nbsp; VPO scientists also hosted  star parties, participated in science fairs, and visited school  classrooms.&nbsp; A public website (http://veritas.sao.arizona.edu) operated  by the VPO provided a description of the VERITAS project and related  science. All refereed VERITAS publications and PhD theses are also  linked to this page, along with a brief description of each result. A  VERITAS Facebook page and Twitter feed are also active, and a YouTube  channel contains video content from VERITAS scientists. &nbsp;Over the course  of the award we also enabled may unique outreach experiences; one of  our more recent endeavors was the VERITAS Muon Hunter partnership with  the Zooniverse project.&nbsp; Here crowd-sourcing was used to test methods  for the classification of VERITAS background (muon) images.&nbsp; Over 5000  volunteers participated in a trial, and over 2 million images were  classified.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The VERITAS collaboration is grateful for the support  of the U.S. National Science Foundation which makes its research  possible.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/10/2018<br>      Modified by: Wystan&nbsp;R&nbsp;Benbow</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[     VERITAS is the world?s most-sensitive very-high-energy (VHE; E  &gt; 100 GeV) gamma-ray observatory, and is located in southern  Arizona.  This award from the NSF partially supported the operations of  the VERITAS telescope array and the array facility for the purposes of  astrophysical research from 2013-2017.  The support covered the  project?s seventh through tenth season of operation.  VERITAS remains  operational, the experiment is in excellent condition and support is  identified to operate the facility through at least 2019.     A  recent external review concluded the VERITAS collaboration "pioneered  the field of ground-based gamma-ray astronomy and is one of three  leading experiments at this time.  It is a key experiment in a triad,  with Fermi and HAWC, allowing the US to decisively lead the field of  gamma-ray astronomy".   The scientific operation of VERITAS was highly  successful during the award.  The VERITAS collaboration has reported the  detection of 60 astrophysical sources of VHE gamma rays, belonging to  ~8 different source classes.  The VERITAS catalog increased by ~20%  during the award period, and overall it now represents about one-third  of the entire VHE catalog.   All VERITAS results are published in  high-impact factor, peer-reviewed journals.  The VERITAS collaboration  has published 99 refereed journal articles and has produced 56 PhD  theses. Forty-three of these articles appeared, and twenty-three of  these theses were completed, during the award period.  This publication  rate compares favorably to other VHE experiments.  While the science  program addressed a number of important topics in astrophysics, one  particular science highlight involves the unexpected detection of VHE  gamma-rays from a galaxy located more than halfway across the universe.   This unique detection was the first detection of large-scale VHE  emission from an extragalactic source, and enabled strong single-source  constraints for cosmology.  Significant science remains to be completed  by VERITAS, including our legacy observing program.  Observing time at  VERITAS remains oversubscribed and approximately 50 VERITAS journal  articles are in preparation, with five near submission. The training  mission of VERITAS also remains strong as 40% of the collaboration  members are students.     During the award period, VERITAS operations  also could only be described as highly successful.  External reviews  held during the award period commented on "impressive levels of  operational efficiency and expanded uptime of the telescopes" and noted  "the project is extremely well managed".  Another report noted VERITAS  "is a mature experiment with a well-developed maintenance and operation  plan that has constantly delivered a stream of quality science data with  high efficiency".  Specifically, an average of 1310 h of data were  taken over the four seasons covered by this award, exceeding the project  requirements of more than 900 h per year.  In addition, all performance  metrics for these data were met and often exceeded and no event  rendered any significant quantity of data unusable.  Significant  cost-cutting measures were also developed and tested, enabling future  VERITAS operations to proceed with more than 20% reduced budget.          Throughout this award the VERITAS collaboration continued its  strong commitment to enabling public understanding of science as an  outcome of its research.  At the VERITAS site itself, the F.L. Whipple  Observatory (FLWO) Visitor?s Center continued to coordinate many ongoing  activities to promote VERITAS science to the public and the wider  community.  Here displays, exhibits and videos presented astronomy and  astrophysics relevant to VERITAS.  VERITAS Project Office (VPO)  scientists also delivered public lectures and participated in the  extensive community outreach program at FLWO.  This included providing  formal &amp; informal tours of the VERITAS site for journalists,  authors, astronomy clubs, and youth groups.  VPO scientists also hosted  star parties, participated in science fairs, and visited school  classrooms.  A public website (http://veritas.sao.arizona.edu) operated  by the VPO provided a description of the VERITAS project and related  science. All refereed VERITAS publications and PhD theses are also  linked to this page, along with a brief description of each result. A  VERITAS Facebook page and Twitter feed are also active, and a YouTube  channel contains video content from VERITAS scientists.  Over the course  of the award we also enabled may unique outreach experiences; one of  our more recent endeavors was the VERITAS Muon Hunter partnership with  the Zooniverse project.  Here crowd-sourcing was used to test methods  for the classification of VERITAS background (muon) images.  Over 5000  volunteers participated in a trial, and over 2 million images were  classified.     The VERITAS collaboration is grateful for the support  of the U.S. National Science Foundation which makes its research  possible.       Last Modified: 01/10/2018       Submitted by: Wystan R Benbow]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
