<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: CI-ADDO-NEW: Ocean-TUNE: A Community Ocean Testbed for Underwater Wireless Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>690000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>690000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tnandago@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924550</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>There is growing global importance of ocean exploration and monitoring as the oceans play a major role in climate regulation, nutrient production, resource retrieval and transportation, etc. Building and deploying a real-time underwater networked sensing infrastructure is thus needed for desired levels of monitoring and data collection. Despite a wave of research efforts in the area of underwater wireless networks, the lack of a community testbed has so far hampered further advances, as there is no common platform to evaluate and compare various communication and networking algorithms and protocols. Furthermore very few studies can afford to consider real system features due to the high cost of system deployment and maintenance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project involves the design and deployment of an open underwater testbed suite, accessible to the public at four sites in Connecticut, California, Texas, and Washington States. The testbed will include flexible choices of surface nodes, bottom nodes, and mobile nodes with reconfigurable modems. It will enable the vision of remote controlled and continuous networked node deployments running tests of communication, networking, sensing, and data streaming. In addition, the testbed will enable oceanographers to study scientific research questions, while using the testbed as a prototype for larger real-time monitoring deployments elsewhere. The testbed will also directly impact undergraduate research and student diversity by involving undergraduate students through REU programs, impacting curriculum development by enabling field courses, and engaging K-12 students and teachers, particularly in underserved communities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1205725</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sumit</FirstName>
<LastName>Roy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sumit Roy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>roy@ee.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2062215261</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000448952</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Payman</FirstName>
<LastName>Arabshahi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Payman Arabshahi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>paymana@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2062216990</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000510540</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981952500</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Electrical Engr Box 352500]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>CCRI-CISE Cmnty Rsrch Infrstrc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>COMPUTING RES INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~690000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The intended goal of this CRI award was to demonstrate the feasibility of a remotely accessible infrastructure for underwater networking experiments, using the OFDM based acoustic modems supplied by vendor AquaSeNT. Four teams - UW, UCLA, TAMU and UCONN - were to deploy individual testbeds at their respective locations and operationalize them, while sharing experiences &nbsp;and knowhow for mutual facilitation during this process. Besides the deployment, each team owned individual research goals, notably -</p> <p>1. Characterization of local underwater propagation channels, building a new link and MAC (cross-layer) design that is fully simulation tested; and</p> <p>2. Transitioning the above design onto the AquaSeNT hardware via the network stack implemented in the software development enviroment SeaLinX.&nbsp;</p> <p>The UW effort successfully implemented 1, and was able to only partially succeed in 2. While challenges to persistent deployment of an underwater infrastructure remain unresolved (i.e. the maximum duration we could operate our network was a working day) due to lack of access issues (in effect, deployments are limited to &nbsp;bodies of water that are 'owned' by university or limited to agreements with 3rd parties who agree to provide access for prolonged deployment- which is rare) , we we were able to demonstrate remote experimental operation over this period, using the configuration shown in the attached figure. Our inability to transition a fully adaptive link layer via SeaLinX points to the inherent constraints imposed by the vendor design (as detailed further in our report).&nbsp;</p> <p>In summary, the over-arching conclusions from this effort are - while OFDM modems do represent a notable technical advance for underwater link layer, achieving their potential in any real deployment will require more 'software defined' features in future versions, akin to their terrestrial counterpart; otherwise a successful community underwater infrastructure will be limited by scope of access and (lack of) flexibility at operation time.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/16/2016<br>      Modified by: Sumit&nbsp;Roy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1205725/1205725_10179696_1470961686402_aquasent--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1205725/1205725_10179696_1470961686402_aquasent--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Underwater Modems"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1205725/1205725_10179696_1470961686402_aquasent--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Underwater Modems"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Acoustic OFDM Modem from AquaSenT</div> <div class="imageCredit">Source</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sumit&nbsp;Roy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Underwater Modems</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1205725/1205725_10179696_1470961754915_RemoteDeployment--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1205725/1205725_10179696_1470961754915_RemoteDeployment--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Remote Operation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1205725/1205725_10179696_1470961754915_RemoteDeployment--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Remote Operation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Remote Experiment Configuration using AquaSenT</div> <div class="imageCredit">UW</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sumit&nbsp;Roy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Remote Operation</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The intended goal of this CRI award was to demonstrate the feasibility of a remotely accessible infrastructure for underwater networking experiments, using the OFDM based acoustic modems supplied by vendor AquaSeNT. Four teams - UW, UCLA, TAMU and UCONN - were to deploy individual testbeds at their respective locations and operationalize them, while sharing experiences  and knowhow for mutual facilitation during this process. Besides the deployment, each team owned individual research goals, notably -  1. Characterization of local underwater propagation channels, building a new link and MAC (cross-layer) design that is fully simulation tested; and  2. Transitioning the above design onto the AquaSeNT hardware via the network stack implemented in the software development enviroment SeaLinX.   The UW effort successfully implemented 1, and was able to only partially succeed in 2. While challenges to persistent deployment of an underwater infrastructure remain unresolved (i.e. the maximum duration we could operate our network was a working day) due to lack of access issues (in effect, deployments are limited to  bodies of water that are 'owned' by university or limited to agreements with 3rd parties who agree to provide access for prolonged deployment- which is rare) , we we were able to demonstrate remote experimental operation over this period, using the configuration shown in the attached figure. Our inability to transition a fully adaptive link layer via SeaLinX points to the inherent constraints imposed by the vendor design (as detailed further in our report).   In summary, the over-arching conclusions from this effort are - while OFDM modems do represent a notable technical advance for underwater link layer, achieving their potential in any real deployment will require more 'software defined' features in future versions, akin to their terrestrial counterpart; otherwise a successful community underwater infrastructure will be limited by scope of access and (lack of) flexibility at operation time.        Last Modified: 08/16/2016       Submitted by: Sumit Roy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
