<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Neutrino Physics at MIT</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1310840.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1477050</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan Whitmore</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928908</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Recent studies involving electron-flavor neutrinos have raised many interesting questions. For example, is there electron-neutrino appearance at short baseline? What is the magnitude of the missing mixing matrix parameter, associated with the electron-flavor? And is there CP violation in the light neutrino sector, which is explored through electron-neutrino appearance? These questions are identified as top priority in advancing knowledge within the neutrino physics field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides support for students and postdocs on a series of neutrino experiments chosen to be phased in time: MiniBooNE, SciBooNE, Double Chooz, MicroBooNE and DAEDALUS. These experiments are selected to have intellectual coherence and to allow the students and postdocs in the group to experience all stages of experimental work within their careers at MIT. MIT has a central role in the MiniBooNE oscillation analysis and in developing associated phenomenological models involving sterile neutrinos. The MiniBooNE results have excited interest in next generation short-baseline experiments, including the MicroBooNE experiment that will address the MiniBooNE event excesses with state-of-the-art liquid argon technology. MIT is responsible for delivering the light collection system on MicroBooNE and for R&amp;D on the first lightguide-based detection system for future large LAr detectors. The group plays a leading role in the US-based analysis of the last neutrino mixing angle from the Double Chooz data. MIT has specialized in monitoring on Double Chooz and this award provides support for a novel directional neutron monitor, DCTPC, which will be constructed in this grant period. DAEDALUS, with its multiple beams and single detector, is an example of how the MIT group develops transformative ideas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The PI is dedicated to expanding participation of women and minorities in STEM, as well as improving STEM education and teacher development. The group is involved in numerous projects to increase public scientific literacy and gives many public talks, communicating the excitement of neutrino physics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1205175</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Conrad</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet M Conrad</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>conrad@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173246281</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000273390</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 Massachusetts Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>HEP-High Energy Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1643</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Cosmic P</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7621</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS-BROADEN PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY PARTICLE ACCEL USER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1515</Code>
<Text>MINORITY GRADUATE EDUC ACTIVIT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~501220</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~493680</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~482150</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Conrad Group at MIT, supported by grant NSF-PHY-1205175, pursues  research in neutrino physics.&nbsp; Our main focus is on Beyond Standard  Model searches, especially as evidenced by oscillations involving  electron neutrinos.&nbsp; We participate in both direct searches and in  development and measurements which support those searches.</p> <p>Our activities have been divided among several experiments and specialized  measurements.&nbsp;&nbsp; The experiments are:&nbsp; MiniBooNE (completed), Double  Chooz (completed participation), IceCube (Ongoing),&nbsp; MicroBooNE (will run in fall, 2015) and IsoDAR (future) and  DAEdALUS-CP (future).&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The latter two are phases of the same  overarching DAEdALUS program.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The top priority of each experiment  falls into one of two categories: 1) understanding the evolving  three-neutrino model, so that we can do precision tests in the future  and 2) searching for new physics beyond the evolving three-neutrino  model. However,&nbsp; it should be recognized that each experiment explores  physics in both categories.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We have also been involved in several  specialized measurements.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The DCTPC studies (complete), which are  fully funded by NSF-PHY-1205175, provide fast neutron measurements for&nbsp;  Double Chooz, MicroBooNE, and &nbsp;for general use in neutrino and dark  matter simulations.&nbsp; &nbsp;The Best studies (complete)&nbsp; are cyclotron  central region tests associated with the DAEdALUS program, with  equipment and travel funded through the MIT EAGER award,  NSF-PHY-1148134, and MIT scientists funded through NSF-PHY-1205175.&nbsp;&nbsp; In  all cases, our contributions to the science have included detector  development and construction, data analysis, and phenomenology.</p> <p>The outcomes of our work are reported in 35 papers to which we provided unique and essential contributions.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; One of these papers now has more than 500 citations.&nbsp;&nbsp; We also contributed to 9 other experimental papers, 3 summaries, and many whitepapers and proposals.&nbsp; Very importantly, we have contributed to increasing the STEM workforce by graduating 4 Ph.D.'s during the time period of this grant.</p> <p>Our work has many creative and transformational aspects:</p> <ul> <li>Award-winning (IUPAP Young Scientist Prize and Primakoff Award) contributions to Lorentz violation studies have set limits at the Planck scale using MiniBooNE and Double Chooz data.</li> <li>Leadership in sterile neutrino studies and fits. The importance of the MIT Group's global fits was highlighted at Neutrino 2014 and our first paper on published in 2002, now has 250 citations.&nbsp;&nbsp; Our 2012 paper supported by this grant now has 82 citations. Our final analysis of the MiniBooNE antineutrino data now has more than 200 citations.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</li> <li>Advancement of LArTPCs through MicroBooNE. We have substantially advanced light collection and&nbsp; high voltage (HV) surge protection&nbsp; systems for LArTPCs during our work on MicroBooNE.&nbsp; Our contributions across the entire MicroBooNE detector were recognized our postdoc was chosen as&nbsp; Co-commissioning-czar of MicroBooNE,&nbsp;&nbsp;</li> <li>Invention of&nbsp; light collection systems for LArTPCs. Invented by our group in 2011 \cite{inventguides},&nbsp; flat-panel lightguides are now the baseline&nbsp; design for&nbsp; the SBND and DUNE Experiments.</li> <li>Development of novel cyclotron-driven sources for isotope an pion/muon decay-at-rest neutrino fluxes. Many publications have arisen from our work in this area and we plan to continue this activity in the next three years.&nbsp; We will focus primarily&nbsp; on IsoDAR, which is Phase II of DAEdALUS.&nbsp; This program is widely regarded as innovative. Our work on DAE$\delta$ALUS has been highlighted in...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Conrad Group at MIT, supported by grant NSF-PHY-1205175, pursues  research in neutrino physics.  Our main focus is on Beyond Standard  Model searches, especially as evidenced by oscillations involving  electron neutrinos.  We participate in both direct searches and in  development and measurements which support those searches.  Our activities have been divided among several experiments and specialized  measurements.   The experiments are:  MiniBooNE (completed), Double  Chooz (completed participation), IceCube (Ongoing),  MicroBooNE (will run in fall, 2015) and IsoDAR (future) and  DAEdALUS-CP (future).       The latter two are phases of the same  overarching DAEdALUS program.     The top priority of each experiment  falls into one of two categories: 1) understanding the evolving  three-neutrino model, so that we can do precision tests in the future  and 2) searching for new physics beyond the evolving three-neutrino  model. However,  it should be recognized that each experiment explores  physics in both categories.     We have also been involved in several  specialized measurements.    The DCTPC studies (complete), which are  fully funded by NSF-PHY-1205175, provide fast neutron measurements for   Double Chooz, MicroBooNE, and  for general use in neutrino and dark  matter simulations.   The Best studies (complete)  are cyclotron  central region tests associated with the DAEdALUS program, with  equipment and travel funded through the MIT EAGER award,  NSF-PHY-1148134, and MIT scientists funded through NSF-PHY-1205175.   In  all cases, our contributions to the science have included detector  development and construction, data analysis, and phenomenology.  The outcomes of our work are reported in 35 papers to which we provided unique and essential contributions.     One of these papers now has more than 500 citations.   We also contributed to 9 other experimental papers, 3 summaries, and many whitepapers and proposals.  Very importantly, we have contributed to increasing the STEM workforce by graduating 4 Ph.D.'s during the time period of this grant.  Our work has many creative and transformational aspects:  Award-winning (IUPAP Young Scientist Prize and Primakoff Award) contributions to Lorentz violation studies have set limits at the Planck scale using MiniBooNE and Double Chooz data. Leadership in sterile neutrino studies and fits. The importance of the MIT Group's global fits was highlighted at Neutrino 2014 and our first paper on published in 2002, now has 250 citations.   Our 2012 paper supported by this grant now has 82 citations. Our final analysis of the MiniBooNE antineutrino data now has more than 200 citations.      Advancement of LArTPCs through MicroBooNE. We have substantially advanced light collection and  high voltage (HV) surge protection  systems for LArTPCs during our work on MicroBooNE.  Our contributions across the entire MicroBooNE detector were recognized our postdoc was chosen as  Co-commissioning-czar of MicroBooNE,   Invention of  light collection systems for LArTPCs. Invented by our group in 2011 \cite{inventguides},  flat-panel lightguides are now the baseline  design for  the SBND and DUNE Experiments. Development of novel cyclotron-driven sources for isotope an pion/muon decay-at-rest neutrino fluxes. Many publications have arisen from our work in this area and we plan to continue this activity in the next three years.  We will focus primarily  on IsoDAR, which is Phase II of DAEdALUS.  This program is widely regarded as innovative. Our work on DAE$\delta$ALUS has been highlighted in the journal Nature. One IsoDAR paper was chosen as a Physical Review Letter Highlight and another was chosen as a Physical Review D Kaleidoscope Feature.   Our work has also had important broader impacts.  Our activities address areas identified by the America Competes Act.    These are:   1) Development of a globally competitive STEM workforce---six papers from the past three years  have undergraduate authors. 2)...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
