<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PIMS Summer School in Probability 2012</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>22685.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>22685</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 2012 Pacific Institute for the Mathematical Sciences Summer School in Probability, to be held at the University of British Columbia from June 4-29, 2012,  will be an opportunity for a few top researchers in the field to interact directly with the advanced graduate students and recent graduates. The participants will learn the current techniques in the most significant areas of probability theory, including growth models and exclusion process, last passage percolation, random maps and their scaling limits. It is expected that the participants will engage in active research on some topics covered by the main courses and related areas. PIMS Summer School 2012 will be a great opportunity for graduate students and junior researchers to learn some of the most significant modern probability theory from the top experts in the field. The junior participants are often current and future academic faculty, able to spread the knowledge of the modern techniques further in the research community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/17/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1206250</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Krzysztof</FirstName>
<LastName>Burdzy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Krzysztof Burdzy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>burdzy@math.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065434297</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000445339</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/17/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhen-Qing</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhen-Qing Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zqchen@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065431907</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000397478</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/17/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~22685</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 2012 PIMS Summer School in Probability was held at the University of British Columbia, Canada, in June 2012. This&nbsp; major training event attracted&nbsp; 88 registered participants from around the world. Among the participants, 10 were women and 22 came from US universities.<br /><br />This Summer School was organized by Omer Angel, Ed Perkins, and Gordon Slade. It was supported financially by Pacific Institute for Mathematical Sciences (PIMS) and Mprime as well as the US National Science Foundation and the UBC Department of Mathematics. Past PIMS Summer Schools in Probability had been held at UBC in 2004, 2005, 2008, 2009 (the latter joint with the Centre de Recherches Mathematiques), and at the University of Washington in 2010.<br /><br />PIMS Summer Schools have a unique format, distinguishing them from other graduate summer schools. The core of the PIMS Summer School consisted of two full-length courses, given by Omer Angel (UBC) and Gr\'egory Miermont (CNRS-PIMS researcher), each comprising 24 hours of lectures. This was supplemented by&nbsp; 30 lectures given by Summer School participants themselves; for many of them, it was their first lecture at an international conference. The two main courses were official UBC graduate courses and were taken for academic credit by UBC graduate students. In addition, five keynote lectures were given by top international researchers: Alexander Holroyd (Microsoft), Rick Kenyon (Brown), Yuval Peres (Microsoft), Gordon Slade (UBC), and B\'alint Vir\'ag (Toronto).<br /><br />The conference relied heavily on the Summer School's Scientific Panel, which consisted of Siva Athreya (Bangalore), Mar\'ia Emilia Caballero (Mexico City), Dayue Chen (Beijing), Zhen-Qing Chen (Seattle), Takashi Kumagai (Kyoto), Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Le Gall (Orsay), Neal Madras (Toronto), and&nbsp;&nbsp; Vladas Sidoravicius (Rio de Janeiro). Panel members encouraged participation of junior scientists from their part of the world and advised the local organizers on the participant funding.&nbsp; Their efforts were successful - the participants included students from India, China, Japan, Israel, Poland, Germany, France, United Kingdom, the Netherlands, Brazil, Mexico, and, of course, from the United States and Canada. The caliber of the attending students was very impressive.<br />&nbsp;<br />Omer Angel's course "Interacting Particle Systems" focused on the many incarnations of totally asymmetric exclusion process, and included a presentation of his work with Holroyd, Romik and Virag on random sorting networks.&nbsp; This is a spectacular example of order coming from complete randomness and although fascinating results have been proved, they remain far away from capturing what the simulations are showing. The resulting conjectures are amazing. The buzz in the room when these simulations were playing and the conjectures were being made was clearly audible. At the breaks Professor Angel was dealing with crowds of students wanting more.<br /><br />Gr\'egory Miermont's course on "Random Maps" focused on a major recent result on scaling limits of random maps that was announced in 2011 and obtained independently by different methods by Miermont and Le Gall.&nbsp; The result was the culmination of over 10 years of work by many mathematicians, in a marvellous blend of combinatorics, geometry, and probability.<br /><br />The summer school was very successful and stimulating.&nbsp; Participants, both graduate students and recent Ph.D.'s, benefited greatly from the main courses, keynote lectures, participants' presentations as well as from the direct access to senior researchers.&nbsp; The NSF PIMS Summer School grant supported 14 graduate students from the US, including two women.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/27/2013<br>      Modified by: Krzysztof&nbsp;Burdzy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 2012 PIMS Summer School in Probability was held at the University of British Columbia, Canada, in June 2012. This  major training event attracted  88 registered participants from around the world. Among the participants, 10 were women and 22 came from US universities.  This Summer School was organized by Omer Angel, Ed Perkins, and Gordon Slade. It was supported financially by Pacific Institute for Mathematical Sciences (PIMS) and Mprime as well as the US National Science Foundation and the UBC Department of Mathematics. Past PIMS Summer Schools in Probability had been held at UBC in 2004, 2005, 2008, 2009 (the latter joint with the Centre de Recherches Mathematiques), and at the University of Washington in 2010.  PIMS Summer Schools have a unique format, distinguishing them from other graduate summer schools. The core of the PIMS Summer School consisted of two full-length courses, given by Omer Angel (UBC) and Gr\'egory Miermont (CNRS-PIMS researcher), each comprising 24 hours of lectures. This was supplemented by  30 lectures given by Summer School participants themselves; for many of them, it was their first lecture at an international conference. The two main courses were official UBC graduate courses and were taken for academic credit by UBC graduate students. In addition, five keynote lectures were given by top international researchers: Alexander Holroyd (Microsoft), Rick Kenyon (Brown), Yuval Peres (Microsoft), Gordon Slade (UBC), and B\'alint Vir\'ag (Toronto).  The conference relied heavily on the Summer School's Scientific Panel, which consisted of Siva Athreya (Bangalore), Mar\'ia Emilia Caballero (Mexico City), Dayue Chen (Beijing), Zhen-Qing Chen (Seattle), Takashi Kumagai (Kyoto), Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Le Gall (Orsay), Neal Madras (Toronto), and   Vladas Sidoravicius (Rio de Janeiro). Panel members encouraged participation of junior scientists from their part of the world and advised the local organizers on the participant funding.  Their efforts were successful - the participants included students from India, China, Japan, Israel, Poland, Germany, France, United Kingdom, the Netherlands, Brazil, Mexico, and, of course, from the United States and Canada. The caliber of the attending students was very impressive.   Omer Angel's course "Interacting Particle Systems" focused on the many incarnations of totally asymmetric exclusion process, and included a presentation of his work with Holroyd, Romik and Virag on random sorting networks.  This is a spectacular example of order coming from complete randomness and although fascinating results have been proved, they remain far away from capturing what the simulations are showing. The resulting conjectures are amazing. The buzz in the room when these simulations were playing and the conjectures were being made was clearly audible. At the breaks Professor Angel was dealing with crowds of students wanting more.  Gr\'egory Miermont's course on "Random Maps" focused on a major recent result on scaling limits of random maps that was announced in 2011 and obtained independently by different methods by Miermont and Le Gall.  The result was the culmination of over 10 years of work by many mathematicians, in a marvellous blend of combinatorics, geometry, and probability.  The summer school was very successful and stimulating.  Participants, both graduate students and recent Ph.D.'s, benefited greatly from the main courses, keynote lectures, participants' presentations as well as from the direct access to senior researchers.  The NSF PIMS Summer School grant supported 14 graduate students from the US, including two women.       Last Modified: 04/27/2013       Submitted by: Krzysztof Burdzy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
