<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Polarized Electron Physics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>610000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>635000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ann Orel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project involves the study of collisions between polarized electrons (having an average spin that points preferentially in one direction) and chiral, or "handed" molecules as well as zinc atoms.  The former experiments address physics questions about the dynamics of electron-molecule scattering, particularly with regard to the role played by electron spin in collisions with molecules that have a handed stereochemical structure.  They will also provide important clues about the origins of biological homochirality -- the fact that all naturally-occurring DNA spirals in the same direction.  The zinc experiments are being done to check the results of an experiment done recently by an Australian group in which states of zinc excited by polarized electrons exhibited linear polarization that was tilted relative to the incident beam direction in the collision.  This result is forbidden by all known theories of atomic collisions; if the Australian result is reproduced, much of our basic theoretical knowledge of how electrons collide with atoms and molecules will be shown to be in error.  Improved sources and analyzers of polarized electrons are being developed.  We are testing increasingly compact designs of electron spin detectors.  We also are studying multiphoton ionization of bulk materials such as the semiconductor GaAs to see if polarized electrons can be photoemitted from such material even when the surface has not been prepared to give it a negative electron affinity -- the normal method used to produce efficient photoemitters. This latter work holds the promise of providing new analytical tools for biological and materials research, and for industry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These experiments will have an impact beyond the immediate community of atomic, molecular, and optical science. In addition to its broader scientific implications, this work will have a significant educational component. Undergraduates working on these projects will have their first experience in scientific research. In an effort to expand the talent pool for atomic, molecular, and optical physics, women and underrepresented minorities will be especially recruited for these positions. The experiments with chiral molecules and their connection to astrobiological questions make an excellent topic for talks that will be given regularly to high school and civic groups, and that serve to illustrate the beauty of basic physics to a large lay audience.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1206067</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Gay</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy J Gay</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tgay1@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4024722773</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000272237</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2200 Vine St]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555456995</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068662618</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska-Lincoln]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>685880430</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[312 N 14th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1290</Code>
<Text>OPTICAL PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1291</Code>
<Text>ATOMIC &amp; MOLECULAR DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1291</Code>
<Text>ATOMIC &amp; MOLECULAR DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9232</Code>
<Text>RES OPPOR AWARDS(ROA) (SUPPLEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~210000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Like bolts and nuts, electrons and some molecules have the property of &ldquo;handedness.&rdquo; Handed molecules (like DNA) have a helical structure. In a beam of electrons moving &ldquo;forward,&rdquo; right- and left-handed electrons have their spins pointing forward or backward, respectively.&nbsp; This award supported experiments that showed, in analogy with the fact that a left-handed bolt cannot be screwed into a right-handed nut (and vice versa), that handed electrons interact differently with right-handed molecules than they do with left-handed ones of the same chemical compound.&nbsp; This work focused on a chemical reaction in which handed electrons dissociated right- or left-handed molecules of bromocamphor (Images 2 and 3).&nbsp; For a given handedness of the electron beam, the bromocamphor breakup rate varied when the molecular handedness was switched from left to right.&nbsp; The goal of this experiment was twofold.&nbsp; First, there is no current theory that can explain why this handedness preference occurs. By studying how the sensitivity to handedness in the breakup collisions depended on, e.g., the energy of the incident electrons, the experiment provided guidance to theorists about what mechanisms might be causing this effect. Second, it provided a connection between handedness specificity in chemical reactions and the fact that all living DNA is right-handed.&nbsp; It has been suggested that the reason for this is that cosmic ray electrons, which are left-handed, might have preferentially destroyed the left-handed precursors of DNA on the primordial earth (Image 1).&nbsp; While the bromocamphor experiment does not prove that this happened, it provided the first demonstration that such a preferential destruction of one handedness of a biological molecule is possible.</p> <p>This award also supported the development of a new kind of source of handed, or &ldquo;polarized&rdquo; electrons.&nbsp; The electron source used in the bromocamphor experiment is very difficult to operate reliably and requires complicated laboratory equipment. It is based on the emission of polarized electrons from a semiconducting material when handed (&ldquo;circularly-polarized&rdquo;) light from a laser strikes its surface.&nbsp; The surface in turn must be extraordinarily clean before this technique will work.&nbsp; The new source is much easier to operate and has relatively modest equipment requirements.&nbsp; It starts with unpolarized electrons, which are easy to produce. They a target full of rubidium vapor.&nbsp; The Rb, having absorbed circularly-polarized light of the right color, contains spin-polarized electrons.&nbsp; As the unpolarized electrons pass through the Rb, they switch places with the target electrons, so the electrons emerging from the target are now spin polarized and ready for experiments.&nbsp; The semiconductor-based source typically requires six months of training for a graduate student to successfully operate it.&nbsp; The Rb source can be made to work the first time by a reasonably astute undergraduate.&nbsp; The new source can now be used to provide polarized electron technology to many laboratories that did not have the wherewithal to use semiconductor sources.</p> <p>The basic physics of electron and photon collisions with simple diatomic molecules was studied.&nbsp; These experiments yielded the first observation of electron-impact-induced rotation of a molecule in a completely-specified quantum mechanical state.&nbsp; It was also discovered that for very low incident electron energies, the shape of the collision-excited electronic charge cloud surrounding the molecule was poorly described by theory.&nbsp; This was particularly surprising, given that the target in question was the simplest molecule there is: H<sub>2</sub>.&nbsp; Experiments supported by this award done at the Advanced Light Source involved the photoionization of N<sub>2<...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Like bolts and nuts, electrons and some molecules have the property of "handedness." Handed molecules (like DNA) have a helical structure. In a beam of electrons moving "forward," right- and left-handed electrons have their spins pointing forward or backward, respectively.  This award supported experiments that showed, in analogy with the fact that a left-handed bolt cannot be screwed into a right-handed nut (and vice versa), that handed electrons interact differently with right-handed molecules than they do with left-handed ones of the same chemical compound.  This work focused on a chemical reaction in which handed electrons dissociated right- or left-handed molecules of bromocamphor (Images 2 and 3).  For a given handedness of the electron beam, the bromocamphor breakup rate varied when the molecular handedness was switched from left to right.  The goal of this experiment was twofold.  First, there is no current theory that can explain why this handedness preference occurs. By studying how the sensitivity to handedness in the breakup collisions depended on, e.g., the energy of the incident electrons, the experiment provided guidance to theorists about what mechanisms might be causing this effect. Second, it provided a connection between handedness specificity in chemical reactions and the fact that all living DNA is right-handed.  It has been suggested that the reason for this is that cosmic ray electrons, which are left-handed, might have preferentially destroyed the left-handed precursors of DNA on the primordial earth (Image 1).  While the bromocamphor experiment does not prove that this happened, it provided the first demonstration that such a preferential destruction of one handedness of a biological molecule is possible.  This award also supported the development of a new kind of source of handed, or "polarized" electrons.  The electron source used in the bromocamphor experiment is very difficult to operate reliably and requires complicated laboratory equipment. It is based on the emission of polarized electrons from a semiconducting material when handed ("circularly-polarized") light from a laser strikes its surface.  The surface in turn must be extraordinarily clean before this technique will work.  The new source is much easier to operate and has relatively modest equipment requirements.  It starts with unpolarized electrons, which are easy to produce. They a target full of rubidium vapor.  The Rb, having absorbed circularly-polarized light of the right color, contains spin-polarized electrons.  As the unpolarized electrons pass through the Rb, they switch places with the target electrons, so the electrons emerging from the target are now spin polarized and ready for experiments.  The semiconductor-based source typically requires six months of training for a graduate student to successfully operate it.  The Rb source can be made to work the first time by a reasonably astute undergraduate.  The new source can now be used to provide polarized electron technology to many laboratories that did not have the wherewithal to use semiconductor sources.  The basic physics of electron and photon collisions with simple diatomic molecules was studied.  These experiments yielded the first observation of electron-impact-induced rotation of a molecule in a completely-specified quantum mechanical state.  It was also discovered that for very low incident electron energies, the shape of the collision-excited electronic charge cloud surrounding the molecule was poorly described by theory.  This was particularly surprising, given that the target in question was the simplest molecule there is: H2.  Experiments supported by this award done at the Advanced Light Source involved the photoionization of N2 molecules with circularly-polarized light.  Diatomic nitrogen is also very simple and is the most common molecule in our atmosphere.  This experiment yielded the first observation of a rotating molecular photofragment, but there was a twi...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
