<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Analytic and geometric approaches to group theory and topology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>158751.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>158751</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI recently proved the Strengthened Hanna Neumann Conjecture (SHNC), and developed a topological and analytic language that allows one to generalize its statement from free groups and graphs to more general groups and complexes. The more general property is called submultiplicativity. This restatement of SHNC shows that there is deep relation between SHNC and the Atiyah Conjecture, which comes from analysis. The PI introduced the deep-fall property, which is useful for each conjecture. This opens a new direction research, which the PI is planning to pursue: finding examples of group actions and matrices that satisfy the deep-fall property. Another part of the proposal is to investigate how PI's earlier constructions of geodesic flow and symmetric join help understanding the geometry of manifolds and more general metric spaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI's research interleaves themes and techniques from three core areas of mathematics: algebra, analysis, and geometry. A group is one of the central notions in algebra. The Hanna Neumann Conjecture, posed by Hanna Neumann in 1956-1957, is a question about a special class of groups called free groups. The PI recently proved this conjecture, and provided a more general point of view that allows asking similar questions in a more general setting, and using the tools from analysis. The PI's program is now to answer similar kinds of questions in this more general setting. Another goal is to investigate the structure of metric spaces, building upon PI's past results in this area. The goal is therefore, broadly, to relate these various branches of mathematics. The PI also plans to present his research results at national and international meetings and to invite research collaborators to the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1206472</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Igor</FirstName>
<LastName>Mineyev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Igor Mineyev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mineyev@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173338984</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000493306</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/24/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618017406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[SUITE A, 1901 SOUTH FIRST ST.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~158751</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>If the product of two numbers is zero, then (at least) one of the two numbers must be zero. This is a well-known fact in the realm of integer numbers, or real numbers, or complex numbers. If one leaves the realm of numbers and asks whether the same statement holds in a more general algebraic structure called group ring, this becomes a famous, extremely difficult, open problem known as the Kaplansky zero divisor conjecture. One of the goals of this project was to address this conjecture and its no-less-famous analytic cousin, the Atiyah problem. My plan was to deal first with a partial case of the Atiyah problem in the case of left-orderable groups, in analogy with my earlier proof of the Hanna Neumann conjecture for free groups. Some types of (co)homology should be helpful for this problem (l^2-homology, bounded cohomology, etc). My initial attempts at attacking the Atyah problem have not been successful. I have learned eventually that the additional assumption of orderability, probably, does not give &nbsp;additional advantage for a proof. After my multiple attempts at approaching this problem, it seems that a more general approach is required, one that might as well work in the full generality of torsion-free groups. I believe that one would need to design a general theory of dimension for arbitrary G-modules, one that would generalize the Murray-von Neumann dimension for Hilbert modules. Stated in this way, this is a vast project, which, if and when it works, would lead to solutions of several major problems in algebra. So my result is negative, but it is a result nevertheless, and it led me far beyond the original scope of the original proposal. I am working on a related project about bounded cohomology, originally defined by B.E.Johnson. My goal is to define bounded cohomology in a way that would use standard tools of homological algebra, and would not use measure theory at all. This would allow, in particular, dealing with groups and spaces that are not necessarily locally compact. The second step will be to define amenability of groups and group actions in purely homological terms, generalizing B.E.Johnson's theorem. Besides defining a notion of dimension (as described above), another distant outcome of this activity could be some result concerning amenability/nonamenability of Thompson's group, which is another notoriously difficult question.</p> <p><br />I developed and taught several graduate courses at UIUC in which the material related to this proposal was incorporated. I also run an informal and regular IGOR'S group (= The Illinois Group on Groups, Geometry, and Other Related Subjects, faculty.math.illinois.edu/~mineyev/math/IGORS/ ) with students at UIUC, in which this material has been discussed. With the support of this grant, I gave numerous lectures at mathematical conferences and seminars around the world, publicizing the set of problems and possible approaches to them. (See faculty.math.illinois.edu/~mineyev/math/talks.html for the full list of talks.)</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/18/2017<br>      Modified by: Igor&nbsp;Mineyev</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ If the product of two numbers is zero, then (at least) one of the two numbers must be zero. This is a well-known fact in the realm of integer numbers, or real numbers, or complex numbers. If one leaves the realm of numbers and asks whether the same statement holds in a more general algebraic structure called group ring, this becomes a famous, extremely difficult, open problem known as the Kaplansky zero divisor conjecture. One of the goals of this project was to address this conjecture and its no-less-famous analytic cousin, the Atiyah problem. My plan was to deal first with a partial case of the Atiyah problem in the case of left-orderable groups, in analogy with my earlier proof of the Hanna Neumann conjecture for free groups. Some types of (co)homology should be helpful for this problem (l^2-homology, bounded cohomology, etc). My initial attempts at attacking the Atyah problem have not been successful. I have learned eventually that the additional assumption of orderability, probably, does not give  additional advantage for a proof. After my multiple attempts at approaching this problem, it seems that a more general approach is required, one that might as well work in the full generality of torsion-free groups. I believe that one would need to design a general theory of dimension for arbitrary G-modules, one that would generalize the Murray-von Neumann dimension for Hilbert modules. Stated in this way, this is a vast project, which, if and when it works, would lead to solutions of several major problems in algebra. So my result is negative, but it is a result nevertheless, and it led me far beyond the original scope of the original proposal. I am working on a related project about bounded cohomology, originally defined by B.E.Johnson. My goal is to define bounded cohomology in a way that would use standard tools of homological algebra, and would not use measure theory at all. This would allow, in particular, dealing with groups and spaces that are not necessarily locally compact. The second step will be to define amenability of groups and group actions in purely homological terms, generalizing B.E.Johnson's theorem. Besides defining a notion of dimension (as described above), another distant outcome of this activity could be some result concerning amenability/nonamenability of Thompson's group, which is another notoriously difficult question.   I developed and taught several graduate courses at UIUC in which the material related to this proposal was incorporated. I also run an informal and regular IGOR'S group (= The Illinois Group on Groups, Geometry, and Other Related Subjects, faculty.math.illinois.edu/~mineyev/math/IGORS/ ) with students at UIUC, in which this material has been discussed. With the support of this grant, I gave numerous lectures at mathematical conferences and seminars around the world, publicizing the set of problems and possible approaches to them. (See faculty.math.illinois.edu/~mineyev/math/talks.html for the full list of talks.)       Last Modified: 10/18/2017       Submitted by: Igor Mineyev]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
