<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Engineering Interface Magnetism via Defect Control in Complex Oxide Heterostructures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdurakie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924892</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>****Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;Complex oxide materials have proven to be an extraordinary platform for discovery of new and useful physical phenomena. Assembling these materials into artificial heterostructures provides a plethora of further opportunities, both for discovery of new science, and for applications in areas such as ferroelectric RAM, fuel cells, and spintronics. However, in order to fully exploit these materials some serious open issues must be resolved, particularly with respect to interfacial strain and defects. The goal of this project is to achieve exactly this, using cobalt oxides as model systems to understand the interplay between strain state, oxygen vacancy formation and ordering, and interface magnetism/electronic transport. Specific opportunities include the use of strain-control over oxygen defects to precisely engineer interfacial magnetic and electronic properties, and the possibility of synthesizing defect-free materials to probe new physics recently predicted by theory. The research will have impact well beyond the immediate disciplines in which it is performed, due to its relevance to emerging technologies, the exceptional educational opportunities provided to students, and inclusion of under-represented groups. Outreach to the public will also be achieved via development of an interactive presentation for the Properties of Matter module in the Minneapolis Public School System, impacting hundreds of 8th grade students.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****Non-Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;Complex oxides, formed by bonding atoms of multiple metallic elements with oxygen, are a set of materials that display extraordinary diversity in physical and chemical properties, yielding some of the most important discoveries in physics. The recently recognized ability to incorporate these materials into artificial structures where multiple oxides are laminated together, with atomic-scale precision, provides a means to fully exploit their properties in a wide variety of applications. These include zero boot-up time memory, clean-burning fuel cells, and low power consumption high-speed electronics. However, critical unsolved issues hinder progress in this area, particularly the formation of unwanted defects associated with missing oxygen atoms. In this project a specific set of complex oxide materials are being used to understand what factors control the formation and arrangement of these defects, the influence they have on properties, and the means by which we can control them. The ultimate goal is to be able to precisely control electronic and magnetic behavior at oxide interfaces in order to fully exploit their unique properties in a wide variety of new devices. The research will have broad impact due to its relevance to emerging technologies, the exceptional educational opportunities provided to students, and inclusion of under-represented groups. Outreach to the public will also be achieved via development of an interactive presentation for the Properties of Matter module in the Minneapolis Public School System, impacting hundreds of 8th grade students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1206278</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Leighton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher Leighton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>leighton@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126254018</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486047</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554550132</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[421 Washington Ave SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Complex oxides, formed by bonding atoms of multiple metallic elements with oxygen, are a set of materials that display extraordinary physical and chemical properties, yielding some of the most important discoveries in physics. The recently recognized ability to incorporate these materials into artificial structures where multiple oxides are laminated together, with atomic-scale precision (known as heterostructures), has provided a means to fully exploit their properties in a wide variety of applications. These potentially include zero boot-up time memory, clean-burning fuel cells, and low power consumption high-speed electronics.</p> <p>One issue with such materials, however, which has often been considered a negative aspect, is their tendency to form defects called oxygen vacancies, essentially missing oxygen atoms. The essential goal of this NSF project was to understand how to control the formation and location of these defects, the ultimate goal being to harness them for useful physical function,<em> i.e.</em> to put the defects to work to generate interesting and useful physical properties. This has primarily been done with two types of oxide materials, based on cobalt and titanium, respectively.&nbsp;</p> <p>In the cobalt oxides, specifically a <em>cobaltite</em> material with chemical formula LaSrCoO<sub>3</sub>, the primary goal was to understand and control a phenomenon called oxygen vacancy ordering. In essence, in this material the missing oxygen atoms can be coaxed into lining up into stripes on an atomic scale, rather than forming in random locations. This is done by creating thin films of the material on top of crystals with slightly different atomic spacings. The resulting strain in the film is accommodated by the ordering of the oxygen defects. One of the main results of this work was to show that by changing the strain and the crystal orientation the oxygen vacancy stripes can be manipulated, almost at will, to run in different directions, and with different total concentrations of vacancies. Critically this allows, in turn, for control of the physical behavior of the material, such as the electronic properties and magnetism. Situations can then be realized where the magnetic and metallic properties of the LaSrCoO<sub>3</sub> can be retained to the ultra-thin limit, just a few atoms thick, where the fundamental physics of the materials is poorly understood. Although directed at these <em>physical</em> properties the work will also have impact in the area of <em>chemical</em> properties, as these materials are of use in devices such as solid oxide fuel cells, where oxygen must be transport (<em>via</em> the missing oxygen positions) through the crystals. &nbsp; &nbsp;<sub> </sub></p> <p>In the titanium oxides, specifically strontium titanate (SrTiO<sub>3</sub>), a non-magnetic semiconductor, the work has focused on: (a) detailed and careful studies of the preparation of the material, (b) understanding the difficulties associated with adding controlled amounts of impurities to control electronic properties ("doping"), and, (c) using controlled addition of oxygen vacancies to create new properties. The latter led to the most arresting result, as it was discovered that illuminating strontium titanate with a particular type of light (called <em>circularly polarized light</em>) can induce magnetism in this otherwise non-magnetic material. Most surprisingly, at cryogenic temperatures this magnetism was even retained after turning off the illumination, creating the ability to optically write, store, and read information. The effect occurs only in samples deliberately prepared to have oxygen vacancies, implicating some form of defect complex. Additional work is underway to understand the nature of this defect, potentially the key to room temperature operation, with exciting implications for data storage devices.</p> <p>This project has also led to impacts b...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Complex oxides, formed by bonding atoms of multiple metallic elements with oxygen, are a set of materials that display extraordinary physical and chemical properties, yielding some of the most important discoveries in physics. The recently recognized ability to incorporate these materials into artificial structures where multiple oxides are laminated together, with atomic-scale precision (known as heterostructures), has provided a means to fully exploit their properties in a wide variety of applications. These potentially include zero boot-up time memory, clean-burning fuel cells, and low power consumption high-speed electronics.  One issue with such materials, however, which has often been considered a negative aspect, is their tendency to form defects called oxygen vacancies, essentially missing oxygen atoms. The essential goal of this NSF project was to understand how to control the formation and location of these defects, the ultimate goal being to harness them for useful physical function, i.e. to put the defects to work to generate interesting and useful physical properties. This has primarily been done with two types of oxide materials, based on cobalt and titanium, respectively.   In the cobalt oxides, specifically a cobaltite material with chemical formula LaSrCoO3, the primary goal was to understand and control a phenomenon called oxygen vacancy ordering. In essence, in this material the missing oxygen atoms can be coaxed into lining up into stripes on an atomic scale, rather than forming in random locations. This is done by creating thin films of the material on top of crystals with slightly different atomic spacings. The resulting strain in the film is accommodated by the ordering of the oxygen defects. One of the main results of this work was to show that by changing the strain and the crystal orientation the oxygen vacancy stripes can be manipulated, almost at will, to run in different directions, and with different total concentrations of vacancies. Critically this allows, in turn, for control of the physical behavior of the material, such as the electronic properties and magnetism. Situations can then be realized where the magnetic and metallic properties of the LaSrCoO3 can be retained to the ultra-thin limit, just a few atoms thick, where the fundamental physics of the materials is poorly understood. Although directed at these physical properties the work will also have impact in the area of chemical properties, as these materials are of use in devices such as solid oxide fuel cells, where oxygen must be transport (via the missing oxygen positions) through the crystals.       In the titanium oxides, specifically strontium titanate (SrTiO3), a non-magnetic semiconductor, the work has focused on: (a) detailed and careful studies of the preparation of the material, (b) understanding the difficulties associated with adding controlled amounts of impurities to control electronic properties ("doping"), and, (c) using controlled addition of oxygen vacancies to create new properties. The latter led to the most arresting result, as it was discovered that illuminating strontium titanate with a particular type of light (called circularly polarized light) can induce magnetism in this otherwise non-magnetic material. Most surprisingly, at cryogenic temperatures this magnetism was even retained after turning off the illumination, creating the ability to optically write, store, and read information. The effect occurs only in samples deliberately prepared to have oxygen vacancies, implicating some form of defect complex. Additional work is underway to understand the nature of this defect, potentially the key to room temperature operation, with exciting implications for data storage devices.  This project has also led to impacts beyond the scientific disciplines discussed above. As discussed, the relevance to developing technologies is high, as these materials and properties are used in data storage devices, electronic device...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
