<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Topology, Noncommutative Geometry, and Mathematical Physics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>348100.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>348100</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research program combines the areas of topology, noncommutative geometry, and mathematical physics. One focus of this proposal will be on applications of topology and noncommutative geometry to duality in string theory, in order to understand topological constraints on dualities between string theories on different spacetime backgrounds, and also to understand situations where duality leads to a field theory on a noncommutative space. Another major area of investigation will be the use of invariants from noncommutative geometry and index theory for studying the geometry and topology of manifolds and of manifold-like spaces, such as manifolds with singularities. Rosenberg will also use methods of geometric analysis and differential topology to study the topology of the space of Riemannian metrics of positive scalar curvature on a manifold, in both low and high dimensions. Finally, the PI will continue preparation of course materials for the use of mathematical software in sophomore-level science/engineering courses in multivariable calculus and differential equations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The interaction between mathematics (especially geometry) and physics has been a long and fruitful one for both disciplines.  This project will advance that interaction, by relying on physics to suggest interesting topics of study in geometry, and using our understanding of geometry to put restrictions on fundamental physical theories. Broader impacts of this project will include (a) mentoring of graduate and undergraduate students, (b) development of materials and courses for the training of undergraduates, graduate students and postdocs, and (c) dissemination of research in geometry and mathematical physics to a wide audience.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1206159</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosenberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan M Rosenberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmr@math.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014055166</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000228928</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~107807</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~240293</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Intellectual merit</strong></p> <p style="text-align: left;">This project dealt with problems in topology and noncommutative geometry motivated by, and applied to, mathematical physics.&nbsp; Roughly speaking, noncommutative geometry is what remains of ordinary geometry when the measurement of one coordinate affects the values of the other coordinates.&nbsp; This might seem paradoxical, but it is a key aspect of quantum mechanics (the Heisenberg uncertainty principle), and thus noncommutative geometry is needed for proper understanding of quantum systems.&nbsp; One major outcome of the project was a new way to define curvature in noncommutative geometry. &nbsp;The project also studied the underlying mathematical reasons why different-looking physical theories sometimes lead to the same predictions, and how one can use the geometry of space to predict such relationships between physical theories.</p> <p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p style="text-align: left;">Broader impacts of the project included the training of several graduate students, participation by several undergraduates in research seminars, and a successful summer research project by a high school student.&nbsp; In addition, the project facilitated the organizing of several international conferences and the creation of the K-Theory Foundation, a charitable organization which publishes a very high-level nonprofit research journal (of which the PI is one of the managing editors) and sponsors prizes for the best young mathematicians working in K-theory and related fields.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;"><strong><br /></strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/14/2016<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;M&nbsp;Rosenberg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Intellectual merit This project dealt with problems in topology and noncommutative geometry motivated by, and applied to, mathematical physics.  Roughly speaking, noncommutative geometry is what remains of ordinary geometry when the measurement of one coordinate affects the values of the other coordinates.  This might seem paradoxical, but it is a key aspect of quantum mechanics (the Heisenberg uncertainty principle), and thus noncommutative geometry is needed for proper understanding of quantum systems.  One major outcome of the project was a new way to define curvature in noncommutative geometry.  The project also studied the underlying mathematical reasons why different-looking physical theories sometimes lead to the same predictions, and how one can use the geometry of space to predict such relationships between physical theories. Broader Impacts Broader impacts of the project included the training of several graduate students, participation by several undergraduates in research seminars, and a successful summer research project by a high school student.  In addition, the project facilitated the organizing of several international conferences and the creation of the K-Theory Foundation, a charitable organization which publishes a very high-level nonprofit research journal (of which the PI is one of the managing editors) and sponsors prizes for the best young mathematicians working in K-theory and related fields.               Last Modified: 06/14/2016       Submitted by: Jonathan M Rosenberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
