<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Novel Strongly Correlated-Electron Materials with Rock-Salt Related Structures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>389995.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>398440</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Birgit Schwenzer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschwenz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924771</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With support from the Solid-State and Materials Chemistry Program in the NSF Division of Materials Research, the proposed research focuses on transition metal oxides AMO2 (A = alkali metal, M = 3d metal) with CdI2-type layers. AMO2 phases demonstrate a large variety of physical properties, including geometrically frustrated magnetism, spin, charge and orbital ordering, thermoelectricity, and nonconventional superconductivity. In all known AMO2 phases, transition metals are only in the 3+ or 3+/4+ oxidation states. Beta-NaFe2O3 is the only known compound with a layered rock-salt related structure and double layer transition metal-oxygen block. The main components of this proposal are synthesis, crystal structure and physical properties investigation: (1) of novel layered phases with CdI2-type layers and M in uniquely low (for such phases) 2+/3+ mixed valent oxidation states and (2) of new n = 2 and n = 3 members of the layered rock-salt related homologue. It is envisioned that implementation of the stated proposal objectives will not only result in novel strongly correlated-electron oxides, but also provide new synthetic methodologies for the preparation of highly unusual phases as well as result in new fundamental insights into correlated-electron behavior, leading to the discovery of compounds with potentially useful thermoelectric and/or magnetic properties. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;In a special class of metal compounds electron - electron interaction results in a variety of physical properties important from fundamental and technological points of view. Properties of these so called strongly correlated-electronic materials depend on details of crystal structure, as well as on transition metal oxidation and spin states. New synthetic methodology developed in this proposal will enable preparation of strongly correlated-electronic materials in a predictable way. Investigation of structure-property relationships will provide deep insights into correlated-electron behavior and  enable development of design principles for new materials capable of converting heat via a temperature gradient into electric energy (thermoelectric materials), as well as compounds with interesting magnetic properties.  Graduate and undergraduate students will be trained in the areas of inorganic synthesis, electrochemistry, crystallography, magnetism, and various characterization techniques. The PI will lead the organization of the Midwestern Symposium on Undergraduate Research in Chemistry. This symposium, spearheaded by the PI targets the undergraduate to graduate school transition and is designed to increase the number of domestic applicants to graduate programs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/04/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1206718</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Viktor</FirstName>
<LastName>Poltavets</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Viktor V Poltavets</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vpoltave@uno.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5042804418</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000577235</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/04/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488241322</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[433 Chemistry]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1762</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~129998</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~138445</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~129997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Design of materials with desired crystal structures and physical properties is often limited by metastability of target compounds. Such metastable, i.e. kinetically stable, phases can only be prepared indirectly. The multistep synthetic approach developed in this proposal enabled synthesis of novel metastable complex transitional metal oxides in a predictable way. The project has extended the limits of our synthetic capabilities and proved the possibility of sequential soft chemistry reactions. Uniquely, for solid state chemistry, metastable intermediates are used in this procedure.</p> <p>During the performance period several new synthetic approaches were developed:</p> <p>- the &ldquo;aliovalent exchange plus intercalation&rdquo; multistep soft chemistry approach, which results in compounds with the alpha&shy;NaFeO2 type structures and, uniquely, with transition metals in mixed valent 2+/3+ oxidation states.</p> <p>- low temperature solvothermal fluorination method was developed. The facile method allows performing fluorination at lower temperature than any other technique.</p> <p>- synthesis of beta&shy;-NaxFe2O3 family of compounds have become possible by utilizing a controlled partial oxygen pressure procedure and low temperature deintercalation steps.</p> <p>These results clearly show that creative synthetic approaches can lead to many more potential compounds of interest, not accessible by traditional synthetic techniques.</p> <p>Training of graduate and undergraduate students is one of the most important outcomes of the project. Students are trained in the areas of inorganic synthesis, electrochemistry, crystallography, magnetism, and various characterization techniques. Four graduate students, who contributed to the project performance, have successfully defended Ph.D. theses. Four undergraduate researchers from my group were admitted to graduate programs.</p> <p>With the support of the National Science Foundation, the principal investigator has established and annually organized the Midwestern Symposium on Undergraduate Research in Chemistry (MSU-R:CHEM). The Symposium targets undergraduate to graduate school transition and it is designed to increase the number of domestic applicants to graduate programs. In the 2011-2014 symposiums, 263 non-MSU and 22 MSU undergraduate researchers presented their scientific results. The effectiveness of the symposium was evaluated through an anonymous online survey of undergraduate students after the symposium. 80% of students indicated that their interest in pursuing an advanced (MS, PhD) degree had increased as result of participation in the symposium. 93% of undergraduate participants noticed an improvement in communication and presentation skills, and 97% of participants indicated an improvement in confidence in discussion of their research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Viktor&nbsp;V&nbsp;Poltavets</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Design of materials with desired crystal structures and physical properties is often limited by metastability of target compounds. Such metastable, i.e. kinetically stable, phases can only be prepared indirectly. The multistep synthetic approach developed in this proposal enabled synthesis of novel metastable complex transitional metal oxides in a predictable way. The project has extended the limits of our synthetic capabilities and proved the possibility of sequential soft chemistry reactions. Uniquely, for solid state chemistry, metastable intermediates are used in this procedure.  During the performance period several new synthetic approaches were developed:  - the "aliovalent exchange plus intercalation" multistep soft chemistry approach, which results in compounds with the alpha&shy;NaFeO2 type structures and, uniquely, with transition metals in mixed valent 2+/3+ oxidation states.  - low temperature solvothermal fluorination method was developed. The facile method allows performing fluorination at lower temperature than any other technique.  - synthesis of beta&shy;-NaxFe2O3 family of compounds have become possible by utilizing a controlled partial oxygen pressure procedure and low temperature deintercalation steps.  These results clearly show that creative synthetic approaches can lead to many more potential compounds of interest, not accessible by traditional synthetic techniques.  Training of graduate and undergraduate students is one of the most important outcomes of the project. Students are trained in the areas of inorganic synthesis, electrochemistry, crystallography, magnetism, and various characterization techniques. Four graduate students, who contributed to the project performance, have successfully defended Ph.D. theses. Four undergraduate researchers from my group were admitted to graduate programs.  With the support of the National Science Foundation, the principal investigator has established and annually organized the Midwestern Symposium on Undergraduate Research in Chemistry (MSU-R:CHEM). The Symposium targets undergraduate to graduate school transition and it is designed to increase the number of domestic applicants to graduate programs. In the 2011-2014 symposiums, 263 non-MSU and 22 MSU undergraduate researchers presented their scientific results. The effectiveness of the symposium was evaluated through an anonymous online survey of undergraduate students after the symposium. 80% of students indicated that their interest in pursuing an advanced (MS, PhD) degree had increased as result of participation in the symposium. 93% of undergraduate participants noticed an improvement in communication and presentation skills, and 97% of participants indicated an improvement in confidence in discussion of their research.       Last Modified: 07/29/2016       Submitted by: Viktor V Poltavets]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
