<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>TeV Studies of Supernovae Powered Regions using Advanced Shower Analysis Techniques with the VERITAS Gamma-Ray Observatory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>474628.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>474628</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jean Allen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcallen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit  VERITAS is currently the most sensitive VHE gamma-ray observatory in the world. Operating at the basecamp of the Fred Lawrence Whipple Observatory in Arizona, the VERITAS project expands the Imaging Atmospheric Cherenkov Telescope technique pioneered by its precursor, the Whipple 10m Telescope, to include an array of four 12m telescopes with a multitelescope trigger for an order-of-magnitude improved sensitivity over the previous generation. VERITAS probes the extreme physics of sources such as the jets of Active Galactic Nuclei, Supernovae Remnants, and microquasars and provides an important complement to the Fermi Gamma-ray Space Telescope.  This award will provide support for the VERITAS science and collaboration service efforts of the Adler Planetarium &amp; Astronomy Museum researchers. The Adler group will lead the development and optimization of advanced gamma-ray analysis methods to increase the performance of VERITAS and play a leading role in calibration efforts. The Adler's science efforts will utilize the improved array performance in the study of extended supernova remnants and pulsar wind nebulae focusing on the case of the Crab Nebula, particularly in light of the recent discovery of the rapid bright synchrotron flares detected by Fermi. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact The Adler serves as the lead institution for VERITAS Education and Outreach efforts. Beyond the management aspects of the VERITAS EPO effort, the Adler VERITAS scientists will engage in a variety of efforts including hosting undergraduate interns from collaborating VERITAS institutions, participating in the daily 'Astronomy Conversations' held at the Adler Planetarium's Space Visualization Laboratory, investigating the feasibility of a Citizen Science project to distinguish gamma rays from cosmic rays, and providing planetarium expertise to the VERITAS project office to develop a VERITAS-themed show.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1206534</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Geza</FirstName>
<LastName>Gyuk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Geza Gyuk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ggyuk@adlerplanetarium.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3123220337</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000339631</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Adler Planetarium</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606052403</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3123220325</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1300 S. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>083081802</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADLER PLANETARIUM, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Adler Planetarium]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606052403</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1300 S. Lake Shore Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1643</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Cosmic P</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~151615</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~163170</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~159843</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award supported participation of the Adler Planetarium's High Energy Astrophysics Group in the VERITAS (Very Energetic Radiation Imaging Telescope Array System) collaboration. VERITAS is one of the world's most sensitive instruments for detecting gamma-rays with energies of hundreds of billions to tens of trillions times that of visible light. Such gamma rays are typically created in environments such as the jets coming from supermassive black holes, the ultra fast winds from pulsars, and the remnants of supernovae explosions. Because of the extreme distances the fluxes of gamma-rays are very low posing tremendous challenges to researchers.&nbsp;</p> <p>Over the period of this award the Adler Planetarium High Energy Astrophysics group has accomplished three main goals:</p> <p>1) We significantly improved the sensitivity and angular resolution of VERITAS gamma-ray observations through the implementation and application of a 3-dimensional (3D) Model air shower event reconstruction method. This has allowed fainter sources to be analysed, and better results to be obtained with up to 50% less time spent on each object. This work was led by post-doc Dr. Jeff Grube.</p> <p>2) We have looked at one such faint object, the starburst galaxy M82, in great detail using many hundreds of hours of observations. Study of M82 allows us to test detailed gamma-ray emission models for cosmic ray acceleration and propagation within star-forming galaxies. Such star forming galaxies consitute a relatively new class of VHE gamma-ray emission. This work was led by then gradute student Gayle Ratliff and&nbsp;was central to her Ph.D. thesis work. Dr. Ratliff recieved her degree in the Fall of 2015 from the Illinois Institute of Technology under the supervision of Drs. Grube (Adler), Gyuk (Adler), and Chris White (IIT).</p> <p>3) The Adler group, led VERITAS calibration and systematic uncertainty studies, providing the service work which is essential to achieving the&nbsp;strong performance of the array. These studies have included analysis of the telescope pointing, optical efficiency (using muon detections), the image forming ability, and the gamma-ray source detection efficiency (using calibration data on the Crab Nebula).</p> <p>Also during the course of the project the supported scientists presented their VERITAS research and a broad range of astrophysics topics to the general museum public during bi-weekly Astronomy Conversations sessions utilizing state of the art astronomy visualizations. Over the course of the grant these Astronomy Conversations reached over 18,000 visitors.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2016<br>      Modified by: Geza&nbsp;Gyuk</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award supported participation of the Adler Planetarium's High Energy Astrophysics Group in the VERITAS (Very Energetic Radiation Imaging Telescope Array System) collaboration. VERITAS is one of the world's most sensitive instruments for detecting gamma-rays with energies of hundreds of billions to tens of trillions times that of visible light. Such gamma rays are typically created in environments such as the jets coming from supermassive black holes, the ultra fast winds from pulsars, and the remnants of supernovae explosions. Because of the extreme distances the fluxes of gamma-rays are very low posing tremendous challenges to researchers.   Over the period of this award the Adler Planetarium High Energy Astrophysics group has accomplished three main goals:  1) We significantly improved the sensitivity and angular resolution of VERITAS gamma-ray observations through the implementation and application of a 3-dimensional (3D) Model air shower event reconstruction method. This has allowed fainter sources to be analysed, and better results to be obtained with up to 50% less time spent on each object. This work was led by post-doc Dr. Jeff Grube.  2) We have looked at one such faint object, the starburst galaxy M82, in great detail using many hundreds of hours of observations. Study of M82 allows us to test detailed gamma-ray emission models for cosmic ray acceleration and propagation within star-forming galaxies. Such star forming galaxies consitute a relatively new class of VHE gamma-ray emission. This work was led by then gradute student Gayle Ratliff and was central to her Ph.D. thesis work. Dr. Ratliff recieved her degree in the Fall of 2015 from the Illinois Institute of Technology under the supervision of Drs. Grube (Adler), Gyuk (Adler), and Chris White (IIT).  3) The Adler group, led VERITAS calibration and systematic uncertainty studies, providing the service work which is essential to achieving the strong performance of the array. These studies have included analysis of the telescope pointing, optical efficiency (using muon detections), the image forming ability, and the gamma-ray source detection efficiency (using calibration data on the Crab Nebula).  Also during the course of the project the supported scientists presented their VERITAS research and a broad range of astrophysics topics to the general museum public during bi-weekly Astronomy Conversations sessions utilizing state of the art astronomy visualizations. Over the course of the grant these Astronomy Conversations reached over 18,000 visitors.          Last Modified: 09/28/2016       Submitted by: Geza Gyuk]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
