<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Ultrafast Acoustics and Heat Transport in Nanostructures, Thin Films, and Crystals</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Sokol</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>****Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;This NSF award will support experimental condensed matter physics research at Vassar College in Poughkeepsie, NY, an undergraduate institution.  This project will seek to answer fundamental materials research questions that are also of technological relevance.  Ultrafast optical techniques will be used to study thermal and acoustic phenomena thin films, crystals, and nanostructures.  In particular, the project will include studies of novel phononic bandgap structures made from silicon, amorphous hydrogenated films (a-Si:H and a-SiC:H), and bulk crystals (GaAs, GaN, SiC, and AlN).  The project is expected to contribute answers to long-standing questions regarding the contributions of long-wavelength phonons to thermal transport and phonon attenuation mechanisms in amorphous and crystalline structures.  The results contributed by this project will have an impact on a number of technologies including microelectronics, solar cells, and thermoelectric devices.  The NSF award will support undergraduate student research at one of the nation's premier liberal arts colleges.  6 summer research students will be funded during the three-year project and many other students will benefit from the expansion of laboratory equipment provided through the award.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****Non-Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;This NSF award will support experimental materials physics research at Vassar College in Poughkeepsie, NY, an undergraduate institution.  This project will seek to answer fundamental questions that are of technological relevance to the semiconductor and nanotech fields.  Ultrafast lasers (which produce pulses less than a millionth of a millionth of a second in duration) will be used as a tool to study heat and ultrasound in novel, nanoscale structures made from silicon and other technologically important materials.  A better understanding of the way heat and ultrasound transport energy in these materials will benefit ongoing research in a number of fields including microelectronics, solar energy, and thermoelectrics.  The NSF award will support undergraduate student research at one of the nation's premier liberal arts colleges.  6 summer research students will be funded during the three-year project and many other students will benefit from the expansion of laboratory equipment provided through the award.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1206681</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Daly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Daly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brdaly@vassar.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8454377351</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000091534</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vassar College</Name>
<CityName>Poughkeepsie</CityName>
<ZipCode>126040657</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8454377092</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>124 Raymond Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080464001</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VASSAR COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>080464001</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vassar College]]></Name>
<CityName>Poughkeepsie</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>126040001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[124 Raymond Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF award entitled RUI: Ultrafast Acoustics and Heat Transport in Nanostructures, Thin Films, and Crystals supported experimental materials physics research at Vassar College in Poughkeepsie, NY for over four years.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit:</p> <p>We used ultrafast lasers (which produce pulses less than a millionth of a millionth of a second in duration) to measure thermal properties of nanometer thick films that are of technological importance to the semiconductor and nanotech industries. &nbsp;We also used lasers to generate and detect some of the highest surface acoustic wave frequencies ever detected and found that our results depended strongly on the nanofabrication techniques used to make the samples. &nbsp;We modeled these waves using 2D molecular dynamics simulations (See Image 1) and found that our nanoscale waves behaved analogously to another well studied form of surface waves: earthquakes!</p> <p>Broader Impacts:</p> <p>The results of our work have contributed to a better understanding of the way heat and ultrasound transport energy in materials under investigation for applications in nanoelectronics, solar energy, and thermoelectrics. &nbsp;The award also supported undergraduate student research at one of the nation&rsquo;s premier liberal arts colleges.&nbsp; 6 summer research students were directly funded through the project and at least ten other students benefitted from the expansion of laboratory equipment and research opportunities provided through the award. &nbsp;Students who worked on the project since 2012 are currently pursuing PhD degrees in physics or materials science at SUNY Stony Brook, University of Pennsylvania, Boston College, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, and New York University.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/05/2016<br>      Modified by: Brian&nbsp;Daly</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1206681/1206681_10190496_1467744958888_Daly_JAP_7--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1206681/1206681_10190496_1467744958888_Daly_JAP_7--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Molecular dynamics simulations of surface acoustic waves in nanostructures"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1206681/1206681_10190496_1467744958888_Daly_JAP_7--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Molecular dynamics simulations of surface acoustic waves in nanostructures"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Detected frequencies for a sample with a 420 nm wide pattern. (b) Detected frequencies for a sample with a 250 nm wide pattern. (c) Simulated waveform at 17.17 GHz for the 250 nm pattern. (d) Simulated waveform at 20.57 GHz for the 250 nm pattern</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. Appl. Phys. 117, 095305 (2015)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Brian&nbsp;Daly</div> <div class="imageTitle">Molecular dynamics simulations of surface acoustic waves in nanostructures</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF award entitled RUI: Ultrafast Acoustics and Heat Transport in Nanostructures, Thin Films, and Crystals supported experimental materials physics research at Vassar College in Poughkeepsie, NY for over four years.  Intellectual Merit:  We used ultrafast lasers (which produce pulses less than a millionth of a millionth of a second in duration) to measure thermal properties of nanometer thick films that are of technological importance to the semiconductor and nanotech industries.  We also used lasers to generate and detect some of the highest surface acoustic wave frequencies ever detected and found that our results depended strongly on the nanofabrication techniques used to make the samples.  We modeled these waves using 2D molecular dynamics simulations (See Image 1) and found that our nanoscale waves behaved analogously to another well studied form of surface waves: earthquakes!  Broader Impacts:  The results of our work have contributed to a better understanding of the way heat and ultrasound transport energy in materials under investigation for applications in nanoelectronics, solar energy, and thermoelectrics.  The award also supported undergraduate student research at one of the nationÆs premier liberal arts colleges.  6 summer research students were directly funded through the project and at least ten other students benefitted from the expansion of laboratory equipment and research opportunities provided through the award.  Students who worked on the project since 2012 are currently pursuing PhD degrees in physics or materials science at SUNY Stony Brook, University of Pennsylvania, Boston College, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, and New York University.          Last Modified: 07/05/2016       Submitted by: Brian Daly]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
