<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Extending the pi-Conjugation Length of Soluble Semiconducting Polymers to Effect Efficient Charge Transport</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>308714.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>308714</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Freddy Khoury</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Realization of polymer architectures with well-defined dimensions and functions is one of the current research challenges in the field of organic semiconducting materials. Materials that meet requisite performance targets and will markedly reduce overall process complexity are essential. The proposal focusses on the design, synthesis and characterization of pi-conjugated polymers having the following characteristics: a low bandgap, a low HOMO level, and effective pi-pi interactions. The aim is to define a strategy for the effective extension of the conjugation length of polymers having electro-optic characteristics. The materials are expected to exhibit enhanced field-effect induced charge transport and photovoltaic properties, features that an imperative for the successful introduction of robust and reliable polymer based devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, the PI will (1) investigate the effectiveness of the vinylene linkage to extend the conjugation length of targeted polymers, (2) investigate alternative alkyl side chains and their ability to solubilize targeted polymers in common organic solvents, allowing for solution processing,  (3) synthesize alternative D-A architectures, (4) perform requisite physical characterization of the targeted materials, (5) fabricate field effect transistor and photovoltaic devices to evaluate the impact of the approach.  Through the studies defined above, it is anticipated that identification of key, synthetically accessible structural features will provide for an extension of the pi-conjugation length of semiconducting polymers with requisite characteristics that will allow for orientation and alignment that are favorable for charge transport. These studies will identify means to achieve energy levels and bandgaps that not only afford desired electro-optic performance, but also support robust and reliable devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conjugated polymeric materials in general, and polymer semiconductors in particular, are of broad interest because of the wide range of possible applications including organic light-emitting diodes (OLED), organic field effect transistors (OFET), photovoltaic devices (PV), electro-optic shutters, printed antennas, plastic-based actuators, and signal switches. Further, polymers offer compatibility with high through-put, low cost processing techniques.   The proposed research program will provide essential insight needed for the development and deployment of advanced polymer materials for electro-optic device applications having significant societal impact, examples of which are described above.   Students participating in this effort will gain invaluable experience working in a multidisciplinary program. This approach will allow them to experience a broad education and to acquire a sound knowledge base in the area of polymer science and engineering coupled with an appreciation of the contributions of other disciplines. The research program will be integrated with undergraduate and graduate students working in teams to further the objectives of the proposal. Additionally, opportunities will be sought for high school students to participate in these teams. Outreach activities will target the local very diverse community, and both the PI and students will participate. Through these activities, public understanding of STEM will be enhanced, thereby positively influencing a diverse future generation of students to enter STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/04/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1207284</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elsa</FirstName>
<LastName>Reichmanis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elsa Reichmanis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>elr420@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9083033264</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000514536</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/04/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue, NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~101648</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~102892</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~104174</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Through the course of this investigation, we identified significant molecular structure-property relationships required to effect high charge carrier transport in solution processed &pi;-conjugated p- (hole transport) and n-channel (electron transport) polymers for organic field effect transistor (OFET) applications. Our focus continues to be on the molecular design and engineering of polymer side chain substituents and backbone components. We used a systematic molecular engineering approach to identify both donor and acceptor polymer backbone units that provided for the desired semiconducting characteristics with requisite solubility in more environmentally benign deposition solvents.&nbsp; In particular, the branched side-chain we developed is expected to facilitate the large-scale fabrication of large-area high performance devices on flexible and/or stretchable substrates. We can envision the future development of devices for energy storage and conversion, display, global security, biomedical and food and water safety applications through low-cost and accessible printing processes.</p> <p>This three year investigation provided support for one Ph.D and one MS student who have graduated and is supporting an additional full-time graduate student who is continuing has graduate studies. All students associated with this program are engaged in multidisciplinary studies at the intersection of materials science, chemistry and chemical engineering, and they are immersed in the physics, electrical and mechanical engineering aspects of devices. As a result, they are developing the skills necessary to be effective global leaders engaged in the design, development and implementation of new advanced technologies for societal well-being.</p> <p>The students have honed their leadership skills through mentoring several undergraduates. They have communicated their research in peer-reviewed publications and presentations at professional society meetings. Importantly, the students trained through this research activity have also been fully engaged in outreach to K-12 students and the general public.&nbsp; For instance, one of the students participated in &ldquo;You be the Chemist&rdquo; demonstrations as part of the Spring 2015 Atlanta Science Festival. The PI and her students are also active in the Georgia Tech Polymer Network (GTPN): the PI serves as an Associate Director while the students are in leadership positions in the GTPN-Student Association (GTPN-SA).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/01/2015<br>      Modified by: Elsa&nbsp;Reichmanis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1207284/1207284_10170393_1435780440692_140825AR168--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1207284/1207284_10170393_1435780440692_140825AR168--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Materials chemistry lab discussions"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1207284/1207284_10170393_1435780440692_140825AR168--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Materials chemistry lab discussions"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The image depicts the outcome of a discussion among students engaged in the project.  The colored solutions in the test-tubes are semiconducting polymer solutions prepared here and structures are drawn on the safety shield of the exhaust hood.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Georgia Tech</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmi...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Through the course of this investigation, we identified significant molecular structure-property relationships required to effect high charge carrier transport in solution processed &pi;-conjugated p- (hole transport) and n-channel (electron transport) polymers for organic field effect transistor (OFET) applications. Our focus continues to be on the molecular design and engineering of polymer side chain substituents and backbone components. We used a systematic molecular engineering approach to identify both donor and acceptor polymer backbone units that provided for the desired semiconducting characteristics with requisite solubility in more environmentally benign deposition solvents.  In particular, the branched side-chain we developed is expected to facilitate the large-scale fabrication of large-area high performance devices on flexible and/or stretchable substrates. We can envision the future development of devices for energy storage and conversion, display, global security, biomedical and food and water safety applications through low-cost and accessible printing processes.  This three year investigation provided support for one Ph.D and one MS student who have graduated and is supporting an additional full-time graduate student who is continuing has graduate studies. All students associated with this program are engaged in multidisciplinary studies at the intersection of materials science, chemistry and chemical engineering, and they are immersed in the physics, electrical and mechanical engineering aspects of devices. As a result, they are developing the skills necessary to be effective global leaders engaged in the design, development and implementation of new advanced technologies for societal well-being.  The students have honed their leadership skills through mentoring several undergraduates. They have communicated their research in peer-reviewed publications and presentations at professional society meetings. Importantly, the students trained through this research activity have also been fully engaged in outreach to K-12 students and the general public.  For instance, one of the students participated in "You be the Chemist" demonstrations as part of the Spring 2015 Atlanta Science Festival. The PI and her students are also active in the Georgia Tech Polymer Network (GTPN): the PI serves as an Associate Director while the students are in leadership positions in the GTPN-Student Association (GTPN-SA).       Last Modified: 07/01/2015       Submitted by: Elsa Reichmanis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
