<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development of Critical Data for Predicting Growth of Secondary Organic Aerosols in Air</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>692478.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>734977</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020104</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Edgerton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sedgerto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928522</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is comprised of a series of studies to measure the uptake coefficients for semi-volatile organic compounds (SVOC) on secondary organic aerosols (SOA) formed from the oxidation of a variety of gas phase precursors. The rationale for these investigations is that SOA growth is better described by a kinetically limited mechanism than one based on equilibrium phase partitioning, and that uptake coefficients for various SVOC on typical atmospheric SOA are needed in order to model SOA growth more accurately. However, uptake coefficients data on SOA are limited. The activities therefore include studies of the generation and composition of SOA formed from oxidation of SOA precursors by nitrate radical or/and ozone inside a large-volume, slow-flow aerosol flow tube; studies of the uptake of organic nitrates and SVOC on SOA as well as studies of possible evaporation of SOA components using attenuated total reflectance Fourier transform infrared spectrometry (ATR-FTIR); measurements of absolute uptake coefficients of organic nitrates and SVOC on SOA using a Knudson cell and a coated wall fast flow reactor; characterization of the uptake of organic nitrates and SVOC on self-assembled monolayers; and analysis of SOA using nano-secondary ion mass spectrometry (nano-SIMS). The research will yield information important in assessing the relative importance of kinetically limited mechanisms versus equilibrium partitioning in SOA growth.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts include providing kinetic data and molecular insights on the uptake of semi-volatile organic compounds onto secondary organic aerosol, disseminating results broadly through publications, summer teacher workshops, hosted lab tours for students and the general public, visits of researchers to local schools, training of undergraduate and graduate students and postdoctoral fellows, continued involvement of underrepresented groups in the principal investigator's research activities, and development of new experiments for the undergraduate curriculum at UC-Irvine.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1207112</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Finlayson-Pitts</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara J Finlayson-Pitts</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bjfinlay@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498247670</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000444786</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926972025</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Rowland Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>Atmospheric Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1078</Code>
<Text>AWARDS TO FACILITATE GEOSCIENCE EDUCATIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~222131</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~456930</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~13417</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~13000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~29499</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goals of the research were to elucidate the mechanisms of growth of particles in air via uptake of species from the gas phase, and to use that as a basis for developing predictive models appropriate for incorporation into atmospheric models from local/regional to global scales. This is important because particles reduce visibility, lead to significant health impacts that include enhanced mortality, and are intimately involved in climate change. Most particles in air are not directly emitted, but rather are formed by chemical reactions of gaseous precursors. Although when initially formed, particles consist of small clusters of relatively few molecules, they then grow into larger particles. At and above ~ 100 nm diameter, they can serve as nuclei for the formation of liquid and ice clouds, affecting the cloud properties such as light scattering and lifetimes, and hence impacts on climate.&nbsp; At this size they are also efficient at scattering visible light, resulting in visibility reduction and they are efficiently taken up in the respiratory system upon inhalation. Because of the importance of size in determining many of the particle properties, it is essential to understand how they grow from tiny seeds to diameters of hundreds of nanometers.</p> <p>&nbsp;This project involved experimental laboratory studies of several different types of particles: secondary organic aerosol (SOA) particles from the oxidation of biogenic organic compounds that are typical of emissions from plants and trees, and dicarboxylic acids which are products of these oxidations and are found in air.&nbsp; We showed that the particles from some important biogenic precursors are not liquid, but semi-solid, wax-like material, and that as they grow, they incorporate quite high volatility gases that would not normally be expected to be found in such particles. This has a major impact on understanding the mechanisms by which particles grow in air, and how this is represented in atmospheric models. A second model system involves a set of compounds that are products of such reactions, the dicarboxylic acids.&nbsp; Our studies showed that when they react with amines, which are emitted from many sources including agricultural activities and human breath, they can form liquid salts, rather than solids as expected. How fast particles grow in air is determined in large part by whether they are liquids or solids, so this impacts how fast particles will grow from seeds. This is also new chemistry that suggests the formation of ionic liquids under some conditions in air should be considered.</p> <p>This project has provided insights into the kinetics and mechanisms of important atmospheric reactions, which is key for determining optimal air pollution control strategies to address particle impacts on human health, climate and visibility.&nbsp; It has also provided training to a number of graduate students, undergraduates and postdoctoral fellows, the majority of whom belong to underrepresented groups in science, particularly women.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/07/2016<br>      Modified by: Barbara&nbsp;J&nbsp;Finlayson-Pitts</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goals of the research were to elucidate the mechanisms of growth of particles in air via uptake of species from the gas phase, and to use that as a basis for developing predictive models appropriate for incorporation into atmospheric models from local/regional to global scales. This is important because particles reduce visibility, lead to significant health impacts that include enhanced mortality, and are intimately involved in climate change. Most particles in air are not directly emitted, but rather are formed by chemical reactions of gaseous precursors. Although when initially formed, particles consist of small clusters of relatively few molecules, they then grow into larger particles. At and above ~ 100 nm diameter, they can serve as nuclei for the formation of liquid and ice clouds, affecting the cloud properties such as light scattering and lifetimes, and hence impacts on climate.  At this size they are also efficient at scattering visible light, resulting in visibility reduction and they are efficiently taken up in the respiratory system upon inhalation. Because of the importance of size in determining many of the particle properties, it is essential to understand how they grow from tiny seeds to diameters of hundreds of nanometers.   This project involved experimental laboratory studies of several different types of particles: secondary organic aerosol (SOA) particles from the oxidation of biogenic organic compounds that are typical of emissions from plants and trees, and dicarboxylic acids which are products of these oxidations and are found in air.  We showed that the particles from some important biogenic precursors are not liquid, but semi-solid, wax-like material, and that as they grow, they incorporate quite high volatility gases that would not normally be expected to be found in such particles. This has a major impact on understanding the mechanisms by which particles grow in air, and how this is represented in atmospheric models. A second model system involves a set of compounds that are products of such reactions, the dicarboxylic acids.  Our studies showed that when they react with amines, which are emitted from many sources including agricultural activities and human breath, they can form liquid salts, rather than solids as expected. How fast particles grow in air is determined in large part by whether they are liquids or solids, so this impacts how fast particles will grow from seeds. This is also new chemistry that suggests the formation of ionic liquids under some conditions in air should be considered.  This project has provided insights into the kinetics and mechanisms of important atmospheric reactions, which is key for determining optimal air pollution control strategies to address particle impacts on human health, climate and visibility.  It has also provided training to a number of graduate students, undergraduates and postdoctoral fellows, the majority of whom belong to underrepresented groups in science, particularly women.        Last Modified: 12/07/2016       Submitted by: Barbara J Finlayson-Pitts]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
