<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Underrepresented Students in Topology and Algebra Research Symposium</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The second annual meeting of the Underrepresented Students in Topology and Algebra Research Symposium (USTARS) is to be held at the University of Iowa on April 13-15, 2012. The project was proposed by a group of underrepresented students in the University of Iowa Mathematics Department and is largely run and organized by graduate students. Speakers will give 30-minute research talks in various subfields of topology and algebra; these subfields include algebraic combinatorics, enumerative geometry, knot theory, and representation theory. One distinguished graduate student will give an hour long presentation and one invited faculty member, Dr. Federico Ardila of San Francisco State University and Universidad de Los Andes, will give a one hour keynote address. Undergraduate participants from the VIGRE/ALLIANCE Summer REU will also present in a poster session.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;USTARS promotes diversity within the mathematical community by providing a platform for collaboration and professional development. Participants are exposed to a variety of current research, ideas, and results, and meet underrepresented professors and students who will become future collaborators or colleagues. The conference also promotes diversity by encouraging women and minorities to attend and give talks. Indeed, the conference organizing committee is diverse in gender, ethnicity, and educational background, and hence is well-positioned to encourage participation from a diverse group of students. The participants of the conference will continue to influence the next generation of students by serving as much needed mentors and encouraging students in the mathematical sciences to advance themselves and participate in research and conference events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;http://www.mathalliance.org/ustars.asp</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1207604</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maggy</FirstName>
<LastName>Tomova</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maggy Tomova</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maggy-tomova@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3193350761</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486832</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
<LastName>Insko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erik A Insko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>einsko@fgcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2395907297</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000568090</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Syvillia</FirstName>
<LastName>Averett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Syvillia Averett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>saverett@ccga.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000568091</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shannon</FirstName>
<LastName>Talbott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shannon Talbott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shannon.talbott.math@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6108611573</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000599491</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Garrett</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Garrett Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>garrett-jones@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3193352123</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000599492</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Iowa</Name>
<CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2 GILMORE HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>062761671</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF IOWA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>062761671</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName>Iowa City</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>522421419</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[14 MLH]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~25000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Underrepresented Students in Topology and Algebra Research Symposium (USTARS) is an event that creates a venue where graduate students from underrepresented groups studying pure mathematics may present their work and form research and social support networks with other mathematicians with related research interests. This meeting happens annually in April, and the goal of the symposium is to showcase the high-quality research being done by underrepresented students.&nbsp;</p> <p>In a 2010 NSF survey of doctoral degree recipients, less than 30% of all mathematics doctorates were awarded to women and less than 4% were awarded to minority students<a href="file:///C:/Users/einsko/Dropbox/2014%20Spring/USTARS%202014/USTARS%20Project%20Outcomes.docx#_ftn1">[1]</a>. &nbsp;&nbsp;USTARS promotes diversity within the mathematical sciences by encouraging underrepresented students to present their research.&nbsp; While doing this, USTARS has provided its participants with an environment that creates a mentoring network as well as a research network in pure mathematical fields.&nbsp; One participant of USTARS 2012 noted that &ldquo;I found the atmosphere at USTARS conducive to collaboration and building social support networks.&rdquo;&nbsp;</p> <p>The symposium also provides an invaluable opportunity for students who have not yet chosen a research area or have switched areas of study to learn about potential research topics. The faculty who attend provide mentorship and collaboration by helping undergraduate students and transitional graduate students find research areas and encouraging students to meet and work with people interested in their areas of research.&nbsp; One such faculty mentor who attended the 2013 conference, and who primarily advises undergraduate research, remarked that &ldquo;I am able to use the USTARS presentations to choose topics that are in line with the research that is being done in graduate school&hellip; I believe that in keeping up with the advances in these areas, I am able better prepare the talented students for the mathematics that they will encounter in graduate school.&rdquo;</p> <p>The primary goal of USTARS has always been to showcase the high-quality research being conducted by these graduate students.&nbsp; Students at all stages of their graduate career have been encouraged to speak at the conference, and these speakers have often gained new insight on how to tackle their research problems from the other mathematicians who were in attendance, and at least two papers have been produced as a result of collaborations formed at USTARS 2012.</p> <p>The broader impact of USTARS is that graduate students who attend are better equipped to seek academic positions, continue the cycle of mathematical research and collaboration within the mathematical community, and give back to their community.&nbsp; For instance, when asked what impact USTARS has had on his mathematical career, one of the 2013 participants wrote that, &ldquo;It gave me the opportunity to meet amazing people and hear about their experiences, their struggles, and their successes, giving me an additional boost to keep researching on my field. &nbsp;Additionally, during conversations I listened to very wise words of advice regarding life after graduate school, how research eventually evolves in unexpected ways.&rdquo;</p> <p>USTARS participants will continue to influence the next generation of students in positive ways by serving as much needed mentors and encouraging students in the mathematical sciences to advance themselves and participate in research and conference events. &nbsp;For instance, one USTARS 2013 participant noted that &ldquo;I was inspired by your (the USTARS organizing) team. I made my own team here at San Francisco State University, and last summer we initiated a first-ever three-day summer math camp for low-income students in the Bay Area.&rdquo;&nbsp; We are gra...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Underrepresented Students in Topology and Algebra Research Symposium (USTARS) is an event that creates a venue where graduate students from underrepresented groups studying pure mathematics may present their work and form research and social support networks with other mathematicians with related research interests. This meeting happens annually in April, and the goal of the symposium is to showcase the high-quality research being done by underrepresented students.   In a 2010 NSF survey of doctoral degree recipients, less than 30% of all mathematics doctorates were awarded to women and less than 4% were awarded to minority students[1].   USTARS promotes diversity within the mathematical sciences by encouraging underrepresented students to present their research.  While doing this, USTARS has provided its participants with an environment that creates a mentoring network as well as a research network in pure mathematical fields.  One participant of USTARS 2012 noted that "I found the atmosphere at USTARS conducive to collaboration and building social support networks."   The symposium also provides an invaluable opportunity for students who have not yet chosen a research area or have switched areas of study to learn about potential research topics. The faculty who attend provide mentorship and collaboration by helping undergraduate students and transitional graduate students find research areas and encouraging students to meet and work with people interested in their areas of research.  One such faculty mentor who attended the 2013 conference, and who primarily advises undergraduate research, remarked that "I am able to use the USTARS presentations to choose topics that are in line with the research that is being done in graduate school&hellip; I believe that in keeping up with the advances in these areas, I am able better prepare the talented students for the mathematics that they will encounter in graduate school."  The primary goal of USTARS has always been to showcase the high-quality research being conducted by these graduate students.  Students at all stages of their graduate career have been encouraged to speak at the conference, and these speakers have often gained new insight on how to tackle their research problems from the other mathematicians who were in attendance, and at least two papers have been produced as a result of collaborations formed at USTARS 2012.  The broader impact of USTARS is that graduate students who attend are better equipped to seek academic positions, continue the cycle of mathematical research and collaboration within the mathematical community, and give back to their community.  For instance, when asked what impact USTARS has had on his mathematical career, one of the 2013 participants wrote that, "It gave me the opportunity to meet amazing people and hear about their experiences, their struggles, and their successes, giving me an additional boost to keep researching on my field.  Additionally, during conversations I listened to very wise words of advice regarding life after graduate school, how research eventually evolves in unexpected ways."  USTARS participants will continue to influence the next generation of students in positive ways by serving as much needed mentors and encouraging students in the mathematical sciences to advance themselves and participate in research and conference events.  For instance, one USTARS 2013 participant noted that "I was inspired by your (the USTARS organizing) team. I made my own team here at San Francisco State University, and last summer we initiated a first-ever three-day summer math camp for low-income students in the Bay Area."  We are grateful to the NSF for their support of USTARS 2012 and 2013.       [1] Doctorate Recipients from U.S. Universities: 2010, Arlington,VA (NSF 12-305)            Last Modified: 03/25/2014       Submitted by: Erik A Insko]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
