<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Design of Peptide Crystal Growth Modifiers Using Experiments and Simulations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>305000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph A. Akkara</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award by the Biomaterials program in the Division of Materials Research to University of Houston focuses on developing fundamental understandings of peptide interactions with surfaces of calcium oxalate monohydrate crystals, a predominant component of human kidney stones. This project will use a synergistic combination of peptide synthesis, materials characterization, and molecular simulations to develop rational design approaches that tailor calcium oxalate monohydrate crystallization. This collaborative proposal between the University of Houston and Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute will utilize the vast chemical and structural space of peptides to discover effective modifiers of calcium oxalate monohydrate crystal growth. This project proposes a high-throughput approach to screen peptide libraries, whereby the most potent candidates will be investigated by scanning probe microscopy to quantify peptide-crystal interactions and molecular modeling to investigate peptide binding to crystal surfaces. The overarching goal of this proposed research is to establish peptide-mediated crystallization as a versatile platform to achieve predictable and tunable structures and/or properties. To this end, the project is expected to advance our understanding of peptide-calcium oxalate monohydrate interactions, and will be transformative in that the philosophy and approach could be applied to crystal and shape engineering of other materials. Developments from this proposed research may lead to the identification of potent calcium oxalate monohydrate growth inhibitors as viable drug targets for kidney stone disease. Moreover, this award will be used to strengthen outreach initiatives at the K-12, undergraduate, and graduate levels to promote science education and research. This investigator will work with KIPP Houston High School (a minority institution) to establish a program that uses the research supported by this award to promote increased interest and participation in STEM.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Crystal engineering is a challenging area of research where advancements in rational design can impact the development of biomimetic systems, therapeutics, and advanced materials. This proposed research project focuses on designing peptides that interact with surfaces of calcium oxalate monohydrate crystals, which are one of the most common constituents of human kidney stones. This is a prototypical example of calcification, which is ubiquitous in many biological and physiological processes. The key intellectual contribution of this project will be to bring to bear unique, yet highly synergistic, expertise to quantify fundamental principles of peptide-crystal interactions. Through a combination of experiments and modeling, this research team will identify which peptides most effectively inhibit calcium oxalate monohydrate crystal growth, and determine which among these candidates exhibit an affinity for binding to specific surfaces of these crystals to enable the tailoring of crystal properties (e.g. size and shape). Rational design of peptide sequences combined with high-throughput screening will allow us to discover the most effective modifiers of the crystal growth, which can potentially lead to the identification of drug targets for kidney stones to address rising worldwide incidence rates of stone disease. General principles of crystal inhibitor design from this project could lead to developments in therapeutics for other diseases, and new methods for improving advanced materials. The integration of crystal engineering with medicine will be used as a tool to promote STEM education at the K-12 level and encourage students to become more active in research projects. The team members will work with local high school students and teachers to offer hands-on research opportunities, present guest lectures on engineering topics to Advanced Placement Chemistry students, develop lesson plans that integrate basic concepts of crystallization, and present seminars to discuss career opportunities in STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1207441</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Rimer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Rimer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jrimer@central.uh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7137434131</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000554330</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Houston</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>036837920</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042916627</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Houston]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4800 Calhoun Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~105000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary objective of this project was to identify effective growth modifiers of calcium oxalate monohydrate (COM) crystals, the predominant constituent of human kidney stones. The scope of the project included studies of modifiers spanning ions and small organic molecules, such as the current drug citrate (CA), to more complex macromolecules such as proteins that serve as native inhibitors of COM growth in the kidney. The knowledge gained by investigation of natural inhibitors was used to design de novo peptides with varying sequences and functionality as a platform to elucidate the physicochemical factors that govern modifier binding to specific surfaces of COM crystals. Extensive investigation of molecular analogues of citrate resulted in the identification of a possible new therapy: hydroxycitrate (HCA). We used a combination of <em>in situ</em> atomic force microscopy, bulk crystallization, and density functional theory calculations to show that HCA is more potent than CA, exhibits unique specificity, and operates by a unique mechanism of strain-induced dissolution. Moreover, the availability of HCA as an over-the-counter supplement (i.e., active component of <em>garcinia cambogia</em>) allowed us to perform human trails wherein we observed that HCA is bioavailable with oral intake. Collectively, these studies have opened new avenues for kidney stone drug discovery.</p> <p>This project led to several fundamental findings regarding the interactions of modifiers with COM crystal surfaces. Our work with alkali and alkaline earth metals revealed specific effects of these cations that could be explained by considering the relative hydration of ions and terminal groups on COM crystal surfaces, based on a theory of matching water affinity. Our investigations of molecular modifiers established the ability to dissolve crystals in highly supersaturated media via strain-induced binding to crystal interfaces. In addition, studies of proteins, such as lysozyme, revealed interesting mechanisms of growth promotion owing to the presence of negative and positive charges in close proximity that anchor the protein to the crystal surface and perturb the local solvent and/or diffuse layer of ions surrounding the crystal, respectively.</p> <p><strong>Outcomes of Intellectual Merit:</strong> Crystal growth modification is a ubiquitous process in natural, biological, and synthetic crystallization where knowledge of the molecular driving force for modifier-crystal interactions, which is often lacking, can have a profound effect on the growth and properties of materials. Although the objectives of this project focused specifically on calcium oxalate, the outcomes of our findings may prove to be applicable to other pathological diseases. Moreover, COM is a model system for studying the impact of growth modification in calcification &ndash; a process that extends well beyond the realm of kidney stones to natural and biological crystal growth. The findings in this project have revealed new and interesting mechanisms by which crystals can be tailored. Indeed, the combination of experiments, modeling, and clinical trials was one of the strengths of this particular project that has generated new insights into controlled crystallization and identified what has the potential to be the next preventative therapy for calcium oxalate kidney stone disease.</p> <p><strong>Outcomes of Broader Impact:</strong> Given the large number of applications and processes that rely on crystallization, designing new routes to control their growth can have substantial impact. Indeed, the ability to discover more efficient modifiers of COM holds promise for developing novel therapeutics and can also serve as a platform for improved understanding of crystal growth phenomena. Given the fact that kidney stone disease is on the rise and little progress has been made in the past 30 years to develop new therapies, the potential replacement of citrate with the newly discovered hydroxycitrate could have broad impact. In terms of outreach and education, this project supported three graduate students (including two female students) and three undergraduate students (two minority and one female). The PI used this project to develop partnerships with local high schools and support activities sponsored by the Lemelson-MIT organization. The PI and students also participated in additional outreach activities, such as Materials Day that was an organized tour given to high school students where they visited labs in various engineering departments throughout the college.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;Rimer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary objective of this project was to identify effective growth modifiers of calcium oxalate monohydrate (COM) crystals, the predominant constituent of human kidney stones. The scope of the project included studies of modifiers spanning ions and small organic molecules, such as the current drug citrate (CA), to more complex macromolecules such as proteins that serve as native inhibitors of COM growth in the kidney. The knowledge gained by investigation of natural inhibitors was used to design de novo peptides with varying sequences and functionality as a platform to elucidate the physicochemical factors that govern modifier binding to specific surfaces of COM crystals. Extensive investigation of molecular analogues of citrate resulted in the identification of a possible new therapy: hydroxycitrate (HCA). We used a combination of in situ atomic force microscopy, bulk crystallization, and density functional theory calculations to show that HCA is more potent than CA, exhibits unique specificity, and operates by a unique mechanism of strain-induced dissolution. Moreover, the availability of HCA as an over-the-counter supplement (i.e., active component of garcinia cambogia) allowed us to perform human trails wherein we observed that HCA is bioavailable with oral intake. Collectively, these studies have opened new avenues for kidney stone drug discovery.  This project led to several fundamental findings regarding the interactions of modifiers with COM crystal surfaces. Our work with alkali and alkaline earth metals revealed specific effects of these cations that could be explained by considering the relative hydration of ions and terminal groups on COM crystal surfaces, based on a theory of matching water affinity. Our investigations of molecular modifiers established the ability to dissolve crystals in highly supersaturated media via strain-induced binding to crystal interfaces. In addition, studies of proteins, such as lysozyme, revealed interesting mechanisms of growth promotion owing to the presence of negative and positive charges in close proximity that anchor the protein to the crystal surface and perturb the local solvent and/or diffuse layer of ions surrounding the crystal, respectively.  Outcomes of Intellectual Merit: Crystal growth modification is a ubiquitous process in natural, biological, and synthetic crystallization where knowledge of the molecular driving force for modifier-crystal interactions, which is often lacking, can have a profound effect on the growth and properties of materials. Although the objectives of this project focused specifically on calcium oxalate, the outcomes of our findings may prove to be applicable to other pathological diseases. Moreover, COM is a model system for studying the impact of growth modification in calcification &ndash; a process that extends well beyond the realm of kidney stones to natural and biological crystal growth. The findings in this project have revealed new and interesting mechanisms by which crystals can be tailored. Indeed, the combination of experiments, modeling, and clinical trials was one of the strengths of this particular project that has generated new insights into controlled crystallization and identified what has the potential to be the next preventative therapy for calcium oxalate kidney stone disease.  Outcomes of Broader Impact: Given the large number of applications and processes that rely on crystallization, designing new routes to control their growth can have substantial impact. Indeed, the ability to discover more efficient modifiers of COM holds promise for developing novel therapeutics and can also serve as a platform for improved understanding of crystal growth phenomena. Given the fact that kidney stone disease is on the rise and little progress has been made in the past 30 years to develop new therapies, the potential replacement of citrate with the newly discovered hydroxycitrate could have broad impact. In terms of outreach and education, this project supported three graduate students (including two female students) and three undergraduate students (two minority and one female). The PI used this project to develop partnerships with local high schools and support activities sponsored by the Lemelson-MIT organization. The PI and students also participated in additional outreach activities, such as Materials Day that was an organized tour given to high school students where they visited labs in various engineering departments throughout the college.       Last Modified: 11/30/2016       Submitted by: Jeffrey Rimer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
