<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Digitization TCN: Collaborative Research: Southwest Collections of Arthropods Network (SCAN): A Model for Collections Digitization to Promote Taxonomic and Ecological Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>362414.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>362414</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Collaborative Research Digitization TCN: Southwest Collections of Arthropods Network (SCAN): A Model for Collections Digitization to Promote Taxonomic and Ecological Research&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Southwest Collections of Arthropods Network (SCAN) brings together 10 diverse arthropod collections at universities and museums throughout the Southwest to create a virtual network of ground dwelling arthropods which are notably responsive to temporal and spatial environmental changes. These 10 collections document much of the Southwest's biodiversity, but currently the data associated with millions of arthropod specimens are not easily accessible. To overcome this, SCAN will develop methods for integrating existing databases, catalogue-image specimens, develop new electronic identification techniques, and produce a virtual library of ground-dwelling arthropods (beetles, grasshoppers, spiders, ants). In addition the project will work with the existing project Filtered Push to increase the capacity of experts to provide remote identifications and annotations of data that can be sent throughout the network.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The comprehensive SCAN online library and expert information will be available to the public as well as professionals in taxonomy, ecology, and climate change science. Smaller institutions will be provided increased access to large data sets for promoting research. The SCAN datasets will support a number of ongoing projects examining the effects of environmental and land-use change on individual arthropod species. By increasing access to this information, SCAN will stimulate new research and increased awareness in biodiversity conservation throughout the region. Over 50 undergraduates also will be trained in cyberinfrastructure, systematics, and ecology. This award is made as part of the National Resource for Digitization of Biological Collections through the Advancing Digitization of Biological Collections program and all data resulting from this award will be available through the national resource, iDigBio.org.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1207033</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Oswald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John D Oswald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>j-oswald@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798623507</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000435010</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M AgriLife Research</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>847205713</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M AGRILIFE RESEARCH</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778431260</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2701 General Services Complex]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6895</Code>
<Text>Digitization</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6895</Code>
<Text>DIGITIZATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~362414</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="style">A primary goal of the Southwest Collections of Arthropods Network (SCAN) was to digitize label data from &gt;1 million specimens of insects and other terrestrial arthropods and to make those data widely and openly available to researchers for use in studies of the ecosystems, ecology, and biodiversity of the southwestern United States. The project focused primarily on ground-dwelling arthropods (e.g., ants, grasshoppers, and selected beetles, spiders, and wasps).</p> <p class="style">&nbsp;As one of the 10 original collections in the SCAN network (in a consortium that eventually grew to &gt;50 natural history collections and museums), the Texas A&amp;M University Insect Collection (TAMUIC) digitized and provided to the SCAN project occurrence record data for more than 340,000 insect specimens. All data were captured using the TAMUIC&rsquo;s local collection management database and were transferred periodically to the SCAN project. The TAMUIC was one of the top occurrence data contributors to the overall project (eventually contributing more than 150% of its original goal of 225,000 specimens), and its records included specimens from most of the project&rsquo;s high priority taxa.</p> <p class="style">Over the course of its five-year participation in the project, the TAMUIC provided opportunities for 33 undergraduate students and 5 graduate students to gain hands-on experience in collection management and biodiversity informatics working within the setting of a large and active entomological research collection.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/22/2017<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;D&nbsp;Oswald</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[A primary goal of the Southwest Collections of Arthropods Network (SCAN) was to digitize label data from &gt;1 million specimens of insects and other terrestrial arthropods and to make those data widely and openly available to researchers for use in studies of the ecosystems, ecology, and biodiversity of the southwestern United States. The project focused primarily on ground-dwelling arthropods (e.g., ants, grasshoppers, and selected beetles, spiders, and wasps).  As one of the 10 original collections in the SCAN network (in a consortium that eventually grew to &gt;50 natural history collections and museums), the Texas A&amp;M University Insect Collection (TAMUIC) digitized and provided to the SCAN project occurrence record data for more than 340,000 insect specimens. All data were captured using the TAMUIC?s local collection management database and were transferred periodically to the SCAN project. The TAMUIC was one of the top occurrence data contributors to the overall project (eventually contributing more than 150% of its original goal of 225,000 specimens), and its records included specimens from most of the project?s high priority taxa. Over the course of its five-year participation in the project, the TAMUIC provided opportunities for 33 undergraduate students and 5 graduate students to gain hands-on experience in collection management and biodiversity informatics working within the setting of a large and active entomological research collection.       Last Modified: 12/22/2017       Submitted by: John D Oswald]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
