<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Charge Transport Pathways in Semiconducting Polymer Films</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>348000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>348000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Lovinger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alovinge@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924933</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The connection between charge transport and molecular order on intermediate length scales in films of semiconducting polymers will be examined.  In most electrical devices, semiconducting polymer chains do not span the distance between the electrodes and the resulting electrical properties are the result of charge transport both along the chains and from chain-to-chain. Through a collaborative effort between scientists at UCSB and NCSU the charge transport pathways in semiconducting polymers will be studied by: 1) measuring the in-plane bulk and interface correlation length of the backbone of semiconducting polymers using a combination of physical and electrical characterization methods and 2) investigating transport in model block co-polymer systems with varying energetic structure to uncover how both positive and negative carriers are transported in complex systems. This work will use a novel polarized soft X-ray scattering method to probe the backbone correlation length that will enable a greater understanding of the connection between morphology and electrical transport. The scattering techniques developed in this work will have impact on characterization of both semiconducting and conventional polymers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conjugated polymers have tremendous potential for use in cheap, flexible, light-weight devices as transistors in simple circuits, light emitting diodes, and solar cells. Improvement of our control of the properties of electrically conducting polymers will enable new types of electronic devices for use in energy conversion and biomedical diagnostics. This work will focus on the determination of the pathways of charge transport in conjugated polymers. Research in polymer electronics is highly multidisciplinary and will provide training for graduate students in materials science, chemistry, and microelectronics. The PIs and graduate students will also provide lab space and training for promising undergraduate students from underrepresented groups to advance their future careers in science and engineering. Outreach to children to promote science education in the local school districts will be done through demonstrations of flexible electronics devices by graduate student researchers at local science nights.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/25/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1207032</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Harald</FirstName>
<LastName>Ade</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Harald W Ade</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>harald_ade@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195151331</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000153930</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276958202</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~112000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~116000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overarching goals of this project were to develop a fundamental understanding of the charge transport pathways in semiconducting polymers by: 1) studying the connection of the carrier mobility and in-plane correlation lengths of the backbones of semiconducting polymers using advanced characterization methods, and 2) studying how carriers flow in novel semiconducting block copolymers that form complex transport pathways due to the texture of ordered domains and the electronic properties of each block. The specific goals of the work were to develop methodologies to study the charge transport pathways in organic semiconducting polymers.&nbsp; Charge transport in organic materials is known to depend on the short range order, i.e. intermolecular contacts, and also upon longer range order (&gt;100 nm) because of the long distances of charge transport in functional thin film devices (many micrometers).&nbsp; three areas: i) to uncover how charge flows in conjugated block co-polymers, ii) to understand microstructure changes upon introduction of carriers in working devices, and iii) develop tools to study the critical dielectric-semiconducting interface in thin film transistors.</p> <p>The work produced several significant outcomes that quantified the morphology of important model systems and related these to the device performance. All results were (or will be) published in the open, peer-reviewed scientific literature. The results were also presented at several major conferences. The work helped educate several students and postdoc to operate in interdisciplinary environment within a network of global collaborators. There is significant interest in flexible thin film electronic devices for applications in low-cost sensors, displays, solar cells, and thermoelectrics.&nbsp; The results of this research will aid in the development of higher performance organic electronic devices.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/02/2016<br>      Modified by: Harald&nbsp;W&nbsp;Ade</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overarching goals of this project were to develop a fundamental understanding of the charge transport pathways in semiconducting polymers by: 1) studying the connection of the carrier mobility and in-plane correlation lengths of the backbones of semiconducting polymers using advanced characterization methods, and 2) studying how carriers flow in novel semiconducting block copolymers that form complex transport pathways due to the texture of ordered domains and the electronic properties of each block. The specific goals of the work were to develop methodologies to study the charge transport pathways in organic semiconducting polymers.  Charge transport in organic materials is known to depend on the short range order, i.e. intermolecular contacts, and also upon longer range order (&gt;100 nm) because of the long distances of charge transport in functional thin film devices (many micrometers).  three areas: i) to uncover how charge flows in conjugated block co-polymers, ii) to understand microstructure changes upon introduction of carriers in working devices, and iii) develop tools to study the critical dielectric-semiconducting interface in thin film transistors.  The work produced several significant outcomes that quantified the morphology of important model systems and related these to the device performance. All results were (or will be) published in the open, peer-reviewed scientific literature. The results were also presented at several major conferences. The work helped educate several students and postdoc to operate in interdisciplinary environment within a network of global collaborators. There is significant interest in flexible thin film electronic devices for applications in low-cost sensors, displays, solar cells, and thermoelectrics.  The results of this research will aid in the development of higher performance organic electronic devices.                Last Modified: 12/02/2016       Submitted by: Harald W Ade]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
