<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Building an Event Horizon Telescope:  (Sub)millimeter VLBI from the South Pole Telescope</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>191204.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>191204</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ralph Gaume</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rgaume@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A research topic of great current interest is the supermassive black hole of about 4 million solar masses that is now known to exist at the center of our Milky Way galaxy.  Similar objects are common in other galaxies.  Most of what is known about the Milky Way's exotic object comes from studies of the kinematics of stars influenced by its strong gravitational field.  No possibility has heretofore existed for directly imaging the black hole, or more technically its event horizon, the gravitational "point of no return" from within which no particle or photon can escape the black hole.  The galactic center region is distant, about 8 kpc, making it extraordinarily difficult to obtain high-spatial-resolution images of the supermassive black hole by any direct technique.  If such images could be obtained, they would be the very first of their kind, and could reveal information not yet imagined about black holes and the dynamics in the cores of galaxies.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;To attack this challenging scientific problem, Drs. D. Marrone of the University of Arizona, S. Doeleman of the Northeast Radio Observatory Corporation, and J. Carlstrom of the University of Chicago intend to enhance an existing array of radio telescopes operating at the very highest radio frequencies (the submillimeter, with wavelengths somewhat shorter than a millimeter) and in a mode where telescopes separated by continental baselines coherently combine their data to achieve unprecedented spatial resolution.  The general technique is termed Very Long Baseline Interferometry, or VLBI, and the particular array of radio telescopes to be used is referred to as the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT), developed in part through a previous award from NSF.  Through a new NSF proposal the researchers plan to add the South Pole Telescope (SPT) as a new station to the EHT.  Adding stations (telescopes) in this manner enhances sensitivity to radio signals and also improves the spatial response of the instrument as an imaging device, so that better-quality maps may be made of fainter objects.  In addition to the addition of a key observing station, the technology will feature a new, sensitive dual-band millimeter-wave VLBI receiver, optimized for the needs of this project, that will employ superconducting mixer technology developed for the Atacama Large Millimeter Array (ALMA) project by the National Radio Astronomy Observatory (NRAO).  Finally, the proven 230 GHz design will be adapted for use at 345 GHz.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Funding for this work is being provided by NSF's Division of Astronomical Sciences through its Advanced Technologies and Instrumentation program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1207704</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sheperd</FirstName>
<LastName>Doeleman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sheperd S Doeleman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sdoeleman@haystack.mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7819815904</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000434335</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeast Radio Observatory Corp</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394307</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531975</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 Massachusetts Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005279778</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEAST RADIO OBSERVATORY CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[MIT Haystack Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Westford</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>018861299</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Route 40]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1218</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES &amp; INSTRM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7697</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~9917</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~159879</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~21408</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Black holes are the most extreme objects thought to exist in the Universe.&nbsp; Formed during the death of massive stars and during the collisions of galaxies, they are the result of a catastrophic gravitational collapse of matter in on itself.&nbsp; The gravity near a black hole is so strong that once matter, or even light, comes too close, it can never escape.&nbsp; This region around a black hole is called the Event Horizon.&nbsp; The Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) project is an effort to link radio dishes together across the globe for form an Earth-sized telescope that can make the first images of the nearest supermassive black holes at the centers of galaxies. This will enable scientists to test whether Einstein&rsquo;s theory of gravity still holds in the most extreme environment we can imagine. &nbsp;</p> <p>This project was focused on extending the EHT to the most remote place on Earth - the South Pole.&nbsp; By outfitting an existing 10m diameter radio dish at the South Pole station, this project increased the magnifying power of the EHT, and greatly increased the EHT&rsquo;s ability to image the two black holes with the largest apparent event horizons: SgrA* at the heart of the Milky Way galaxy (25,000 light years away), and M87 at the center of the Virgo A galaxy (52 million light years distant).</p> <p>Our team designed and built a new system for the South Pole Telescope that enabled it to carry out entirely new science than it was originally designed to do.&nbsp; The SPT spends most of its time looking at the remnant radiation from the Big-Bang, the original cataclysm from which the Universe was born.&nbsp; Now that we have added an ability to observe black holes, it will also become a key part of the EHT and lead to a greater understanding of how black holes shape the Universe, and allow us to use them as &lsquo;extreme laboratories&rsquo; to test our notions of gravity.</p> <p>The two images attached to this report show the South Pole Telescope and the locations on the globe of the two EHT stations we linked to test the systems we installed at the South Pole. &nbsp;The other site was the APEX dish in Chile. &nbsp;When the SPT and APEX were successfully linked in January 2015, our team formed a virtual telescope with a magnifying power equivalent to being able to see an orange on the moon. &nbsp;This is the angular resolution required to image even the closest black holes.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/07/2015<br>      Modified by: Sheperd&nbsp;S&nbsp;Doeleman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1207704/1207704_10193478_1449470591987_SPT.1.21.12--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1207704/1207704_10193478_1449470591987_SPT.1.21.12--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The South Pole Telescope"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1207704/1207704_10193478_1449470591987_SPT.1.21.12--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The South Pole Telescope"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The South Pole Telescope (SPT) that was outfitted with new instrumentation as part of this project.  The SPT is 10m in diameter and is designed to operate in the extreme cold of the South Pole environment.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Mallon III, National Science Foundation</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sheperd&nbsp;S&nbsp;Doeleman</div> <div class="imageTitle">The South Pole Te...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Black holes are the most extreme objects thought to exist in the Universe.  Formed during the death of massive stars and during the collisions of galaxies, they are the result of a catastrophic gravitational collapse of matter in on itself.  The gravity near a black hole is so strong that once matter, or even light, comes too close, it can never escape.  This region around a black hole is called the Event Horizon.  The Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) project is an effort to link radio dishes together across the globe for form an Earth-sized telescope that can make the first images of the nearest supermassive black holes at the centers of galaxies. This will enable scientists to test whether EinsteinÆs theory of gravity still holds in the most extreme environment we can imagine.    This project was focused on extending the EHT to the most remote place on Earth - the South Pole.  By outfitting an existing 10m diameter radio dish at the South Pole station, this project increased the magnifying power of the EHT, and greatly increased the EHTÆs ability to image the two black holes with the largest apparent event horizons: SgrA* at the heart of the Milky Way galaxy (25,000 light years away), and M87 at the center of the Virgo A galaxy (52 million light years distant).  Our team designed and built a new system for the South Pole Telescope that enabled it to carry out entirely new science than it was originally designed to do.  The SPT spends most of its time looking at the remnant radiation from the Big-Bang, the original cataclysm from which the Universe was born.  Now that we have added an ability to observe black holes, it will also become a key part of the EHT and lead to a greater understanding of how black holes shape the Universe, and allow us to use them as æextreme laboratoriesÆ to test our notions of gravity.  The two images attached to this report show the South Pole Telescope and the locations on the globe of the two EHT stations we linked to test the systems we installed at the South Pole.  The other site was the APEX dish in Chile.  When the SPT and APEX were successfully linked in January 2015, our team formed a virtual telescope with a magnifying power equivalent to being able to see an orange on the moon.  This is the angular resolution required to image even the closest black holes.       Last Modified: 12/07/2015       Submitted by: Sheperd S Doeleman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
