<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Geometry in nonsmooth optimization</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>412971.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>412971</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Steuerwalt</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>While nonsmooth optimization is ubiquitous across science and engineering, variational analysis - its elegant mathematical foundation - has achieved narrower practical impact than it warrants.  This project attacks that deficit through "structure":  not in the traditional explicit computational sense, but rather in the sense of intrinsic geometry.  The investigator studies two overlapping mathematical strategies.  The first uses semi-algebraic geometry as a rich and natural model for the world of concrete optimization problems.  In that world, much of the technicality and pathology obscuring variational analysis for practitioners is transformed, leaving powerful stratification tools and simple access to "generic" properties in optimization.  The second strategy emphasizes partial smoothness, a powerful geometric property originating from the theory of optimality conditions and sensitivity analysis, but also in perfect resonance with active-set algorithms.  With these theoretical tools at hand, the investigator focuses foremost on two fresh and promising computational methods for nonsmooth optimization.  The first is, counter-intuitively, just the classical BFGS method for smooth optimization, mildly adjusted for the nonsmooth world.  BFGS is simple, intuitive, general-purpose, much easier to implement successfully than traditional "bundle" methods, and broadly effective in practical applications, notably in robust control.  Mysteriously, BFGS always (essentially) seems to converge linearly and to identify partly smooth structure.  The investigator seeks explanations.  The second focal computational method is a proximal algorithm for composite optimization that is simple, versatile, and, in contrast with BFGS, well-grounded theoretically.  This algorithm has proved successful on huge problems, such as compressed sensing, but is potentially slow.  Partial smoothness will strengthen convergence in theory, and speed it in practice.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader significance and importance of this project derive from the investigator's transformative goal of bridging the gulf between mathematical theory and data-driven practice in resource allocation problems beyond the reach of traditional calculus.  A particularly important example is the kind of robust control engineering underlying applications like modern aircraft electronics.  The investigator builds on a strong track-record of high-calibre publications, innovative scholarship and outreach, and intellectual leadership.  PhD students based in Cornell's highly ranked School of ORIE (where the investigator is Director) will engage all aspects of the project, publishing and presenting at professional meetings;  the investigator will engage more broadly through seminars and his award-winning teaching, as well as through graduate texts, survey articles, multidisciplinary collaboration, and prominent international lectures to broad scientific and engineering audiences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1208338</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrian</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrian S Lewis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>adrian.lewis@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072559147</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000162071</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148533801</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[School of ORIE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~412971</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Nonsmooth optimization problems, as they arise in resource allocation problems across the applied sciences and engineering, lie beyond the reach of classical calculus, being highly sensitive to parameters.&nbsp; However, they often hide simple inherent structures.&nbsp; This project transformed our view of such structures, using an inherent geometric lens, rather than more traditional data-driven perspectives.&nbsp; It thereby bridged the gap between two distinct mathematical fields: computational optimization on the one hand, fundamentally driven by applications and numerical methods, and on the other hand, the elegant formal mathematical models of variational analysis.<br /><br />Two key creative ingredients particularly distinguished this project.&nbsp; The first original tool was an extensive appeal to semi-algebraic geometry, with its focus on sets of vectors defined through polynomial inequalities, as an illuminating model for concrete optimization problems.&nbsp; Several joint articles with D. Drusvyatskiy (U. Washington) and A. Ioffe (Technion) relied heavily on this approach, including a breakthrough in our understanding of von Neumann's method of alternating projections for nonconvex sets.&nbsp; The second tool permeating much of the project was the Principal Investigator's original notion of "partial smoothness", again a bridging idea between classical and nonsmooth calculus.&nbsp; A joint article with S. Wright (U. Wisconsin) illustrated the idea in the context of a prox-linear framework unifying numerical optimization methods ranging from the 1980's to the contemporary big data era.<br /><br />The project outcomes have been diverse, directly advancing knowledge in the field through more than a dozen substantial articles in top-rank international journals and a dozen high-profile lectures around the world, including an invited lecture at the 2014 International Congress of Mathematicians in Seoul, among the mathematical world's most prestigious invitations.<br /><br />In broader impact, the project supported the primary work of three doctoral students:&nbsp; D. Drusvyatskiy, now tenure-track (U. Washington), whose thesis was a runner-up for the 2015 Tucker Prize;&nbsp; S. Zhang, now with Amazon in Seattle; and J. Guo, soon to finish.&nbsp; The HANSO nonsmooth optimization software associated with the project's nonsmooth quasi-Newton component, and reported in a joint article with M.L. Overton (NYU) has been widely used in mathematical, scientific and engineering applications, including another joint article on a famous matrix conjecture of Crouzeix with A. Greenbaum (U. Washington) that nicely unified the project's goals.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/15/2016<br>      Modified by: Adrian&nbsp;S&nbsp;Lewis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Nonsmooth optimization problems, as they arise in resource allocation problems across the applied sciences and engineering, lie beyond the reach of classical calculus, being highly sensitive to parameters.  However, they often hide simple inherent structures.  This project transformed our view of such structures, using an inherent geometric lens, rather than more traditional data-driven perspectives.  It thereby bridged the gap between two distinct mathematical fields: computational optimization on the one hand, fundamentally driven by applications and numerical methods, and on the other hand, the elegant formal mathematical models of variational analysis.  Two key creative ingredients particularly distinguished this project.  The first original tool was an extensive appeal to semi-algebraic geometry, with its focus on sets of vectors defined through polynomial inequalities, as an illuminating model for concrete optimization problems.  Several joint articles with D. Drusvyatskiy (U. Washington) and A. Ioffe (Technion) relied heavily on this approach, including a breakthrough in our understanding of von Neumann's method of alternating projections for nonconvex sets.  The second tool permeating much of the project was the Principal Investigator's original notion of "partial smoothness", again a bridging idea between classical and nonsmooth calculus.  A joint article with S. Wright (U. Wisconsin) illustrated the idea in the context of a prox-linear framework unifying numerical optimization methods ranging from the 1980's to the contemporary big data era.  The project outcomes have been diverse, directly advancing knowledge in the field through more than a dozen substantial articles in top-rank international journals and a dozen high-profile lectures around the world, including an invited lecture at the 2014 International Congress of Mathematicians in Seoul, among the mathematical world's most prestigious invitations.  In broader impact, the project supported the primary work of three doctoral students:  D. Drusvyatskiy, now tenure-track (U. Washington), whose thesis was a runner-up for the 2015 Tucker Prize;  S. Zhang, now with Amazon in Seattle; and J. Guo, soon to finish.  The HANSO nonsmooth optimization software associated with the project's nonsmooth quasi-Newton component, and reported in a joint article with M.L. Overton (NYU) has been widely used in mathematical, scientific and engineering applications, including another joint article on a famous matrix conjecture of Crouzeix with A. Greenbaum (U. Washington) that nicely unified the project's goals.       Last Modified: 12/15/2016       Submitted by: Adrian S Lewis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
