<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in Singapore</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5954.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5954</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds Elizabeth Ann Gilbert of The University of Virginia to conduct a research project, entitled "Does imagining how outcomes could have been different explain cross-cultural differences in how we decide whom to blame?" during the summer of 2012 at Nanyang Technological University in Singapore.  The host scientist is Chi-Yue Chiu.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of the research project is to explore cultural factors in styles of thinking and better understand whether East Asians think about causation and blame differently than Americans do. Specifically, does the process of imagining the ways that bad outcomes could have been prevented affect East Asians' tendency to blame the environment rather than the individual?  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language.   These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1209743</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Gilbert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth A Gilbert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6185345259</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000607622</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/23/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gilbert                 Elizabeth      A</Name>
<CityName>Charlottesville</CityName>
<ZipCode>229031111</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Virginia]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlottesville</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229032926</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5927</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA, OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~5954</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml> <o:OfficeDocumentSettings> <o:AllowPNG /> </o:OfficeDocumentSettings> </xml><![endif]--> <p class="MsoNormal">This project examined how East Asians (from Singapore) and Westerners (from the United States) think differently about the causes of events.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>Previous research had shown, for instance, that East Asians consider more things to be relevant to causing a bad outcome (like an illness or a bankruptcy) than do Westerners.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>We however ran a series of studies examining <em style="mso-bidi-font-style: normal;">why</em> different cultures assign causation differently.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span></p> <p class="MsoNormal">Specifically, we tested the hypothesis that Westerners may be more likely to rely on &ldquo;analytic&rdquo; thinking whereas East Asians may be more likely to rely on &ldquo;analogical&rdquo; thinking.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>That is, when thinking about what leads to an outcome, Westerners may tend to apply a straight-forward cause-and-effect analysis (where one specific &ldquo;causal factor&rdquo; leads to one specific outcome). East Asians, however, may be more likely to rely on analogical thinking, meaning that they use information about what led to an outcome in one domain to understand what might have led to the outcome in a different domain.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>This analogical analysis would allow for many different causes to be related to many different outcomes, rather than a specific isolated cause leading to a specific isolated outcome.</p> <p class="MsoNormal">To test this hypothesis, participants in both Singapore and the United States were asked either to generate analogies (e.g., &ldquo;the early bird gets the worm&rdquo;) or causal factors (e.g., &ldquo;get an early start on homework&rdquo;) for understanding an outcome (e.g., &ldquo;being successful in school&rdquo;).<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>Results showed that Singaporeans reported that it is easier to generate and understand analogies related to causation than did Americans. They were also, on average, able to generate more analogies than Americans. Americans, on the other hand, reported that it was easier to generate and understand simple causal factors than did Singaporeans.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>These findings may help facilitate conversations between East Asians and Westerners, and may help explain how different people understand their worlds.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>Future work will continue to analyze whether such thinking occurs spontaneously and may account for cultural differences in causal attribution.</p> <p class="MsoNormal">This project facilitated collaboration between United States and East Asian collaborators (PI Elizabeth Gilbert is from the US and she worked for 8 weeks in the psychology and culture laboratory of CY Chiu, who is a researcher at the National Technological University in Singapore).<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>It also facilitated the testing of participants from outside of the United States (in Singapore), to help determine whether certain styles of thinking are basic to all people or whether cultural differences might exist. <span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp;</span></p> <!--[if gte mso 9]><xml> <w:WordDocument> <w:View>Normal</w:View> <w:Zoom>0</w:Zoom> <w:TrackMoves /> <w:TrackFormatting /> <w:PunctuationKerning /> <w:ValidateAgainstSchemas /> <w:SaveIfXMLInvalid>false</w:SaveIfXMLInvalid> <w:IgnoreMixedContent>false</w:IgnoreMixedContent> <w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText>false</w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText> <w:DoNotPromoteQF /> <w:LidThemeOther>EN-US</w:LidThemeOther> <w:LidThemeAsian>JA</w:LidThemeAsian> <w:LidThemeComplexScript>X-NONE</w:LidThemeComplexScript> <w:Compatibility> <w:BreakW...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[     This project examined how East Asians (from Singapore) and Westerners (from the United States) think differently about the causes of events.  Previous research had shown, for instance, that East Asians consider more things to be relevant to causing a bad outcome (like an illness or a bankruptcy) than do Westerners.  We however ran a series of studies examining why different cultures assign causation differently.   Specifically, we tested the hypothesis that Westerners may be more likely to rely on "analytic" thinking whereas East Asians may be more likely to rely on "analogical" thinking.  That is, when thinking about what leads to an outcome, Westerners may tend to apply a straight-forward cause-and-effect analysis (where one specific "causal factor" leads to one specific outcome). East Asians, however, may be more likely to rely on analogical thinking, meaning that they use information about what led to an outcome in one domain to understand what might have led to the outcome in a different domain.  This analogical analysis would allow for many different causes to be related to many different outcomes, rather than a specific isolated cause leading to a specific isolated outcome. To test this hypothesis, participants in both Singapore and the United States were asked either to generate analogies (e.g., "the early bird gets the worm") or causal factors (e.g., "get an early start on homework") for understanding an outcome (e.g., "being successful in school").  Results showed that Singaporeans reported that it is easier to generate and understand analogies related to causation than did Americans. They were also, on average, able to generate more analogies than Americans. Americans, on the other hand, reported that it was easier to generate and understand simple causal factors than did Singaporeans.  These findings may help facilitate conversations between East Asians and Westerners, and may help explain how different people understand their worlds.  Future work will continue to analyze whether such thinking occurs spontaneously and may account for cultural differences in causal attribution. This project facilitated collaboration between United States and East Asian collaborators (PI Elizabeth Gilbert is from the US and she worked for 8 weeks in the psychology and culture laboratory of CY Chiu, who is a researcher at the National Technological University in Singapore).  It also facilitated the testing of participants from outside of the United States (in Singapore), to help determine whether certain styles of thinking are basic to all people or whether cultural differences might exist.     Normal 0     false false false  EN-US JA X-NONE                                                                                                                                                                          table.MsoNormalTable  {mso-style-name:"Table Normal";  mso-tstyle-rowband-size:0;  mso-tstyle-colband-size:0;  mso-style-noshow:yes;  mso-style-priority:99;  mso-style-parent:";  mso-padding-alt:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;  mso-para-margin-top:0in;  mso-para-margin-right:0in;  mso-para-margin-bottom:10.0pt;  mso-para-margin-left:0in;  line-height:115%;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:11.0pt;  font-family:"Calibri","sans-serif";  mso-ascii-font-family:Calibri;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-hansi-font-family:Calibri;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;}         Last Modified: 08/01/2013       Submitted by: Elizabeth A Gilbert]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
