<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Modeling and Analysis of Fracture Network for Shale Gas Development and Its Environmental Impact</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gabor Szekely</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gszekely@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Hydraulic fracturing stimulation is one of the key technologies in shale gas development. Though it has been widely used in oil and gas industry for many years, it remains a great challenge to quantitatively characterize the hydraulic fracturing induced fracture network in shale gas development due to the complex shale gas formation and the lack of observational data. Consequently, it is extremely difficult to evaluate and predict its efficiency and environmental impacts. In this collaborative research project the investigators study the hydraulic stimulation induced fracture network through advanced statistical analysis and mathematical modelling. Armed with micro-seismic data and production yield curve, they develop a statistical dynamical system for the fracture network, mimicking the network formation process under imposed hydraulic pressure. A Bayesian framework is used for parameter inferences, utilizing prior knowledge of the geological structure of the field under study. A mathematical subsurface flow model and an advanced numerical method, the sub-region method, is used to link a given fracture network to the production yield curve, providing vital information of the unobservable fracture network underground. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By combining creative statistical analysis with advanced mathematical modelling and numerical method, the project addresses a very challenging application with important national interests. The project yields a better understanding of the hydraulic stimulation process, provides useful guidance for control and optimization of hydraulic fracturing process as well as assessing its environmental risks and consequences. Such knowledge helps policy makers to make more informed decision and more accurate cost analysis. The project spans both research and education aspects, including training of undergraduate, doctoral and post-doctoral students in interdisciplinary research, crossing the boundary of statistical analysis and numerical analysis, on an important application. The resulting software, available in public domain, will be used as an educational, research, and engineering tool well beyond the project duration.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1209124</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Guan</FirstName>
<LastName>Qin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Guan Qin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gqin@uwyo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7137434300</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000414022</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Houston</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>036837920</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042916627</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Houston]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>772044004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7215</Code>
<Text>OPPORTUNITIES FOR RESEARCH CMG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~72180</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~27820</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Hydraulic fracturing stimulation is one of the key technologies in shale gas development. Though it has been widely used in oil and gas industry for many years, it remains a great challenge to quantitatively characterize the hydraulic fracturing induced fracture network in shale gas development due to the complex shale gas formation and the lack of observational data. Consequently, it is extremely difficult to evaluate and predict its efficiency and environmental impacts.</p> <p>This project studies the hydraulic stimulation induced fracture network through advanced statistical analysis and mathematical modelling. Armed with micro-seismic data and production yield curve, we develop a statistical dynamical system for the fracture network, mimicking the network formation process under imposed hydraulic pressure. A Bayesian framework is used for parameter inferences, utilizing prior knowledge of the geological structure of the field under study. A mathematical subsurface flow model and an advanced numerical method, the sub-region method, is used to link a given fracture network to the production yield curve, providing vital information of the unobservable fracture network underground.</p> <p>This work is the first attempt to study hydraulic fracturing induced fracture network by integration of stochastic and deterministic numerical approaches. The project goal is achieved by a team of researchers with complimentary expertise in statistics and numerical simulation on subsurface flow processes. The great synergy between the statistical analysis and mathematical modelling makes it possible to attack this complex and difficult problem with a novel approach and with success.</p> <p>This project combines creative statistical analysis with advanced mathematical modelling and numerical method to address a very challenging application with important national interests. The developed dynamic model and the accompanying Monte Carlo methods create a new approach for network analysis, advancing the methodology development and application of statistical analysis of networks. The developed numerical simulation method on fluid flow in the fractured subsurface formation extends the existing methods in an important direction that allows for efficient computation and accurate approximation. The combination of statistical analysis and numerical method provides a unique synergy that links the information-rich micro-seismic data and fracture stimulation control variables to the observed production curve, allowing model calibration and thus environmental impact assessment and prediction. The project also results many other advances in theory and methods of statistics and mathematics.</p> <p>The project spans both research and education aspects, including training of undergraduate, doctoral and post-doctoral students in interdisciplinary research, crossing the boundary of statistical analysis and numerical analysis, on an important application. A better and more realistic understanding of hydraulic fracturing stimulation processes gained from this project provide useful guidance for control and optimization as well as assessing its environmental risks and consequences. Such a knowledge will help policy makers make more informed decisions. It also provides the industry more accurate cost analysis that will thus help improve the operation efficiency and integrity in shale gas development.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/13/2017<br>      Modified by: Guan&nbsp;Qin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Hydraulic fracturing stimulation is one of the key technologies in shale gas development. Though it has been widely used in oil and gas industry for many years, it remains a great challenge to quantitatively characterize the hydraulic fracturing induced fracture network in shale gas development due to the complex shale gas formation and the lack of observational data. Consequently, it is extremely difficult to evaluate and predict its efficiency and environmental impacts.  This project studies the hydraulic stimulation induced fracture network through advanced statistical analysis and mathematical modelling. Armed with micro-seismic data and production yield curve, we develop a statistical dynamical system for the fracture network, mimicking the network formation process under imposed hydraulic pressure. A Bayesian framework is used for parameter inferences, utilizing prior knowledge of the geological structure of the field under study. A mathematical subsurface flow model and an advanced numerical method, the sub-region method, is used to link a given fracture network to the production yield curve, providing vital information of the unobservable fracture network underground.  This work is the first attempt to study hydraulic fracturing induced fracture network by integration of stochastic and deterministic numerical approaches. The project goal is achieved by a team of researchers with complimentary expertise in statistics and numerical simulation on subsurface flow processes. The great synergy between the statistical analysis and mathematical modelling makes it possible to attack this complex and difficult problem with a novel approach and with success.  This project combines creative statistical analysis with advanced mathematical modelling and numerical method to address a very challenging application with important national interests. The developed dynamic model and the accompanying Monte Carlo methods create a new approach for network analysis, advancing the methodology development and application of statistical analysis of networks. The developed numerical simulation method on fluid flow in the fractured subsurface formation extends the existing methods in an important direction that allows for efficient computation and accurate approximation. The combination of statistical analysis and numerical method provides a unique synergy that links the information-rich micro-seismic data and fracture stimulation control variables to the observed production curve, allowing model calibration and thus environmental impact assessment and prediction. The project also results many other advances in theory and methods of statistics and mathematics.  The project spans both research and education aspects, including training of undergraduate, doctoral and post-doctoral students in interdisciplinary research, crossing the boundary of statistical analysis and numerical analysis, on an important application. A better and more realistic understanding of hydraulic fracturing stimulation processes gained from this project provide useful guidance for control and optimization as well as assessing its environmental risks and consequences. Such a knowledge will help policy makers make more informed decisions. It also provides the industry more accurate cost analysis that will thus help improve the operation efficiency and integrity in shale gas development.       Last Modified: 01/13/2017       Submitted by: Guan Qin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
