<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Materials World Network: Collaborative Research: Understanding the Optical Response of Designer Epsilon-Near-Zero Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>239998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>239998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tania M. Paskova</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;The understanding of, and control over, the optical properties of materials provides important insight into the fundamentals of light-matter interaction. At the same time, these capabilities serve as the foundation for the design and development of novel applications of optical science. This Materials World Network project explores the science behind the interaction of light with exotic material structures having vanishingly small dielectric permittivity, also known as epsilon-near-zero (ENZ) materials, that are potentially able to dramatically suppress diffraction of light and to extend the applicability of the quasi-static approximation to wavelength-scale systems. In this project, the researchers will create a novel material platform of "designer" ENZ media and will use this platform for building an analytical description of the optics of ENZ-related systems. Specifically, a set of experimental techniques will be developed for subwavelength lateral control of the permittivity profile of our materials, targeting important visible and IR frequency ranges. Optical characterization of these structures will be used to provide the foundation for novel numerical and analytical techniques capable of describing the light-matter interaction in complex ENZ-based media. It is expected that both the experimental and theoretical results of this work will have broader application for plasmonic- and meta- materials across the UV to THz wavelength ranges. The students involved in the project will benefit from the unique exposure to modern interdisciplinary projects combining materials science, chemistry, physics, and applied mathematics, and involving multiple institutions across the globe. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;Optical science is increasingly interwoven with many aspects of our everyday life, from optical communications, to imaging, to a broad range of optical sensing technologies in health-, environmental, and security-related applications. New optical materials, with unique, yet designer-enabled, properties, promise to further improve the quality or our life, and perhaps as importantly, provide a better understanding of the fundamental interaction between two building blocks of our Universe, light and matter. In this Materials World Network project, an international team will develop a unique new class of materials, known as epsilon-near-zero materials, and analyze the interaction of these materials with light. This research has the potential to provide a novel material platform for merging optics and electronics technologies, bringing together the benefits of high-speed optical communications with the compactness of integrated circuits. The complementary expertise of the participants will provide a unique opportunity to expose participating students to modern interdisciplinary international collaboration, enhancing multi-discipline and multi-cultural exchange. The interaction between the research teams and the broader community will aim at increasing the participation of emerging scientists in STEM-related disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported by the Electronic and Photonic Materials program and Office of Special Programs, Division of Materials Research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1209761</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Viktor</FirstName>
<LastName>Podolskiy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Viktor A Podolskiy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>viktor_podolskiy@uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9789343398</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000493531</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Lowell</Name>
<CityName>Lowell</CityName>
<ZipCode>018543692</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9789344170</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[600 Suffolk Street - Suite 212]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>956072490</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Lowell]]></Name>
<CityName>Lowell</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>018542827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One University Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7488</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS WORLD NETWORK</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~159999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~79999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Materials form the foundation for the very existence of human civilization. In this collaborative project three teams from University of Massachusetts at Lowell (UML), University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign (UIUC), and Kings College London (KCL) aimed to develop new complex composite material platforms aimed to control and utilize light. The UIUC team has focused on development of new semiconductor-based materials with highly controlled doping, operating at infrared range, important for a number of sensing, security, and thermal vision applications. At infrared frequencies, highly doped semiconductor materials, developed by UIUC, exhibit optical response similar to optical response of noble metals at visible frequencies. For this reason, the doped semiconductor platform is dubbed &ldquo;designer metal&rdquo;. The frequency at which material turns reflective, also known as epsilon-near-zero transition, was of particular interest to this program. KCL team was focused on a different kind of material platform that comprises array of aligned metallic nanowires embedded into transparent host, seen in Fig.2. Although different in structure and composition, nanowire metamaterials also exhibited tuneable epsilon-near-zero behavior, although at visible frequencies. UML team was responsible for development of analytical and numerical tools to model, understand, and utilize optical response of both material platforms.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The program has resulted in over 10 publications in professional media, as well as numerous invited and contributed presentations. In particular, UML-KCL collaboration have demonstrated that nanowire metamaterials can be used for optical detection of ultrasound waves, opening the door for design of new ultrasonic detectors that can be used for medical and materials science applications (Fig 2). In a separate project, the UML-KCL collaboration has developed a new platform for high resolution optical imaging (Fig.3) that can be potentially used for identification and characterization of nanoparticles, viruses, and other similar-sized objects.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The UIUC has perfected the designer metal material platform and, in collaboration with UML, have demonstrated that designer metal material platform can be used to construct a special type of waveguide, known as optical wire, that can be potentially used to realize high-speed processing based on manipulation of optical signals with composite media. A crossection of such optical wire is shown in Fig.1. The optical wire is a major building block for the new paradigm known as metatronics that combines the benefits of photonics and electronics. In a separate collaborative project, UML and UIUC have demonstrated a novel design of highly transparent, and at the same time highly conductive interface. In fact, the team has demonstrated a structured interface that has 50% of its surface covered by reflective metal and transmits over 90% of incident light (see Fig.4).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition, UML has developed a new computational formalism that allows for calculation of optical response of thin diffractive structures, known as metasurfaces. Computational tools, developed by the UML, can be readily used to understand optical response of a wide class of composite materials, and as such, are of potential interest to researchers and high-tech industries working in materials science, optics, and photonics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>At UML, the program contributed to Ph.D. research of two graduate students. Apart from educational and research activities, the teams have participated in a number of outreach events, promoting science and enhancing Physics education among high- and middle-school students and teachers.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Viktor&nbsp;A&nbsp;Podolskiy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1209761/1209761_10199716_1472573178633_ENZmodeHiRes--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1209761/1209761_10199716_1472573178633_ENZmodeHiRes--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Photonic wire"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1209761/1209761_10199716_1472573178633_ENZmodeHiRes--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Photonic wire"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The photonic wire, formed by doped semiconductor (designer metal) substrate and surrounded by highly-conducting metal. The wire operates on the surface mode that guides light (colored shading) along the air-semiconductor interface</div> <div class="imageCredit">C. Roberts, U Mass Lowell</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Viktor&nbsp;A&nbsp;Podolskiy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Photonic wire</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1209761/1209761_10199716_1472572998588_acoustoOptics--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1209761/1209761_10199716_1472572998588_acoustoOptics--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Metamaterials-enhanced ultrasound sensing."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1209761/1209761_10199716_1472572998588_acoustoOptics--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Metamaterials-enhanced ultrasound sensing."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Reflection of metamaterial (yellow pillars) is monitored with optical beam (thick arrows). Acoustic pressure wave (cloud-shaped signal) modulates the response of the liquid on top of metamaterial (not shown), changing the amplitude of the reflected light.</div> <div class="imageCredit">V. Yakovlev, Texas A&M U</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Viktor&nbsp;A&nbsp;Podolskiy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Metamaterials-enhanced ultrasound sensing.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1209761/1209761_10199716_1472572764337_optica.cover.vp--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1209761/1209761_10199716_1472572764337_optica.cover.vp--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Interscale Mixing Microscopy"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1209761/1209761_10199716_1472572764337_optica.cover.vp--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Interscale Mixing Microscopy"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The technique allows characterization of nano-objects positioned in proximity of diffraction gratings (yellow structure). The system is illuminated by a laser beam, and the signal is collected through an objective. The post-processed signal (background) reveals the position and size of the object</div> <div class="imageCredit">V. Podolskiy, UML</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Viktor&nbsp;A&nbsp;Podolskiy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Interscale Mixing Microscopy</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1209761/1209761_10199716_1472573639864_adma.201505111--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1209761/1209761_10199716_1472573639864_adma.201505111--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Optically transparent electrically conductive interface."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1209761/1209761_10199716_1472573639864_adma.201505111--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Optically transparent electrically conductive interface."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">In the process known as metal-assisted chemical etching, semiconductor pillars emerge through the holes in the metallic sheet (background). Although 50% of surface is covered by metal, the interface transmits more than 90% of incident light by guided guiding it around the metal (inset).</div> <div class="imageCredit">C. Roberts, U Mass Lowell</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Viktor&nbsp;A&nbsp;Podolskiy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Optically transparent electrically conductive interface.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Materials form the foundation for the very existence of human civilization. In this collaborative project three teams from University of Massachusetts at Lowell (UML), University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign (UIUC), and Kings College London (KCL) aimed to develop new complex composite material platforms aimed to control and utilize light. The UIUC team has focused on development of new semiconductor-based materials with highly controlled doping, operating at infrared range, important for a number of sensing, security, and thermal vision applications. At infrared frequencies, highly doped semiconductor materials, developed by UIUC, exhibit optical response similar to optical response of noble metals at visible frequencies. For this reason, the doped semiconductor platform is dubbed "designer metal". The frequency at which material turns reflective, also known as epsilon-near-zero transition, was of particular interest to this program. KCL team was focused on a different kind of material platform that comprises array of aligned metallic nanowires embedded into transparent host, seen in Fig.2. Although different in structure and composition, nanowire metamaterials also exhibited tuneable epsilon-near-zero behavior, although at visible frequencies. UML team was responsible for development of analytical and numerical tools to model, understand, and utilize optical response of both material platforms.     The program has resulted in over 10 publications in professional media, as well as numerous invited and contributed presentations. In particular, UML-KCL collaboration have demonstrated that nanowire metamaterials can be used for optical detection of ultrasound waves, opening the door for design of new ultrasonic detectors that can be used for medical and materials science applications (Fig 2). In a separate project, the UML-KCL collaboration has developed a new platform for high resolution optical imaging (Fig.3) that can be potentially used for identification and characterization of nanoparticles, viruses, and other similar-sized objects.     The UIUC has perfected the designer metal material platform and, in collaboration with UML, have demonstrated that designer metal material platform can be used to construct a special type of waveguide, known as optical wire, that can be potentially used to realize high-speed processing based on manipulation of optical signals with composite media. A crossection of such optical wire is shown in Fig.1. The optical wire is a major building block for the new paradigm known as metatronics that combines the benefits of photonics and electronics. In a separate collaborative project, UML and UIUC have demonstrated a novel design of highly transparent, and at the same time highly conductive interface. In fact, the team has demonstrated a structured interface that has 50% of its surface covered by reflective metal and transmits over 90% of incident light (see Fig.4).     In addition, UML has developed a new computational formalism that allows for calculation of optical response of thin diffractive structures, known as metasurfaces. Computational tools, developed by the UML, can be readily used to understand optical response of a wide class of composite materials, and as such, are of potential interest to researchers and high-tech industries working in materials science, optics, and photonics.     At UML, the program contributed to Ph.D. research of two graduate students. Apart from educational and research activities, the teams have participated in a number of outreach events, promoting science and enhancing Physics education among high- and middle-school students and teachers.           Last Modified: 08/30/2016       Submitted by: Viktor A Podolskiy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
