<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in Taiwan</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5836.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5836</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds Adrienne George of the University of South Florida to conduct a research project, entitled "Cataloguing coral diseases and parasites in Taiwan," during the summer of 2012 at Biodiversity Research Center, Academia Sinica in Taipei, Taiwan.  The host scientist is Dr. Chaolun Allen Chen.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit lies within identifying the health issues of Taiwan's coral so that management practices can be implemented to protect one of Taiwan's most important natural resources. This will be the first comprehensive study to characterize and identify the coral diseases of Taiwan.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Broader Impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language.  These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1209902</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrienne</FirstName>
<LastName>George</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrienne George</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>2158689079</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000604723</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George                  Adrienne</Name>
<CityName>St. Petersburg</CityName>
<ZipCode>337015016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George                  Adrienne]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>337015016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5924</Code>
<Text>TAIWAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~5836</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Cataloguing coral&nbsp;diseases in Taiwan</strong></span></p> <p>This project characterized coral diseases in Taiwan through coral health surveys, analysis of carbon requirements of the microbes in coral mucus, denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (DGGE), and histological examination at near shore reefs near Taipei, Taiwan (Bitou and Yeliu) and Green Island, and Taitung (Figure 1). Because coral mucus is the first line of defense against disease, the Biolog Ecoplate<sup>TM</sup> was a useful tool to detect differences in microbial assemblages in the surface mucopolysaccharide (mucus) layer when comparing healthy and diseased corals. DGGE provided insight into the microbial communities present not only in the mucus, but throughout the coral. Histological examination was essential to document structural changes in coral tissue in response to diseases. The gross lesions from diseased samples fit into four categories: discoloration associated with color loss (bleaching), discoloration associated with pink line syndrome, growth anomalies, and tissue loss (Figures 2-5). There were 14 samples collected for Biolog Ecoplate<sup>TM</sup> analysis (each sample included a mucus sample from a healthy region of the coral and from an abnormal region of the coral) along with a water sample from each site (Bitou and Yeliu), 34 samples collected for DGGE analysis along with a water sample from each site, and 35 samples collected and processed for histology.&nbsp; Preliminary results of the Biolog Ecoplates suggest that samples with abnormalities utilized more carbon sources than healthy samples, indicating that there is a microbe or group of microbes present within the lesion that is not present in the healthy area of the same coral (Figure 6). Preliminary results of DGGE suggest that the microbial communities varied between the diseased region of the coral and the healthy region of the same coral. Sequencing of DGGE bands are currently being performed to identify the microbial communities. Histological samples are still being analyzed.</p> <p><br /><strong>Intellectual Merits</strong><br />This is the first comprehensive study to characterize and identify the coral diseases of Taiwan. The intellectual merit lies within identifying the health issues of Taiwan&rsquo;s corals so that management practices can be implemented to protect one of Taiwan&rsquo;s most important natural resources.</p> <p><br /><strong>Broader Impacts</strong><br />The broader impacts lie within the training of an under-represented female and the wide dissemination of results including a catalogue that will be&nbsp;posted on Dr. Chen&rsquo;s Academia Sinica (host) website made available to scientists and the public. The findings of this study will be included in the PI&rsquo;s PhD dissertation, and compared to findings from her master&rsquo;s thesis. Histological slides will be scanned and uploaded into Aperio, a software that allows scientists to view slides digitally.&nbsp; Slides from PI&rsquo;s master&rsquo;s thesis were uploaded into Aperio, and professors at the University of Florida used the slides to teach undergraduate, graduate and veterinarian students coral histology. The histological slides generated from this research experience will be available to do the same.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2012<br>      Modified by: Adrienne&nbsp;George</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Cataloguing coral diseases in Taiwan  This project characterized coral diseases in Taiwan through coral health surveys, analysis of carbon requirements of the microbes in coral mucus, denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (DGGE), and histological examination at near shore reefs near Taipei, Taiwan (Bitou and Yeliu) and Green Island, and Taitung (Figure 1). Because coral mucus is the first line of defense against disease, the Biolog EcoplateTM was a useful tool to detect differences in microbial assemblages in the surface mucopolysaccharide (mucus) layer when comparing healthy and diseased corals. DGGE provided insight into the microbial communities present not only in the mucus, but throughout the coral. Histological examination was essential to document structural changes in coral tissue in response to diseases. The gross lesions from diseased samples fit into four categories: discoloration associated with color loss (bleaching), discoloration associated with pink line syndrome, growth anomalies, and tissue loss (Figures 2-5). There were 14 samples collected for Biolog EcoplateTM analysis (each sample included a mucus sample from a healthy region of the coral and from an abnormal region of the coral) along with a water sample from each site (Bitou and Yeliu), 34 samples collected for DGGE analysis along with a water sample from each site, and 35 samples collected and processed for histology.  Preliminary results of the Biolog Ecoplates suggest that samples with abnormalities utilized more carbon sources than healthy samples, indicating that there is a microbe or group of microbes present within the lesion that is not present in the healthy area of the same coral (Figure 6). Preliminary results of DGGE suggest that the microbial communities varied between the diseased region of the coral and the healthy region of the same coral. Sequencing of DGGE bands are currently being performed to identify the microbial communities. Histological samples are still being analyzed.   Intellectual Merits This is the first comprehensive study to characterize and identify the coral diseases of Taiwan. The intellectual merit lies within identifying the health issues of TaiwanÆs corals so that management practices can be implemented to protect one of TaiwanÆs most important natural resources.   Broader Impacts The broader impacts lie within the training of an under-represented female and the wide dissemination of results including a catalogue that will be posted on Dr. ChenÆs Academia Sinica (host) website made available to scientists and the public. The findings of this study will be included in the PIÆs PhD dissertation, and compared to findings from her masterÆs thesis. Histological slides will be scanned and uploaded into Aperio, a software that allows scientists to view slides digitally.  Slides from PIÆs masterÆs thesis were uploaded into Aperio, and professors at the University of Florida used the slides to teach undergraduate, graduate and veterinarian students coral histology. The histological slides generated from this research experience will be available to do the same.       Last Modified: 12/01/2012       Submitted by: Adrienne George]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
