<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute for FY 2012 in China</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5836.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5836</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds Henry Lo of the University of Massachusetts Boston to conduct a research project, entitled "A graph-based road model for plotting GPS trajectories," during the summer of 2012 at Tongji University in Shanghai, China.  The host scientist is Professor Weian Wang.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of the research project lies in advancing GPS information extraction, the production of a general graph model for understanding trajectories, and developoing a framework from which further data mining techniques on spatio-temporal sequences can be developed.  The research involves merging GPS and road data into a network model to understand traffic flows and trajectories and developing algorithms that quickly and correctly extract interesting patterns from the model.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Broader Impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1209646</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Henry</FirstName>
<LastName>Lo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Henry Lo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6173192011</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000607316</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Institute for Reproducible Research</Name>
<CityName>Somerville</CityName>
<ZipCode>021453641</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Boston]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021253393</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~5836</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>My original project was to develop techniques to organize and understand GPS traces. &nbsp;But, government restrictions on who gets to access GPS data, as well as the fact that all documentation for the project was in Chinese, made working on this project infeasible. &nbsp;Instead, I worked on a project to predict landslides from sensor data.</p> <p>The Sichuan province of China is covered by mountains, and rains year-round. &nbsp;These conditions cause many landslides in this area, which regularly block road traffic and damage infrastructure.</p> <p>My host institute runs a research project to monitor and predict landslide activity. &nbsp;At first, they developed a landslide simulator called MUNOLD. &nbsp;THe platform consisted of a slope of dirt, sand, and clay, with various sensors attached. &nbsp;Experiments to simulate landslides began with a steady pouring of "rain", until the landslide actually occurred. &nbsp;Meanwhile, acceleration, humidity,water porosity, and other readings were fed into a database in real time.</p> <p>With this platform, the group collected data from a successful landslide simulation. &nbsp;One of the reasons for this data collection was to see whether models can be developed which would predict landslide failure from sensor data over time. &nbsp;With my expertise in data mining and statistics, I attempted to do so by applying an often mentioned model, the Voight model of material failure, to the data. &nbsp;If the model was successful, it may be deployed in a real sensor network in the mountains of Sichuan to monitor landslides.</p> <p>The Voight model, which was developed in the wake of the Mt. St. Helens explosion, generalizes several material failure models. &nbsp;It describes the evolution of sensor readings from a wide range of natural catastrophes, predicting that the differences between consecutive readings will increase exponentially as the catastrophe nears. &nbsp;In other words, quickly changing sensor readings would indicate looming catastrophe; so theoretically, detecting these quick changes would be useful for predicting the time of failure.</p> <p>I first attempted to see whether or not this model described our data. &nbsp;I found that for the accelerometer and tiltmeter readings, it did. &nbsp;But, when I tried to use the model to predict the time of failure, the predictions fluctuated wildly. &nbsp;Most of the predictions were nowhere near the actual time of failure. &nbsp;I later found that the model itself is very susceptible to noisy measurements, and has significant difficulty in predicting time of failure.</p> <p>In conclusion, we found that the Voight model for material failure by itself was not a reliable method of determining when a landslide would occur. &nbsp;Thought this model is highly regarded and used throughout the field, we hope that our findings indicate that the model is not very useful when attempting to predict landslides, and that newer methods should be considered.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/03/2013<br>      Modified by: Henry&nbsp;Lo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2012/1209646/1209646_10174739_1354401096213_landslide--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2012/1209646/1209646_10174739_1354401096213_landslide--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Landslide in Sichuan"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2012/1209646/1209646_10174739_1354401096213_landslide--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Lan...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ My original project was to develop techniques to organize and understand GPS traces.  But, government restrictions on who gets to access GPS data, as well as the fact that all documentation for the project was in Chinese, made working on this project infeasible.  Instead, I worked on a project to predict landslides from sensor data.  The Sichuan province of China is covered by mountains, and rains year-round.  These conditions cause many landslides in this area, which regularly block road traffic and damage infrastructure.  My host institute runs a research project to monitor and predict landslide activity.  At first, they developed a landslide simulator called MUNOLD.  THe platform consisted of a slope of dirt, sand, and clay, with various sensors attached.  Experiments to simulate landslides began with a steady pouring of "rain", until the landslide actually occurred.  Meanwhile, acceleration, humidity,water porosity, and other readings were fed into a database in real time.  With this platform, the group collected data from a successful landslide simulation.  One of the reasons for this data collection was to see whether models can be developed which would predict landslide failure from sensor data over time.  With my expertise in data mining and statistics, I attempted to do so by applying an often mentioned model, the Voight model of material failure, to the data.  If the model was successful, it may be deployed in a real sensor network in the mountains of Sichuan to monitor landslides.  The Voight model, which was developed in the wake of the Mt. St. Helens explosion, generalizes several material failure models.  It describes the evolution of sensor readings from a wide range of natural catastrophes, predicting that the differences between consecutive readings will increase exponentially as the catastrophe nears.  In other words, quickly changing sensor readings would indicate looming catastrophe; so theoretically, detecting these quick changes would be useful for predicting the time of failure.  I first attempted to see whether or not this model described our data.  I found that for the accelerometer and tiltmeter readings, it did.  But, when I tried to use the model to predict the time of failure, the predictions fluctuated wildly.  Most of the predictions were nowhere near the actual time of failure.  I later found that the model itself is very susceptible to noisy measurements, and has significant difficulty in predicting time of failure.  In conclusion, we found that the Voight model for material failure by itself was not a reliable method of determining when a landslide would occur.  Thought this model is highly regarded and used throughout the field, we hope that our findings indicate that the model is not very useful when attempting to predict landslides, and that newer methods should be considered.       Last Modified: 06/03/2013       Submitted by: Henry Lo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
