<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Do the concomitant effects of pH and ammonium concentration on ammonia availability explain differential ammonia oxidation by bacteria and archaea?</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Ammonia oxidation, a key step in the global nitrogen cycle, is only known to be performed by two groups of microorganisms, ammonia oxidizing bacteria and archaea. Although these groups both occur in large numbers in soil environments, they, like many microorganisms, may only be active under certain conditions. This study will investigate how environmental conditions interact to control the activity of ammonia oxidizing bacteria and archaea. Soil samples will be exposed to different environmental conditions and the activity of ammonia oxidizing bacteria and archaea will be measured using molecular based techniques. Experimental treatments will include variation in ammonium concentrations and soil pH, both of which have been shown to individually alter the activity of cultured representatives from these two groups. Use of naturally occurring populations of soil microorganisms will lend field relevance to these culture-based observations, and should lead to a better understanding of nitrification by investigating the ecology of the organisms that perform this important nutrient transformation in the nitrogen cycle.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of this project will include an additional research opportunity for the doctoral student. In addition, undergraduate students will be involved in various aspects of this project, providing them with exposure to research and opportunities to develop their own independent research projects.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1210607</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Barrett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John E Barrett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jebarre@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402313827</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000190056</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/17/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Norman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey S Norman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jsnorman7@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5408086446</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000607400</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/17/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1010 Derring Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~14999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Ammonia oxidizing microbes play a pivotal role in soil ecosystems, oxidizing ammonia, a form of inorganic nitrogen, and use the energy from this process to fix atmospheric carbon similarly to the way plants use sunlight.&nbsp; The actions of these microbes have important influences on nitrogen availability in terrestrial environments.&nbsp; Ammonia oxidation is the first step of nitrification, the two-step biological conversion of ammonia to nitrate, a highly mobile form form of inorganic nitrogen. &nbsp;While ammonia does not readily move through soils due to its positive charge and affinity for the negatively charged surfaces of clays, organic matter and soil colloids, nitrate is highly mobile due to its negative charge.&nbsp; Thus, understanding the drivers of ammonia oxidizing microbe distributions and activity is critical to predicting the availability and mobility of nitrogen in both terrestrial landscapes and downstream aquatic environments.&nbsp; This project sought to understand the drivers of ammonia oxidizing microbe activity in soil ecosystems.</p> <p>Ammonia oxidizing microbes are broadly divided into two groups: ammonia-oxidizing bacteria (AOB) and ammonia-oxidizing archaea (AOA).&nbsp; AOA and AOB co-occur in most environments and play the same ecological role in soils. &nbsp;However, activity by these groups is differentially-affected by various environmental conditions, most-notably ammonium availability and soil pH. &nbsp;In this project, we used techniques from molecular biology in conjunction with field-based incubation experiments to assess the activity of AOA and AOB in temperate forest soils.&nbsp; We predicted that these low-ammonium acidic systems would favor AOA activity over AOB activity based on laboratory observations by other researchers.&nbsp; However, we found that activity by both groups were necessary to understand patterns of nitrification in the field.&nbsp; From these data we were also able to develop a statistical model to investigate patterns in carbon and nitrogen metabolism by each group and we found that forest soil AOA and AOB are remarkably similar in their growth requirements, despite the large phylogenetic distance between these groups.</p> <p>This grant provided critical research support for graduate student and Co-PI Jeff Norman, who successfully defended his PhD. dissertation entitled &ldquo;Environmental Controls on the Diversity, Growth, and Activity of Ammonia-Oxidizing Microorganisms in Temperate Forest Soils&rdquo; in December of 2013.&nbsp; Dr. Norman is now a postdoctoral research fellow in the Department of Plant Biology at Michigan State University.&nbsp; So far this grant has generated one publication in the journal &ldquo;Soil Biology and Biochemistry&rdquo; and two more papers are currently being prepared for publication based on work funded by this grant.&nbsp; This NSF grant supported undergraduate research at Virginia Tech as well:&nbsp; Mahtaab Bagherzadeh, a biological sciences major, is currently continuing research into microbial community dynamics at Coweeta Hydrologic Laboratory, the NSF funded research site where the aforementioned investigations were conducted, using funding from this grant as well.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2014<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;E&nbsp;Barrett</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Ammonia oxidizing microbes play a pivotal role in soil ecosystems, oxidizing ammonia, a form of inorganic nitrogen, and use the energy from this process to fix atmospheric carbon similarly to the way plants use sunlight.  The actions of these microbes have important influences on nitrogen availability in terrestrial environments.  Ammonia oxidation is the first step of nitrification, the two-step biological conversion of ammonia to nitrate, a highly mobile form form of inorganic nitrogen.  While ammonia does not readily move through soils due to its positive charge and affinity for the negatively charged surfaces of clays, organic matter and soil colloids, nitrate is highly mobile due to its negative charge.  Thus, understanding the drivers of ammonia oxidizing microbe distributions and activity is critical to predicting the availability and mobility of nitrogen in both terrestrial landscapes and downstream aquatic environments.  This project sought to understand the drivers of ammonia oxidizing microbe activity in soil ecosystems.  Ammonia oxidizing microbes are broadly divided into two groups: ammonia-oxidizing bacteria (AOB) and ammonia-oxidizing archaea (AOA).  AOA and AOB co-occur in most environments and play the same ecological role in soils.  However, activity by these groups is differentially-affected by various environmental conditions, most-notably ammonium availability and soil pH.  In this project, we used techniques from molecular biology in conjunction with field-based incubation experiments to assess the activity of AOA and AOB in temperate forest soils.  We predicted that these low-ammonium acidic systems would favor AOA activity over AOB activity based on laboratory observations by other researchers.  However, we found that activity by both groups were necessary to understand patterns of nitrification in the field.  From these data we were also able to develop a statistical model to investigate patterns in carbon and nitrogen metabolism by each group and we found that forest soil AOA and AOB are remarkably similar in their growth requirements, despite the large phylogenetic distance between these groups.  This grant provided critical research support for graduate student and Co-PI Jeff Norman, who successfully defended his PhD. dissertation entitled "Environmental Controls on the Diversity, Growth, and Activity of Ammonia-Oxidizing Microorganisms in Temperate Forest Soils" in December of 2013.  Dr. Norman is now a postdoctoral research fellow in the Department of Plant Biology at Michigan State University.  So far this grant has generated one publication in the journal "Soil Biology and Biochemistry" and two more papers are currently being prepared for publication based on work funded by this grant.  This NSF grant supported undergraduate research at Virginia Tech as well:  Mahtaab Bagherzadeh, a biological sciences major, is currently continuing research into microbial community dynamics at Coweeta Hydrologic Laboratory, the NSF funded research site where the aforementioned investigations were conducted, using funding from this grant as well.          Last Modified: 09/29/2014       Submitted by: John E Barrett]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
