<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Materials World Network: Nanostructuring and Phase Transformations in Beta-Ti Alloys</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diana Farkas</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technical Summary:&lt;br/&gt;Researchers at the University of California at Davis, USA (UCD) and the Ufa State Aviation Technical University, Ufa, Russia (USATU) will investigate the influence of nanostructuring on the phase transformations and mechanical behavior in beta-Ti alloys.  A variety of materials synthesis and processing techniques including mechanical alloying by cryomilling, spark plasma sintering (SPS), equal-channel angular pressing (ECAP) and high pressure torsion (HPT) will be implemented to synthesize nanostructured beta-Ti alloys.  Fundamental information generated will be used to establish the relationship between nanostructuring characteristics, thermal stability, phase transformations, and mechanical response in beta-Ti alloys.  Microstructure characterization studies using advanced diagnostic techniques (i.e., SEM, TEM), will provide an  understanding of the effect of the mechanical alloying, SPS and severe plastic deformation (ECAP/HPT) processing on nanostructural features, and furthermore understanding of fundamental phenomena (e.g., thermal stability, phase transformations and mechanical behavior) associated with nanostructuring in beta-Ti alloys.  Mechanical behavior will be studied to establish the relationship between nanostructural features and mechanical response (i.e., elastic modulus, strength, ductility) in nanostructured beta-Ti alloys.  Implementation of in-situ SEM and TEM mechanical characterization will provide direct observation of the dynamic deformation and microstructural changes in nanostructured beta-Ti alloys.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-Technical Summary:&lt;br/&gt;Ti alloys are of scientific and technological interest, and in particular nanostructured beta-Ti alloys may exhibit a high strength with low elastic modulus, which are very attractive for biomedical applications, for example.  The collaborative research program will contribute towards the establishment of a fundamental understanding of the science of nanostructured beta-Ti alloys, as well as providing insight into the fundamental relationships that link alloy composition, microstructure and processing history of nanostructured alloys with mechanical behavior.  The novel approaches to be implemented, based on complementary expertise and resources between University of California at Davis, USA (UCD) and the Ufa State Aviation Technical University, Ufa, will generate comprehensive information that is currently lacking for understanding of the relationship between nanostructuring, phase transformation and mechanical behavior in beta-Ti alloys and beyond.  This, in turn, will ultimately impact the development of Ti materials with potential for applications in the biomedical, aerospace, and automotive industries.  The research activities will help nurture intellectual collaborations and academic exchanges through mutual visits, in particular with participation of students at the graduate and undergraduate levels between UCD and USATU.  This international collaboration will also enrich UCD's outreach program and will involve regional universities, colleges, and K-12.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is supported by the Metals and Metallic Nanostructures program and the Office of Special Programs, Division of Materials Research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1210437</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Enrique</FirstName>
<LastName>Lavernia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Enrique J Lavernia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lavernia@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9492946296</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000478605</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956165929</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Shields Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7488</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS WORLD NETWORK</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This collaborative NSF research program has contributed to the establishment of a fundamental understanding of the science of nanostructured Ti alloys, as well as providing insight into the fundamental relationships that link alloy composition, microstructure and processing history of nanostructured alloys with mechanical behavior.&nbsp; The research has generated comprehensive information that is useful for understanding the relationship between synthesis/processing, microstructure (e.g., grain refinement, phase transformation) and mechanical behavior in Ti alloys.&nbsp; For instance, one of the research efforts was dedicated to investigate phase transformations in Ti-Nb-Ta-Zr alloys synthesized by equal channel angular pressing (ECAP) technique.&nbsp; The phenomenon of high-strain-induced reverse martensitic transformation was documented in an ultra-fine-grained (UFG) Ti&ndash;Nb&ndash;Ta&ndash;Zr alloy processed by ECAP at room temperature. The results showed that a martensitic transformation from BCC &beta; matrix to orthorhombic &alpha;&Prime;martensite occurs under the relatively low-strain ECAP conditions, whereas a large portion (~34%) of martensite reversely transforms into a &beta; matrix phase with the increase in ECAP strain to a high value (e.g. 4) with a corresponding reduction in &alpha;&Prime;-lath thickness and refinement of grain size in the matrix phase. Our results suggest that the high-strain-induced internal heating effect is not sufficient to trigger the observed reverse martensitic transformation, whereas other mechanisms, e.g. dislocation activity under high-strain conditions, likely contribute to this phenomenon.&nbsp; Additional research efforts were devoted to an investigation of bimodal alloy (TiFeCo)NbAl with ultra-high yield strength of 2050 MPa and plasticity of 19.7%.&nbsp; The results suggest that these remarkable mechanical properties were attributed to the blocking, branching and multiplication of &beta;-Ti lamellae, dislocation interactions in Ti(Fe, Co) lamellae, and the stability of the coherent interface.&nbsp; The Ti(Fe, Co) lamellae played an unusual role as the ductile phase, instead of &beta;-Ti lamellae, which can be rationalized on the orientational relationship of the coherent&nbsp;interface and the actual slip directions of the crystal planes (-110) and (1-10) of Ti(Fe, Co) according to the crystallographic slip theory.</p> <p>The collaborative research program has generated fundamental knowledge that will ultimately impact the development of Ti materials with potential for applications in the biomedical, aerospace, and automotive industries.&nbsp; The research activities has promoted intellectual collaborations and academic exchanges between UC Davis and Ufa State Aviation Technical University (USATU), via joint research efforts in novel materials processing, i.e., high pressure torsion, equal channel angular extrusion, and mutual visits.&nbsp; Graduate students from USATU visited UC Davis to conduct joint research and give technical presentation, and postdoctoral researched from UC Davis made a visit to Russia for further technical exchange. &nbsp;This program has also promoted international student and postdoc exchanges with universities in China including Shanghai Jiaotong University (Shanghai, China), South China University of Technology (Guangzhou, China), and Wuhan University of Technology (Wuhan, China).&nbsp; This international collaboration has also enriched UCD&rsquo;s outreach program. &nbsp;&nbsp;Graduate student who worked on the program introduced the NSF research to visiting Japanese and Chinese undergraduate students via UC Davis Extension exchange program.</p> <p>Through the performance period (09/01/2012 to 08/31/2016), this program  has generated eleven journal papers, one conference proceedings paper,  and three conference presentations, and trained two graduate students  and five postdoctoral researchers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Enrique&nbsp;J&nbsp;Lavernia</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This collaborative NSF research program has contributed to the establishment of a fundamental understanding of the science of nanostructured Ti alloys, as well as providing insight into the fundamental relationships that link alloy composition, microstructure and processing history of nanostructured alloys with mechanical behavior.  The research has generated comprehensive information that is useful for understanding the relationship between synthesis/processing, microstructure (e.g., grain refinement, phase transformation) and mechanical behavior in Ti alloys.  For instance, one of the research efforts was dedicated to investigate phase transformations in Ti-Nb-Ta-Zr alloys synthesized by equal channel angular pressing (ECAP) technique.  The phenomenon of high-strain-induced reverse martensitic transformation was documented in an ultra-fine-grained (UFG) Ti&ndash;Nb&ndash;Ta&ndash;Zr alloy processed by ECAP at room temperature. The results showed that a martensitic transformation from BCC &beta; matrix to orthorhombic &alpha;&Prime;martensite occurs under the relatively low-strain ECAP conditions, whereas a large portion (~34%) of martensite reversely transforms into a &beta; matrix phase with the increase in ECAP strain to a high value (e.g. 4) with a corresponding reduction in &alpha;&Prime;-lath thickness and refinement of grain size in the matrix phase. Our results suggest that the high-strain-induced internal heating effect is not sufficient to trigger the observed reverse martensitic transformation, whereas other mechanisms, e.g. dislocation activity under high-strain conditions, likely contribute to this phenomenon.  Additional research efforts were devoted to an investigation of bimodal alloy (TiFeCo)NbAl with ultra-high yield strength of 2050 MPa and plasticity of 19.7%.  The results suggest that these remarkable mechanical properties were attributed to the blocking, branching and multiplication of &beta;-Ti lamellae, dislocation interactions in Ti(Fe, Co) lamellae, and the stability of the coherent interface.  The Ti(Fe, Co) lamellae played an unusual role as the ductile phase, instead of &beta;-Ti lamellae, which can be rationalized on the orientational relationship of the coherent interface and the actual slip directions of the crystal planes (-110) and (1-10) of Ti(Fe, Co) according to the crystallographic slip theory.  The collaborative research program has generated fundamental knowledge that will ultimately impact the development of Ti materials with potential for applications in the biomedical, aerospace, and automotive industries.  The research activities has promoted intellectual collaborations and academic exchanges between UC Davis and Ufa State Aviation Technical University (USATU), via joint research efforts in novel materials processing, i.e., high pressure torsion, equal channel angular extrusion, and mutual visits.  Graduate students from USATU visited UC Davis to conduct joint research and give technical presentation, and postdoctoral researched from UC Davis made a visit to Russia for further technical exchange.  This program has also promoted international student and postdoc exchanges with universities in China including Shanghai Jiaotong University (Shanghai, China), South China University of Technology (Guangzhou, China), and Wuhan University of Technology (Wuhan, China).  This international collaboration has also enriched UCD?s outreach program.   Graduate student who worked on the program introduced the NSF research to visiting Japanese and Chinese undergraduate students via UC Davis Extension exchange program.  Through the performance period (09/01/2012 to 08/31/2016), this program  has generated eleven journal papers, one conference proceedings paper,  and three conference presentations, and trained two graduate students  and five postdoctoral researchers.       Last Modified: 11/30/2016       Submitted by: Enrique J Lavernia]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
