<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Materials World Network: Complex Oxides for Heterogeneous Optoelectronic Integration</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Z.  Ying</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cying@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY: &lt;br/&gt;This US-UK Materials World Network collaboration focuses on adding magneto-optical (MO) and electro-optical (EO) properties that are orders of magnitude greater than currently available to semiconductor photonics by integrating both doped yttrium iron garnet and lithium niobate, respectively, onto III-V structures. With motivations such as source-integrated photonic integrated circuits and electronically-reconfigurable opto-electronic integrated circuits, there has been intense work on adding MO and EO materials to semiconductor platforms. However, complex oxide integration requires thermal crystallization methods together with thermal expansion mismatch, substrate dissociation, and interfacial diffusion. This work aims to converge on a solution involving controlled strain and interfaces using buffer layers and seed layers (both ~10 nm), oxide patterning, and rapid thermal annealing for minimized thermal treatment. Subsequent doping in thicker films is used to meet specifications of maximized MO or EO activity. The optical, magnetic, and electronic properties are characterized to analyze the both the structures and compositions, and the materials performance is tested on carefully designed waveguide structures. In the case of MO integration, non-reciprocity is expected to be realized without the high-power options. Integrated ferroelectric oxides also unlocks doors to EO functionality in both near and long term applications, such as active frequency modulation and reconfigurable photonics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY: &lt;br/&gt;This research project is a collaboration between US and UK scientists. The research focuses on integration of magneto-optical and electro-optical materials with semiconductor materials, opening doors for novel properties such as enhanced magneto-optical activity and new devices such as photonic isolators so that optical sources can be integrated with photonic integrated circuits. The team meets online with tools that enable attendees to see each other's faces, writings and slides, and to hear each other's voices. The pedagogy of these tools will be an interesting side study. In addition, students exchange time in each other's lab to gain important experience with new cultures and new science. It is anticipated that the online/exchange interaction model developed here in international research will be extended to US-Kenya and UK-Pakistan collaborations in the future - building on relationships that are already underway.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project is supported by the Electronic and Photonic Materials program and Office of Special Programs, Division of Materials Research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1210818</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bethanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Stadler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bethanie J Stadler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>stadler@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126261628</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000281329</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7488</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS WORLD NETWORK</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Outcomes for Materials World Network: Complex oxides for heterogeneous optoelectronic integration</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The goal of this was to bring new functionalities to semiconductor systems by using materials research to identify paths of integration for functional oxide claddings onto semiconductor structures, such as waveguides.&nbsp; A US oxide processing specialist (Stadler) worked together with a UK semiconductor photonics expert (Hutchings) to add new materials to the palettes of designers interested in electronics, photonics, sensors, and unimagined future areas.&nbsp; Specifically, magneto-optical (MO) garnets and electro-optical (EO) perovskites were integrated with Si on insulator (SOI) waveguides. These oxides are orders of magnitude greater than the materials currently available to semiconductors.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Intellectual Merit. </em>Here, the classic materials research tetrahedron (processing, structure, properties, performance) was used to rapidly converge on a solution involving controlled strain and interfaces using buffer layers and seed layers (both~10nm), oxide patterning, and rapid thermal annealing for minimized thermal treatment.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Processing/structure. In magneto-optics, a new garnet (terbium iron garnet- TIG) was sputtered onto a variety of substrates and annealed at low thermal budgets by rapid thermal annealing.&nbsp; The garnet structure was found after anneals as low as 750C, Fig. 1.&nbsp; Its properties were found to be superior to the standard yttrium iron garnet (YIG) with 2.5x the Faraday rotation than updoped YIG. This new TIG garnet was then doped with Bi and Ce and found to form garnet <em>without the seedlayers</em> required by YIG.&nbsp; This is significant because the light in a garnet cladding will only include the evanescent tail from the underlying Si guide, Fig. 2.&nbsp; A seedlayer therefore simply represents at best a deadspace between the guide and the active garnet cladding.&nbsp; If a garnet, such as YIG, is used as the seedlayer, its sign is opposite to the active garnet, which is even more detrimental than a deadspace.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In the electro-optic materials area, barium strontium titanate was successfully integrated with a variety substrates. Importantly, the full range of Ba-Sr ratios could be determined by lattice spacings, Fig.3. For this calibration, wavelength dispersion spectroscopy (WDS) had to be used due to overlapping peaks in EDS.&nbsp; Once calibrated XRD could be used more easily. It was found that at 10-20% Ba, films were best suited for electro-optical control.<em></em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Properties/Performance. Simple waveguides and interferometers were made to measure the properties of both the garnets and perovskites, Fig. 4.&nbsp; These were defined using laser-writing for direct masks. Analogous to electronic diodes, prototype isolators were made and optical sources can soon be integrated with PICs- a development that will revolutionize photonics immediately and other fields as designers begin to dream.&nbsp; Integrated ferroelectric oxides will also unlock doors to never explored EO functionality in both near and long term applications, such as active frequency modulation and reconfigurable photonics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Broader Impacts.</em> In addition to the scientific benefits of combining III-V platforms with complex oxides, value was added by this US-UK collaboration in a broader sense.&nbsp; Online group meetings utilized web-meetings with Skype and UMConnect to enable attendees to see each other&rsquo;s faces, writings and slides and to hear each other&rsquo;s voices.&nbsp; Individual skype video-conferencing between students for real-time experimental exchange will allow rapid advances of this research.&nbsp; The findings of this online interaction will be disseminated via the MRS materials education symposia.&nbsp; A student/...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Outcomes for Materials World Network: Complex oxides for heterogeneous optoelectronic integration     The goal of this was to bring new functionalities to semiconductor systems by using materials research to identify paths of integration for functional oxide claddings onto semiconductor structures, such as waveguides.  A US oxide processing specialist (Stadler) worked together with a UK semiconductor photonics expert (Hutchings) to add new materials to the palettes of designers interested in electronics, photonics, sensors, and unimagined future areas.  Specifically, magneto-optical (MO) garnets and electro-optical (EO) perovskites were integrated with Si on insulator (SOI) waveguides. These oxides are orders of magnitude greater than the materials currently available to semiconductors.     Intellectual Merit. Here, the classic materials research tetrahedron (processing, structure, properties, performance) was used to rapidly converge on a solution involving controlled strain and interfaces using buffer layers and seed layers (both~10nm), oxide patterning, and rapid thermal annealing for minimized thermal treatment.      Processing/structure. In magneto-optics, a new garnet (terbium iron garnet- TIG) was sputtered onto a variety of substrates and annealed at low thermal budgets by rapid thermal annealing.  The garnet structure was found after anneals as low as 750C, Fig. 1.  Its properties were found to be superior to the standard yttrium iron garnet (YIG) with 2.5x the Faraday rotation than updoped YIG. This new TIG garnet was then doped with Bi and Ce and found to form garnet without the seedlayers required by YIG.  This is significant because the light in a garnet cladding will only include the evanescent tail from the underlying Si guide, Fig. 2.  A seedlayer therefore simply represents at best a deadspace between the guide and the active garnet cladding.  If a garnet, such as YIG, is used as the seedlayer, its sign is opposite to the active garnet, which is even more detrimental than a deadspace.     In the electro-optic materials area, barium strontium titanate was successfully integrated with a variety substrates. Importantly, the full range of Ba-Sr ratios could be determined by lattice spacings, Fig.3. For this calibration, wavelength dispersion spectroscopy (WDS) had to be used due to overlapping peaks in EDS.  Once calibrated XRD could be used more easily. It was found that at 10-20% Ba, films were best suited for electro-optical control.     Properties/Performance. Simple waveguides and interferometers were made to measure the properties of both the garnets and perovskites, Fig. 4.  These were defined using laser-writing for direct masks. Analogous to electronic diodes, prototype isolators were made and optical sources can soon be integrated with PICs- a development that will revolutionize photonics immediately and other fields as designers begin to dream.  Integrated ferroelectric oxides will also unlock doors to never explored EO functionality in both near and long term applications, such as active frequency modulation and reconfigurable photonics.     Broader Impacts. In addition to the scientific benefits of combining III-V platforms with complex oxides, value was added by this US-UK collaboration in a broader sense.  Online group meetings utilized web-meetings with Skype and UMConnect to enable attendees to see each otherÆs faces, writings and slides and to hear each otherÆs voices.  Individual skype video-conferencing between students for real-time experimental exchange will allow rapid advances of this research.  The findings of this online interaction will be disseminated via the MRS materials education symposia.  A student/junior researcher exchange was conducted in the summers, with Andrew Block going from Minneapolis to Glasgow in August 2013 and Cui Zhang going in reverse in June 2014.       Last Modified: 08/31/2014       Submitted by: Bethanie J Stadler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
