<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Self-Assembly of Nanoparticles from Evaporating Drops and Liquid Films: Science, Engineering and Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>208001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>208001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ying Sun</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>yisun@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927443</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Have you ever wondered at the variety of self assembled deposit structures that can be obtained by evaporating liquids containing nanoparticles on top of a solid substrate. Deposit shapes vary from rings around a coffee drop, to hexagonal cells and fractal patterns. An interdisciplinary team of Columbia University scientists will study the related fascinating multiscale physics, using a combination of experimental, theoretical and numerical techniques. The team has the following skills: multiphase flow (Attinger, PI), colloids (Somasundaran), pattern recognition (Chang) and open-source computational fluid dynamics (Spiegelman). The complex self-assembly of nanoparticles will be studied by using first physical principles to explain the resulting selfassembled patterns (what we call a top-down approach), and by identifying features in the patterns that are signs of specific basic laws or transport rules (bottom-up approach).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Experiments will involve the spotting of microdrops of complex fluids on various substrates, fluorescence microscopy and laser profilometry to scan the three dimensional deposits. The first intellectual merit will be to describe with a phase diagram the self-assembly of nanoparticles during liquid evaporation on a solid substrate. The use of a phase diagram in that context is novel and allows a simple but powerful comparison of the magnitude of competing transport phenomena, such as evaporation at the wetting line, Marangoni recirculation, electrostatic and van der Waals forces, buoyancy, and dielectrophoresis. The phase diagram will provide an insight and an overview of the complex interplay between multiphase processes, influenced by the geometry of the liquid drop or film: fluid mechanics, heat transfer, mass transfer, colloidal interactions.  Second, an available proprietary 2D-axisymmetric numerical code with a moving mesh able to very accurately track the free surface will be extended to 3D (see Chandra collaboration letter).  This will allow the simulation of a wider ranges of boundary conditions, permitting the consideration of thin films and complex geometries.  Explaining the self-assembly of nanoparticles from evaporating drops and liquid films from first principles is a challenging approach, given the multiple transport phenomena and time/length scales. Therefore, we will also develop a bottom-up approach based on pattern recognition of selfassembled features. We will test the hypothesis that the patterns tell us the about the physics that created them.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will deliver innovative solutions to pattern nanoparticles on solid substrates, with applications in organic electronics and patterning of biomolecules for biosensors.  Methods to increase printing resolution by two orders of magnitude (see Sonoplot letter), and to pattern uniform layers of particles will be investigated. The pattern recognition algorithms developed in this proposal will be tested to identify biomolecules (see Zenhausern letter) and enhance the accuracy of bloodstain pattern analysis, in collaboration with forensics expert MacDonell (see collaboration letter). Also, the 3D code developed in this proposal will be distributed freely as an open-source code, allowing every interested scientist to study problems involving drop and film transport phenomena such as drop impact, drop evaporation, film drying. Funding will support one graduate student.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/17/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1211187</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Attinger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Attinger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>attinger@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152941423</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000154653</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/17/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ames</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112161</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2025 Black Engineering]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>058E</Code>
<Text>Newtonian fluids</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~715</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~119621</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~87665</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual merit</strong></p> <p>The intellectual merit of this grant is to study evaporative self-assembly processes of micro- and nano-particles either by using physical principles to explain the deposit morphology (called a <em>top-down</em> approach), or by identifying features in the stains that are signs of specific basic laws or transport rules (<em>bottom-up</em> approach).</p> <p>Two contributions have highlighted the relationship between the transport phenomena during the drying of a drop and the resulting stain shape. A first contribution has defined the limits between two stain shapes: a uniform deposit or a central bump, using a phase diagram. An analytical model estimates the magnitude of the thermocapillary flow responsible for central bump formation. A second contributions was to understand how the inspection of stains informs about the presence of specific proteins in the particles dispersed in the drop or on the substrate where the drop dries. The biological bonding interactions between the particles and the substrate influence the shape of the stain, together with three other forces acting on the particles at the edge of the drying drop: the hydrodynamic drag, the friction force and the surface tension force. A balance of these forces defines a parameter that can predict the stain shape, with either particles covering the entire area of the original drop, or particles concentrated at its center. The understanding of biological interactions on the drying process is a first step towards developing methods to detect and quantify specific biomarker in a biological fluid.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader impact</strong></p> <p>The broader impact involves student training and the development of engineering applications for forensic and biodiagnostic processes.</p> <p>One graduate student has been trained to microfluidic techniques including flow visualization, substrate and particle preparation and characterization, infra-red measurement of temperature, and experimental design. The student received a best poster award at the 2016 summer heat transfer and microchannels conference of the ASME. A second graduate student was trained to the theoretical and experimental study of evaporative self-assembly in complex geometries. A third graduate student was trained at designing an experimental setup to study the relationship between drop impact conditions and stain shape. An undergraduate student was trained to the performance and characterization of self-assembly experiments using a blade-directed setup.</p> <p>The results have been disseminated in peer-reviewed journal articles and in ASME conferences. Our work on the interpretation of bloodstains for forensics application has been featured in news media such as Fox News and Iowa Public Radio, as well as in conferences organized by the US National Institute of Justice. Presentations of the work on convective self-assembly were given at the University of Washington Seattle, two universities in the region of Beijing China, and to a team 10 technicians "repairing" artwork and historical garments and artefacts in Quebec.</p> <p>An impact of the project is on medicine with the design of a method that performs rapid diagnostic, based on the observation of the shape of stains. A related invention report was published in 2013, that describes pattern recognition techniques for identifying the composition of a target fluid using a set of vectors representing known residue patterns for two or more fluids including said target fluid is provided.</p> <p>Problems involving drying of dispersion drops have been integrated in a graduate course "Microfluidics: Theory, Design and Devices".<strong> </strong>A specific aspect of this course is that the students were presented with the necessary physics and then asked to solve several related design problems, where physical principles were used towards the development of useful methods and devices. Evaluations of the teaching effectiveness of the instructor and the overall learning experience were significantly above the average of the courses in my department. Students in their comments appreciated the effectiveness of problem-based learning.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Change/Problem</strong></p> <p>It is the duty of a primary investigator to report circumstances that negatively impact the performance of a Federal award. In an elected function in my academic department, I experienced a conflict with an administrator about the respect of academic freedom and governance rules. The administrator then interfered with my research team, harassed me in multiple ways, and projected similar accusations on me. Other administrators closed rank and disrupted further my ability to lead and perform research. These years of harassment brought unhealthy consequences for my mentees and our families. The dispute eventually was settled. The settlement grants me a new supervisor, ends most of the harassment, and reinstates some of my ability to lead a research team and pursue academic goals. I believe that the above episode illustrates how conflicts of interest and loyalty make it challenging for universities to investigate and prosecute issues of harassment. Maybe it is time to start a candid conversation on the goals, priorities and limits of the University as an institution.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/15/2019<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Attinger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1211187/1211187_10017733_1573866190706_forcesonbeads--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1211187/1211187_10017733_1573866190706_forcesonbeads--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Modeling of forces on chain of particles in a convective self-assembly process"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1211187/1211187_10017733_1573866190706_forcesonbeads--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Modeling of forces on chain of particles in a convective self-assembly process"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic of the forces acting on a linear chain of particles near an evaporating wetting line.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Attinger/Bhardwaj/Andalib</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;Attinger</div> <div class="imageTitle">Modeling of forces on chain of particles in a convective self-assembly process</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit  The intellectual merit of this grant is to study evaporative self-assembly processes of micro- and nano-particles either by using physical principles to explain the deposit morphology (called a top-down approach), or by identifying features in the stains that are signs of specific basic laws or transport rules (bottom-up approach).  Two contributions have highlighted the relationship between the transport phenomena during the drying of a drop and the resulting stain shape. A first contribution has defined the limits between two stain shapes: a uniform deposit or a central bump, using a phase diagram. An analytical model estimates the magnitude of the thermocapillary flow responsible for central bump formation. A second contributions was to understand how the inspection of stains informs about the presence of specific proteins in the particles dispersed in the drop or on the substrate where the drop dries. The biological bonding interactions between the particles and the substrate influence the shape of the stain, together with three other forces acting on the particles at the edge of the drying drop: the hydrodynamic drag, the friction force and the surface tension force. A balance of these forces defines a parameter that can predict the stain shape, with either particles covering the entire area of the original drop, or particles concentrated at its center. The understanding of biological interactions on the drying process is a first step towards developing methods to detect and quantify specific biomarker in a biological fluid.     Broader impact  The broader impact involves student training and the development of engineering applications for forensic and biodiagnostic processes.  One graduate student has been trained to microfluidic techniques including flow visualization, substrate and particle preparation and characterization, infra-red measurement of temperature, and experimental design. The student received a best poster award at the 2016 summer heat transfer and microchannels conference of the ASME. A second graduate student was trained to the theoretical and experimental study of evaporative self-assembly in complex geometries. A third graduate student was trained at designing an experimental setup to study the relationship between drop impact conditions and stain shape. An undergraduate student was trained to the performance and characterization of self-assembly experiments using a blade-directed setup.  The results have been disseminated in peer-reviewed journal articles and in ASME conferences. Our work on the interpretation of bloodstains for forensics application has been featured in news media such as Fox News and Iowa Public Radio, as well as in conferences organized by the US National Institute of Justice. Presentations of the work on convective self-assembly were given at the University of Washington Seattle, two universities in the region of Beijing China, and to a team 10 technicians "repairing" artwork and historical garments and artefacts in Quebec.  An impact of the project is on medicine with the design of a method that performs rapid diagnostic, based on the observation of the shape of stains. A related invention report was published in 2013, that describes pattern recognition techniques for identifying the composition of a target fluid using a set of vectors representing known residue patterns for two or more fluids including said target fluid is provided.  Problems involving drying of dispersion drops have been integrated in a graduate course "Microfluidics: Theory, Design and Devices". A specific aspect of this course is that the students were presented with the necessary physics and then asked to solve several related design problems, where physical principles were used towards the development of useful methods and devices. Evaluations of the teaching effectiveness of the instructor and the overall learning experience were significantly above the average of the courses in my department. Students in their comments appreciated the effectiveness of problem-based learning.     Change/Problem  It is the duty of a primary investigator to report circumstances that negatively impact the performance of a Federal award. In an elected function in my academic department, I experienced a conflict with an administrator about the respect of academic freedom and governance rules. The administrator then interfered with my research team, harassed me in multiple ways, and projected similar accusations on me. Other administrators closed rank and disrupted further my ability to lead and perform research. These years of harassment brought unhealthy consequences for my mentees and our families. The dispute eventually was settled. The settlement grants me a new supervisor, ends most of the harassment, and reinstates some of my ability to lead a research team and pursue academic goals. I believe that the above episode illustrates how conflicts of interest and loyalty make it challenging for universities to investigate and prosecute issues of harassment. Maybe it is time to start a candid conversation on the goals, priorities and limits of the University as an institution.          Last Modified: 11/15/2019       Submitted by: Daniel Attinger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
