<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The Hidden Side of Rapidly Growing Black Holes: Host Masses and Evolution of Obscured Quasars with SDSS and WISE</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249228.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249228</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Barvainis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to combine data from the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) and the Wide-Field Infrared Survey Explorer (WISE) to provide a high-precision measurement of the spatial clustering of obscured quasars. The scientific objective is to establish if the obscured QSO population has a different origin from unobscured QSOs, for example if they live in larger dark matter halos.  This may lead to important new probes Dark Matter Halo structures and the evolution of galaxies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of the work include training of undergraduate students, and outreach to middle-school teachers via summer workshops in collaboration with the Department of Secondary Education at the University of Wyoming, with the primary goal of increasing the quality of middle- and secondary-level physics education in Wyoming and New Hampshire.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1211112</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Myers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adam D Myers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>geordiemyers@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3077666244</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000381963</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Burrows</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea C Burrows</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>andrea.c.burrows@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3077665011</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000607989</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wyoming</Name>
<CityName>Laramie</CityName>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3077665320</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 E. University Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Department 3355]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069690956</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WYOMING</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069690956</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wyoming]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~249228</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Work on our project was conducted by PI Myers' research group at the University of Wyoming in a collaborative fashion with Prof. Ryan C. Hickox's research group at Dartmouth College.</p> <p>The  intellectual merit of our program was based on using powerful new  astronomical data sets to understand the supermassive black holes that  reside at the centers of galaxies. In particular, we wished to  understand how these black holes grow and change over the history of the  Universe, with a focus on the dust-obscured rapidly-growing black holes  ("quasars") that have only recently been detected in large numbers with  observatories that operate at mid-infrared wavelengths. One important  clue as to the nature of obscured black holes comes from how they are  clustered together in space, which allows us to determine the masses of  the dark matter halos in which they reside. In some theoretical models,  some quasars are only seen as obscured because we are viewing them from  particular direction (the "orientation" model), while other models  suggest that obscuration happens during an important phase in the  formation of galaxies associated with rapid star formation (the  "evolutionary" model).&nbsp;</p> <p><span>In  this NSF research program we performed some of the first clustering  measurements of obscured quasars that allow us to distinguish between  these two scenarios. We focused on using data from the Wide-Field  Infrared Survey Explorer (WISE) and Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS), as  well as a number of other ground- and space-based telescopes.&nbsp;</span><br /><br /><span>Our  work has confirmed that obscured quasars are more strongly clustered  than unobscured quasars, providing support for an evolutionary model for quasars. However, we found that the magnitude of this difference is  smaller than obtained in previous studies, due to improvements in our  handling of complex effects in the WISE data. We have also verified this  result by developing a new technique for measuring dark matter halos  through gravitational lensing of the cosmic microwave background. To  interpret these clustering results, we have physically characterized obscured quasars using a range of  observations, allowing us to understand the radiative power of these  quasars and how deeply buried they are behind obscuring material.</span><br /><br /><span>Results of our work that are partially or fully attributable to efforts at the University of Wyoming were disseminated in 29 articles in  major journals and 14 conference proceedings. Masks to ameliorate complex effects in the data have been made  available online to the scientific community, together with codebases for conducting and modeling our measurements.</span><br /><br /><span>The  broader impacts of this program were based on working with teachers to  include astronomical concepts in their curricula. Through this  collaborative grant we organized four teacher training workshops in  Laramie, Wyoming that reached nearly 60 teachers from Wyoming and New  Hampshire, the states that are home to the two institutions collaborating on our grant (the  University of Wyoming and Dartmouth College). These workshops were based  on learning hands-on activities and developing inquiry-based lesson  plans for use in classrooms. Materials and activities from these  workshops have been made freely available online.</span><br /><br /><span>At the University of Wyoming, this  grant contributed to the professional training of three postdoctoral researchers. The two postdocs who worked most heavily on this grant have gone on to broad success; one has obtained a faculty job and the other has taken a postdoctoral position at an Ivy League college. This grant also partially comprised part of the thesis work of two graduate students. Finally, this grant informed the research work of an undergraduate scholar who has gone on to graduate school at an Ivy League college.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/11/2016<br>      Modified by: Adam&nbsp;D&nbsp;Myers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Work on our project was conducted by PI Myers' research group at the University of Wyoming in a collaborative fashion with Prof. Ryan C. Hickox's research group at Dartmouth College.  The  intellectual merit of our program was based on using powerful new  astronomical data sets to understand the supermassive black holes that  reside at the centers of galaxies. In particular, we wished to  understand how these black holes grow and change over the history of the  Universe, with a focus on the dust-obscured rapidly-growing black holes  ("quasars") that have only recently been detected in large numbers with  observatories that operate at mid-infrared wavelengths. One important  clue as to the nature of obscured black holes comes from how they are  clustered together in space, which allows us to determine the masses of  the dark matter halos in which they reside. In some theoretical models,  some quasars are only seen as obscured because we are viewing them from  particular direction (the "orientation" model), while other models  suggest that obscuration happens during an important phase in the  formation of galaxies associated with rapid star formation (the  "evolutionary" model).   In  this NSF research program we performed some of the first clustering  measurements of obscured quasars that allow us to distinguish between  these two scenarios. We focused on using data from the Wide-Field  Infrared Survey Explorer (WISE) and Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS), as  well as a number of other ground- and space-based telescopes.   Our  work has confirmed that obscured quasars are more strongly clustered  than unobscured quasars, providing support for an evolutionary model for quasars. However, we found that the magnitude of this difference is  smaller than obtained in previous studies, due to improvements in our  handling of complex effects in the WISE data. We have also verified this  result by developing a new technique for measuring dark matter halos  through gravitational lensing of the cosmic microwave background. To  interpret these clustering results, we have physically characterized obscured quasars using a range of  observations, allowing us to understand the radiative power of these  quasars and how deeply buried they are behind obscuring material.  Results of our work that are partially or fully attributable to efforts at the University of Wyoming were disseminated in 29 articles in  major journals and 14 conference proceedings. Masks to ameliorate complex effects in the data have been made  available online to the scientific community, together with codebases for conducting and modeling our measurements.  The  broader impacts of this program were based on working with teachers to  include astronomical concepts in their curricula. Through this  collaborative grant we organized four teacher training workshops in  Laramie, Wyoming that reached nearly 60 teachers from Wyoming and New  Hampshire, the states that are home to the two institutions collaborating on our grant (the  University of Wyoming and Dartmouth College). These workshops were based  on learning hands-on activities and developing inquiry-based lesson  plans for use in classrooms. Materials and activities from these  workshops have been made freely available online.  At the University of Wyoming, this  grant contributed to the professional training of three postdoctoral researchers. The two postdocs who worked most heavily on this grant have gone on to broad success; one has obtained a faculty job and the other has taken a postdoctoral position at an Ivy League college. This grant also partially comprised part of the thesis work of two graduate students. Finally, this grant informed the research work of an undergraduate scholar who has gone on to graduate school at an Ivy League college.       Last Modified: 11/11/2016       Submitted by: Adam D Myers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
