<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Characterization of Binary and Triple Systems in the Near-Earth, Main Belt, and Trans-Neptunian Populations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>405379.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>405379</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Faith Vilas</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Principal Investigator (PI) and supported graduate students will conduct a study to characterize binary and triple systems in the near-Earth object, main-belt asteroid, and trans-Neptunian object populations, with the goal of constraining the nature, origin, and evolution of minor planets. The proposing team will conduct ground-based observations using a variety of observational techniques, including direct optical imaging, adaptive optics imaging, radar imaging, and light curve observations. The specific objectives are (1) to measure the physical properties of minor planets, including masses, sizes, and densities, which will constrain thermal and mechanical properties as well as interior structure; (2) to test theories for the formation of binaries and subsequent evolutionary processes, including tidal evolution, radiative evolution, collisional evolution, and collisionless interactions mediated by gravity; and (3) to infer constraints on the compositional and thermal characteristics of the early Solar System, and on the current distribution of volatiles. The team anticipates a detailed characterization of several near-Earth multiples, several main belt multiples, and at least one trans-Neptunian multiple during the project. The supported graduate students will gain expertise in observation planning, observing techniques, calibration, analysis, astrometric measurements, statistical and numerical methods, and scientific communication. A collaborative research environment (wiki) serving the community of radar observers will be developed. The team will actively engage in public outreach with presentations at various events and teacher workshops, and plans to disseminate exciting results to the public through social media.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1211581</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jean-Luc</FirstName>
<LastName>Margot</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jean-Luc Margot</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jlm@epss.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3102068345</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000161563</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951567</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[595 Charles E Young Dr. East]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1214</Code>
<Text>PLANETARY ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~405379</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This investigation enabled detailed observations and analysis of binary asteroid systems.&nbsp; A binary asteroid is composed of a primary component and a secondary component that orbit one another as the binary system orbits the sun.&nbsp; We used primarily the planetary radar at the Arecibo Observatory to characterize binaries in the near-Earth population and the Keck telescope to characterize binaries in the main belt population.&nbsp; We were able to measure asteroid masses, sizes, and densities of both primary and secondary components of the binary systems.&nbsp; By measuring the orbital and physical characteristics of the binary components, we were able to understand the processes that govern the formation and evolution of these systems.&nbsp;</p> <p>We wrote three peer-reviewed articles and two peer-reviewed book chapters to describe our results, which we also presented at scientific conferences and invited seminars.&nbsp; Our most important publication that results from this work is a major review chapter that describes our findings as well as the current state of knowledge about asteroids binaries, triples, and pairs:</p> <p>J. L. Margot, P. Pravec, P. Taylor, B. Carry, S. Jacobson.&nbsp; Asteroid Systems:<br />Binaries, Triples, and Pairs.&nbsp; In Asteroids IV, 355-373, 2015. http://arxiv.org/abs/1504.00034</p> <p>Over the course of our investigation, we trained four graduate students in both radar and optical observing techniques, as well as in celestial mechanics, computer science, signal processing, and planetary science.&nbsp; We also presented our results at a number of education and public outreach events.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/21/2017<br>      Modified by: Jean-Luc&nbsp;Margot</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This investigation enabled detailed observations and analysis of binary asteroid systems.  A binary asteroid is composed of a primary component and a secondary component that orbit one another as the binary system orbits the sun.  We used primarily the planetary radar at the Arecibo Observatory to characterize binaries in the near-Earth population and the Keck telescope to characterize binaries in the main belt population.  We were able to measure asteroid masses, sizes, and densities of both primary and secondary components of the binary systems.  By measuring the orbital and physical characteristics of the binary components, we were able to understand the processes that govern the formation and evolution of these systems.   We wrote three peer-reviewed articles and two peer-reviewed book chapters to describe our results, which we also presented at scientific conferences and invited seminars.  Our most important publication that results from this work is a major review chapter that describes our findings as well as the current state of knowledge about asteroids binaries, triples, and pairs:  J. L. Margot, P. Pravec, P. Taylor, B. Carry, S. Jacobson.  Asteroid Systems: Binaries, Triples, and Pairs.  In Asteroids IV, 355-373, 2015. http://arxiv.org/abs/1504.00034  Over the course of our investigation, we trained four graduate students in both radar and optical observing techniques, as well as in celestial mechanics, computer science, signal processing, and planetary science.  We also presented our results at a number of education and public outreach events.       Last Modified: 11/21/2017       Submitted by: Jean-Luc Margot]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
