<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Interpretation of Galactic Chemical Evolution Surveys</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>261437.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>261437</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Glen Langston</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>glangsto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924937</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Dr. Weinberg and his team develop and apply modeling methods to interpret measurements of radial velocities and multi-element chemical abundances from large spectroscopic surveys of tens or hundreds of thousands of stars. Such studies are necessary to improve our understanding of the physical processes in galaxy formation and galactic chemical evolution. The primary focus for near-term applications is to use data from the Apache Point Observatory Galactic Evolution Experiment (APOGEE) survey, which is a follow-up survey of the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS-III). This survey will measure precise radial velocities and multi-element chemistry (about 15 elements per star) for about 100,000 red giant stars in all regions of the Milky Way. Other target data sets include the Sloan Extension for Galactic Understanding and Exploration survey (SEGUE, another follow up survey to SDSS), and the Radial Velocity Experiment (RAVE) survey of the solar neighborhood, but also data from other large surveys planned in the future .The research employs three complementary modeling approaches: Analytic chemical evolution models that incorporate radial mixing and dynamical processes, N-body/hydrodynamic simulations that model growth of a galaxy disk either in isolation or in the presence of accreting satellite galaxies, and simulations of galactic disk formation from fully cosmological initial conditions. The growing disk simulations use the Gasoline code, which is also used in the cosmological runs, but gas is added to the disk as a prescribed function of radius and time. This approach provides controlled simulations that can isolate the effects of specific physical processes, and realize distinct scenarios that can be used to distinguish processes such as galactic bulge formation by secular evolution versus formation through minor mergers. The investigators will develop and apply the technique of Principal Component Abundance Analysis (PCAA) to characterize any correlated variations of elemental abundances in large stellar data sets. The PCAA tool will be a valuable tool for understanding systematic effects and statistical errors in the APOGEE chemical abundance data and for characterizing its multi-dimensional measurements in compact form. This and other tools are likely to increase the impact of the SDSS-III data sets. For example, by applying these tools to the interpretation of APOGEE and other data sets, the investigators can address questions about the origin of the Galactic thick disk, bulge, and stellar halo, and the history of chemical enrichment and migration of stars within the thin disk. The PCAA and data-model comparisons are used to analyze the distribution of stellar chemical compositions as a function of metallicity and spatial location, and to characterize the level of chemo-dynamical substructure in different components of the Galaxy. This can constrain the importance of satellite perturbations and mergers, and by identifying the principal patterns of enrichment and rare outliers from these patterns, one can gain insights insight into the key pathways of stellar nucleosynthesis. Graduate students and postdoctoral researchers are involved in this project and will be trained in developing and applying theory, observation, and statistical analysis tools to problems in Galaxy formation and evolution.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1211853</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Weinberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David H Weinberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dhw@astronomy.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142922022</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000240164</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jaj@astronomy.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142925651</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000242583</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stelios</FirstName>
<LastName>Kazantzidis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stelios Kazantzidis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>stelios@mps.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142471501</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000512602</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University, Astronomy]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101173</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[140 W. 18th Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1216</Code>
<Text>GALACTIC ASTRONOMY PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7480</Code>
<Text>ARCHIVAL DATA ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~261437</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The chemical elements other than hydrogen and helium were forged in the nuclear furnaces of stars, then ejected by stellar explosions into interstellar gas, from which they could be incorporated into subsequent generations of stars and planets (and people, buildings, furniture, etc.).&nbsp; Thus, the "fingerprint" of elements present in a star contains clues to all the stars that preceded it and produced those elements.&nbsp; A major goal of Galactic astronomy is to measure these fingerprints in large populations of stars and to use them to decode the history of the Milky Way and the physical mechanisms that produce different elements.&nbsp; Our project developed new tools for this "decoding" and applied them to new maps of the elements in the Milky Way, most notably the map created by the APOGEE project of the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS).<br /><br />Most stars in the Milky Way reside in a thin, rotating disk, which we see (from our perspective within this disk) as a band of light on the sky.&nbsp; Observations have shown that older stars tend to be further from the plane of the disk than younger stars.&nbsp; Using one of the most advanced cosmological simulations of the formation of a Milky Way-like galaxy, we showed that this pattern was likely "imprinted at birth," as stars formed from a disk of gas that became gradually thinner over time.&nbsp; This contrasts with the conventional view that stars are born in a thin layer that is puffed up over time.&nbsp; We described our proposed scenario as "upside down" disk formation.</p> <p>In subsequent work we focused on the detailed evolution over time of different chemical elements.&nbsp; Although this is a long-standing field, our approach was considerably more systematic in showing how different theoretical assumptions about star formation and galactic winds affect the predictions, and in isolating the information conveyed by different elements.&nbsp; We discovered new classes of analytic solutions to the chemical evolution equations, allowing "pencil and paper" calculations of results that would otherwise require computers.&nbsp; These analytic solutions provide insight into the underlying physics that guides chemical evolution, and they are a useful practical tool for modeling observations.&nbsp; We used both these solutions and computer calculations to interpret some of the most interesting results from the APOGEE maps, which show systematic changes in the distribution of chemical elements in stars at different locations within the Milky Way disk.&nbsp; Among other results, we showed that the APOGEE measurements provide evidence for the "upside down" formation scenario mentioned above.&nbsp; We also examined the curious case of deuterium ("heavy" hydrogen, with one proton and one neutron in its nucleus), which is observed to constitute about 0.002 percent of the hydrogen in interstellar gas.&nbsp; Our theoretical models explain this observation quite naturally, but to do so they require (a) that most massive stars explode as supernovae rather than collapsing directly into black holes, and (b) that star formation in the Milky Way drives a galactic wind that carries away at least as much mass as is formed into stars.&nbsp; Another interesting implication of the observed deuterium: while all of the "heavy" atoms in the human body (carbon, oxgyen, etc.) were once inside a star, 90 percent of the hydrogen atoms, and roughly half of the total atoms, have come straight from the big bang.<br /><br />The SDSS has played a key role in creating the largest maps of the distant universe and the Milky Way galaxy.&nbsp; The project began more than 25 years ago and has been through several phases.&nbsp; At different times during the period of this grant, Weinberg served as the Project Scientist of SDSS-III and Johnson served as the Project Spokesperson of SDSS-IV.&nbsp; Johnson is now heading the stellar and Galactic astrophysics program planned for SDSS-V, which will observe ten times more stars than the previous phases of the SDSS combined.<br /><br />This project also supported a variety of public outreach activities.&nbsp; Johnson spearheaded a major renovation of the Ohio State planetarium into a modern facility that now brings in many thousands of visitors per year.&nbsp; Weinberg collaborated with artist Josiah McElheny on a sculpture based on SDSS observations that illustrates fundamental ideas about structure and homogeneity in the universe.</p> <p>Support from this project contributed to the training of four PhD students at different phases of their graduate education; two are still at Ohio State and two have moved on to new universities.&nbsp; Astronomy is a global field with global impact.&nbsp; Co-Investigator Kazantzidis was a postdoctoral fellow at Ohio State at the beginning of this grant, and he is now a faculty member at the University of Athens, training a new generation of astronomers in the country that was the cradle of scientific thought more than two millenia ago.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/05/2018<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;H&nbsp;Weinberg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The chemical elements other than hydrogen and helium were forged in the nuclear furnaces of stars, then ejected by stellar explosions into interstellar gas, from which they could be incorporated into subsequent generations of stars and planets (and people, buildings, furniture, etc.).  Thus, the "fingerprint" of elements present in a star contains clues to all the stars that preceded it and produced those elements.  A major goal of Galactic astronomy is to measure these fingerprints in large populations of stars and to use them to decode the history of the Milky Way and the physical mechanisms that produce different elements.  Our project developed new tools for this "decoding" and applied them to new maps of the elements in the Milky Way, most notably the map created by the APOGEE project of the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS).  Most stars in the Milky Way reside in a thin, rotating disk, which we see (from our perspective within this disk) as a band of light on the sky.  Observations have shown that older stars tend to be further from the plane of the disk than younger stars.  Using one of the most advanced cosmological simulations of the formation of a Milky Way-like galaxy, we showed that this pattern was likely "imprinted at birth," as stars formed from a disk of gas that became gradually thinner over time.  This contrasts with the conventional view that stars are born in a thin layer that is puffed up over time.  We described our proposed scenario as "upside down" disk formation.  In subsequent work we focused on the detailed evolution over time of different chemical elements.  Although this is a long-standing field, our approach was considerably more systematic in showing how different theoretical assumptions about star formation and galactic winds affect the predictions, and in isolating the information conveyed by different elements.  We discovered new classes of analytic solutions to the chemical evolution equations, allowing "pencil and paper" calculations of results that would otherwise require computers.  These analytic solutions provide insight into the underlying physics that guides chemical evolution, and they are a useful practical tool for modeling observations.  We used both these solutions and computer calculations to interpret some of the most interesting results from the APOGEE maps, which show systematic changes in the distribution of chemical elements in stars at different locations within the Milky Way disk.  Among other results, we showed that the APOGEE measurements provide evidence for the "upside down" formation scenario mentioned above.  We also examined the curious case of deuterium ("heavy" hydrogen, with one proton and one neutron in its nucleus), which is observed to constitute about 0.002 percent of the hydrogen in interstellar gas.  Our theoretical models explain this observation quite naturally, but to do so they require (a) that most massive stars explode as supernovae rather than collapsing directly into black holes, and (b) that star formation in the Milky Way drives a galactic wind that carries away at least as much mass as is formed into stars.  Another interesting implication of the observed deuterium: while all of the "heavy" atoms in the human body (carbon, oxgyen, etc.) were once inside a star, 90 percent of the hydrogen atoms, and roughly half of the total atoms, have come straight from the big bang.  The SDSS has played a key role in creating the largest maps of the distant universe and the Milky Way galaxy.  The project began more than 25 years ago and has been through several phases.  At different times during the period of this grant, Weinberg served as the Project Scientist of SDSS-III and Johnson served as the Project Spokesperson of SDSS-IV.  Johnson is now heading the stellar and Galactic astrophysics program planned for SDSS-V, which will observe ten times more stars than the previous phases of the SDSS combined.  This project also supported a variety of public outreach activities.  Johnson spearheaded a major renovation of the Ohio State planetarium into a modern facility that now brings in many thousands of visitors per year.  Weinberg collaborated with artist Josiah McElheny on a sculpture based on SDSS observations that illustrates fundamental ideas about structure and homogeneity in the universe.  Support from this project contributed to the training of four PhD students at different phases of their graduate education; two are still at Ohio State and two have moved on to new universities.  Astronomy is a global field with global impact.  Co-Investigator Kazantzidis was a postdoctoral fellow at Ohio State at the beginning of this grant, and he is now a faculty member at the University of Athens, training a new generation of astronomers in the country that was the cradle of scientific thought more than two millenia ago.          Last Modified: 01/05/2018       Submitted by: David H Weinberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
