<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>How Do Galaxies End Their Star-Formation?</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>345322.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>345322</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Barvainis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will investigate the population of galaxies that are in transition from star-forming to non-star-forming, with greater accuracy than was previously possible. The Principal Investigator and graduate students supported by the award will combine optical-wavelength data from the Sloan Digital Sky Survey, ultraviolet data from the Galaxy Evolution Explorer (GALEX) spacecraft, and mid-infrared data from the Wide-Field Infrared Survey Explorer (WISE) spacecraft, to identify transition galaxies and to constrain their metallicities, star-formation rates, dust extinctions, stellar masses, and active nucleus content at low redshift. They will then use PRIMUS, a 120,000 galaxy survey sampling the redshift range between 0.2 and 1.0, combined with GALEX and Spitzer Space Telescope data, to perform a similar analysis at higher redshift. The objectives are (1) to obtain an accurate and representative census of the transition population; (2) to determine whether star-formation is turning off the same way in isolated galaxies as in cluster populations; and (3) to determine whether active galactic nuclei are related to the transition phenomenon. In addition to supporting graduate student training, the project will enable expansion of the NASA-Sloan Atlas of galaxies to include newly released WISE data and development of educational and outreach tools within the existing web interface.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1211644</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Blanton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael R Blanton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mb144@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2129987770</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000158225</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100036603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4 Washington Place]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7480</Code>
<Text>ARCHIVAL DATA ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~176549</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~168773</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Galaxies consist of hundreds of millions of stars that have formedover the fourteen billion years of the Universe's history. In early periods, around ten billion years ago, stars were forming at a furiousrate, but that rate has slowed since then by a factor of ten. This slow down has occured partly because star forming galaxies have slowed their star formation on average, but also because some of them have ceased forming stars altogether and become quiescent. How and why galaxies end their star formation is a critical question inastrophysics.</p> <p><br />To address this question, we have studied the population of nearby anddistant galaxies in an attempt to better measure star formation and to identify how galaxies transition from star forming to quiescence. Wehave combined observations from two NASA satellites (called GALEX and WISE) with results from the ground-based Sloan Digital Sky Survey(SDSS) to enhance the measurements of a catalog of nearby galaxies. GALEX uses measurements of ultraviolet light, SDSS uses measurements of optical light, and WISE uses measurements of infrared light. We have also studied the evolution of galaxies over cosmic time using a survey called PRIMUS of distant galaxies (which we see at anearly phase of their evolution).</p> <p><br />We have found for the nearby galaxies that the infrared measurements are critical to understand the star formation rates of galaxies, because dust surrounding young stars extincts their ultraviolet light. This effect was known and methods had been developed to correct for it, but by examining the environments of star forming galaxies we provide new, independent evidence that these corrections are insufficient.</p> <p><br />We have also found using PRIMUS that galaxies transition from star forming to quiescent at rates that are similar independent of their surrounding environment. Although some galaxies are known to end their star formation due to effects related to falling into a rich cluster of galaxies, it appears that this does not explain how star formation ends in most galaxies. Most galaxies end their star formation due to internal processes within them and not due to external influences.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/20/2015<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;R&nbsp;Blanton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Galaxies consist of hundreds of millions of stars that have formedover the fourteen billion years of the Universe's history. In early periods, around ten billion years ago, stars were forming at a furiousrate, but that rate has slowed since then by a factor of ten. This slow down has occured partly because star forming galaxies have slowed their star formation on average, but also because some of them have ceased forming stars altogether and become quiescent. How and why galaxies end their star formation is a critical question inastrophysics.   To address this question, we have studied the population of nearby anddistant galaxies in an attempt to better measure star formation and to identify how galaxies transition from star forming to quiescence. Wehave combined observations from two NASA satellites (called GALEX and WISE) with results from the ground-based Sloan Digital Sky Survey(SDSS) to enhance the measurements of a catalog of nearby galaxies. GALEX uses measurements of ultraviolet light, SDSS uses measurements of optical light, and WISE uses measurements of infrared light. We have also studied the evolution of galaxies over cosmic time using a survey called PRIMUS of distant galaxies (which we see at anearly phase of their evolution).   We have found for the nearby galaxies that the infrared measurements are critical to understand the star formation rates of galaxies, because dust surrounding young stars extincts their ultraviolet light. This effect was known and methods had been developed to correct for it, but by examining the environments of star forming galaxies we provide new, independent evidence that these corrections are insufficient.   We have also found using PRIMUS that galaxies transition from star forming to quiescent at rates that are similar independent of their surrounding environment. Although some galaxies are known to end their star formation due to effects related to falling into a rich cluster of galaxies, it appears that this does not explain how star formation ends in most galaxies. Most galaxies end their star formation due to internal processes within them and not due to external influences.       Last Modified: 11/20/2015       Submitted by: Michael R Blanton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
