<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Launching and Collimation of Outflows from Young Solar-type Stars</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>342572.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>342572</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Neff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jneff@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922475</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI and her team will apply 2D and 3D magnetohydrodynamic simulations to observed collimated outflows from young solar-type stars.   They will follow a two phase approach of 1) investigating launching and collimation on small spatial scales of less than 1 AU, and then 2) extending the work to simulations of much larger scales of 10-100 AU.  Simulations from the second phase will be compared to observations of young stellar objects (YSO's) with outflows over similar distance scales. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will also contribute to other topics relevant to stellar astrophysics, including developing physical understanding and intuition about material undergoing gravitational infall, constraining models of initial mass functions and angular momentum.  The PI will  mentor a postdoctoral researcher and undergraduate students in participating in this resarch project, and will also organize and run a public outreach exibit through the Ithaca Science Center.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1211318</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Lovelace</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard V Lovelace</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>RVL1@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072556915</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000393537</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marina</FirstName>
<LastName>Romanova</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marina Romanova</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>romanova@astro.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072556915</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000160964</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148536801</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[410 Space Science Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~342572</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><br /><strong>Overview of the Problem: </strong>Powerful outflows are observed in many young, newly forming stars. &nbsp;It is commonly believed that the outflows are responsible for transporting excess angular momentum away from the star-disk system, and for the formation of newly born stars. Despite the recent high spatial resolution observations of such outflows, their exact launching and collimation mechanisms were not well understood. The main objective of the proposed research was to understand the formation and collimation mechanisms of the outflows associated with young solar-type stars, such as classical T Tauri stars (CTTSs). To achieve this goal, we explored a &nbsp;set of possible scenarios of outflow formation and collimation by employing magnetohydrodynamic(MHD) simulations and by comparing our models with observations.</p> <p><br /><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> &nbsp;Our studies have led to several important conclusions: (1) Young, recently formed stars may be in the ``propeller regime", where a star rotates more rapidly than the inner parts of the accretion disk. Our simulations show that, in these cases, a significant part of the inner disk matter can be redirected into conically shaped winds, which are gradually collimated by the magnetic force. A smaller amount of the inner disk matter flows into a well-collimated, low-density jet along the stellar field lines. The jet component is driven and collimated by the magnetic force. Comparisons with the observations show that the two-component outflows are often present in CTTSs and other young stars. (2) In some young stars, accretion is non-stationary and episodic, where episodes of high accretion rate alternate with episodes of very low accretion rate. Our simulations show that when new matter comes into the disk it compresses the magnetosphere and provides the conditions for persistent conical winds. This mechanism can explain the winds from young stars where episodes of very high accretion rate are observed, such as in EXOrs and FU Ori type stars. (3) If a significant part of the inner disk is threaded with poloidal field lines, then matter flows from the inner disk to the wind along these field lines. Such a field may either come from large distances (together with the disk matter), or may form locally due to the dynamo mechanism. &nbsp;We studied the formation of the field through the dynamo mechanism, and observed that the generated field has the shape of loops of different sizes.We observed from the simulations that the inner loops inflate and open due to the differential rotation between the star and the inner disk, and that matter flows into the wind along these field lines. Simulations show that the field is typically asymmetric about the equatorial plane, and that the outflows are also asymmetric. Comparisons with the observations show that the outflows from young stars are often asymmetric. Our studies have shown that the different observational properties of outflows can be explained by the winds and jets observed in the simulations.</p> <p>Our models are calculated in dimensionless form, and can be applied to a variety of accreting magnetized objects, including neutron stars, white dwarfs, brown dwarfs and forming planets.<br /><br /><strong>Broader Impact:&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Two graduate students and one research associate were trained during this research award. The graduate students have successfully defended their theses. Continued<strong> </strong>support and renewal of the ongoing exhibit ``Star Birth'' in The Sciencenter of Ithaca has been provided. &nbsp;This exhibit was developed and supported by our Plasma Astrophysics group at Cornell. One of the graduate students has given several lectures in physics and astronomy in the rural elementary schools near Ithaca.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2016<br>      Modified by: Marina&nbsp;Romanova</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1211318/1211318_10212381_1480288347166_KurosawaRomanova2014-plot-landscape--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1211318/1211318_10212381_1480288347166_KurosawaRomanova2014-plot-landscape--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Example of axisymmetric simulations of conical winds"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1211318/1211318_10212381_1480288347166_KurosawaRomanova2014-plot-landscape--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Example of axisymmetric simulations of conical winds"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The matter flux distribution, sample field lines and homogeneous velocity vectors in a conical wind.</div> <div class="imageCredit">From Kurosawa and Romanova 2012</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Marina&nbsp;Romanova</div> <div class="imageTitle">Example of axisymmetric simulations of conical winds</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Overview of the Problem: Powerful outflows are observed in many young, newly forming stars.  It is commonly believed that the outflows are responsible for transporting excess angular momentum away from the star-disk system, and for the formation of newly born stars. Despite the recent high spatial resolution observations of such outflows, their exact launching and collimation mechanisms were not well understood. The main objective of the proposed research was to understand the formation and collimation mechanisms of the outflows associated with young solar-type stars, such as classical T Tauri stars (CTTSs). To achieve this goal, we explored a  set of possible scenarios of outflow formation and collimation by employing magnetohydrodynamic(MHD) simulations and by comparing our models with observations.   Intellectual Merit:  Our studies have led to several important conclusions: (1) Young, recently formed stars may be in the ``propeller regime", where a star rotates more rapidly than the inner parts of the accretion disk. Our simulations show that, in these cases, a significant part of the inner disk matter can be redirected into conically shaped winds, which are gradually collimated by the magnetic force. A smaller amount of the inner disk matter flows into a well-collimated, low-density jet along the stellar field lines. The jet component is driven and collimated by the magnetic force. Comparisons with the observations show that the two-component outflows are often present in CTTSs and other young stars. (2) In some young stars, accretion is non-stationary and episodic, where episodes of high accretion rate alternate with episodes of very low accretion rate. Our simulations show that when new matter comes into the disk it compresses the magnetosphere and provides the conditions for persistent conical winds. This mechanism can explain the winds from young stars where episodes of very high accretion rate are observed, such as in EXOrs and FU Ori type stars. (3) If a significant part of the inner disk is threaded with poloidal field lines, then matter flows from the inner disk to the wind along these field lines. Such a field may either come from large distances (together with the disk matter), or may form locally due to the dynamo mechanism.  We studied the formation of the field through the dynamo mechanism, and observed that the generated field has the shape of loops of different sizes.We observed from the simulations that the inner loops inflate and open due to the differential rotation between the star and the inner disk, and that matter flows into the wind along these field lines. Simulations show that the field is typically asymmetric about the equatorial plane, and that the outflows are also asymmetric. Comparisons with the observations show that the outflows from young stars are often asymmetric. Our studies have shown that the different observational properties of outflows can be explained by the winds and jets observed in the simulations.  Our models are calculated in dimensionless form, and can be applied to a variety of accreting magnetized objects, including neutron stars, white dwarfs, brown dwarfs and forming planets.  Broader Impact:   Two graduate students and one research associate were trained during this research award. The graduate students have successfully defended their theses. Continued support and renewal of the ongoing exhibit ``Star Birth'' in The Sciencenter of Ithaca has been provided.  This exhibit was developed and supported by our Plasma Astrophysics group at Cornell. One of the graduate students has given several lectures in physics and astronomy in the rural elementary schools near Ithaca.             Last Modified: 11/28/2016       Submitted by: Marina Romanova]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
