<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Ages for Red Giants: New Insights into the Star Formation of the Milky Way</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>71932.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>71932</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hans Krimm</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hkrimm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922761</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this collaborative award, the PIs will determine stellar ages to within 20% using Kepler and CoRoT asteroseismic data, and high-resolution spectra of more than 10,000 red giant branch (RGB) stars.  The investigators plan to capitalize on the fact that if the mass and composition of an RGB star can be measured, then the age of the star can be determined accurately because of the swiftness of evolution after the main sequence.  Asteroseismological data provides information on RGB pulsation amplitudes, which are combined with metallicity information from spectroscopy and photometry in order to derive the stars? ages.  The improved stellar ages are needed to constrain models of star formation and galactic evolution. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal has stated broader impacts in that it will help train a graduate student, some undergraduate students.  Also, the work will be relevant to stellar modeling as well as well as Galactic modeling, and the investigators will produce a catalog of red giants with ages, stellar parameters and chemical abundances.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1211144</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Harding</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul Harding</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>paul.harding@case.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2163684510</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000605750</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
<CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[10900 Euclid Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077758407</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CASE WESTERN RESERVE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>077758407</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Case Western Reserve University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cleveland</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[109000 Euclid Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~71932</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The age of an individual star is one of the most difficult properties to determine, especially for the majority of stars that are billions of years old, such as our Sun. Yet accurate ages of stars are crucial in order to understand the formation history of our own and other galaxies.&nbsp; <br /><br />In the past few decades we have learned that galaxies grow by repeated merging of smaller galaxies. We can see evidence for this clearly in other galaxies and also within our own galaxy, specially since the spectacular discovery of the ongoing accretion of the Sagittarius dwarf. Each of these "growth spurts" imprints a pattern on the properties of stars involved. Sometimes the subsequent evolution of the galaxy blurs the pattern; other times it is well preserved. Studying this history is appropriately called Galactic archeology.<br /><br />Precision photometry by the Kepler satellite enabled the discovery of thousands of planets and also allowed the measurement of the "vibrations" of many stars. These stellar vibrations show up as very subtle regular variations in brightness. Just like in a musical instrument, these vibrations have preferred values which in a star are related to its interior structure. The best stars for these studies are the luminous red giants. The signature of vibrations depends on the density of the star, from which we can determine its mass and thus age. This technique is known as Asteroseismology.<br />To obtain a precise age estimate it is necessary to also know the star's composition, ie the&nbsp; relative mix of elements. This research measured the composition of red giant stars that were observed by the Kepler satellite. Observations were obtained with the APOGEE infrared spectrograph, part of the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) III. <br /><br />The research resulted in a catalog (named APOKASC) of the composition, radii and masses for approximately 2000 red giants in the Kepler field. Several papers were published discussing these results.<br />Of particular interest was the study of stars that formed very early in the Galaxy's history, because the gas from which these stars formed was enriched with heavier elements by only one or a few supernovae. We found that the masses of these stars were overestimated by 10 to 20 percent when the standard equations of asteroseismology were used. These very old stars are extremely rare in the part of the galaxy observed by Kepler, and were thus preselected&nbsp; based on a specialized system of ground based photometry. This work was done at CWRU's Burrell Schmidt telescope, and undergraduate students were heavily involved in all parts of the project, providing valuable and in some cases unique training opportunities.&nbsp; A catalog of this photometry is in preparation. Spectra of Kepler giants continue to be observed by APOGEE as part of SDSS IV and the APOKASC catalog has grown to over 6000 stars.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2019<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;Harding</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The age of an individual star is one of the most difficult properties to determine, especially for the majority of stars that are billions of years old, such as our Sun. Yet accurate ages of stars are crucial in order to understand the formation history of our own and other galaxies.    In the past few decades we have learned that galaxies grow by repeated merging of smaller galaxies. We can see evidence for this clearly in other galaxies and also within our own galaxy, specially since the spectacular discovery of the ongoing accretion of the Sagittarius dwarf. Each of these "growth spurts" imprints a pattern on the properties of stars involved. Sometimes the subsequent evolution of the galaxy blurs the pattern; other times it is well preserved. Studying this history is appropriately called Galactic archeology.  Precision photometry by the Kepler satellite enabled the discovery of thousands of planets and also allowed the measurement of the "vibrations" of many stars. These stellar vibrations show up as very subtle regular variations in brightness. Just like in a musical instrument, these vibrations have preferred values which in a star are related to its interior structure. The best stars for these studies are the luminous red giants. The signature of vibrations depends on the density of the star, from which we can determine its mass and thus age. This technique is known as Asteroseismology. To obtain a precise age estimate it is necessary to also know the star's composition, ie the  relative mix of elements. This research measured the composition of red giant stars that were observed by the Kepler satellite. Observations were obtained with the APOGEE infrared spectrograph, part of the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) III.   The research resulted in a catalog (named APOKASC) of the composition, radii and masses for approximately 2000 red giants in the Kepler field. Several papers were published discussing these results. Of particular interest was the study of stars that formed very early in the Galaxy's history, because the gas from which these stars formed was enriched with heavier elements by only one or a few supernovae. We found that the masses of these stars were overestimated by 10 to 20 percent when the standard equations of asteroseismology were used. These very old stars are extremely rare in the part of the galaxy observed by Kepler, and were thus preselected  based on a specialized system of ground based photometry. This work was done at CWRU's Burrell Schmidt telescope, and undergraduate students were heavily involved in all parts of the project, providing valuable and in some cases unique training opportunities.  A catalog of this photometry is in preparation. Spectra of Kepler giants continue to be observed by APOGEE as part of SDSS IV and the APOKASC catalog has grown to over 6000 stars.       Last Modified: 08/05/2019       Submitted by: Paul Harding]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
