<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Differential and Total Cross Sections for Top Quark Production and other Processes at the LHC</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>120000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>120000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds the research activities of Professor Nikolaos Kidonakis at Kennesaw State University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project will involve calculations for the production of elementary particles such as the top quark, the Higgs boson, and Z bosons at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC), the world's highest-energy collider. The top quark is the most massive fundamental particle that has ever been discovered:  it has many unique properties and may be crucial to understanding the origin of electroweak symmetry breaking. For these reasons, the top quark was the centerpiece of the physics program at the Tevatron collider at Fermilab, and it is now a central part of the physics program at the LHC.  Similarly, the Higgs boson is the particle thought to be responsible for mass generation and its discovery is also a priority for the LHC.  As part of this project, Professor Kidonakis will improve theoretical predictions for top-quark production in top-antitop and single-top channels as well as for Higgs production and other processes.  He will do this by performing state-of-the-art calculations of higher-order corrections.  These calculations will ultimately be important for understanding the implications of upcoming LHC data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work is also envisioned to have significant broader impacts.  The proposed research is very timely since it addresses physics that is relevant to the LHC. The research findings will also be widely disseminated through publication in refereed journals and presentations in international conferences and workshops.  Finally, this project will strengthen the educational and research programs at Kennesaw State University. Professor Kidonakis has actively involved undergraduate and graduate students in his research, and this project offers numerous research and educational opportunities for student involvement.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1212472</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nikolaos</FirstName>
<LastName>Kidonakis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nikolaos Kidonakis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nkidonak@kennesaw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4705786607</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000458976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kennesaw State University Research and Service Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Kennesaw</CityName>
<ZipCode>301445591</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4705786381</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 Chastain Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MD 0111]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832879733</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KENNESAW STATE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH AND SERVICE FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Kennesaw State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Kennesaw</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>301445591</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 Chastain Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Professor Nikolaos Kidonakis performed research in theoretical elementary particle  physics, in particular calculations for the production of top quarks, W and Z bosons, and Higgs bosons in high-energy colliders. This work is relevant to the Large Hadron Collider (LHC), which is  the highest-energy particle collider in the world. By colliding high-energy protons  against each other, physicists expect to learn about  the fundamental particles of matter and their interactions.  The top quark is the most massive fundamental particle that has been  discovered and it has many unique properties, while the Higgs boson is responsible for mass generation.</p> <p>Professor Kidonakis greatly improved theoretical predictions  for top quark production by performing  state-of-the-art calculations of higher-order soft-gluon corrections. Theoretical methods were developed to make precise  predictions for top-quark and Higgs processes at the LHC and Tevatron colliders. This project&nbsp; also had significant broader impacts. Professor Kidonakis involved  students in his &nbsp;research, and thereby provided critical training. He also  gave public lectures and was interviewed by print and TV media on his research results. Thus, the project had impact on improving public knowledge of particle physics and recent discoveries.</p> <p>A total of twenty publications, including eight papers in international refereed journals and twelve papers in conference proceedings, were produced from the results of this project. Fifteen talks were presented at national and international conferences, and three talks were delivered at an international summer school. The numerical results from the project were shared with the experimental collaborations at the LHC and the Tevatron, who requested additional and updated predictions, and were widely used and cited in comparisons of theoretical predictions with experimental data. Further details about the theoretical analytical results were communicated to other theorists upon request.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/02/2015<br>      Modified by: Nikolaos&nbsp;Kidonakis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Professor Nikolaos Kidonakis performed research in theoretical elementary particle  physics, in particular calculations for the production of top quarks, W and Z bosons, and Higgs bosons in high-energy colliders. This work is relevant to the Large Hadron Collider (LHC), which is  the highest-energy particle collider in the world. By colliding high-energy protons  against each other, physicists expect to learn about  the fundamental particles of matter and their interactions.  The top quark is the most massive fundamental particle that has been  discovered and it has many unique properties, while the Higgs boson is responsible for mass generation.  Professor Kidonakis greatly improved theoretical predictions  for top quark production by performing  state-of-the-art calculations of higher-order soft-gluon corrections. Theoretical methods were developed to make precise  predictions for top-quark and Higgs processes at the LHC and Tevatron colliders. This project  also had significant broader impacts. Professor Kidonakis involved  students in his  research, and thereby provided critical training. He also  gave public lectures and was interviewed by print and TV media on his research results. Thus, the project had impact on improving public knowledge of particle physics and recent discoveries.  A total of twenty publications, including eight papers in international refereed journals and twelve papers in conference proceedings, were produced from the results of this project. Fifteen talks were presented at national and international conferences, and three talks were delivered at an international summer school. The numerical results from the project were shared with the experimental collaborations at the LHC and the Tevatron, who requested additional and updated predictions, and were widely used and cited in comparisons of theoretical predictions with experimental data. Further details about the theoretical analytical results were communicated to other theorists upon request.          Last Modified: 08/02/2015       Submitted by: Nikolaos Kidonakis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
