<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Comparative Analysis of Transfer RNAs by Mass Spectrometry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>496967.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>496967</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lin He</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lhe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924956</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With support from the Chemical Measurement and Imaging Program in the Division of Chemistry, Professor Patrick Limbach and his group at University of Cincinnati are developing instrumental approaches based on mass spectrometry for the identification, sequencing and analysis of an important class of biomolecules, namely transfer ribonucleic acids (tRNAs).  Because tRNAs are involved in the fundamental process of protein translation, it is important that new tools and approaches be developed that enable the sensitive and accurate determination of tRNA population and extent of modifications to the original tRNA sequence. This research will significantly advance the field of tRNA characterization by establishing the techniques required for multiplexed characterizations of tRNA populations. The advantage of multiplexed characterization is that significantly more information on tRNA identity and sequence modification can be obtained in a shorter time period and from less sample, as compared to current methods that analyze one tRNA at a time. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project is multidisciplinary, involving the areas of chemistry, biochemistry and molecular biology, thus undergraduates and graduate students working on this project will gain key instruction and insights into the field of modern biological mass spectrometry. These activities continue a long-standing emphasis of Professor Limbach on expanding the number of engaged underrepresented minorities in science, in general, and mass spectrometry, in particular.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1212625</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Limbach</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick A Limbach</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pat.limbach@uc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5135561871</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000287808</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Cincinnati Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>Cincinnati</CityName>
<ZipCode>452210222</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5135564358</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Hall, Suite 530</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[51 Goodman Dr.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041064767</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CINCINNATI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041064767</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Cincinnati Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Cincinnati</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>452210172</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[404 Crosley Tower]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL MEASUREMENT &amp; IMAGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~496967</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The research proposed in NSF CHE 1212625 builds upon our previous developments in NSF CHE 0910751 where we developed new mass spectrometry approaches to map modified nucleotides onto the sequence of specific ribonucleic acids (RNAs). These approaches now enable complex mixtures of RNAs to be evaluated, which improves the community&rsquo;s ability to understand the prevalence and biological function of RNA modifications.&nbsp; During CHE 1212625, we proposed to examine a new strategy for RNA modification mapping &ndash; a strategy build upon the comparative analysis of RNA digestion products (<strong>Figure 1</strong>).</p> <p>The outcomes of our research resulted in an entirely new approach that allows one to examine changes in RNA modification patterns. While others have examined changes in RNA modification status by analyzing modified nucleosides, our approach is unique in that we are viewing how the RNAs vary - both in RNA abundance and modification patterns. As this approach presents the RNA sequence locations where modifications vary, a much clearer understanding of the biological significance of any modification changes can be gained. As our approaches can be applied to any class of RNAs, we anticipate these mass spectrometry strategies will prove important in validating data on RNA modifications that is obtained using high throughput sequencing technologies. While accomplishing these research goals, we also trained the next generation of scientists in modern biochemical research.&nbsp; These students ranged from undergraduates to graduate students as well as post-doctoral researchers.&nbsp; Such students have become better prepared to tackle new challenges in biochemical research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/01/2015<br>      Modified by: Patrick&nbsp;A&nbsp;Limbach</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1212625/1212625_10187776_1443709420490_OutcomesFigure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1212625/1212625_10187776_1443709420490_OutcomesFigure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CHE 1212625 Outcomes Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1212625/1212625_10187776_1443709420490_OutcomesFigure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CHE 1212625 Outcomes Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Schematic outline of comparative sequencing by isotope labeling and LC-MS where E. coli (or another organism whose complete set of RNA modifications is known) serves as the reference and the candidate contains the set of RNAs whose modification patterns are unknown.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Patrick A Limbach</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Patrick&nbsp;A&nbsp;Limbach</div> <div class="imageTitle">CHE 1212625 Outcomes Figure 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The research proposed in NSF CHE 1212625 builds upon our previous developments in NSF CHE 0910751 where we developed new mass spectrometry approaches to map modified nucleotides onto the sequence of specific ribonucleic acids (RNAs). These approaches now enable complex mixtures of RNAs to be evaluated, which improves the communityÆs ability to understand the prevalence and biological function of RNA modifications.  During CHE 1212625, we proposed to examine a new strategy for RNA modification mapping &ndash; a strategy build upon the comparative analysis of RNA digestion products (Figure 1).  The outcomes of our research resulted in an entirely new approach that allows one to examine changes in RNA modification patterns. While others have examined changes in RNA modification status by analyzing modified nucleosides, our approach is unique in that we are viewing how the RNAs vary - both in RNA abundance and modification patterns. As this approach presents the RNA sequence locations where modifications vary, a much clearer understanding of the biological significance of any modification changes can be gained. As our approaches can be applied to any class of RNAs, we anticipate these mass spectrometry strategies will prove important in validating data on RNA modifications that is obtained using high throughput sequencing technologies. While accomplishing these research goals, we also trained the next generation of scientists in modern biochemical research.  These students ranged from undergraduates to graduate students as well as post-doctoral researchers.  Such students have become better prepared to tackle new challenges in biochemical research.          Last Modified: 10/01/2015       Submitted by: Patrick A Limbach]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
