<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Entanglement in Biology -- How Nature Controls the Topology of Proteins</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>540000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>540000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Krastan Blagoev</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kblagoev@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924666</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Proteins with non-trivial topology - knotted proteins - provide the greatest challenge in protein folding. Therefore, understanding the mechanisms of knot formation and stability will have a major impact on our understanding of protein folding and functional dynamics at large. This project is focused on understanding and characterizing the underlying physical principles responsible for knot formation in the alpha/beta knot methyltransferase family of proteins. Research will focus on a monomeric member of the family, firmly simplifying folding analyses. This discovery of a monomeric knotted protein will allow the dissection of the underlying principles that lead to knot formation and the impact on protein function. Consequently, these studies will provide the fundamental basis for future protein design efforts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BROADER IMPACT. This project bridges the fields of mathematics, biology, chemistry, and physics, inspiring cutting-edge interdisciplinary collaborations, and will be important in defining the key problems in folding for the next decade. Graduate students will be exposed to chemistry, mathematics, physics and biology through this study and will be provided with valuable experimental and theoretical skills (molecular biology, protein biochemistry, chemical synthesis, coordination chemistry, spectroscopic techniques, electrochemistry, crystallography) that will better assist them as they tackle complex scientific problems later in their careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is being supported jointly by the Physics of Living Systems Program in the Physics Division and by the Molecular Biophysics Program in Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1212312</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patricia</FirstName>
<LastName>Jennings</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patricia A Jennings</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pajennings@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585346417</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000193667</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7246</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>BIOMOLECULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7183</Code>
<Text>MINORITY GRAD STDNT TRAVEL AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7246</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default"><em><strong>Intellectual Merit.</strong></em>The principle focus of our NSF- award (PHY-1212312), that was entitled &ldquo;Entanglement in Biology--How Nature Controls the Topology of Proteins&rdquo; was to understand what drives folding and formation of complex knotted topologies in proteins and how knotted regions regulate function. The work for this proposal arose from the strong collaborative effort between our experimental efforts with that of our theoretical partners (The Onuchic and Sulkowska Groups) and the continued training and mentorship of fellows who bridge the experimental and theoretical realms. This project resulted in the pioneering experimental discoveries of&nbsp; (A) a new class of proteins, the pierced lasso (PL) topology, (B) investigations of the origins of hysteresis (or uncommon bistability as a result of unusual topology and stability) in complex topologies, and led to our discovery of how to (C) explore threading mechanisms and (D) untie a knotted protein. The training this funding allowed us to develop the experimental advantage to ask fundamental questions in the protein theory field: How can a protein form a threaded element? How does knotting affect function? How can it fold into a deeply knotted biologically active protein? To fully understand how nature controls the topology of proteins, extensive theoretical, numerical and experimental progress is required. The progress we achieved necessitated the efforts of top researchers working at the interface of mathematics, biology, chemistry, and physics.</p> <p class="Default"><em><strong>Broader Impact.</strong></em> Our NSF funding allowed us to bridge these fields, inspired cutting-edge interdisciplinary collaborations, and was essential for defining key problems for the next decade. Ultimately, understanding the biophysical biochemistry of knotted proteins can be used to design and engineer novel classes of proteins that have superior mechanical and thermal stability properties. Knotting, threading and slip knotting in proteins are new and challenging topics in knot theory, for which new formalisms must be derived and must take into account physical properties of these biological objects.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/02/2015<br>      Modified by: Patricia&nbsp;A&nbsp;Jennings</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Intellectual Merit.The principle focus of our NSF- award (PHY-1212312), that was entitled "Entanglement in Biology--How Nature Controls the Topology of Proteins" was to understand what drives folding and formation of complex knotted topologies in proteins and how knotted regions regulate function. The work for this proposal arose from the strong collaborative effort between our experimental efforts with that of our theoretical partners (The Onuchic and Sulkowska Groups) and the continued training and mentorship of fellows who bridge the experimental and theoretical realms. This project resulted in the pioneering experimental discoveries of  (A) a new class of proteins, the pierced lasso (PL) topology, (B) investigations of the origins of hysteresis (or uncommon bistability as a result of unusual topology and stability) in complex topologies, and led to our discovery of how to (C) explore threading mechanisms and (D) untie a knotted protein. The training this funding allowed us to develop the experimental advantage to ask fundamental questions in the protein theory field: How can a protein form a threaded element? How does knotting affect function? How can it fold into a deeply knotted biologically active protein? To fully understand how nature controls the topology of proteins, extensive theoretical, numerical and experimental progress is required. The progress we achieved necessitated the efforts of top researchers working at the interface of mathematics, biology, chemistry, and physics. Broader Impact. Our NSF funding allowed us to bridge these fields, inspired cutting-edge interdisciplinary collaborations, and was essential for defining key problems for the next decade. Ultimately, understanding the biophysical biochemistry of knotted proteins can be used to design and engineer novel classes of proteins that have superior mechanical and thermal stability properties. Knotting, threading and slip knotting in proteins are new and challenging topics in knot theory, for which new formalisms must be derived and must take into account physical properties of these biological objects.            Last Modified: 12/02/2015       Submitted by: Patricia A Jennings]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
