<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Titanium Dioxide Photocatalysis:  Interactions of band edge carriers with molecules by ultrafast photoemission spectroscopy and theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gjanini@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928840</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award from the Chemical Catalysis Program of the Chemistry Division of the National Science Foundation, Prof. Hrvoje Petek, his collaborator Dr. Jin Zhao and their students at the University of Pittsburgh will study by experiment and theory the electron driven processes in photocatalytic chemistry on rutile titanium dioxide surfaces. Excitation of carriers across the band gap of titanium dioxide with near-ultraviolet light is known to initiate a variety of photocatalytic processes involving interaction of adsorbed molecules with energetic electrons and holes. The timescales of photophysical and photochemical processes span femtoseconds to seconds. The interaction of photoexcited electrons with adsorbed molecules and defects will be studied for molecule covered single crystal titanium dioxide surfaces under ultrahigh vacuum conditions by time-resolved two-photon photoemission spectroscopy. The extension of the two-photon photoemission technique to 4.6 eV will enable the study of dynamics of the most chemically significant conduction band edge electrons with chemisorbed molecules. In parallel, advanced theoretical methods will be used to study how photoexcited carriers initiate chemical reactions of chemisorbed molecules.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Titanium dioxide is a model photocatalyst of significant fundamental interest for the conversion of solar to chemical energy starting with abundant chemical feedstocks such as water and carbon dioxide. A central issue in photocatalysis is how photoexcited carriers (electrons and holes) interact with adsorbed molecules to initiate chemical reactions. Such knowledge can be used to design more efficient photocatalyst materials and practical solar energy conversion processes. The potential advances in harnessing solar energy can conceivably reduce our reliance on fossil fuels and convert potentially harmful byproducts of combustion into valuable chemical fuels. This research will be used to train the next generation of scientists since students will be exposed to high-level experimental and theoretical methods for investigation of ultrafast interfacial dynamics. They will explore research areas that can have major impacts on society, and will be exposed to international collaboration with colleagues at the University of Science and Technology of China.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1213189</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hrvoje</FirstName>
<LastName>Petek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hrvoje Petek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>petek@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126249000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000178382</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jin</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jin Zhao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jiz38@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126247400</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000519411</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1108</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL CATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7289</Code>
<Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH RESOURCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7905</Code>
<Text>MPS SUST ENERGY SCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~450000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual merit.</strong> Titanium dioxide (TiO<sub>2</sub>) is a large band gap semiconductor of significant interest for conversion of solar to chemical or electrical energy through processes such as photocatalysis and photovoltaics. These processes are initiated by excitation of TiO<sub>2</sub> across its band gap of 3.0 eV (for the rutile polymorph) to generate electrons in the conduction band and holes in the valence band. The properties of these electrons and holes, such as electrical mobility, and their interactions with adsorbed molecules significantly affect the efficiency of energy transduction processes. The efficiency of these processes can be further enhanced by coupling TiO<sub>2</sub> with small metallic clusters with intense plasmonic resonances. The significant body of research on TiO<sub>2</sub> has made it a <em>de facto</em> paradigm for photocatalytic and photovoltaic solar energy harvesting, yet the character of electrons and holes and their interaction with molecules is poorly understood, because the primary excitation and relaxation processes occur on the femtosecond time scale (10<sup>-15</sup> s).</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We have investigated the character of electrons and holes in TiO<sub>2</sub> by time-resolved two-photon photoemission spectroscopy, which exploits two-photon absorption to emit electrons from TiO<sub>2</sub> surface into vacuum where it can be analyzed with respect to kinetic energy and emission angle to obtain information on the electronic structure and electron lifetimes in the conduction band of TiO<sub>2</sub>. Through such studies we have discovered an optical transition between the d-orbitals of Ti atoms that provide valuable information on the structure of electrons in the conduction band of TiO<sub>2</sub>. These spectra have been performed as a function of the excitation laser wavelength, polarization, TiO<sub>2</sub> crystal azimuthal orientation, temperature, molecular adsorption, as well as metal nanoparticle adsorption, as suggested in the provided figure. These studies provided evidence that electrons in the conduction band of TiO<sub>2</sub> form polarons, which are quasiparticles consisting of an electron and a lattice distortion that is caused by their mutual coulomb interaction. These studies provide valuable evidence for the theoretical description of charge carriers in TiO<sub>2</sub>.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Furthermore, we have employed high level electronic structure theory, which is capable of describing the electronically excited states and perform dynamical calculations at finite temperatures to describe the electron and hole acceptor states for adsorbed molecules (water and methanol) on TiO<sub>2</sub> surfaces, as well as their charge transfer and energy relaxation rates. These theoretical studies explain many experimentally observed features of TiO<sub>2</sub> photocatalysis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts.</strong> The research was performed through an international collaboration between Hrvoje Petek (PI; University of Pittsburgh) and Jin Zhao (co-PI; Univ. of Science and Technology of China), who respectively led the experimental and theoretical aspects of this project. The broad theme of the project provided new fundamental information on the clean energy generation by photocatalytic and photovoltaic effects. The students and postdocs involved in this research obtained advanced experimental and theoretical training in an international (USA and China) setting. The results of this collaboration were broadly disseminated by, for example, Petek and Zhao organizing the &ldquo;<em>Symposium on &ldquo;Fundamental Science of Photon and Electron Induced Surface Processes</em>,&rdquo; Honolulu, HI. Dec. 15-20, 2016.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Hrvoje&nbsp;Petek</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1213189/1213189_10187797_1475156386263_NSFreportfig--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1213189/1213189_10187797_1475156386263_NSFreportfig--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2PP spectroscopy of TiO2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1213189/1213189_10187797_1475156386263_NSFreportfig--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2PP spectroscopy of TiO2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Analysis of the structure of electrons in the conduction band of TiO2 by wavelength, polarization, and crystal azimuth dependent two-photon photoemission (2PP) spectroscopy. 2PP spectra with 3.44 eV light are shown for different laser polarizations to select different optical transitions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">S. Tan, A. Argondizzo, H. Petek</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hrvoje&nbsp;Petek</div> <div class="imageTitle">2PP spectroscopy of TiO2</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit. Titanium dioxide (TiO2) is a large band gap semiconductor of significant interest for conversion of solar to chemical or electrical energy through processes such as photocatalysis and photovoltaics. These processes are initiated by excitation of TiO2 across its band gap of 3.0 eV (for the rutile polymorph) to generate electrons in the conduction band and holes in the valence band. The properties of these electrons and holes, such as electrical mobility, and their interactions with adsorbed molecules significantly affect the efficiency of energy transduction processes. The efficiency of these processes can be further enhanced by coupling TiO2 with small metallic clusters with intense plasmonic resonances. The significant body of research on TiO2 has made it a de facto paradigm for photocatalytic and photovoltaic solar energy harvesting, yet the character of electrons and holes and their interaction with molecules is poorly understood, because the primary excitation and relaxation processes occur on the femtosecond time scale (10-15 s).              We have investigated the character of electrons and holes in TiO2 by time-resolved two-photon photoemission spectroscopy, which exploits two-photon absorption to emit electrons from TiO2 surface into vacuum where it can be analyzed with respect to kinetic energy and emission angle to obtain information on the electronic structure and electron lifetimes in the conduction band of TiO2. Through such studies we have discovered an optical transition between the d-orbitals of Ti atoms that provide valuable information on the structure of electrons in the conduction band of TiO2. These spectra have been performed as a function of the excitation laser wavelength, polarization, TiO2 crystal azimuthal orientation, temperature, molecular adsorption, as well as metal nanoparticle adsorption, as suggested in the provided figure. These studies provided evidence that electrons in the conduction band of TiO2 form polarons, which are quasiparticles consisting of an electron and a lattice distortion that is caused by their mutual coulomb interaction. These studies provide valuable evidence for the theoretical description of charge carriers in TiO2.              Furthermore, we have employed high level electronic structure theory, which is capable of describing the electronically excited states and perform dynamical calculations at finite temperatures to describe the electron and hole acceptor states for adsorbed molecules (water and methanol) on TiO2 surfaces, as well as their charge transfer and energy relaxation rates. These theoretical studies explain many experimentally observed features of TiO2 photocatalysis.     Broader impacts. The research was performed through an international collaboration between Hrvoje Petek (PI; University of Pittsburgh) and Jin Zhao (co-PI; Univ. of Science and Technology of China), who respectively led the experimental and theoretical aspects of this project. The broad theme of the project provided new fundamental information on the clean energy generation by photocatalytic and photovoltaic effects. The students and postdocs involved in this research obtained advanced experimental and theoretical training in an international (USA and China) setting. The results of this collaboration were broadly disseminated by, for example, Petek and Zhao organizing the "Symposium on "Fundamental Science of Photon and Electron Induced Surface Processes," Honolulu, HI. Dec. 15-20, 2016.          Last Modified: 09/29/2016       Submitted by: Hrvoje Petek]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
