<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Receptor Mediated Circular Dichroism Spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>505500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>505500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program is supporting the research of Professor Babak Borhan (Michigan State University) in the area of chiroptical spectroscopy.  With prior NSF CAREER funding, his laboratory has shown that porphyrin tweezers (two metalloporphyrins linked via an alkyl linker) can serve as host systems for chiral guest molecules, which upon complexation lead to an observable circular dichroic (CD) spectrum.  The resultant spectrum is easily deciphered to extract stereochemical information of the bound chiral guest molecule.  The advantages are that the methodology is non-empirical in assignment of helicity for the interacting porphyrins, it is micro-scale in nature requiring microgram amounts of chiral substrate, it is non-destructive (chiral material can be recovered), has little prep work, and provides the answer in a matter of minutes.  Future work will focus on expanding the repertoire of host systems such that a larger subset of chiral organic molecules can succumb to analysis.  Most importantly, guest molecules that only have one site of complexation (thus cannot complex with both porphyrins of the tweezer) require a new strategy.  It is hypothesized that appropriately designed pseudo-cage host systems with the ability to complex molecules that contain only one site of attachment will predominantly adopt either a P or M helicity upon interaction with chiral guest substrates.  The resultant complex is CD active and will provide information required for analysis of absolute stereochemistry.  The target chiral molecules for absolute stereochemical determinations are alcohols, amines, diols, diamines, epoxy alcohols, and hydroxy ketones, saturated and unsaturated heterocyclic molecules, and molecules with remote stereochemistry, to name a few.  The latter list of compound families is a large subset of chiral molecules that serve as chiral pool reagents for numerous applications in organic synthesis, organic materials, and the medicinal and pharmaceutical arena.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A routine, microscale, easy, and reliable method for stereochemical determinations is critical in many areas of chemistry and biology, benefiting a large number of researchers in the latter areas.  The nature of the research proposed here is interdisciplinary.  Student training will couple chemical synthesis with the design of chromophoric hosts based on a thorough understanding of molecular and structural dynamics.  The students will also have to be proficient and knowledgeable spectroscopists.  The proposal also has elements that are fit for less accomplished students to participate in research.  For the past ten years, the group has organized and directed the Project SEED program at Michigan State University.  Continuing to recruit, train, and scientifically stimulate high school students will be a top priority.  The training of undergraduate students will be no less important.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1213759</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Babak</FirstName>
<LastName>Borhan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Babak Borhan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>borhan@cem.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173559715</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000448956</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488241046</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6879</Code>
<Text>Structure,Dynamics &amp;Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6879</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURE, DYNAMIC &amp; MECHANISM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~505500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;The overarching goals of our project were to develop simple, routine, and efficient means by which the absolute stereochemistry of small organic molecules could be determined.&nbsp; Certain molecules are referred to as chiral.&nbsp; In the simplest case, a chiral carbon has four different substituents, which leads to two possible arrangements of the tetrahedral carbon; the two arrangements are non-superimposable, much like mirror images of two objects, or the left and right hands of an individual.&nbsp; This difference in symmetry, which leads to two distinct molecules, can and often has very different biological activities, yet posses&rsquo; very similar physical properties.&nbsp; Numerous synthetic methodologies have and are being developed to synthesize molecules of specific chirality with absolute control.&nbsp; Nonetheless, methods to assign the absolute stereochemistry of asymmetric centers has lacked far behind.&nbsp; Our interest is to devise methods that address the latter shortcoming.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our approach in this grant was to devise host molecular systems that are able to bind chiral molecules, and via transfer of chiral information, lead to an arrangement in the host molecule that can be easily detected through circular dichroic measurements.&nbsp; Exciton Coupled Circular Dichroism (ECCD) is a principle in spectroscopy that can relate the observed signal obtained from the sample to the helicity (or otherwise chirality) of the host system.&nbsp; Since the host system gains its asymmetry from the bound chiral molecule, we can in turn relate the observed signal to the determination of the guests&rsquo; absolute stereochemistry.&nbsp; In this grant period, we devised a new host system, the MAPOL series, that have a binding cavity for non-covalent attachment of the guest molecules, and a chromophoric segment that is under the influence of the bound molecule.&nbsp; The response induced in the MAPOL host system is easily observed through CD measurements.&nbsp; We addressed the absolute stereochemical determination of historically difficult families of molecules using the MAPOL system; these include, monoamines, cyanohydrins, and sulfoxides.&nbsp;</p> <p>The MAPOL series was not the only host system devised.&nbsp; We began our investigations into developing a new host system capable of covalent attachment for absolute stereochemical determination of molecules such as amines and alcohols.&nbsp; The advantage of this system is its ability for rapid and micro scale derivatization, leading to a system that is very hopefully for high throughput screening (HTS) efforts.&nbsp; We also extended our prior work into developing methods for the absolute stereochemical determination of aziridines, a highly important functional group in organic chemistry.&nbsp; Finally, we have begun to investigate, and successfully show that stereochemistry residing remote from a binding functional group such as an alcohol or amine can be solved using our methodology with the appropriate host designed.&nbsp; Our investigations have provided the community with robust techniques for routine determination of absolute stereochemistry.&nbsp; We have been cognizant of the fact that these methodologies must be accessible to researchers that are necessarily not experts in the area spectroscopy or stereochemical elucidations.&nbsp; Thus, all of our methods are devised with the appropriate mnemonics that guide the user for operational ease, but yet provide the confidence that is required for stereochemical determination.&nbsp; It should be noted that these methods are micro scale in nature, requiring less than a microgram of host per analysis, and equivalent amount of analyte for binding.&nbsp; The results are obtained within minutes of mixing the host and the guest system.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Babak&nbsp;Borhan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The overarching goals of our project were to develop simple, routine, and efficient means by which the absolute stereochemistry of small organic molecules could be determined.  Certain molecules are referred to as chiral.  In the simplest case, a chiral carbon has four different substituents, which leads to two possible arrangements of the tetrahedral carbon; the two arrangements are non-superimposable, much like mirror images of two objects, or the left and right hands of an individual.  This difference in symmetry, which leads to two distinct molecules, can and often has very different biological activities, yet posses? very similar physical properties.  Numerous synthetic methodologies have and are being developed to synthesize molecules of specific chirality with absolute control.  Nonetheless, methods to assign the absolute stereochemistry of asymmetric centers has lacked far behind.  Our interest is to devise methods that address the latter shortcoming.   Our approach in this grant was to devise host molecular systems that are able to bind chiral molecules, and via transfer of chiral information, lead to an arrangement in the host molecule that can be easily detected through circular dichroic measurements.  Exciton Coupled Circular Dichroism (ECCD) is a principle in spectroscopy that can relate the observed signal obtained from the sample to the helicity (or otherwise chirality) of the host system.  Since the host system gains its asymmetry from the bound chiral molecule, we can in turn relate the observed signal to the determination of the guests? absolute stereochemistry.  In this grant period, we devised a new host system, the MAPOL series, that have a binding cavity for non-covalent attachment of the guest molecules, and a chromophoric segment that is under the influence of the bound molecule.  The response induced in the MAPOL host system is easily observed through CD measurements.  We addressed the absolute stereochemical determination of historically difficult families of molecules using the MAPOL system; these include, monoamines, cyanohydrins, and sulfoxides.   The MAPOL series was not the only host system devised.  We began our investigations into developing a new host system capable of covalent attachment for absolute stereochemical determination of molecules such as amines and alcohols.  The advantage of this system is its ability for rapid and micro scale derivatization, leading to a system that is very hopefully for high throughput screening (HTS) efforts.  We also extended our prior work into developing methods for the absolute stereochemical determination of aziridines, a highly important functional group in organic chemistry.  Finally, we have begun to investigate, and successfully show that stereochemistry residing remote from a binding functional group such as an alcohol or amine can be solved using our methodology with the appropriate host designed.  Our investigations have provided the community with robust techniques for routine determination of absolute stereochemistry.  We have been cognizant of the fact that these methodologies must be accessible to researchers that are necessarily not experts in the area spectroscopy or stereochemical elucidations.  Thus, all of our methods are devised with the appropriate mnemonics that guide the user for operational ease, but yet provide the confidence that is required for stereochemical determination.  It should be noted that these methods are micro scale in nature, requiring less than a microgram of host per analysis, and equivalent amount of analyte for binding.  The results are obtained within minutes of mixing the host and the guest system.                   Last Modified: 01/28/2017       Submitted by: Babak Borhan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
