<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Chemical Biology of Energy-Dependent Proteolysis in Mitochondria</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>270000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Rockcliffe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>drockcli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927123</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this award from the Chemistry of Life Processes Program in the Chemistry Division, Dr. Irene Lee, from Case Western Reserve University, will develop a chemical biology approach to evaluating the contribution of ATP-dependent proteolysis in the maintenance of mitochondria homeostasis at a post-translational level. The mitochondrion is an important organelle that provides energy to sustain life. One of the key biochemical reactions is oxidative phosphorylation, which frequently generates reactive oxidizing species (ROS) as by-products. If allowed to accumulate, these ROS threaten the integrity of mitochondria by damaging the chemical integrity of lipids, nucleic acids and proteins in the organelles. In the matrix of mitochondria, protein quality control is presumably maintained by two energy dependent proteases, one of which is known as ClpXP (caseinolytic protease complex XP).  Dr. Lee's work will generate selective substrates and inhibitors of human ClpXP to allow for evaluation of protease functions in mitochondrial protein lysates and intact mitochondria in the model cell line HeLa. Once proven to be effective, the strategy proposed in this study will find broad applications in generating tools to elucidate the roles played by non-proteasomal ATP-dependent proteases in the maintenance of cellular homeostasis in the future. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project employs a multi-disciplinary approach to develop selective activity probes and inhibitors that will be used to address the physiological functions of a protease machine in mitochondria. Students will acquire training in enzyme kinetics, protein chemistry, liquid chromatography, mass spectrometry, chemical synthesis, solid phase peptide synthesis, fluorescence spectroscopy, protein purification and molecular cloning. These research activities provide excellent training opportunities to undergraduate and graduate students in chemical biology.  Each graduate student in Dr. Lee's group will also be involved in undergraduate education, as each student will train and work with an undergraduate researcher for at least one semester. This endeavor is designed to provide graduate students teaching and mentoring experiences.  Taken together, this project will provide students with the technical and social skills needed to enter a research or science education career. Additionally, all personnel working in the Lee group serve as volunteers to the National Youth Sports Program (NYSP), a summer program offered to children of low-income families in the Greater Cleveland area between the ages of 10 and 16. The Lee group teaches these children chemistry of daily life through experimentation with household chemicals and dry ice. This annual outreach activity has become a tradition in the Lee group, where undergraduate and graduate students learn to become more involved in the community and education for the underprivileged.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1213175</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Irene</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Irene Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ixl13@po.cwru.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2163686001</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000284672</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
<CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[10900 Euclid Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077758407</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CASE WESTERN RESERVE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>077758407</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Case Western Reserve University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cleveland</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>441067078</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Chemistry, 2080 Adelbert Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Mitochondria are organelles responsible for generating energy in mammalian cells.&nbsp; The goal of this project is to generate chemical probes to quantitatively detect and/or inactivate the activities of the ATP-dependent proteases known as Lon and ClpXP, respectively.&nbsp; These two proteases are found nearby each other in the mitochondria.&nbsp; Their exact physiological functions are currently not well defined but both are speculated to be responsible for removing damaged proteins in mitochondria, a process needed to maintain proper organelle function.&nbsp; Supported by this award, our lab has successfully generated two fluorogenic peptide substrates and one irreversible inhibitor for human ClpXP.&nbsp; Mechanistic characterization revealed that these chemical probes are very selective as they do not target human Lon at all.&nbsp; Given such success, these chemical probes are being tested in cell lysate and mitochondrial extracts to detect endogenous human ClpXP activity.&nbsp; The ultimate goal for this portion of the research is to optimize these chemical probes into imaging agents to allow for the detection of ClpXP activity in live cells such that we can learn about when ClpXP is needed during mitochondria metabolism.</p> <p>The broader impacts of this award are the generation of chemical probes to study the physiological mechanisms by which ATP-dependent proteolysis maintain mitochondrial functions.&nbsp; Students participating in this project were trained with research skills in enzymology, molecular cloning, fluorescence spectroscopy, chemical synthesis and teaching biochemistry to children ages between 10 to 16 years old.&nbsp; The teaching component was incorporated into part of an outreach program known as National Youth Sport Program (NYSP).&nbsp;&nbsp; Children enrolled in the NYSP program typically come from the inner city of Cleveland.&nbsp; Trainees supported by this award interacted with the NYSP children through lab activities, with primary focus on oxidative reactions and their effects on living organisms such as bacteria.&nbsp; Through these interactions, trainees learned to refine their scientific communication and teaching skills.&nbsp; It was our hope that children from the NYSP program might enjoy their experiences enough to consider pursuing an advanced degree at a University in the future.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2015<br>      Modified by: Irene&nbsp;Lee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Mitochondria are organelles responsible for generating energy in mammalian cells.  The goal of this project is to generate chemical probes to quantitatively detect and/or inactivate the activities of the ATP-dependent proteases known as Lon and ClpXP, respectively.  These two proteases are found nearby each other in the mitochondria.  Their exact physiological functions are currently not well defined but both are speculated to be responsible for removing damaged proteins in mitochondria, a process needed to maintain proper organelle function.  Supported by this award, our lab has successfully generated two fluorogenic peptide substrates and one irreversible inhibitor for human ClpXP.  Mechanistic characterization revealed that these chemical probes are very selective as they do not target human Lon at all.  Given such success, these chemical probes are being tested in cell lysate and mitochondrial extracts to detect endogenous human ClpXP activity.  The ultimate goal for this portion of the research is to optimize these chemical probes into imaging agents to allow for the detection of ClpXP activity in live cells such that we can learn about when ClpXP is needed during mitochondria metabolism.  The broader impacts of this award are the generation of chemical probes to study the physiological mechanisms by which ATP-dependent proteolysis maintain mitochondrial functions.  Students participating in this project were trained with research skills in enzymology, molecular cloning, fluorescence spectroscopy, chemical synthesis and teaching biochemistry to children ages between 10 to 16 years old.  The teaching component was incorporated into part of an outreach program known as National Youth Sport Program (NYSP).   Children enrolled in the NYSP program typically come from the inner city of Cleveland.  Trainees supported by this award interacted with the NYSP children through lab activities, with primary focus on oxidative reactions and their effects on living organisms such as bacteria.  Through these interactions, trainees learned to refine their scientific communication and teaching skills.  It was our hope that children from the NYSP program might enjoy their experiences enough to consider pursuing an advanced degree at a University in the future.       Last Modified: 10/29/2015       Submitted by: Irene Lee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
