<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Silica Nanopores Surface-Modified with Ionomer Brushes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gjanini@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928840</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project, funded by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program of the Chemistry Division, Ilya Zharov of the University of Utah will prepare and investigate novel nanostructured proton- and lithium-conducting membranes, in which ordered inorganic nanopores are surface-modified with well-defined polymer molecules carrying acidic and/or basic functional groups.  The highly ordered inorganic materials displaying continuous networks of nanopores that will be investigated are silica colloidal crystals, inverse silica colloidal crystals and silica-coated anodized alumina.  They will serve as solid matrixes providing mechanical stability and supporting the proton- and ion-conducting polymers.  The architecture of these membranes makes them particularly suitable for systematic studies needed to understand the ion transport through polymer brushes inside confined spaces.  Structure-property relationships will be determined for nanopores of different geometry and for polymer brush architectures prepared by surface-initiated living polymerization inside the inorganic nanopores. The broader impacts involve interdisciplinary training of graduate and undergraduate students, recruitment of underrepresented groups in chemical sciences to participate in the research project, and outreach to local elementary, middle and high schools through the Natural History Museum of Utah's Youth Teaching Youth (YTY) program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In practical terms, proton- and lithium-conducting membranes are key components of fuel cells and batteries, respectively, and the membranes that will be investigated possess unique features that are fundamentally different from the traditional polyelectrolyte or composite organic-inorganic membranes.  Therefore, this research, although fundamental in nature, has the potential to lead to breakthroughs in energy technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1213628</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ilya</FirstName>
<LastName>Zharov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ilya Zharov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>i.zharov@utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015879335</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000417412</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Second Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF UTAH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Utah]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841120850</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6885</Code>
<Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1948</Code>
<Text>SYNTHESIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goals of the project were to prepare and investigate novel nanostructured ion-conducting membranes, in which highly ordered inorganic nanopores are surface-modified with well-defined polymer molecules carrying acid or base functionalities. In the course of our work we&nbsp;conducted four major activities: (1) preparation of porous silica matrices by the assembly of silica nanoparticles; (2) preparation of proton-conducting membranes by pore-filling porous silica matrices with sulfonated polymer brushes; (3) preparation of lithium-conducting membranes by pore-filling porous silica matrices with polyether polymer brushes; (4) preparation of novel ion-conducting membranes using polymer brush nanoparticles.</p> <p>We were able to develop methods for the preparation of ordered silica membranes from the corresponding silica nanoparticles. We prepared proton-and lithium ion-conducting membranes by filling the nanopores in silica with polymer brushes. We discovered a novel method for the preparation of functional membranes by self-assembly of polymer brush nanoparticles. Such membranes can be prepared with high ionic ocnductivity or with size- and charge- selective transport.</p> <p>The result of this work were reported in 65 invited and contributed talks by the PI and the students working on the project. The results were also reported in 20 peer-reviewed publications.</p> <p>Four graduate students (two defended their PhD dissertations and two more are expected to defend ) and two undergraduate students have participated in the project activities and thus have been trained in the interdisciplinary and collaborative environment, and made outstanding progress on their path to independent scientific careers. The PI and the students working on the project participated in various outreach activities at&nbsp;local elementary, middle and high schools, as well as the&nbsp;the Natural History Museum of Utah.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Ilya&nbsp;Zharov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goals of the project were to prepare and investigate novel nanostructured ion-conducting membranes, in which highly ordered inorganic nanopores are surface-modified with well-defined polymer molecules carrying acid or base functionalities. In the course of our work we conducted four major activities: (1) preparation of porous silica matrices by the assembly of silica nanoparticles; (2) preparation of proton-conducting membranes by pore-filling porous silica matrices with sulfonated polymer brushes; (3) preparation of lithium-conducting membranes by pore-filling porous silica matrices with polyether polymer brushes; (4) preparation of novel ion-conducting membranes using polymer brush nanoparticles.  We were able to develop methods for the preparation of ordered silica membranes from the corresponding silica nanoparticles. We prepared proton-and lithium ion-conducting membranes by filling the nanopores in silica with polymer brushes. We discovered a novel method for the preparation of functional membranes by self-assembly of polymer brush nanoparticles. Such membranes can be prepared with high ionic ocnductivity or with size- and charge- selective transport.  The result of this work were reported in 65 invited and contributed talks by the PI and the students working on the project. The results were also reported in 20 peer-reviewed publications.  Four graduate students (two defended their PhD dissertations and two more are expected to defend ) and two undergraduate students have participated in the project activities and thus have been trained in the interdisciplinary and collaborative environment, and made outstanding progress on their path to independent scientific careers. The PI and the students working on the project participated in various outreach activities at local elementary, middle and high schools, as well as the the Natural History Museum of Utah.       Last Modified: 11/30/2017       Submitted by: Ilya Zharov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
