<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Enhancing the Bactericidal Activity of Copper: An Economically Viable Solution for Lowering Copper Usage Rates in Agriculture</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project describes a cost-effective method for reducing the quantities of copper used for agricultural crop protection. Currently, millions of pounds of copper are being sprayed onto plants each year. This copper is released into the environment, resulting in contamination of soil and waterways and deleterious effects on the ecosystem. Furthermore, pathogens are becoming resistant to copper pesticides, necessitating even higher rates of copper usage. The scope of the proposed project is to optimize the structure of Agile Sciences? library of small, non-toxic organic compounds, to provide an economically viable solution for reducing the amount of copper released into the environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project includes both environmental and economic considerations. Bacterial pathogens are becoming increasingly resistant to copper, but farmers currently have few economically feasible alternatives. Agile?s compounds enhance the efficacy of copper treatments, so that the amount of copper released into the environment is substantially reduced.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/19/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1214791</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Reyes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel O Reyes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sreyes@agilesci.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9194573308</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000566286</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Agile Sciences Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276062576</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9194573308</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1791 Varsity Dr.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 150]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>828576202</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AGILE SCIENCES, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Agile Sciences Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276063550</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1791 Varsity Dr., Suite 150]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The scope of this Phase I project was to develop an improved product for controlling bacterial disease on plants.&nbsp;&nbsp;The global market for bactericidal products is estimated to be $400M, and upwards of 95% of bacterial strains on plants are resistant to the current standard copper treatment.&nbsp; Millions of pounds of copper are sprayed on plants each year, resulting in substantial pollution.&nbsp;</p> <p>During this Phase I project period, a highly potent organic compound was identified that enhances the effectiveness of the current industry-standard copper treatment in controlling bacterial plant disease. &nbsp;This compound was identified through a chemical optimization effort that systematically examined the structure-activity relationship of Agile Sciences'&nbsp;proprietary compound library.&nbsp; When evaluated <em>in vitro</em>,&nbsp;the lead compound<sup>&nbsp;</sup>lowered the minimum inhibitoryconcentration (MIC) of copper by &gt;8-fold when used at low ppm rates.&nbsp; When tested on live pepper plants infected with <em>Xanthomonas</em> bacteria, the Agile compound + copper treatment provided a clear benefit over the standard copper treatment in reducing the bacterial disease.&nbsp;</p> <p>In our Phase II project, we&nbsp;will scale up production of the lead compound;<br />perform additional studies to define product use rates, application time, and<br />formulation; and conduct toxicity studies that will be required for EPA<br />approval of the product. <strong></strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/09/2013<br>      Modified by: Samuel&nbsp;O&nbsp;Reyes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The scope of this Phase I project was to develop an improved product for controlling bacterial disease on plants.  The global market for bactericidal products is estimated to be $400M, and upwards of 95% of bacterial strains on plants are resistant to the current standard copper treatment.  Millions of pounds of copper are sprayed on plants each year, resulting in substantial pollution.   During this Phase I project period, a highly potent organic compound was identified that enhances the effectiveness of the current industry-standard copper treatment in controlling bacterial plant disease.  This compound was identified through a chemical optimization effort that systematically examined the structure-activity relationship of Agile Sciences' proprietary compound library.  When evaluated in vitro, the lead compound lowered the minimum inhibitoryconcentration (MIC) of copper by &gt;8-fold when used at low ppm rates.  When tested on live pepper plants infected with Xanthomonas bacteria, the Agile compound + copper treatment provided a clear benefit over the standard copper treatment in reducing the bacterial disease.   In our Phase II project, we will scale up production of the lead compound; perform additional studies to define product use rates, application time, and formulation; and conduct toxicity studies that will be required for EPA approval of the product.        Last Modified: 09/09/2013       Submitted by: Samuel O Reyes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
