<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Oceanographic Technical Services, R/V Marcus G. Langseth, 2012 ? 2016</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14600251.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20548369</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Holik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jholik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927711</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory (LDEO) of Columbia University proposes to support technical services on R/V Marcus Langseth as part of the U.S. Academic Fleet which is scheduled by the University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System (UNOLS).   R/V Langseth, a 235? seismic survey vessel purchased in 2005 from Western GECO to be operated as a geophysical research vessel (with some additional general purpose oceanographic capabilities) is owned by the National Science Foundation and replaced R/V Maurice Ewing, a 236? research vessel operated by LDEO from 1990 to 2005.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;LDEO is requesting funds to support both basic and specialized services for multichannel seismic data acquisition.  They propose to provide at least three technicians on each seagoing research project to provide basic services and to maintain equipment calibrate sensors and provide support for qualified users.  Specialized services include both single cable and multiple cable seismic operations. LDEO proposes to sail eight technicians for single cable mode and 12 technicians for multi-cable mode. The budget in this proposal is for the first year of a 5-year continuing grant.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The principal impact of the present proposal is under criterion two, providing infrastructure support for scientists to use the vessel and its shared-use instrumentation in support of their NSF-funded oceanographic research projects (which individually undergo separate review by the relevant research program of NSF).  The support of maintenance and operation of shared-use instrumentation allows NSF-funded researchers from any US university or lab access to working, calibrated instruments for their research, reducing the cost of that research, and expanding the base of potential researchers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1214328</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David S Goldberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>goldberg@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8453658674</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000162566</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
<LastName>Higgins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sean M Higgins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sean@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8453658528</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000404622</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Rupert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Rupert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rupert@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128546851</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000563308</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Palisades</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>109648000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Rt 9W]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1680</Code>
<Text>OCEAN TECH &amp; INTERDISC COORDIN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5112</Code>
<Text>ANT Earth Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5140</Code>
<Text>Antarctic Operations Support</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5411</Code>
<Text>SHIP OPERATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5415</Code>
<Text>OCEANOGRAPHIC TECHNICAL SERVCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6899</Code>
<Text>OCE-Ocean Sciences Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~3220733</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~3482878</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~3489633</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~3818900</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~3555974</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~2980251</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Oceanographic Technical Services award for the R/V Marcus G. Langseth provides for the science support necessary to carry out assigned oceanographic research projects. &nbsp;The R/V Langseth is owned by the National Science Foundation and operated by Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory (LDEO) of Columbia University. This ship is a 235-foot global class research vessel that is a specialized facilty within the U.S. Academic Research Fleet and &nbsp;provides substantial capability for seismic imaging of the subseafloor of the worlds oceans. The ship also has the capability to continuously collect other complimentary data sets like gravity, magnetics, wide swath bathymetric seafloor mapping, current profiling, and dissolved carbon dioxide in sea surface waters. Projects have been supported primarily by NSF and NOAA and US Geological Survey (Law of the Sea mapping) but also other US institutions/foundations and international collaborators.</p> <p>Seismic imaging is accomplished by using sound source towed behind the vessel along with a long towed solid streamer (6-15km) which contains the hydrophones or &nbsp;receivers that listen for&nbsp;sounds &nbsp;reflected by the sediment and rock layers and structures in the subseafloor. By using a single streamer, we can create 2-dimensional acoustic images. &nbsp;With 4 streamers (6km each), we can develop a full 3D image of the target area. &nbsp;The depth under the seafloor that we are able to image varies by project goal but can range from a just a few km to as much as 60-70km. &nbsp;Targets of interest for these projects range widely but include study of mid-ocean ridges, subduction zones, earthquake and other geohazard prone areas, origins of hot spots, hydrothermal fields, plate behavior, continental margins, fluids and hydrogeology of ocean crust and more.</p> <p>Over the period of this award from 2012 through 2017, 24 major projects were accomplished throughout the Pacific and Atlantic Oceans and the Mediterranean Sea. 18 of these were for 2D or 3D seismic imaging using &nbsp;reflection with Multi-Channel Seismic or seismic refraction experiments using Ocean Bottom Seismometers or a combination of both. &nbsp;The other six projects included supporitng sediment coring , ROV deployment, electromagnetic imaging, multibeam mapping, to chemical/biological oceanography. &nbsp;</p> <p>The Technical Services award also provides for the environmental compliance and permitting/authorizations both nationally and internationally for our projects. Protected Species Observers are required for all seismic imaging projects and they enforce any necessary mitigation efforts. LDEO also supports research on the in situ acoustics aspects of our research and several peer-reviewed papers have been produced by LDEO research scientists.</p> <p>Over the period of the award, the marine seismic system was substantially upgraded via NSF support and equipment donations from industry partners. This has enabled the facility to support new marine geology and geophysics proposals from the science community&nbsp;that could not have been done before. &nbsp;Continued evolution of the science systems also improves the educational and training aspects of our projects.</p> <p>Training the next generation of earth scientists is a critical part of our mission in the academic research fleet. Each projects brings new students to sea often for the first time to get hands on experience on how science is conducted in the field. &nbsp;In addition, annual outreach events at our institution as well as in ports where we visit created important ongoing opportunities to engage people and students in our work. One highlight of such portcall events was a visit by President of Chile in January 2017 when R/V Langseth was conducting research on earthquake prone areas along Chilean coast in collaboration with Chilean scientists.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2018<br>      Modified by: Sean&nbsp;M&nbsp;Higgins</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1214328/1214328_10211800_1540988871566_APS_3714A--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1214328/1214328_10211800_1540988871566_APS_3714A--rgov-800width.jpg" title="R/V Langseth-NYC Harbor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1214328/1214328_10211800_1540988871566_APS_3714A--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="R/V Langseth-NYC Harbor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">R/V Marcus G. Langseth as it passes Statue of Liberty in New York City Harbor.</div> <div class="imageCredit">LDEO and APS, Orangeburg, NY</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sean&nbsp;M&nbsp;Higgins</div> <div class="imageTitle">R/V Langseth-NYC Harbor</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1214328/1214328_10211800_1541001693911_PresidentofChile-VisittoLanseth--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1214328/1214328_10211800_1541001693911_PresidentofChile-VisittoLanseth--rgov-800width.jpg" title="President of Chile Visits R/V Langseth"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1214328/1214328_10211800_1541001693911_PresidentofChile-VisittoLanseth--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="President of Chile Visits R/V Langseth"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">President of Chile visits R/V Langseth and speaking at onboard press conference in January 2017 to talk about threats of earthquakes to Chile and need for research.</div> <div class="imageCredit">LDEO/Columbia University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sean&nbsp;M&nbsp;Higgins</div> <div class="imageTitle">President of Chile Visits R/V Langseth</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Oceanographic Technical Services award for the R/V Marcus G. Langseth provides for the science support necessary to carry out assigned oceanographic research projects.  The R/V Langseth is owned by the National Science Foundation and operated by Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory (LDEO) of Columbia University. This ship is a 235-foot global class research vessel that is a specialized facilty within the U.S. Academic Research Fleet and  provides substantial capability for seismic imaging of the subseafloor of the worlds oceans. The ship also has the capability to continuously collect other complimentary data sets like gravity, magnetics, wide swath bathymetric seafloor mapping, current profiling, and dissolved carbon dioxide in sea surface waters. Projects have been supported primarily by NSF and NOAA and US Geological Survey (Law of the Sea mapping) but also other US institutions/foundations and international collaborators.  Seismic imaging is accomplished by using sound source towed behind the vessel along with a long towed solid streamer (6-15km) which contains the hydrophones or  receivers that listen for sounds  reflected by the sediment and rock layers and structures in the subseafloor. By using a single streamer, we can create 2-dimensional acoustic images.  With 4 streamers (6km each), we can develop a full 3D image of the target area.  The depth under the seafloor that we are able to image varies by project goal but can range from a just a few km to as much as 60-70km.  Targets of interest for these projects range widely but include study of mid-ocean ridges, subduction zones, earthquake and other geohazard prone areas, origins of hot spots, hydrothermal fields, plate behavior, continental margins, fluids and hydrogeology of ocean crust and more.  Over the period of this award from 2012 through 2017, 24 major projects were accomplished throughout the Pacific and Atlantic Oceans and the Mediterranean Sea. 18 of these were for 2D or 3D seismic imaging using  reflection with Multi-Channel Seismic or seismic refraction experiments using Ocean Bottom Seismometers or a combination of both.  The other six projects included supporitng sediment coring , ROV deployment, electromagnetic imaging, multibeam mapping, to chemical/biological oceanography.    The Technical Services award also provides for the environmental compliance and permitting/authorizations both nationally and internationally for our projects. Protected Species Observers are required for all seismic imaging projects and they enforce any necessary mitigation efforts. LDEO also supports research on the in situ acoustics aspects of our research and several peer-reviewed papers have been produced by LDEO research scientists.  Over the period of the award, the marine seismic system was substantially upgraded via NSF support and equipment donations from industry partners. This has enabled the facility to support new marine geology and geophysics proposals from the science community that could not have been done before.  Continued evolution of the science systems also improves the educational and training aspects of our projects.  Training the next generation of earth scientists is a critical part of our mission in the academic research fleet. Each projects brings new students to sea often for the first time to get hands on experience on how science is conducted in the field.  In addition, annual outreach events at our institution as well as in ports where we visit created important ongoing opportunities to engage people and students in our work. One highlight of such portcall events was a visit by President of Chile in January 2017 when R/V Langseth was conducting research on earthquake prone areas along Chilean coast in collaboration with Chilean scientists.       Last Modified: 10/31/2018       Submitted by: Sean M Higgins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
