<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Micro Laser Assisted Machining</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149964.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>168714</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will demonstrate proof of concept and determine the feasibility of a micro-laser assisted machining (micro-LAM) process that will both reduce the time, cost, and effort, and extend the capability, associated with machining of hard and brittle semiconductors and ceramics.  The proposed research is unique, and the research team is well-qualified to perform the feasibility research around this innovative process, which couples a laser to a diamond cutting tool in a hybrid package arrangement to perform precision machining of semiconductors and engineered ceramics.  Experiments will be conducted, based upon a bench scale laboratory configuration, to test and evaluate the micro-LAM process and system for feasibility in an industrial setting on industrial processing equipment. Tool wear, machined material surface finish and subsurface damage data, as a function of laser and process parameters, will be evaluated relative to the potential for the micro-LAM process to be developed into a successful commercial product.  The overall result of this project will be a cost-effective method for the production of useful and commercially viable consumer and industrial products manufactured from advanced semiconductors and engineered ceramics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project will occur in semiconductor (micro-electronic) manufacturing, and for manufacturing of optical (mirror and windows) and precision mechanical products (e.g. bearings and seals), where the superior properties of advanced semiconductor and engineered ceramic materials are required to achieve the desired performance.  The micro-LAM technology offers a new way to realize the high pressures and temperatures that are needed for processing these hard and nominally brittle materials.  This technology will enable entirely new capabilities for production of materials and products currently not viable or achievable due to processing or use limitations.  The new method has potential applications to emerging technologies, such as wind turbines and plug-in electric vehicles, where high-power and high-temperature operation of advanced devices is required.  The served available market that includes machine tools for diamond turning, milling, and drilling is approximately $4.5 billion. The micro-LAM technology will initially target existing (~10,000 units) and new ($150 million/year) diamond turning machines as an add-on accessory.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/02/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1214772</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deepak</FirstName>
<LastName>Ravindra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deepak Ravindra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>deepak.ravindra@micro-lam.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2692884100</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000522756</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/02/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Micro Laser Assisted Machining Technologies, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Portage</CityName>
<ZipCode>490029712</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2692884100</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5960 S. Sprinkle Rd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969977029</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICRO LASER ASSISTED MACHINING TECHNOLOGIES, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Micro Laser Assisted Machining Technologies, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Portage</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>490247893</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7593 Mac Arthur Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~149964</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~18750</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>For companies that would benefit from the softening of hard materials and reduced brittleness during machining, Micro-LAM Technologies LLC offers cutting edge technology that increases productivity, provides a better surface and reduces tooling and finishing costs. The company provides an easily adaptable tool that delivers precision machining capabilities for ceramics, semiconductors, glass and metals, leading to greater efficiency and improved profitability. Micro-LAM has designed the only patented laser-coupled diamond cutting tool that heats and softens hard and brittle materials, making them easier to machine. The Micro-LAM (&micro;-LAM) technology improves productivity and quality, minimizes waste and reduces tooling costs for such industries as optics, semiconductors, glass and metals, enabling companies to be more profitable. Manufactured in the USA, Micro-LAM&rsquo;s hybrid laser-diamond cutting tool is the only one of its kind and has been proven through intensive research, testing and customer trial. The technology&rsquo;s inventors hold exclusive license to the patents, the science and technology trade secrets.</p> <p>Based on very successful preliminary beta testing results at our industrial partner&rsquo;s sites, the following value propositions are estimated for large scale part manufacturers. Micro-LAM is currently engaged in pilot programs with strategic partners from large-scale manufacturing industries with the product being tested on-site. Performing beta testing at these partner sites provide reliable means of acquiring direct feedback related to increased productivity and tool life, improved part quality and ease of use from multiple customers representing the optics, machine tool, glass and semiconductor industries.</p> <p>The work done in Phase I/IB successfully reveals that there is a viable and novel method to productively manufacture hard and brittle materials such as ceramics, semiconductors and glass that overcomes the key challenges and drawbacks encountered by conventional routes. The feasibility of the &micro;-LAM process was not only demonstrated in a laboratory environment but also at a high-volume part-manufacturing site. The value propositions were discussed with over 160 prospective customers and unmet needs for various industries, including semiconductor, optics, advanced ceramics and automotive glass, were identified. The Micro-LAM team has succeeded in accomplishing all (and more) of the Phase I/IB&rsquo;s proposed tasks.</p> <p>As demonstrated in Phase I/IB, Micro-LAM has proven the ability to perform work in Phase I. Micro-LAM has also demonstrated the feasibility of developing an industrial grade prototype that has been tested at customer sites. The outline of this Phase II proposal is a continuation of the same skills and approaches that have been demonstrated. With the highly skilled project team (described below), staffing plans and support from advisors and partners, Micro-LAM will be able to complete the objective of Phase II and launch this product in the targeted market by Q4 of 2013. The Micro-LAM team has the perfect DNA and is well positioned to commercialize the &micro;-LAM product development.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/24/2013<br>      Modified by: Deepak&nbsp;Ravindra</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1214772/1214772_10169879_1369413227160_ValuePropositions--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1214772/1214772_10169...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For companies that would benefit from the softening of hard materials and reduced brittleness during machining, Micro-LAM Technologies LLC offers cutting edge technology that increases productivity, provides a better surface and reduces tooling and finishing costs. The company provides an easily adaptable tool that delivers precision machining capabilities for ceramics, semiconductors, glass and metals, leading to greater efficiency and improved profitability. Micro-LAM has designed the only patented laser-coupled diamond cutting tool that heats and softens hard and brittle materials, making them easier to machine. The Micro-LAM (&micro;-LAM) technology improves productivity and quality, minimizes waste and reduces tooling costs for such industries as optics, semiconductors, glass and metals, enabling companies to be more profitable. Manufactured in the USA, Micro-LAMÆs hybrid laser-diamond cutting tool is the only one of its kind and has been proven through intensive research, testing and customer trial. The technologyÆs inventors hold exclusive license to the patents, the science and technology trade secrets.  Based on very successful preliminary beta testing results at our industrial partnerÆs sites, the following value propositions are estimated for large scale part manufacturers. Micro-LAM is currently engaged in pilot programs with strategic partners from large-scale manufacturing industries with the product being tested on-site. Performing beta testing at these partner sites provide reliable means of acquiring direct feedback related to increased productivity and tool life, improved part quality and ease of use from multiple customers representing the optics, machine tool, glass and semiconductor industries.  The work done in Phase I/IB successfully reveals that there is a viable and novel method to productively manufacture hard and brittle materials such as ceramics, semiconductors and glass that overcomes the key challenges and drawbacks encountered by conventional routes. The feasibility of the &micro;-LAM process was not only demonstrated in a laboratory environment but also at a high-volume part-manufacturing site. The value propositions were discussed with over 160 prospective customers and unmet needs for various industries, including semiconductor, optics, advanced ceramics and automotive glass, were identified. The Micro-LAM team has succeeded in accomplishing all (and more) of the Phase I/IBÆs proposed tasks.  As demonstrated in Phase I/IB, Micro-LAM has proven the ability to perform work in Phase I. Micro-LAM has also demonstrated the feasibility of developing an industrial grade prototype that has been tested at customer sites. The outline of this Phase II proposal is a continuation of the same skills and approaches that have been demonstrated. With the highly skilled project team (described below), staffing plans and support from advisors and partners, Micro-LAM will be able to complete the objective of Phase II and launch this product in the targeted market by Q4 of 2013. The Micro-LAM team has the perfect DNA and is well positioned to commercialize the &micro;-LAM product development.          Last Modified: 05/24/2013       Submitted by: Deepak Ravindra]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
