<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SEES Fellows: Social-Ecological Resilience of Coastal Shoreline Ecosystems: Developing a Framework for Informed Decision-Making</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>503447.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>503447</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Sieracki</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>msierack@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927585</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This interdisciplinary project will investigate the social, ecological and engineering factors that contribute to coastal resilience and develop a framework for improved communication and informed decision making.  The study aims to understand how social, ecological and engineering objectives for coastal shorelines are interlinked with the health of fisheries and fish habitats in order to develop a framework to improve social and ecological resilience. Study sites include Narragansett and Mobile Bays, which are both large, densely-populated estuarine embayments that have experienced dramatic declines in nearshore marine habitats.  The research effort will 1) identify and model the fisheries consequences of shifts in habitat composition; 2) investigate the social, cultural and political factors that affect the sustainability of shoreline ecosystems, 3) assess the shoreline protection capacity and habitat complexity of wave-attenuating breakwaters; and 4) incorporate the social, ecological and engineering indices generated by the first three tasks into a decision-making framework.  The project will involve collaboration between researchers and practitioners in the academic, government and private sectors, and include a variety of outreach activities to students and the public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the complexity of factors related to resilience of human and natural communities is of high priority for those tasked with managing resources on a changing planet.  In the past, most coastal conservation planning and prioritization has occurred without adequate knowledge or consideration of socio-cultural or engineering impacts.  The goal of this research is to provide managers with decision support tools to enable restoration and sustainability efforts that maximize social capital.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported under the NSF Science, Engineering and Education for Sustainability Fellows (SEES Fellows) program, with the goal of helping to enable discoveries needed to inform actions that lead to environmental, energy and societal sustainability while creating the necessary workforce to address these challenges.  With SEES Fellows support, this project will enable a promising early career researcher to establish themselves in an independent research career related to sustainability.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1215825</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Scyphers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven Scyphers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>s.scyphers@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3347018864</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000610514</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/05/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[177-500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7978</Code>
<Text>Global Systems Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8055</Code>
<Text>SEES Fellows</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8055</Code>
<Text>Capacity-Building Projects</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~503447</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Coastal shorelines are disproportionally concentrated with human populations and natural capital, but unfortunately, many natural shoreline habitats and the ecosystem services they provide have been severely degraded. Understanding the complexity of factors that influence shoreline decision-making and promote the resilience of human and natural communities is of high priority for those tasked with managing ecosystems and societies on a changing planet. This study integrated social theory with ecological and engineering considerations to advance our understanding of social-ecological resilience and develop a useful framework to improve coastal shoreline decision-making. The outcomes of this project include several important insights on social drivers and ecological and engineering outcomes of shoreline development, as well as new pathways and optimized tools for promoting sustainable decision-making along coastlines.</p> <p>Through surveys and interviews of coastal residents, we sought to understand how waterfront and broader coastal residents value coastal habitats, resources, and ecosystems, perceive their sustainability, and make decisions. Across both groups, we found that the vast majority of coastal residents consider natural shoreline habitats, such as marshes and seagrasses, to be key components of sustainable coasts and associate them with many other social and ecological dimensions (Figure 1). Our research also advanced our understanding of the values, beliefs, and attitudes that have lead to traditionally divergent patterns of shoreline degradation or natural habitat conservation in coastal systems. However, although most waterfront residents are concerned with environmental impacts and prefer the aesthetics of natural landscapes, priorities and misperceptions related to the cost-effectiveness of various shoreline management strategies can promote cascading shoreline degradation. We found that modest economic incentives could be effective at shifting decision-making away from traditional hard structures and towards emerging nature-based shoreline strategies, as well as that the existence of sociocultural values associated with natural habitats can bolster the effectiveness of incentives. Finally, our survey research also revealed that artificial shoreline structures, such as vertical walls and revetments, were not associated with significantly reduced concern for coastal hazards such as coastal storms and sea level rise.</p> <p>Our research also aimed to address existing and significant gaps in scientific knowledge on the ecology and engineering performance of natural and artificial shorelines. For instance, we coupled high resolution shoreline maps with 11 years of fishery-independent data to assess the potential impacts of natural and artificial shorelines on ecological resilience in an estuarine embayment. This work revealed that the similarity and stability of fish communities near artificial shorelines were generally lower than fish communities near natural shorelines. However, not all shoreline types were similar as structurally complex artificial shorelines appeared to promote greater stability than simpler yet more common structure vertical walls, which were most dissimilar from natural shorelines and had the lowest stability. Collectively, these results demonstrate how complex social processes can shape ecological functions but also that they can be disentangled to better understand the dynamics and promote the sustainability of ecosystems.</p> <p>Another overarching goal of this work was to develop and test a framework for simultaneously incorporating engineering, ecological, and social considerations in coastal shoreline decision-making. For this aspect of our project, we focused on developing an integrated approach to address three key needs that emerged from our research endeavors. First, building off of our network of concepts that residents and key stakeholder associated with sustainability, we conducted a series of focus groups and developed user-friendly models to illustrate the complex trade-offs that waterfront homeowners face under various scenarios. Second, we produced high resolution maps and geodatabases to facilitate more holistic planning and decision-making by managers and practitioners to account for social, ecological, and engineering objectives. Third, we launched an interactive &ldquo;ShoreLines&rdquo; network of waterfront homeowners, scientists, conservation practitioners, and other coastal stakeholders aimed at promoting communication, reciprocal learning, and citizen science. Approximately one year after launching, the ShoreLines citizen science project on iNaturalist.org (www.inaturalist.org/projects/shorelines) has accumulated more than 1,700 observations of 671 different species by more than 200 people.</p> <p>Finally, high priorities throughout this project involved maximizing its educational opportunities for future scientists and non-scientist citizens alike, as well was to increase the public&rsquo;s scientific literacy on social-ecological systems and coastal sustainability. The project supported semester-long research experiences for five undergraduate students, and we completed several activities that illustrate our commitment to the educational impacts of research. Most notably, by leveraging our research system and study, we developed an immersive case study involving waterfront homeowner decision-making as a real-world scenario for teaching socio-environmental synthesis. The case &ldquo;Do Good Seawalls make Bad Neighbors?&rdquo; is publicly available at SESYNC&rsquo;s Resources for Teachers (www.sesync.org), has been used multiple times per year with audiences from high school to graduate students, and has been featured in a peer-reviewed publication on effective case studies for teaching socio-environmental synthesis.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2016<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;Scyphers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1215825/1215825_10187109_1475103109780_SEES_Network1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1215825/1215825_10187109_1475103109780_SEES_Network1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Waterfront Homeowner Network of Sustainability"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1215825/1215825_10187109_1475103109780_SEES_Network1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Waterfront Homeowner Network of Sustainability"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Network visualization of the concepts the concepts that waterfront residents associated with "coastal sustainability". Node size reflect the relative popularity of each term.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Scyphers</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;Scyphers</div> <div class="imageTitle">Waterfront Homeowner Network of Sustainability</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Coastal shorelines are disproportionally concentrated with human populations and natural capital, but unfortunately, many natural shoreline habitats and the ecosystem services they provide have been severely degraded. Understanding the complexity of factors that influence shoreline decision-making and promote the resilience of human and natural communities is of high priority for those tasked with managing ecosystems and societies on a changing planet. This study integrated social theory with ecological and engineering considerations to advance our understanding of social-ecological resilience and develop a useful framework to improve coastal shoreline decision-making. The outcomes of this project include several important insights on social drivers and ecological and engineering outcomes of shoreline development, as well as new pathways and optimized tools for promoting sustainable decision-making along coastlines.  Through surveys and interviews of coastal residents, we sought to understand how waterfront and broader coastal residents value coastal habitats, resources, and ecosystems, perceive their sustainability, and make decisions. Across both groups, we found that the vast majority of coastal residents consider natural shoreline habitats, such as marshes and seagrasses, to be key components of sustainable coasts and associate them with many other social and ecological dimensions (Figure 1). Our research also advanced our understanding of the values, beliefs, and attitudes that have lead to traditionally divergent patterns of shoreline degradation or natural habitat conservation in coastal systems. However, although most waterfront residents are concerned with environmental impacts and prefer the aesthetics of natural landscapes, priorities and misperceptions related to the cost-effectiveness of various shoreline management strategies can promote cascading shoreline degradation. We found that modest economic incentives could be effective at shifting decision-making away from traditional hard structures and towards emerging nature-based shoreline strategies, as well as that the existence of sociocultural values associated with natural habitats can bolster the effectiveness of incentives. Finally, our survey research also revealed that artificial shoreline structures, such as vertical walls and revetments, were not associated with significantly reduced concern for coastal hazards such as coastal storms and sea level rise.  Our research also aimed to address existing and significant gaps in scientific knowledge on the ecology and engineering performance of natural and artificial shorelines. For instance, we coupled high resolution shoreline maps with 11 years of fishery-independent data to assess the potential impacts of natural and artificial shorelines on ecological resilience in an estuarine embayment. This work revealed that the similarity and stability of fish communities near artificial shorelines were generally lower than fish communities near natural shorelines. However, not all shoreline types were similar as structurally complex artificial shorelines appeared to promote greater stability than simpler yet more common structure vertical walls, which were most dissimilar from natural shorelines and had the lowest stability. Collectively, these results demonstrate how complex social processes can shape ecological functions but also that they can be disentangled to better understand the dynamics and promote the sustainability of ecosystems.  Another overarching goal of this work was to develop and test a framework for simultaneously incorporating engineering, ecological, and social considerations in coastal shoreline decision-making. For this aspect of our project, we focused on developing an integrated approach to address three key needs that emerged from our research endeavors. First, building off of our network of concepts that residents and key stakeholder associated with sustainability, we conducted a series of focus groups and developed user-friendly models to illustrate the complex trade-offs that waterfront homeowners face under various scenarios. Second, we produced high resolution maps and geodatabases to facilitate more holistic planning and decision-making by managers and practitioners to account for social, ecological, and engineering objectives. Third, we launched an interactive "ShoreLines" network of waterfront homeowners, scientists, conservation practitioners, and other coastal stakeholders aimed at promoting communication, reciprocal learning, and citizen science. Approximately one year after launching, the ShoreLines citizen science project on iNaturalist.org (www.inaturalist.org/projects/shorelines) has accumulated more than 1,700 observations of 671 different species by more than 200 people.  Finally, high priorities throughout this project involved maximizing its educational opportunities for future scientists and non-scientist citizens alike, as well was to increase the public?s scientific literacy on social-ecological systems and coastal sustainability. The project supported semester-long research experiences for five undergraduate students, and we completed several activities that illustrate our commitment to the educational impacts of research. Most notably, by leveraging our research system and study, we developed an immersive case study involving waterfront homeowner decision-making as a real-world scenario for teaching socio-environmental synthesis. The case "Do Good Seawalls make Bad Neighbors?" is publicly available at SESYNC?s Resources for Teachers (www.sesync.org), has been used multiple times per year with audiences from high school to graduate students, and has been featured in a peer-reviewed publication on effective case studies for teaching socio-environmental synthesis.           Last Modified: 09/28/2016       Submitted by: Steven Scyphers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
