<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SHF: Small: Pipelined and wireless ultra-low power straintronics: An acoustically clocked combinational and sequential nanomagnetic  architecture</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>440000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>440000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sabasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927843</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Elliptical single-domain nanomagnets with two stable magnetization orientations are far more energy-efficient as logic switches than traditional transistors. However, the method employed to switch them must be energy-efficient as well in order to build ultra-low-power nanomagnetic logic and memory paradigms. It has been theoretically shown that using multiferroic (magnetostrictive-piezoelectric) nanomagnets, whose magnetization can be flipped with strain generated by a tiny electrostatic potential applied across the piezoelectric layer, results in a remarkably energy-efficient switching scheme. It reduces the dissipation in the switching/clocking circuit by four orders of magnitude at a clock rate of ~ 1 GHz compared to other nanomagnet switching schemes. While this is attractive, an unattractive trait of nanomagnetic logic chains is that in order to build a pipelined architecture and hence retain an acceptable bit transfer rate, each magnet must be clocked individually. This necessitates contacting each magnetic with a contact line, which imposes a Herculean lithographic burden. The PIs propose to overcome this problem completely by designing and fabricating a novel acoustic scheme for clocking that allows pipelining and at the same time does not require contacts to every magnet, thereby completely lifting the lithography burden.  A surface acoustic wave (SAW) launched in the substrate, and slowed down with periodically placed masses, generates strain in an array of magnets in the correct sequence for bit transfer, as long as the spacing between the magnets is one quarter of the SAW?s wavelength. With this scheme, the energy dissipation in a gate operation at room temperature can be very low. This project will: (i) design combinational and sequential logic based on acoustically clocked magnetostrictive nanomagnets acting as logic switches, as well as perform extensive simulations using the stochastic Landau-Lifshitz-Gilbert (LLG) equation to understand and optimize reliability and fault tolerance in the presence of thermal noise; (ii) experimentally demonstrate pipelined unidirectional logic flow, and (iii) develop comprehensive coupled models for the switching dynamics of nanomagnets stressed by surface acoustic wave (SAW). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will result in a novel computational paradigm whose astonishing energy efficiency combined with very little lithographic burden could enable the production of cheap, high yield and extremely low power processors. Such processors would consume so little energy that they can be run off the energy harvested from the environment. This could open up hitherto unimaginable applications such as medically implanted processors powered only by the motion of the patient's body, or processors that monitor the structural health of bridges and buildings while being powered by vibrations caused by wind or traffic. Integration of this research with education and mentoring will result in traditional training activities such as guiding two doctoral students who will gain multidisciplinary skills in advanced nanofabrication, nanocharacterization and modeling, as well as undergraduate projects on SAW devices and nanofabrication of magnetostrictive nanomagnets that will be mentored by the PI and co-PI?s doctoral students. Other innovative outreach programs will include holding workshops on nanomagnets and computing for high school students through the Math Science Innovation Center (MSIC) and incorporating diversity into outreach programs by hosting under-represented K-12 students in summer with the help of VCUs Richmond Area Program for Minorities in Engineering (RAPME) program. These students will perform nanolithography under supervision and study the magnetic structures they create with MFM.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1216614</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Supriyo</FirstName>
<LastName>Bandyopadhyay</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Supriyo Bandyopadhyay</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sbandy@vcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8048276275</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000314700</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jayasimha</FirstName>
<LastName>Atulasimha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jayasimha Atulasimha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jatulasimha@vcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8048286772</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513211</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Commonwealth University</Name>
<CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
<ZipCode>232980568</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8048286772</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 980568</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>105300446</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA COMMONWEALTH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>105300446</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Commonwealth University]]></Name>
<CityName>Richmond</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>232980568</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 980568]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7947</Code>
<Text>NANOCOMPUTING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~440000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Bistable nanomagnets can act as far more energy-efficient logic switches than traditional transistors as the internal energy dissipated in switching them from one state (&ldquo;0&rdquo; or &ldquo;1&rdquo;) to the other state (&ldquo;1&rdquo; or &ldquo;0&rdquo;) is miniscule. Furthermore, information, once written, can be retained for several years without any standby power dissipation. However, the method employed to switch nanomagnets must also be energy-efficient in order to keep the external energy dissipated low and build ultra-low-power nanomagnetic logic and memory paradigms. It has been theoretically shown that using multiferroic (magnetostrictive-piezoelectric) nanomagnets, whose magnetizations can be flipped with strain generated by a tiny electrostatic potential applied across the piezoelectric layer, results in an extremely energy-efficient magnet switching scheme. One drawback that afflicts all nanomagnet switching schemes when it comes to pipelined clocking of nanomagnet chains is that each nanomagnet in the chain has to be switched sequentially, and hence each nanomagnet must be individually accessed by a contact line. That imposes a large lithographic burden. This burden can be relieved if an acoustic wave is used to generate strain sequentially in an array of nanomagnets. This will switch each nanomagnet when the crest of the wave reaches the nanomagnet, resulting in pipelined Bennett clocking <em>without</em> the need to electrically access each nanomagnet.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: Under this grant, the PI&rsquo;s and co-PI&rsquo;s research groups have:</p> <p>1. Identified what causes the high dynamic switching error rate when nanomagnets switch in the presence of thermal noise and designed robust memory and logic architectures that have low dynamic switching error rate at room temperature. These studies were carried out using stochastic simulations of magnetization dynamics.</p> <p>2. Established feasibility of clocking combinational and sequential logic circuits with SAW based on extensive simulations.</p> <p>3. Experimentally demonstrated clocking of nanomagnets with acoustic waves for potential memory and logic applications. <strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Broader impact: Work performed under this grant has developed a paradigm that may indeed emerge as a low power method of clocking nanomagnetic computing devices, provided innovative architectures and materials with large magneto-elastic coupling are developed to address dynamic error issues that are common to all nanomagnetic computing paradigms.&nbsp; In addition, several journal papers have been published, invited and contributed conference talks presented, five PhD thesis (partly funded on the grant) have been awarded, and 2 US patents on nanomagnetic computing (memory/logic) have been obtained. The PI held two hands on workshops (2012, 2013) and a virtual workshop (2015) on nanomagnetism and nanomagnetic devices for school students. The PI and the co-PI worked with <em>Richmond Area Program for Minorities in Engineering (RAPME) to host 2-3 </em>students for a month (4-5 weeks) each summer in 2012, 2013, 2014, 2015. They have also co-edited a book for Wiley on energy efficient spintronic and nanomagnetic computing devices</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2016<br>      Modified by: Jayasimha&nbsp;Atulasimha</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1216614/1216614_10178892_1475094975335_TOC_saw--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1216614/1216614_10178892_1475094975335_TOC_saw--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nano_Letters_TOC_image"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1216614/1216614_10178892_1475094975335_TOC_saw--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nano_Letters_TOC_image"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Acoustic wave based manipulation of magnetization in a magnetostrictive nanomagnet</div> <div class="imageCredit">This image is reproduced with permission from Nano  Letters, 16, 5681, 2016. http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acs.nanolett.6b02342</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jayasimha&nbsp;Atulasimha</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nano_Letters_TOC_image</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Bistable nanomagnets can act as far more energy-efficient logic switches than traditional transistors as the internal energy dissipated in switching them from one state ("0" or "1") to the other state ("1" or "0") is miniscule. Furthermore, information, once written, can be retained for several years without any standby power dissipation. However, the method employed to switch nanomagnets must also be energy-efficient in order to keep the external energy dissipated low and build ultra-low-power nanomagnetic logic and memory paradigms. It has been theoretically shown that using multiferroic (magnetostrictive-piezoelectric) nanomagnets, whose magnetizations can be flipped with strain generated by a tiny electrostatic potential applied across the piezoelectric layer, results in an extremely energy-efficient magnet switching scheme. One drawback that afflicts all nanomagnet switching schemes when it comes to pipelined clocking of nanomagnet chains is that each nanomagnet in the chain has to be switched sequentially, and hence each nanomagnet must be individually accessed by a contact line. That imposes a large lithographic burden. This burden can be relieved if an acoustic wave is used to generate strain sequentially in an array of nanomagnets. This will switch each nanomagnet when the crest of the wave reaches the nanomagnet, resulting in pipelined Bennett clocking without the need to electrically access each nanomagnet.  Intellectual Merit: Under this grant, the PI?s and co-PI?s research groups have:  1. Identified what causes the high dynamic switching error rate when nanomagnets switch in the presence of thermal noise and designed robust memory and logic architectures that have low dynamic switching error rate at room temperature. These studies were carried out using stochastic simulations of magnetization dynamics.  2. Established feasibility of clocking combinational and sequential logic circuits with SAW based on extensive simulations.  3. Experimentally demonstrated clocking of nanomagnets with acoustic waves for potential memory and logic applications.    Broader impact: Work performed under this grant has developed a paradigm that may indeed emerge as a low power method of clocking nanomagnetic computing devices, provided innovative architectures and materials with large magneto-elastic coupling are developed to address dynamic error issues that are common to all nanomagnetic computing paradigms.  In addition, several journal papers have been published, invited and contributed conference talks presented, five PhD thesis (partly funded on the grant) have been awarded, and 2 US patents on nanomagnetic computing (memory/logic) have been obtained. The PI held two hands on workshops (2012, 2013) and a virtual workshop (2015) on nanomagnetism and nanomagnetic devices for school students. The PI and the co-PI worked with Richmond Area Program for Minorities in Engineering (RAPME) to host 2-3 students for a month (4-5 weeks) each summer in 2012, 2013, 2014, 2015. They have also co-edited a book for Wiley on energy efficient spintronic and nanomagnetic computing devices          Last Modified: 09/28/2016       Submitted by: Jayasimha Atulasimha]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
