<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ICES: Small: Collaborative Research: Data-driven mechanisms in healthcare</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tracy Kimbrel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tkimbrel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927924</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The main objective of the project is to develop and study new incentive and reimbursement mechanisms within the context of the delivery of medical care. The project takes a game-theoretic perspective, with the main players being the government, health plans, healthcare providers, and patients. Some of the design goals of the mechanisms are to motivate the parties involved to improve healthcare quality while controlling costs. Among others, the study will try to extend the algorithmic game theory framework to address the unique challenges that occur in the context of healthcare. A key goal of the study is understanding the extent to which utilizing electronically available medical records may enable new mechanisms in the context of healthcare. In particular, the project studies potential advantages of high quality risk-adjustment schemes that are empowered by the application of machine learning to medical data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In recent years, much of the focus in the US public policy debate has been given to problems surrounding providing and sustaining healthcare services. One of the key problems the US healthcare system faces is that of aligning incentives among the various stakeholders - the government, health plans, care providers, and patients - to ensure favorable outcomes and efficient resource utilization. The study will use tools from algorithms and game theory to develop new alignment strategies. In particular, the study will look at ways in which the collection and data-mining of electronic health records may be used to provide better incentives for the stakeholders, and lead to better overall care at lower cost.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1216011</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohsen</FirstName>
<LastName>Bayati</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mohsen Bayati</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bayati@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507252285</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000610206</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943057216</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[655 Knight Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8052</Code>
<Text>Inter Com Sci Econ Soc S (ICE)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~199997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This collaborative project has advanced our understanding of potential uses of data and incentives to improve various aspects of the healthcare system. From the game-theoretic perspective, the healthcare system consists of a number of players, which include patients, providers (such as doctors and hospitals), and payers. There is ample opportunity to use incentives to make the system function better as a whole, but the complexity of the system makes mechanism design in healthcare (i.e. incentive design) not only difficult in practice, but also in theory.</p> <p>The project had several subprojects. The first subproject was a collaboration on studying the recent pay-for-performance mechanisms implemented by the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS). In particular, starting 2013 CMS has been imposing penalties on hospitals that performed poorly in terms of quality of care for certain outcomes (e.g., patients&rsquo; rehospitalizations soon after the discharge from a hospital). We studied the impact of these incentive payments on overall efficiency (a combination of quality and cost of care) from a game theoretic viewpoint using mathematical models. In our model we proved that a small amount of incentive payment can dramatically improve the efficiency. In addition, our theoretical results demonstrate that, compared to the current penalty-based incentives, higher efficiency can be achieved when the incentives also include bonuses for high quality hospitals.</p> <p>Additional subprojects explored two interrelated directions: the design and study of novel mechanisms within the healthcare context, and devising new ways of using data to improve the system&rsquo;s efficiency.</p> <p>One the mechanism design side, one subproject, which culminated in the paper &ldquo;Optimal provision-after-wait in healthcare&rdquo; considered the problem of optimizing efficiency in scenarios where patients are the strategic agents, and a constrained resource creates waiting times. We concluded that in some cases (but not always) lotteries are a good alternative to waiting times in allocating a scarce resource, and gave a partial characterization for when this is the case. Another subproject, which resulted in the paper &ldquo;Data-driven incentive alignment in capitation schemes&rdquo;, considered insurers as the strategic agents, and suggested a data-driven way to prevent plans from &ldquo;cherry picking&rdquo; good risks from the patient pool. Such &ldquo;cherry picking&rdquo; is considered to be a major problem for marketplaces where private insurers compete with each other for patients, and where premiums are fixed.</p> <p>On the data utilization side one subproject used CMS data to demonstrate that insurance claims data is not a reliable source for assessing quality of care. In particular, in the paper &ldquo;Evidence of strategic upcoding in Medicare claims reporting&rdquo; we found that a large number of hospital acquired conditions (HACs) are incorrectly reported as present-on-admission (POA). This type of reporting, called &ldquo;upcoding&rdquo;, allows the providers to collect full reimbursement for the treatment of the HACs which are not reimbursable under a 2008 CMS policy. In this paper, using variations in the state level regulations on adverse event reporting we find policies that can mitigate upcoding. A second subproject that led to the paper &ldquo;A low-cost method for multiple disease prediction&rdquo; aimed at finding a small set of biomarkers that can accurately predict the risk of multiple chronic diseases. This provides an affordable approach for monitoring the quality of health of individuals and for more accurate risk-adjustment purposes that are at the core of pay-for-performance mechanisms used by CMS.</p> <p>The project&rsquo;s funds had been primarily used to support the training of the next generation of scholars (graduate students and postdoctoral scho...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This collaborative project has advanced our understanding of potential uses of data and incentives to improve various aspects of the healthcare system. From the game-theoretic perspective, the healthcare system consists of a number of players, which include patients, providers (such as doctors and hospitals), and payers. There is ample opportunity to use incentives to make the system function better as a whole, but the complexity of the system makes mechanism design in healthcare (i.e. incentive design) not only difficult in practice, but also in theory.  The project had several subprojects. The first subproject was a collaboration on studying the recent pay-for-performance mechanisms implemented by the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS). In particular, starting 2013 CMS has been imposing penalties on hospitals that performed poorly in terms of quality of care for certain outcomes (e.g., patientsÆ rehospitalizations soon after the discharge from a hospital). We studied the impact of these incentive payments on overall efficiency (a combination of quality and cost of care) from a game theoretic viewpoint using mathematical models. In our model we proved that a small amount of incentive payment can dramatically improve the efficiency. In addition, our theoretical results demonstrate that, compared to the current penalty-based incentives, higher efficiency can be achieved when the incentives also include bonuses for high quality hospitals.  Additional subprojects explored two interrelated directions: the design and study of novel mechanisms within the healthcare context, and devising new ways of using data to improve the systemÆs efficiency.  One the mechanism design side, one subproject, which culminated in the paper "Optimal provision-after-wait in healthcare" considered the problem of optimizing efficiency in scenarios where patients are the strategic agents, and a constrained resource creates waiting times. We concluded that in some cases (but not always) lotteries are a good alternative to waiting times in allocating a scarce resource, and gave a partial characterization for when this is the case. Another subproject, which resulted in the paper "Data-driven incentive alignment in capitation schemes", considered insurers as the strategic agents, and suggested a data-driven way to prevent plans from "cherry picking" good risks from the patient pool. Such "cherry picking" is considered to be a major problem for marketplaces where private insurers compete with each other for patients, and where premiums are fixed.  On the data utilization side one subproject used CMS data to demonstrate that insurance claims data is not a reliable source for assessing quality of care. In particular, in the paper "Evidence of strategic upcoding in Medicare claims reporting" we found that a large number of hospital acquired conditions (HACs) are incorrectly reported as present-on-admission (POA). This type of reporting, called "upcoding", allows the providers to collect full reimbursement for the treatment of the HACs which are not reimbursable under a 2008 CMS policy. In this paper, using variations in the state level regulations on adverse event reporting we find policies that can mitigate upcoding. A second subproject that led to the paper "A low-cost method for multiple disease prediction" aimed at finding a small set of biomarkers that can accurately predict the risk of multiple chronic diseases. This provides an affordable approach for monitoring the quality of health of individuals and for more accurate risk-adjustment purposes that are at the core of pay-for-performance mechanisms used by CMS.  The projectÆs funds had been primarily used to support the training of the next generation of scholars (graduate students and postdoctoral scholars), and developing teaching units on the topics of this highly interdisciplinary area.            Last Modified: 11/04/2015       Submitted by: Mohsen Bayati]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
