<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Numerical simulation and analysis of transient waves in unbounded domains</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project focuses on numerical approximation of wave propagation phenomena in transient cases, with an emphasis on techniques based on the use of boundary integral methods. As a set of physically motivated applications, the investigator will concentrate on different models of scattering of acoustic waves in two and three dimensions and in wave-structure interaction. The proposal includes numerical analysis and implementation of three kinds of schemes: (1) Galerkin and delta-based space semi-discretization with Convolution Quadrature for time domain boundary integral equations; (2) coupling of Finite and Boundary Elements with Convolution Quadrature in time, for models that combine the acoustic wave equation on non-homogeneous media with time domain boundary integral equations; (3) Hybridizable Discontinuous Galerkin methods for complex wave propagation problems, with an emphasis on wave-structure interaction in the time domain. At the analytical level, the investigator and his collaborators will work on the development of new mathematical tools for time domain boundary integral equations, using time domain techniques instead of the usual Laplace domain tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Computer simulation is an indispensable part of modern science and technology, often showing the path in design of new devices and predicting the behavior of complicated physical models that are expensive to experiment with. Through deep mathematical understanding, numerical analysis gives not only certainty in the ability of the computational simulations to yield the right answers, but also shows the expected quality of these results, and proposes new techniques to handle problems of increasing difficulty. The investigator and his team will work on the development of algorithmic and mathematical tools to study transient phenomena. The proposed work deals with propagation of sound and the interaction of mechanical vibrations with fluid motion, with potential applications in the simulation of propagation of noise inside vibrating structures (vehicles, for instance). The techniques that the investigator and his team will develop are general in scope and can be potentially applied to other wave propagation problems, including seismic and electromagnetic waves.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1216356</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Francisco</FirstName>
<LastName>Sayas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Francisco J Sayas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fjsayas@math.udel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3028312136</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000578351</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Delaware]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[210 Hullihen Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~299999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project addressed the simulation of the propagation and scattering by obstacles of transient waves, as well as the mathematical justification of the good properties (stability and approximation) of these computation simulations. Wave propagation and scattering is general moniker for a wide field of science ranging from mathematical study of complex models to practical computational simulation, and encompassing models in acoustics, seismology, electromagnetism, and biology, with a large range of potential applications in fields as diverse as oil exploration, material damage assessment or medical imaging.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The theoretical work developed in the project has expanded the existing views on the analysis of retarded potentials and time domain boundary integral equations, which are some of the main mathematical tools to model transient waves when they interact with obstacles. The research has furthered the understanding of stability of the mathematical models used to describe these phenomena, as well as of their computable approximations. These findings have been set in the first monograph published on the subject. Implementation and code development has been an important goal of the project, with the outcome of two fully documented and openly accessible Matlab packages for integral methods for two dimensional waves (which has the additional value of having been built so that it can be used for educational purposes) and for continuum three dimensional models using the versatile Hybridizable Discontinuous Galerkin method.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The work on a problem of this complexity, involving modern advanced mathematical tools of very different type and the coupling and development of code for large simulations has proved to be an ideal training ground for a new generation of researchers and practitioners in numerical analysis and scientific computing. Five graduate students have finished their doctoral dissertations in the frame of this project and yearly summer teams of undergraduates and freshmen graduate students have been introduced to research through the interaction with the group.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/13/2016<br>      Modified by: Francisco&nbsp;J&nbsp;Sayas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project addressed the simulation of the propagation and scattering by obstacles of transient waves, as well as the mathematical justification of the good properties (stability and approximation) of these computation simulations. Wave propagation and scattering is general moniker for a wide field of science ranging from mathematical study of complex models to practical computational simulation, and encompassing models in acoustics, seismology, electromagnetism, and biology, with a large range of potential applications in fields as diverse as oil exploration, material damage assessment or medical imaging.     The theoretical work developed in the project has expanded the existing views on the analysis of retarded potentials and time domain boundary integral equations, which are some of the main mathematical tools to model transient waves when they interact with obstacles. The research has furthered the understanding of stability of the mathematical models used to describe these phenomena, as well as of their computable approximations. These findings have been set in the first monograph published on the subject. Implementation and code development has been an important goal of the project, with the outcome of two fully documented and openly accessible Matlab packages for integral methods for two dimensional waves (which has the additional value of having been built so that it can be used for educational purposes) and for continuum three dimensional models using the versatile Hybridizable Discontinuous Galerkin method.     The work on a problem of this complexity, involving modern advanced mathematical tools of very different type and the coupling and development of code for large simulations has proved to be an ideal training ground for a new generation of researchers and practitioners in numerical analysis and scientific computing. Five graduate students have finished their doctoral dissertations in the frame of this project and yearly summer teams of undergraduates and freshmen graduate students have been introduced to research through the interaction with the group.             Last Modified: 09/13/2016       Submitted by: Francisco J Sayas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
