<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Mercury in the Atmosphere Over the Eastern United States</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>38755.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>38755</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020104</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Edgerton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sedgerto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928522</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project comprises the first large-scale airborne experiment focused on mercury over North America. The project has two primary objectives: 1) Constrain emissions of mercury from major source regions in the eastern United States, 2) Quantify the distribution and chemical transformations of mercury in the lower troposphere. To address these goals the NSF/National Center for Atmsopheric Research C-130 aircraft will be equipped with a suite of state-of-the-art instrumentation to measure gaseous elemental mercury (GEM), gaseous oxidized mercury (GOM), particle-bound Hg (pHg) and a suite of other compounds for air mass characterization. Flight plans will be designed to study industrial mercury sources over the Ohio River Valley, outflow of North American mercury to the Atlantic, and the impact of convective precipitation on surface wet deposition of mercury over the Southeast U.S. Operational planning will utilize regional and global forecast models to optimize the use of flight time. The C-130 observations will be integrated and analyzed after the mission with several chemical transport and Lagrangian models. These models will be used to examine the consistency between observations and emission inventories, allow the integration of ground-based observations with aircraft observations in a unified framework, constrain source-receptor relationships, and test different hypotheses about the chemical transformations and global cycling of mercury.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Human exposure to mercury is a significant health risk and a problem of national and global significance. Project results will reduce the uncertainties concerning source-receptor relationships and the relative contributions of domestic, foreign and natural sources to the inventory of atmospheric mercury over the eastern U.S. The research will involve a number of graduate and undergraduate students from several different U.S. institutions and thus will expose these students to working on high-level scientific problems of great national significance. In addition to a core group of scientists from the U.S., mercury scientists from Canada, Italy, Germany and Russia will also collaborate in the work, thus strengthening international scientific cooperation on global environmental problems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1216707</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Noelle</FirstName>
<LastName>Selin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Noelle E Selin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>selin@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173242592</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000556203</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/17/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394307</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>Atmospheric Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~38755</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We participated in a large-scale campaign to measure mercury concentrations in the atmosphere over the Southeastern U.S. Mercury and other atmospheric pollutants were measured from an aircraft during a six week period in the summer of 2013. The project aimed to improve scientific understanding of 1) the sources of mercury over the United States, and 2) the chemical reactions that mercury undergoes in the atmosphere. At MIT, our role was to conduct modeling of mercury chemistry and transport in the atmosphere. The model was used to help plan aircraft sampling strategy, as well as to help interpret the data that was collected. &nbsp;</p> <p>Using our model during the measurement campaign, we provided daily forecasts of mercury and other pollutant concentrations to assist in developing aircraft flight plans. We were able to identify times and locations where we predicted that mercury would be elevated in the atmosphere, which were then successfully sampled by the aircraft measurements. Work led by the MIT group compared measurements taken by the aircraft while over land and those taken over water to help understand how mercury cycles between the atmosphere, land surface, and ocean. Results of this work resulted in an improved estimate of how much mercury that was previously deposited to land and ocean surfaces is currently affecting the atmosphere. We contributed through conducting model analyses to work that helped to understand the chemical reactions that mercury undergoes in the atmosphere. Additionally, we contributed to work that better quantified the current industrial sources of atmospheric mercury.</p> <p>As mercury is a toxic trace metal that is regulated both nationally and internationally as an environmental pollutant, our work has broader impacts that are relevant to society as well as regulators and policy-makers. Understanding how mercury behaves in the atmosphere and environment is important for evaluating and implementing mercury reduction policies. We communicated our findings to public and policy audiences. In addition, two graduate students were trained in atmospheric chemistry modeling as part of this project.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/31/2015<br>      Modified by: Noelle&nbsp;E&nbsp;Selin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We participated in a large-scale campaign to measure mercury concentrations in the atmosphere over the Southeastern U.S. Mercury and other atmospheric pollutants were measured from an aircraft during a six week period in the summer of 2013. The project aimed to improve scientific understanding of 1) the sources of mercury over the United States, and 2) the chemical reactions that mercury undergoes in the atmosphere. At MIT, our role was to conduct modeling of mercury chemistry and transport in the atmosphere. The model was used to help plan aircraft sampling strategy, as well as to help interpret the data that was collected.    Using our model during the measurement campaign, we provided daily forecasts of mercury and other pollutant concentrations to assist in developing aircraft flight plans. We were able to identify times and locations where we predicted that mercury would be elevated in the atmosphere, which were then successfully sampled by the aircraft measurements. Work led by the MIT group compared measurements taken by the aircraft while over land and those taken over water to help understand how mercury cycles between the atmosphere, land surface, and ocean. Results of this work resulted in an improved estimate of how much mercury that was previously deposited to land and ocean surfaces is currently affecting the atmosphere. We contributed through conducting model analyses to work that helped to understand the chemical reactions that mercury undergoes in the atmosphere. Additionally, we contributed to work that better quantified the current industrial sources of atmospheric mercury.  As mercury is a toxic trace metal that is regulated both nationally and internationally as an environmental pollutant, our work has broader impacts that are relevant to society as well as regulators and policy-makers. Understanding how mercury behaves in the atmosphere and environment is important for evaluating and implementing mercury reduction policies. We communicated our findings to public and policy audiences. In addition, two graduate students were trained in atmospheric chemistry modeling as part of this project.           Last Modified: 12/31/2015       Submitted by: Noelle E Selin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
