<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Photonics Enabled Extreme Bandwidth Wireless Communications Spectrum Manager</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project aims to use and adapt a photonics based extreme bandwidth RF and Microwave spectrum analyzer as a real-time spectral manager for wireless communication systems.  The approach is enabled by a spatial-spectral holographic based spectrum analyzer developed by the STTR team that can have instantaneous processing bandwidth of 40 GHz or greater while retaining with high spectral resolution and low latency (&lt;&lt;1 ms) output.  This sensor hardware will be applied to wideband, real-time spectral management of wireless communications for operation in environments with new spectral access regulatory models.  When combined with low latency digital processing, using specialized digital signal processing hardware such as field programmable gate arrays and appropriate databases and software, the system will allow continuous and simultaneous monitoring of all common wireless communication bands for rapid distribution of channel occupancy data.  Project activities include: identifying the physical measurements and spectral signatures needed for wideband spectrum management, implementing specialized computer based algorithms to extract this information for real-time management, and investigating advanced spatial-spectral optical signal processing architectures to automatically recognize wireless signal characteristics such as modulation formats that are beyond the current power spectrum measurement capability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project includes uses in commercial wireless communication systems, RF test and measurement, defense signal intelligence and communications, regulatory spectrum management, and navigation and geo-location applications.  The first commercial impact is to enable dynamic identification and allocation of unused spectral resources in real time, in order to maximize the efficiency and increase the capacity of wireless networks.  The large bandwidth and frequency scalability of the spatial-spectral sensor technology could assist the growth of emerging radio communication technologies in existing bands, and in emerging bands such as E-band.  Additionally, this technology could assist governmental spectrum regulatory compliance enforcement, which could help to lead to changes in spectrum allocation policy.  Increased wireless capacity will help to enhance access to broadband internet access, including to poor or rural areas, where the capital costs of implementing physical infrastructure like fiber optic lines is cost prohibitive (evidenced by the developing world's use of cellular phones over landlines).  Beyond communications, RF monitoring has several applications ranging from electronic defense, to navigation and geo-location.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/17/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1217637</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zeb</FirstName>
<LastName>Barber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zeb W Barber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>barber@spectrum.montana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4069945925</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000509990</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristian</FirstName>
<LastName>Merkel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristian D Merkel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>merkel@s2corporation.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4069220334</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000520094</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>S2 Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
<ZipCode>597156504</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4069220334</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2310 University Way Bldg 4 -1</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>169797383</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>S2 CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[S2 Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>597156504</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2310 University Way, 4-1]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>105E</Code>
<Text>RF/Microwave &amp; mm-wave tech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>153E</Code>
<Text>Wireless comm &amp; sig processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In summary, a successful Phase 1 STTR effort in the assessment and use of the S2 Corporation novel radio frequency spectrum monitoring device over wide instantaneous bandwidths 0.5-18 GHz was completed, for the Extending the Access to the Radio Spectrum (EARS) program, that resulted in completion of the tasks proposed and beyond what was proposed.The following list highlights the results:</p> <ul> <li>AS PROPOSED - Identified spectral manager (SM) measurement specifications. Simulated SM performance and development analysis tools.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>AS PROPOSED - Demonstrated phase detection on waveforms with various modulation formats.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>AS PROPOSED - Developed real time digital processing algorithms for the spectrum analysis data stream, including real time "Max Hold" and "Averaging" to identify occupied and unoccupied portions of the RF spectrum, with thresholding. We implemented and tested algorithms in graphical processing unit (GPU) hardware. We integrated these into a graphical user interface (GUI). We implemented a new &ldquo;max-hold only&rdquo; option in offline processing software.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>AS PROPOSED AND BEYOND AS PROPOSED - Demonstrated the S2 spectrum analysis receiver in hardware over 0.5-18 GHz in the laboratory and created high-resolution spectrograms of data from spectrum collects.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>BEYOND AS PROPOSED - Demonstrated approach for significant improved performance for S2 processing with &gt;60 dB dynamic range (spur free) over 0.5-18 GHz. This rpresents a 6 dB improvement in SFDR over previous approach, with more gains possible.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>BEYOND AS PROPOSED - Performed a 0.5-10.5 GHz spectrum collect effort outside of the lab with a wideband antenna and S2 spectrum monitoring hardware.&nbsp; Created high-resolution spectrograms of data from spectrum collects.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>BEYOND AS PROPOSED - Established a technical path to extend the RF coverage to 40 GHz.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>AS PROPOSED - Completed the Phase 1 Deliverables</li> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/25/2013<br>      Modified by: Kristian&nbsp;D&nbsp;Merkel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1217637/1217637_10173675_1374725572328_Slide2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1217637/1217637_10173675_1374725572328_Slide2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Aspects of the S2 technology"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1217637/1217637_10173675_1374725572328_Slide2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Aspects of the S2 technology"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">List of various attributes of the S2 Corporation radio frequency spectrum monitoring technology</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kris Merkel, S2 Corporation</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kristian&nbsp;D&nbsp;Merkel</div> <div class="imageTitle">Aspects of the S2 technology</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1217637/1217637_10173675_1374725679922_Slide3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1217637/1217637_10173675_1374725679922_Slide3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Comparison of S2 spectrum analysis to conventional narrowband systeme"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2013/1217637/1217637_10173675_1374725679922_Slide3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Comparison of S2 spectrum analysis to conventional narrowband systeme"></a> <div class=...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In summary, a successful Phase 1 STTR effort in the assessment and use of the S2 Corporation novel radio frequency spectrum monitoring device over wide instantaneous bandwidths 0.5-18 GHz was completed, for the Extending the Access to the Radio Spectrum (EARS) program, that resulted in completion of the tasks proposed and beyond what was proposed.The following list highlights the results:  AS PROPOSED - Identified spectral manager (SM) measurement specifications. Simulated SM performance and development analysis tools.   AS PROPOSED - Demonstrated phase detection on waveforms with various modulation formats.   AS PROPOSED - Developed real time digital processing algorithms for the spectrum analysis data stream, including real time "Max Hold" and "Averaging" to identify occupied and unoccupied portions of the RF spectrum, with thresholding. We implemented and tested algorithms in graphical processing unit (GPU) hardware. We integrated these into a graphical user interface (GUI). We implemented a new "max-hold only" option in offline processing software.   AS PROPOSED AND BEYOND AS PROPOSED - Demonstrated the S2 spectrum analysis receiver in hardware over 0.5-18 GHz in the laboratory and created high-resolution spectrograms of data from spectrum collects.   BEYOND AS PROPOSED - Demonstrated approach for significant improved performance for S2 processing with &gt;60 dB dynamic range (spur free) over 0.5-18 GHz. This rpresents a 6 dB improvement in SFDR over previous approach, with more gains possible.   BEYOND AS PROPOSED - Performed a 0.5-10.5 GHz spectrum collect effort outside of the lab with a wideband antenna and S2 spectrum monitoring hardware.  Created high-resolution spectrograms of data from spectrum collects.   BEYOND AS PROPOSED - Established a technical path to extend the RF coverage to 40 GHz.   AS PROPOSED - Completed the Phase 1 Deliverables        Last Modified: 07/25/2013       Submitted by: Kristian D Merkel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
