<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Multiscale Turbulent Reacting Flows and Data-Based Modeling</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rosemary Renaut</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project investigates a multiscale flame-embedding approach for the computation of turbulent flames. The model is based on the coupling of large-eddy simulation (LES) for the description of the flow and for flame tracking and embedded 1D stochastic solutions of flamelets based on the one-dimensional turbulence (ODT) model. Important features of the framework include the upscaling of ODT solution to the LES, the downscaling of LES solutions to ODT, and capturing of the flame front. The Lagrangian LES-ODT formulation requires the tracking, spawning, and removal of ODT solutions as they are advected along the flame. The formulation also requires a robust formulation for the filtering of the density from the fine-grained solution of ODT to the LES along with the filtering of transport and source terms for scalars used to track the flame in LES. Wavelet-based methods will be investigated to establish consistency between the LES and ODT velocity fields and their transport. An optimal parameterization of the thermo-chemical scalars using principal component analysis will be used to improve computational efficiency. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research addresses the prediction of physical processes occurring in the production of energy through combustion. The work aims to develop next-generation modeling tools that can potentially reduce the turn-around time for the design of combustion systems through simulation and to investigate mechanisms to improve combustion efficiency and reduce pollutants.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1217200</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tarek</FirstName>
<LastName>Echekki</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tarek Echekki</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>techekk@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195155238</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000467512</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957910</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[911 Oval Drive - EB III 3252]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~66933</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~68350</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~64717</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of the study is to develop multiscale modeling strategies in turbulent combustion. Two key strategies were investigated. The first involves the development of a flame-embedding model in combustion large-eddy simulation (LES). The model is based on implementing fully-resolved 1D solutions on a flame surface, which capture the structure and dynamics (locally) of the flame. The solutions, based on one-dimensional turbulence (ODT), are spatially filtered to larger grid to capture the evolution of the filtered density field in LES as well as filtered chemical source terms. In addition to filtering, ODT management strategies were developed. They involve the injection of ODT solutions at inlets, their motion along the flame surface and their removal once they exit a flame surface. The multiscale modeling approach has been demonstrated in a turbulent jet diffusion flame.</p> <p>The second set of strategies are related to the development of schemes to accelerate chemistry integration. This integration tends to be a bottle-nect in resolved simulations in combustion. The schemes are built on a model-reduction approach that couples chemistry and transport using principla component analysis (PCA), which develops a representative set of scalars that represent the entire composition space. Both a priori and a posteriori validation studies have been carried out to demonstrate the PCA-based approach. The effort involves the development of tabulation strategies to invert from principal components' (PCs) solutions to the larger set of thermo-chemical scalars (using artificial neural networks, ANN), the derivation of models for the diffusion coefficients for these PCs, and the validation of these different models in both low-dimensional numerical simulations and direct numerical simulations (DNS). Significant computational saving is obtained such that 3D DNS with PC transport can be carried out at costs computational cost of 2D DNS based on the transport of thermo-chemical scalars.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/13/2016<br>      Modified by: Tarek&nbsp;Echekki</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of the study is to develop multiscale modeling strategies in turbulent combustion. Two key strategies were investigated. The first involves the development of a flame-embedding model in combustion large-eddy simulation (LES). The model is based on implementing fully-resolved 1D solutions on a flame surface, which capture the structure and dynamics (locally) of the flame. The solutions, based on one-dimensional turbulence (ODT), are spatially filtered to larger grid to capture the evolution of the filtered density field in LES as well as filtered chemical source terms. In addition to filtering, ODT management strategies were developed. They involve the injection of ODT solutions at inlets, their motion along the flame surface and their removal once they exit a flame surface. The multiscale modeling approach has been demonstrated in a turbulent jet diffusion flame.  The second set of strategies are related to the development of schemes to accelerate chemistry integration. This integration tends to be a bottle-nect in resolved simulations in combustion. The schemes are built on a model-reduction approach that couples chemistry and transport using principla component analysis (PCA), which develops a representative set of scalars that represent the entire composition space. Both a priori and a posteriori validation studies have been carried out to demonstrate the PCA-based approach. The effort involves the development of tabulation strategies to invert from principal components' (PCs) solutions to the larger set of thermo-chemical scalars (using artificial neural networks, ANN), the derivation of models for the diffusion coefficients for these PCs, and the validation of these different models in both low-dimensional numerical simulations and direct numerical simulations (DNS). Significant computational saving is obtained such that 3D DNS with PC transport can be carried out at costs computational cost of 2D DNS based on the transport of thermo-chemical scalars.       Last Modified: 12/13/2016       Submitted by: Tarek Echekki]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
