<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>III: Small: Towards Spatial Database Management Systems for Flash Memory Storage</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this research project is to design and develop highly efficient spatial and spatio-temporal database systems on flash memory storage. More specifically, this project conducts research, develops requisite scientific knowledge, builds software infrastructure, and integrates teaching activities with research for four specific aims: (1) Supporting efficient spatial indexing on flash memory, which includes data- and space-partitioning index structures, (2) Supporting efficient spatial query processing and optimization, which includes supporting various forms of the spatial join operation and query cost estimation, (3) Supporting spatio-temporal indexing and querying, which includes extending the spatial index data structures and the query processor to support the high update frequency common in spatio-temporal applications, and (4) Exploiting a storage hierarchy of flash and magnetic disks where spatial and spatio-temporal indexing, query processing, and optimization can exploit the full potential of both storage media. Besides its impact on industry, this project will have significant broader impact across multiple segments of society that include enhancing productivity, graduate and undergraduate student education, curriculum development, and tutorial presentations. Publications, technical reports, open-source software, and experimental data from this research are disseminated via the project web site (http://www.cs.umn.edu/~mokbel/flash).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1218168</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shashi</FirstName>
<LastName>Shekhar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shashi Shekhar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shekhar@cs.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126248307</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000467497</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohamed</FirstName>
<LastName>Mokbel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mohamed F Mokbel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mokbel@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126263025</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000294385</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota - Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 Oak St, SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~166739</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~333261</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project started by changing the way that researchers, developers, and practitioners deal with the flash storage. Traditionally, the flash storage has been dealt with as a new storage media that is faster, lighter, and more durable. Existing index structures are designed with the implicit assumption that the underlying external memory storage is the conventional magnetic hard disk drives. This assumption is going to be invalid soon, as flash memory storage is increasingly adopted as the main storage media in mobile devices, digital cameras, embedded sensors, and notebooks. Though it is direct and simple to port existing tree index structures on the flash memory storage, that direct approach does not consider the unique characteristics of flash memory, i.e., slow write operations, and erase-before-update property, which would result in a sub optimal performance. This project has redesigned the way that database systems deal with flash storage. Index structures are modified in a generic way to fit to the new properties of flash storage, and take advantage of its distinguishing properties.</p> <p><br />Then, the project went ahead for scalability, where it develops the SpatialHadoop system as the first full-fledged opensource Map-Reduce-based system that is geared towards indexing, querying, and visualizing Big Spatial Data. SpatialHadoop was downloaded more than 80,000 times within one year of its release, and become the de facto system when dealing with Big Spatial Data. All source code, tutorials, and examples of SpatialHadoop, along with about a terra byte of freely available Big Spatial Data can be downloaded from: http://spatialhadoop.cs.umn.edu/</p> <p><br />The project also introduces HadoopViz; a Map-Reduce-based framework for visualizing big spatial data. HadoopViz exposes an extensible interface, which allows users to define new visualization types by defining few abstract functions. HadoopViz is capable of generating big images with giga-pixel resolution by employing a three-phase technique, partition-plot-merge.</p> <p>Finally, the project has introduced ST-Hadoop; the first full-fledged open-source MapReduce framework with a native support for spatio-temporal data. ST-Hadoop is a comprehensive extension to Hadoop and SpatialHadoop that injectsspatio-temporal data awareness inside each of their layers, mainly, language, indexing, and operations layers. In the language layer, ST-Hadoop provides built in spatiotemporal data types and operations. In the indexing layer, ST-Hadoop spatio-temporally loads and divides data across computation nodes in Hadoop Distributed File System in a way that mimics spatio-temporal index structures, which result in achieving orders of magnitude better performance than Hadoop and SpatialHadoop when dealing with spatio-temporal data and queries. In the operations layer, ST-Hadoop shipped with support for two fundamental spatio-temporal queries, namely, spatio-temporal range and join queries. Extensibility of ST-Hadoop allows others to expand features and operations easily using similar approach. The key idea behind the performance gained in ST-Hadoop is its ability in indexing spatio-temporal data within Hadoop Distributed File System. All source code, tutorials, and examples of ST-Hadoop, can be downloaded from: http://st-hadoop.cs.umn.edu/</p> <p><br />The project has supported eight PhD students, five of them have already graduated, securing jobs in major academia and research labs. Publications and results coming our from this projects are available in: http://www.cs.umn.edu/~mokbel</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/16/2017<br>      Modified by: Mohamed&nbsp;F&nbsp;Mokbel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project started by changing the way that researchers, developers, and practitioners deal with the flash storage. Traditionally, the flash storage has been dealt with as a new storage media that is faster, lighter, and more durable. Existing index structures are designed with the implicit assumption that the underlying external memory storage is the conventional magnetic hard disk drives. This assumption is going to be invalid soon, as flash memory storage is increasingly adopted as the main storage media in mobile devices, digital cameras, embedded sensors, and notebooks. Though it is direct and simple to port existing tree index structures on the flash memory storage, that direct approach does not consider the unique characteristics of flash memory, i.e., slow write operations, and erase-before-update property, which would result in a sub optimal performance. This project has redesigned the way that database systems deal with flash storage. Index structures are modified in a generic way to fit to the new properties of flash storage, and take advantage of its distinguishing properties.   Then, the project went ahead for scalability, where it develops the SpatialHadoop system as the first full-fledged opensource Map-Reduce-based system that is geared towards indexing, querying, and visualizing Big Spatial Data. SpatialHadoop was downloaded more than 80,000 times within one year of its release, and become the de facto system when dealing with Big Spatial Data. All source code, tutorials, and examples of SpatialHadoop, along with about a terra byte of freely available Big Spatial Data can be downloaded from: http://spatialhadoop.cs.umn.edu/   The project also introduces HadoopViz; a Map-Reduce-based framework for visualizing big spatial data. HadoopViz exposes an extensible interface, which allows users to define new visualization types by defining few abstract functions. HadoopViz is capable of generating big images with giga-pixel resolution by employing a three-phase technique, partition-plot-merge.  Finally, the project has introduced ST-Hadoop; the first full-fledged open-source MapReduce framework with a native support for spatio-temporal data. ST-Hadoop is a comprehensive extension to Hadoop and SpatialHadoop that injectsspatio-temporal data awareness inside each of their layers, mainly, language, indexing, and operations layers. In the language layer, ST-Hadoop provides built in spatiotemporal data types and operations. In the indexing layer, ST-Hadoop spatio-temporally loads and divides data across computation nodes in Hadoop Distributed File System in a way that mimics spatio-temporal index structures, which result in achieving orders of magnitude better performance than Hadoop and SpatialHadoop when dealing with spatio-temporal data and queries. In the operations layer, ST-Hadoop shipped with support for two fundamental spatio-temporal queries, namely, spatio-temporal range and join queries. Extensibility of ST-Hadoop allows others to expand features and operations easily using similar approach. The key idea behind the performance gained in ST-Hadoop is its ability in indexing spatio-temporal data within Hadoop Distributed File System. All source code, tutorials, and examples of ST-Hadoop, can be downloaded from: http://st-hadoop.cs.umn.edu/   The project has supported eight PhD students, five of them have already graduated, securing jobs in major academia and research labs. Publications and results coming our from this projects are available in: http://www.cs.umn.edu/~mokbel          Last Modified: 10/16/2017       Submitted by: Mohamed F Mokbel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
