<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CSR: CC: Small: Collaborative Research: Language and Runtime Support for Large-Scale Data Analytics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>246905.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>246905</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marilyn McClure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmcclure@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>As the cost of computing and communication resources has plummeted, applications have become data-centric with data products growing explosively in both number and size.  Although accessing such data using the compute power necessary for its analysis and processing is cheap and readily available via cloud computing (intuitive, utility-style access to vast resource pools), doing so currently requires significant expertise, experience, and time (for customization, configuration, deployment, etc).  This work investigates new models of cloud computing that combine domain-targeted languages with scalable data processing, sharing, and management abstractions within a distributed service platform that "scales" programmer productivity.  To enable this, this research explores new programming language, runtime, and distributed systems techniques and technologies that integrate the R programming language environment with open source cloud platform-as-a-service (PaaS) in ways that simplify processing massive datasets, sharing datasets across applications and users, and tracking and enforcing data provenance.  The PIs' plans for research, outreach, integrated curricula, and open source release of research artifacts have the potential for making cloud computing more accessible to a much wider range of users: The data analytics community who use the R statistical analysis environment to apply their techniques and algorithms to important problems in areas such as biology, chemistry, physics, political science and finance, by enabling them to use cloud resources transparently for their analyses, and to share their scientific data/results in a way that enables others to reproduce and verify them.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1218808</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Krintz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chandra Krintz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ckrintz@cs.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058934321</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000288955</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931065110</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University of California]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~246905</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>Our work has investigated new models of cloud computing that combine domain-targeted languages with scalable data processing, sharing, and management abstractions within a distributed service platform to bridge this programmer&nbsp;</span>productivity gap. To enable this, our research has explored new programming language, runtime, and distributed systems techniques and technologies that integrate the R programming language environment with open source cloud platform-as-a- service (PaaS) in ways that simplify processing massive datasets, sharing datasets across applications and users, and tracking and enforcing data provenance. In particular, our work has investigated new techniques that efficiently link R programs to distributed cloud services transparently, provide API-level dataset access control, and facilitate verification of data authenticity, ownership, and reproducibility.&nbsp;</p> <p>The key outcomes of our project include the investigation, development, and evaluation of techniques surrouding code and data provenance. &nbsp;This includes the open source release of extensions for the AppScale cloud platform and StochSS -- stochastic simulation as a service. &nbsp;Our extensions make it possible for scientists and web programmers to capture state changes in their programs to perform tracking and checking for offline data analysis. &nbsp;They also faciliate replay of programs across cloud computing systems. &nbsp;Such functionality enable users of our tools to understand the computing and storage requirements of their applications as well as the cost for their execution in different public clouds. &nbsp;In addition, they faciliate sharing and collaboration based on data products with well defined provenance. &nbsp;Specific open source software tools that have resulted from this work are CloudRunner, CloudTracker, and FlexCloud among others.</p> </div> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/02/2016<br>      Modified by: Chandra&nbsp;Krintz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[     Our work has investigated new models of cloud computing that combine domain-targeted languages with scalable data processing, sharing, and management abstractions within a distributed service platform to bridge this programmer productivity gap. To enable this, our research has explored new programming language, runtime, and distributed systems techniques and technologies that integrate the R programming language environment with open source cloud platform-as-a- service (PaaS) in ways that simplify processing massive datasets, sharing datasets across applications and users, and tracking and enforcing data provenance. In particular, our work has investigated new techniques that efficiently link R programs to distributed cloud services transparently, provide API-level dataset access control, and facilitate verification of data authenticity, ownership, and reproducibility.   The key outcomes of our project include the investigation, development, and evaluation of techniques surrouding code and data provenance.  This includes the open source release of extensions for the AppScale cloud platform and StochSS -- stochastic simulation as a service.  Our extensions make it possible for scientists and web programmers to capture state changes in their programs to perform tracking and checking for offline data analysis.  They also faciliate replay of programs across cloud computing systems.  Such functionality enable users of our tools to understand the computing and storage requirements of their applications as well as the cost for their execution in different public clouds.  In addition, they faciliate sharing and collaboration based on data products with well defined provenance.  Specific open source software tools that have resulted from this work are CloudRunner, CloudTracker, and FlexCloud among others.              Last Modified: 10/02/2016       Submitted by: Chandra Krintz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
