<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2012 S-STEM Principal Investigators Meeting</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1056637.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1056637</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joyce B. Evans</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The NSF S-STEM program provides scholarships to talented and financially needy students enabling them to enroll full time in a STEM discipline. Because the S-STEM program provides limited support for dissemination and community interaction, it has been difficult for schools administering S-STEM scholarships to communicate and learn from each other. This project is bringing exemplary S-STEM principal investigators together with new S-STEM principal investigators and facilitating an exchange of lessons learned and best practices among projects. The face-to-face meeting of PIs is critical to generate a thorough exchange of ideas and the documentation of best practices that cannot be captured in other forms of gatherings. The meeting results are being disseminated nationally and therefore the meeting benefits not only the attendees but also all current and near future proposers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1219584</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Norman</FirstName>
<LastName>Fortenberry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Norman L Fortenberry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>N.Fortenberry@asee.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023313500</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000397411</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/14/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/06/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Yoder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Yoder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>b.yoder@asee.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023313535</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000624475</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Society For Engineering Education</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200362476</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023313500</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1818 N ST NW STE 600</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020293395</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR ENGINEERING EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020293395</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Society For Engineering Education]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200362476</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1818 N Street, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1056637</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The National Science Foundation (NSF) is the federal government&rsquo;s primary entity for funding research in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM). The NSF S-STEM program makes grants to universities for academically talented students with financial need, allowing students to enter the STEM workforce or graduate school after graduation. The program emphasizes comprehensive approaches that pull together recruitment, academic support, mentoring, and facilitated career placement.&nbsp;</p> <p>The key individual at each college or university that receives an S-STEM project grant is the Principal Investigator, or PI. Because the PI&rsquo;s often work &ldquo;siloed&rdquo; from other S-STEM PI&rsquo;s, there is limited ability to share best practices, learn from mistakes and successes at other institutions, and collaborate.</p> <p>This project started with a 2012 workshop that brought together S-STEM PI&rsquo;s from around the country to encourage them to network with colleagues who have experienced similar challenges and opportunities to the ones they face as they implement their S-STEM grants. The expectation for the workshop was that PIs would recognize that different projects in different places, often in different disciplines, face similar challenges, and that sharing best practices to deal with them would send them home better equipped to handle them at their institution.&nbsp; During breakout sessions PIs learned of commonalities with others in the room, not just at peer institutions but also at very different colleges or universities. There were calls in several sessions for more networking opportunities for project teams, including more educational opportunities, such as another S-STEM Projects Meeting.&nbsp; Another educational outcome was increased clarity over what PIs can and can&rsquo;t do with NSF S-STEM grant funds because of program rules, NSF policy, or federal law.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/14/2016<br>      Modified by: Brian&nbsp;Yoder</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The National Science Foundation (NSF) is the federal government?s primary entity for funding research in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM). The NSF S-STEM program makes grants to universities for academically talented students with financial need, allowing students to enter the STEM workforce or graduate school after graduation. The program emphasizes comprehensive approaches that pull together recruitment, academic support, mentoring, and facilitated career placement.   The key individual at each college or university that receives an S-STEM project grant is the Principal Investigator, or PI. Because the PI?s often work "siloed" from other S-STEM PI?s, there is limited ability to share best practices, learn from mistakes and successes at other institutions, and collaborate.  This project started with a 2012 workshop that brought together S-STEM PI?s from around the country to encourage them to network with colleagues who have experienced similar challenges and opportunities to the ones they face as they implement their S-STEM grants. The expectation for the workshop was that PIs would recognize that different projects in different places, often in different disciplines, face similar challenges, and that sharing best practices to deal with them would send them home better equipped to handle them at their institution.  During breakout sessions PIs learned of commonalities with others in the room, not just at peer institutions but also at very different colleges or universities. There were calls in several sessions for more networking opportunities for project teams, including more educational opportunities, such as another S-STEM Projects Meeting.  Another educational outcome was increased clarity over what PIs can and can?t do with NSF S-STEM grant funds because of program rules, NSF policy, or federal law.        Last Modified: 12/14/2016       Submitted by: Brian Yoder]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
