<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Analysis of Fault Growth and Linkage Using Work Minimization</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>232101.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>232101</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030103</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Fountain</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>To predict fault growth it is important to understand crack linkage under shear. If fault growth is governed by maximizing mechanical efficiency, a fault system will accommodate deformation either via slip on existing faults or via the growth of a new fault, depending on which is energetically easiest. Consequently, whether small flaws or cracks will link to form a larger crack depends on whether the energetic gain in efficient connection of cracks exceeds the work required to create the linking crack. Using the principle of work minimization, this research project numerically investigates how faults link and grow with two approaches: 1) parametric investigation of crack coalescence in order to test and calibrate the application of work minimization and 2) simulation of the evolution of the San Jacinto fault in southern California. The first approach uses mechanical models in a suite of parametric and stochastic investigations to evaluate the configuration of new fault growth that would both maximize efficiency of the system and are energetically favored to develop, i.e. the work cost is less than the efficiency gained. The stochastic models will incorporate different distributions of flaws in a sample under a variety of loading conditions to explore the effect of differing degrees of anisotropy. Furthermore, an investigation of the scaling of mechanical efficiency from the lab to regional scales will facilitate the second approach employed in the project. The second approach uses three-dimensional models to investigate the work associated with the evolution of a stepover between the Clark fault and the Coyote Creek fault, which are part of the San Jacinto fault in southern California. Numerical models will simulate several stages in the interpreted fault development at this stepover and assess the evolving mechanical efficiency. The study will (a) provide insight into the mechanical efficiency of fracture growth and coalescence, including the impact of anisotropy and the scale of the models; and (b) analyze the development of the San Jacinto fault through the growth and linkage of two fault segments based on the principle of work minimization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Tectonic plate boundaries in the Earth contain many active faults that slip in devastating earthquakes and contribute to building large mountain ranges. The size of potential earthquakes depends on the length of the fault; the larger the fault, the bigger the potential earthquakes. While the behavior of faults is understood, how they grow is not. Within the laboratory, scientists observed that within rocks, smaller cracks link to form fault surfaces. Since many rocks already have abundant small cracks but not all rocks contain faults, we need to understand the conditions that contribute to crack linkage and eventual fault development. This project examines how cracks link to form faults by applying the principle of work minimization. This principle implies that the Earth is lazy. Within a lazy Earth, cracks will only link up if the energetic cost of linking the cracks is less than the energetic benefit of having the cracks linked up. In the case of geologic faults, the benefit is that linked up cracks may more readily accommodate slip and the cost is the energy need to break the rock at the linkage. The project will develop tools to predict crack linkage that are based on work minimization. Once these tools are developed, they will be applied to the San Jacinto fault in southern California, which has a recent history of linkage of two segments. If the model predictions match the interpreted history of the San Jacinto fault then this tool may be of use for investigating other regions of the world and predicting future fault evolution.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1219919</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michele</FirstName>
<LastName>Cooke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michele L Cooke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cooke@geo.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135773142</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000203696</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039297</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[611 North Pleasant Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1572</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~112533</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~119568</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong>Cracks and earthquake faults within rock grow by a complex combination of opening failure (tension) and failure by slipping (shear). Before this study, well-tested theories explained either tensile failure or shear failure but we didn&rsquo;t have an approach that explicitly considered these two failure modes together. In other words, we would have to assume a fault grew either by one failure mode or the other.&nbsp;&nbsp; With NSF funding, the UMass geomechanics team led by the Principal Investigator, Cooke and including post-doctoral scholar Madden and PhD candidate Mc Beck developed a new modeling tool that predicts fault growth by finding the failure mode and orientation that put the entire fault system at an optimal energy level. This tool is called GROW (GRowth by Optimization of Work) and we have now thoroughly tested this tool in a variety of scenarios. GROW predictions match various analytical solutions as well as laboratory experiments of fault growth.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The work analysis also provides insight about different components of fault system&rsquo;s work budget.&nbsp; For example, we learned that contrary to previous assumptions, the work of fault growth depends on the fault&rsquo;s setting, such as stress level, and is not a property of the rock type.&nbsp; We also learned that growth by tensile failure has greater impact on the total work of a fault system than shear failure. Thus, we should expect faults within geologic materials to often propagate in tension. This is supported by abundant field evidence for tensile failure near fault tips.&nbsp; The work budget analysis also allows us to assess the power that the fault system has to grow the faults. For echelon fault segments, this power decreases as the faults propagate towards one another but then increases sharply as the fault tips near one another.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We used the echelon geometry of faults to simulate the development of the step between the active Hayward and Rogers Creek faults underlying the San Pablo Bay region of north California.&nbsp; Our models suggests that the basement rocks of the region have northwest-southeast oriented planes of weakness that control the orientation of active faulting and prevent the fault segments from curving around and linking up.&nbsp; Since linked faults can produce larger earthquakes than segmented faults, understanding this potential for linkage is important for seismic hazard assessment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Even without fault linkage, earthquakes may be able to jump from one fault segment to another across steps between the faults.&nbsp; Field data suggest that the potential for this to occur depends on the geometry of the step between the faults and the presence of small fractures around the faults, which are called damage. We investigate this with models that simulate earthquake slip and the explicitly incorporate the development of damage.&nbsp; In agreement with paleoseismic observations, the models show that earthquake ruptures can propagate from one fault segment to another across small steps between the echelon faults.&nbsp; Larger steps stop ruptures from propagating to the second fault. The propagation of rupture across the step also depends on the echelon geometry of the faults (right-stepping or left-stepping). For example, right-lateral slip along right-stepping faults creates tension between the faults so that slip is more easily transferred to the second fault. For these steps, the creation of damage facilitates the transfer of slip across the step. In contrast, right-lateral slip along the left-stepping faults will create compression between the faults that inhibits both slip transfer across the step and the development of damage</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong> The GROW software tool is available for use.&nbsp; The source code, read me fi...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: Cracks and earthquake faults within rock grow by a complex combination of opening failure (tension) and failure by slipping (shear). Before this study, well-tested theories explained either tensile failure or shear failure but we didnÆt have an approach that explicitly considered these two failure modes together. In other words, we would have to assume a fault grew either by one failure mode or the other.   With NSF funding, the UMass geomechanics team led by the Principal Investigator, Cooke and including post-doctoral scholar Madden and PhD candidate Mc Beck developed a new modeling tool that predicts fault growth by finding the failure mode and orientation that put the entire fault system at an optimal energy level. This tool is called GROW (GRowth by Optimization of Work) and we have now thoroughly tested this tool in a variety of scenarios. GROW predictions match various analytical solutions as well as laboratory experiments of fault growth.       The work analysis also provides insight about different components of fault systemÆs work budget.  For example, we learned that contrary to previous assumptions, the work of fault growth depends on the faultÆs setting, such as stress level, and is not a property of the rock type.  We also learned that growth by tensile failure has greater impact on the total work of a fault system than shear failure. Thus, we should expect faults within geologic materials to often propagate in tension. This is supported by abundant field evidence for tensile failure near fault tips.  The work budget analysis also allows us to assess the power that the fault system has to grow the faults. For echelon fault segments, this power decreases as the faults propagate towards one another but then increases sharply as the fault tips near one another.      We used the echelon geometry of faults to simulate the development of the step between the active Hayward and Rogers Creek faults underlying the San Pablo Bay region of north California.  Our models suggests that the basement rocks of the region have northwest-southeast oriented planes of weakness that control the orientation of active faulting and prevent the fault segments from curving around and linking up.  Since linked faults can produce larger earthquakes than segmented faults, understanding this potential for linkage is important for seismic hazard assessment.     Even without fault linkage, earthquakes may be able to jump from one fault segment to another across steps between the faults.  Field data suggest that the potential for this to occur depends on the geometry of the step between the faults and the presence of small fractures around the faults, which are called damage. We investigate this with models that simulate earthquake slip and the explicitly incorporate the development of damage.  In agreement with paleoseismic observations, the models show that earthquake ruptures can propagate from one fault segment to another across small steps between the echelon faults.  Larger steps stop ruptures from propagating to the second fault. The propagation of rupture across the step also depends on the echelon geometry of the faults (right-stepping or left-stepping). For example, right-lateral slip along right-stepping faults creates tension between the faults so that slip is more easily transferred to the second fault. For these steps, the creation of damage facilitates the transfer of slip across the step. In contrast, right-lateral slip along the left-stepping faults will create compression between the faults that inhibits both slip transfer across the step and the development of damage     Broader Impacts: The GROW software tool is available for use.  The source code, read me files, example input files and userÆs manual are posted on the Umass Geomechanics web page and also at github. This tool provides an innovative approach that could transform the way that we analyze fault propagation.     This project has supported the ca...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
