<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>At a Cross-Roads--Tracking The First Mediterranean Island Colonizers: Interdisciplinary Investigations at Early Neolithic Ais Giorkis, Cyprus</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>214998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224658</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With support from the National Science Foundation, Dr. Alan Simmons and an international research team will conduct an archaeological investigation of the initial human colonization of the Mediterranean island of Cyprus.  This occurred during the Neolithic period, which represented the shift from hunting and gathering to the domestication of plants and animals and settled village life. The "Neolithic Revolution," one of humanity's most momentous transformations, first occurred in the Near East around 10,000 years ago. The adjacent Mediterranean islands were considered marginal to Neolithic research, since early studies indicated that most of them were not occupied until well after the Neolithic had begun.  Recent research, however, has revolutionized perspectives on the colonization of these islands, showing that Cyprus was occupied far earlier than previously believed.  These studies have changed how archaeologists view domestication, its accompanying social changes, and how the Neolithic spread. &lt;br/&gt;Simmons and his team will conduct two excavation seasons and one study season at the site of Ais Girokis (ca., 7,500 cal. BC).  This site is one of but a handful of recently discovered settlements that have pushed the Neolithic  colonization of Cyprus back by over a 1,000 years.  Ais Giorkis stands out from other sites due to its unique uplands location, as opposed to the coastal setting of other early sites.  It contains evidence of feasting, has unique architectural features, and has some of the earliest domestic plants and animals (including cattle, which previously had not been documented in early Cyprus) in the entire Near East.   &lt;br/&gt;The central theoretical framework of the project relates to how under-inhabited regions, such as islands, were permanently colonized. It is  hypothesized that Ais Giorkis formed a unique part of Cyprus' initial colonization strategy that was distinct from coastal settlements.  The intellectual merit of this study views Cyprus within the wider Near Eastern landscape, providing a broader context for early seafaring technology and the expansion of the "Neolithic Package" from its continental cores. This is important since conventional wisdom was that the Neolithic spread overland from the Near East to Europe.  The new Cypriot research, however, suggests that maritime routes also may have been used.  Indeed, a recent DNA study of a Scandinavian Neolithic burial shows some genetic linkages to both modern Greeks and Cypriots.  The Ais Giorkis project has anthropological significance that involves global comparisons of island colonization, seafaring technologies, and adaptations related to economic and social networks involved in settling new lands.  &lt;br/&gt;The project's broader impacts include how scientists understand the Neolithic transformation, a critical period in the evolution of human societies.  This research, the only American project in Cyprus dealing with the Neolithic, partners with international collaborators and  contributes to the professional training of both US and non-US  undergraduates and graduate students. This research also provides insight into how ancient farming societies adapted to expanding populations, new environments,  and resource depletion.  Understanding their choices may help contemporary society as it encounters many of the same challenges that these early farmers faced.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1220351</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
<LastName>Simmons</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alan H Simmons</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alan.simmons@unlv.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7028953912</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000415756</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nevada Las Vegas</Name>
<CityName>Las Vegas</CityName>
<ZipCode>891549900</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7028951357</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4505 MARYLAND PARKWAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>098377336</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS NEVADA SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067808063</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nevada Las Vegas]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>891541055</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>Archaeology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~214998</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~9660</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The <em>Ais Giorkis</em> Archaeological Project investigated the early settlement of the Mediterranean island of Cyprus nearly 10,000 years ago.&nbsp; This interdisciplinary project represents a contribution to a better understanding of the transition from hunting and gathering to food production and the establishment of sedentary communities (the "Neolithic"). &nbsp;This was a transformative change to all aspects of human society, setting the stage for the development of complex societies that evolved into the contemporary world.&nbsp; This event occurred independently, but is best documented and is the oldest in the Near East.&nbsp; One of the most dramatic new changes to our perception of the Neolithic involves the colonization of Cyprus, and <em>Ais Giorkis</em> has provided substantial new data.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Conventional wisdom was that most of the Mediterranean islands were not occupied until the later Neolithic.&nbsp; Current research, however, has up-ended this perspective.&nbsp;&nbsp; There is now compelling evidence that some of the islands were occupied prior to the Neolithic.&nbsp; In Cyprus, Akrotiri <em>Aetokremnos</em> was one of the first sites to break the Neolithic barrier, documenting a firm Late Epipaleolithic use around 10,000 cal. B.C.&nbsp; This is some 3,000 years earlier than Cyprus' traditional Neolithic, the Khirokitia Culture (KC).&nbsp; More controversially, the site has a huge assemblage of extinct pygmy hippopotamus, thereby contributing to the controversial issue of human vs. environmental causes of Pleistocene extinctions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Subsequent to <em>Aetokremnos'&nbsp;</em>excavation, a few sites now nearly erase the gap between <em>Aetokremnos</em> and the KC.&nbsp; Pre-Pottery Neolithic A (PPNA) and PPNB sites are now documented, making the Cypriot Neolithic as early as that on the mainland.&nbsp; Most of these sites are near the coast, with the exception of <em>Ais Giorkis</em>, which is in the foothills of the Troodos Mountains (Figure 1).&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Primary NSF support allowed for several excavation seasons, and data from <em>Ais Giorkis</em> have been thoroughly analyzed. Several MA theses and two Ph.D. dissertations also have been produced.&nbsp; While tentative until final data integration, several observations on the project's intellectual merit can be made.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Beyond its upland location, <em>Ais Giorkis </em>differs from contemporary sites in several ways. It is larger than originally thought (Figure 2), likely representing a seasonal village. &nbsp;Geoarchaeological investigations demonstrated substantial intact deposits, despite erosion and modern plowing.&nbsp; <em>Ais Giorkis</em> contains unusual features, such as oval stone platforms (Figures 3, 4).&nbsp; We retrieved amongst the largest chipped stone and faunal assemblages on the island.&nbsp; The chipped stone shows technological resemblance to mainland PPNB sites.&nbsp; The ground stone suggests only limited milling activities, but includes several axes and a complete plaster bowl (Figure 5), very rare in Cyprus. &nbsp;External trade is suggested by imported obsidian and carnelian.&nbsp; Cattle are documented, now occurring at three PPNB sites.&nbsp;&nbsp; This is important, since cattle were not believed to have been in Cyprus until the Bronze Age.&nbsp; Their presence may have ceremonial as well as economic significance, given the former function on the mainland.&nbsp; However, in Cyprus they may simply have been "beasts of burden," becoming too "expensive" to maintain. &nbsp;Other animals include pig, sheep, goat, and deer, all but the latter domesticated.&nbsp; Deer is the most common animal, indicating the importance of hunting.&nbsp; An innovative isotopic study indicates that sheep and goat were left to winter in the uplands, rather than being transported to the lowlands.&nbsp; Some of the domestic fauna also may have become feral.&nbsp; Botanical remains (Figure 6) include barley and emmer wheat, some of the earliest domesticates in the Near East. &nbsp;Only two burials were recovered:&nbsp; an infant and an adult male.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Much of the material cultural hints at feasting activities, perhaps for bringing together upland and lowland groups.&nbsp; Many lines of evidence also point to the utilization of woodland resources, perhaps even the use of superior timber for refurbishing ships.&nbsp; Thus, Ais<em> Giorkis'</em>&nbsp;upland location indicates that even during Cyprus' initial colonization, interior regions were being used to exploit several resources.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The project's broader impacts contribute to both archaeology and wider issues. &nbsp;For archaeology, the project has considerable significance not only to Cyprus and the Near East, but also sheds light on how islands were colonized on a more global basis.&nbsp; These Cypriot sites suggest that these early bearers of village life had an efficient seafaring technology allowing for the transport of both people and resources. Cyprus can no longer be regarded as a footnote of the Neolithic Revolution, but rather as an integral part of this tumultuous time.&nbsp; Beyond its archaeological significance, the project also has contributed to public awareness of archaeology, international research cooperation, and the promotion of early-career women in science (most of the theses/dissertations were by women).&nbsp; Even more broadly, why these early Neolithic emigrants initially left the mainland cannot yet be answered--perhaps it related to expanding populations and resource scarcity, a situation paralleled by the current migrant situation in the Mediterranean.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/04/2018<br>      Modified by: Alan&nbsp;H&nbsp;Simmons</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541392373707_simmonsfig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541392373707_simmonsfig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541392373707_simmonsfig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Overview of Ais Giorkis, with Troodos Mountains in the background</div> <div class="imageCredit">alan simmons</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alan&nbsp;H&nbsp;Simmons</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541392688230_simmonsfig2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541392688230_simmonsfig2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541392688230_simmonsfig2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Drone image of completed excavations, showing oval structures and other units.</div> <div class="imageCredit">alan simmons</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alan&nbsp;H&nbsp;Simmons</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541392947992_simmonsfig3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541392947992_simmonsfig3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541392947992_simmonsfig3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Feature 17, the largest platform structure, under excavation.</div> <div class="imageCredit">alan simmons</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alan&nbsp;H&nbsp;Simmons</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541393056763_simmonsfig4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541393056763_simmonsfig4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541393056763_simmonsfig4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Overview of main excavation area, showing structures.</div> <div class="imageCredit">alan simmons</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alan&nbsp;H&nbsp;Simmons</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541393153900_simmonsfig5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541393153900_simmonsfig5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 5"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541393153900_simmonsfig5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 5"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Plaster "vaiselle blanche" bowl, found near infant burial.</div> <div class="imageCredit">alan simmons</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alan&nbsp;H&nbsp;Simmons</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 5</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541393223184_simmonsfig6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541393223184_simmonsfig6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 6"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220351/1220351_10206148_1541393223184_simmonsfig6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 6"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Some of the carbonized and datable domestic plant remains recovered.</div> <div class="imageCredit">alan simmons</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alan&nbsp;H&nbsp;Simmons</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 6</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Ais Giorkis Archaeological Project investigated the early settlement of the Mediterranean island of Cyprus nearly 10,000 years ago.  This interdisciplinary project represents a contribution to a better understanding of the transition from hunting and gathering to food production and the establishment of sedentary communities (the "Neolithic").  This was a transformative change to all aspects of human society, setting the stage for the development of complex societies that evolved into the contemporary world.  This event occurred independently, but is best documented and is the oldest in the Near East.  One of the most dramatic new changes to our perception of the Neolithic involves the colonization of Cyprus, and Ais Giorkis has provided substantial new data.                 Conventional wisdom was that most of the Mediterranean islands were not occupied until the later Neolithic.  Current research, however, has up-ended this perspective.   There is now compelling evidence that some of the islands were occupied prior to the Neolithic.  In Cyprus, Akrotiri Aetokremnos was one of the first sites to break the Neolithic barrier, documenting a firm Late Epipaleolithic use around 10,000 cal. B.C.  This is some 3,000 years earlier than Cyprus' traditional Neolithic, the Khirokitia Culture (KC).  More controversially, the site has a huge assemblage of extinct pygmy hippopotamus, thereby contributing to the controversial issue of human vs. environmental causes of Pleistocene extinctions.     Subsequent to Aetokremnos' excavation, a few sites now nearly erase the gap between Aetokremnos and the KC.  Pre-Pottery Neolithic A (PPNA) and PPNB sites are now documented, making the Cypriot Neolithic as early as that on the mainland.  Most of these sites are near the coast, with the exception of Ais Giorkis, which is in the foothills of the Troodos Mountains (Figure 1).                  Primary NSF support allowed for several excavation seasons, and data from Ais Giorkis have been thoroughly analyzed. Several MA theses and two Ph.D. dissertations also have been produced.  While tentative until final data integration, several observations on the project's intellectual merit can be made.      Beyond its upland location, Ais Giorkis differs from contemporary sites in several ways. It is larger than originally thought (Figure 2), likely representing a seasonal village.  Geoarchaeological investigations demonstrated substantial intact deposits, despite erosion and modern plowing.  Ais Giorkis contains unusual features, such as oval stone platforms (Figures 3, 4).  We retrieved amongst the largest chipped stone and faunal assemblages on the island.  The chipped stone shows technological resemblance to mainland PPNB sites.  The ground stone suggests only limited milling activities, but includes several axes and a complete plaster bowl (Figure 5), very rare in Cyprus.  External trade is suggested by imported obsidian and carnelian.  Cattle are documented, now occurring at three PPNB sites.   This is important, since cattle were not believed to have been in Cyprus until the Bronze Age.  Their presence may have ceremonial as well as economic significance, given the former function on the mainland.  However, in Cyprus they may simply have been "beasts of burden," becoming too "expensive" to maintain.  Other animals include pig, sheep, goat, and deer, all but the latter domesticated.  Deer is the most common animal, indicating the importance of hunting.  An innovative isotopic study indicates that sheep and goat were left to winter in the uplands, rather than being transported to the lowlands.  Some of the domestic fauna also may have become feral.  Botanical remains (Figure 6) include barley and emmer wheat, some of the earliest domesticates in the Near East.  Only two burials were recovered:  an infant and an adult male.      Much of the material cultural hints at feasting activities, perhaps for bringing together upland and lowland groups.  Many lines of evidence also point to the utilization of woodland resources, perhaps even the use of superior timber for refurbishing ships.  Thus, Ais Giorkis' upland location indicates that even during Cyprus' initial colonization, interior regions were being used to exploit several resources.                 The project's broader impacts contribute to both archaeology and wider issues.  For archaeology, the project has considerable significance not only to Cyprus and the Near East, but also sheds light on how islands were colonized on a more global basis.  These Cypriot sites suggest that these early bearers of village life had an efficient seafaring technology allowing for the transport of both people and resources. Cyprus can no longer be regarded as a footnote of the Neolithic Revolution, but rather as an integral part of this tumultuous time.  Beyond its archaeological significance, the project also has contributed to public awareness of archaeology, international research cooperation, and the promotion of early-career women in science (most of the theses/dissertations were by women).  Even more broadly, why these early Neolithic emigrants initially left the mainland cannot yet be answered--perhaps it related to expanding populations and resource scarcity, a situation paralleled by the current migrant situation in the Mediterranean.                 Last Modified: 11/04/2018       Submitted by: Alan H Simmons]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
