<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research/RUI: Testing Hypotheses on Pillow Lava Production During Glaciovolcanic Eruptions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>126905.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>126905</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030107</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Wade</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwade@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924739</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>As recently witnessed during the 2010 Eyjafjallajokull eruption in Iceland, interactions between lava and ice can have devastating local and global implications. However, because these eruptions most frequently occur in remote, hard-to-access places, we do not fully understand many of the processes that can produce glaciovolcanic hazards from rapidly melting ice, such as floods and mudflows. In order to better understand the role of lava flow formation during eruptions within and beneath ice, we propose to study one of the products of subglacial eruptions, called 'pillow lavas'. Although pillow lavas are one of the most common types of lavas on the ocean floor, which covers about 70 percent of Earth's surface, their formation beneath ice is relatively unstudied. We are going to work in two areas with exceptionally well-exposed examples of glaciovolcanic pillow lavas in Iceland and British Columbia, Canada. Our work will help other scientists to better understand how heat is transferred from lava to water and ice during glaciovolcanic eruptions, which may lead to better methods for predicting the sizes of floods resulting from lava-ice interactions. Through our research, we will also have a better understanding of how to use pillow lavas from ancient deposits to unravel mysteries related to ice-age global climate. Finally, we hope that our data will also be useful for better understanding of the formation of the Earth's ocean floors, which may be important for future mineral and energy resources. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The main goals of this research are to use pillow lavas covering a range of basaltic compositions for testing hypotheses about the formation of subglacial pillow mounds, including models for lava transport within a growing pillow-dominated volcano and the potential for sudden transitions between explosive versus effusive eruption styles. Specifically we will address the following questions:&lt;br/&gt;i) Is the initiation of pillow lava emplacement preceded by an explosive phase?&lt;br/&gt;ii) How is lava distributed along and across the ridge structure?&lt;br/&gt;iii) What are effusion rates during subglacial, pillow-dominated eruptions?&lt;br/&gt;iv) Are multiple eruptive centers active along a fissure segment during a single eruptive episode?&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;We will pursue answers to these questions by using modern field and analytical techniques to document the three-dimensional structure, stratigraphy and geochemistry of two different pillow ridges with exceptional exposures: (1) open-pit rock quarries along a single fissure segment on the Reykjanes Peninsula in southwestern Iceland and (2) the crest of Pillow Ridge in northern British Columbia. Both locations have similar lithofacies, including a specific stratigraphic sequence of vitric tuff-breccia cut by dikes that feed pillow lava flows emplaced immediately above the tuff-breccias (TDP lithofacies association). We have established a broad-based research team, comprising US, Icelandic and Canadian scientists working in full collaboration with the PIs, to build a comprehensive database of subglacial pillow characteristics for comparison to pillow lavas produced in other environments and potentially to revise existing models for the construction of the pillow-dominated parts of subglacial volcanoes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1220176</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Meagen</FirstName>
<LastName>Pollock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Meagen Pollock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mpollock@wooster.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3302632133</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000531416</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>College of Wooster</Name>
<CityName>Wooster</CityName>
<ZipCode>446912363</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3302632293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1189 Beall Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076744085</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE COLLEGE OF WOOSTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>076744085</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[College of Wooster]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>446912363</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~49314</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~45699</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~31892</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goal of our project was to increase our understanding of subglacial volcanic eruptions. Our work has broader implications for understanding dangerous and costly glaciovolcanic hazards, such as glacial outburst floods and the widespread distribution of volcanic ash. Our findings also allow us to estimate past ice thickness, which adds important data points to paleoclimate models.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>When a volcano erupts beneath a glacier, the interaction of lava and ice can be explosive (generating glassy, fragmented material) or effusive (generating bulbous pillow lavas). Pillow lavas are the most abundant lava type on Earth, but are difficult to study because they are generally inaccessible, forming deep on the ocean floor or beneath glaciers. Two field sites in southwest Iceland and northern British Columbia, Canada have exposed subglacial pillow lavas as a result of deglaciation. We have studied these exposures to test hypotheses about the formation of subglacial pillow lavas. During the period of the grant, we conducted field work at each of our sites for two field seasons. We collected over 200 samples, measured thousands of pillow lavas, and acquired terabytes of photographs and GPS data.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Overall, we have added to our current understanding of subglacial eruptions by identifying multiple eruptions within a single ridge. We found that effusive eruptive events may be initiated by explosive eruptive activity and that eruption style can alternate during the life of the ridge. Although the current model suggests that eruption style is related to overlying ice thickness, we have discovered a link between eruption style and the underlying magmatic system. Finally, we have found that magma is distributed through a subglacial ridge through elongated, tabular dikes that can transport magma over several kilometers, and through irregular bodies that transport magma more locally.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our analytical work has generated several geochemical datasets that can be used by the entire scientific community. Our photographs and spatial data are being used in two novel ways: (1) we have generated 3-D models that allow us to make measurements of places that are difficult or impossible to safely access, and (2) we are creating on online tour for visitors to the Reykjanes Geopark. We have helped train future geoscientists for the workforce by involving 15 undergraduate students as researchers and incorporating our research into our classes and outreach programs aimed at middle school girls.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2016<br>      Modified by: Meagen&nbsp;Pollock</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1220176/1220176_10190289_1475098755897_PollocketalFig10--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1220176/1220176_10190289_1475098755897_PollocketalFig10--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Development of a Subglacial Pillow Ridge"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1220176/1220176_10190289_1475098755897_PollocketalFig10--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Development of a Subglacial Pillow Ridge"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Illustration of the interpreted eruptive events at Undirhlíðar in southwest Iceland. Eruption style alternates between explosive and effusive. Dikes and intrusions transport magma within the growing volcanic edifice.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Pollock et al., 2014, http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.lithos.2014.04.023</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Meagen&nbsp;Pollock</div> <div class="imageTitle">Development of a Subglacial Pillow Ridge</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1220176/1220176_10190289_1475099380646_PillowLava--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1220176/1220176_10190289_1475099380646_PillowLava--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pillow Lava"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1220176/1220176_10190289_1475099380646_PillowLava--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Pillow Lava"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">End-view of a rounded pillow lava, surrounded by orange, weathered, glassy material.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Benjamin R. Edwards</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Meagen&nbsp;Pollock</div> <div class="imageTitle">Pillow Lava</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goal of our project was to increase our understanding of subglacial volcanic eruptions. Our work has broader implications for understanding dangerous and costly glaciovolcanic hazards, such as glacial outburst floods and the widespread distribution of volcanic ash. Our findings also allow us to estimate past ice thickness, which adds important data points to paleoclimate models.     When a volcano erupts beneath a glacier, the interaction of lava and ice can be explosive (generating glassy, fragmented material) or effusive (generating bulbous pillow lavas). Pillow lavas are the most abundant lava type on Earth, but are difficult to study because they are generally inaccessible, forming deep on the ocean floor or beneath glaciers. Two field sites in southwest Iceland and northern British Columbia, Canada have exposed subglacial pillow lavas as a result of deglaciation. We have studied these exposures to test hypotheses about the formation of subglacial pillow lavas. During the period of the grant, we conducted field work at each of our sites for two field seasons. We collected over 200 samples, measured thousands of pillow lavas, and acquired terabytes of photographs and GPS data.     Overall, we have added to our current understanding of subglacial eruptions by identifying multiple eruptions within a single ridge. We found that effusive eruptive events may be initiated by explosive eruptive activity and that eruption style can alternate during the life of the ridge. Although the current model suggests that eruption style is related to overlying ice thickness, we have discovered a link between eruption style and the underlying magmatic system. Finally, we have found that magma is distributed through a subglacial ridge through elongated, tabular dikes that can transport magma over several kilometers, and through irregular bodies that transport magma more locally.     Our analytical work has generated several geochemical datasets that can be used by the entire scientific community. Our photographs and spatial data are being used in two novel ways: (1) we have generated 3-D models that allow us to make measurements of places that are difficult or impossible to safely access, and (2) we are creating on online tour for visitors to the Reykjanes Geopark. We have helped train future geoscientists for the workforce by involving 15 undergraduate students as researchers and incorporating our research into our classes and outreach programs aimed at middle school girls.          Last Modified: 09/28/2016       Submitted by: Meagen Pollock]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
