<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Lake Pátzcuaro Archaeological Project: Urbanism at Angamuco During The Postclassic Period</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>192417.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>192417</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cities form the core of modern society and a deeper understanding of the evolution of the urban form can potentially help to understand the modern world. One place that can make an important archaeological contribution to this debate is the Lake Pátzcuaro Basin, Michoacán, Mexico (LPB), which at the time of European contact was the core of the Late Postclassic (LPC) (A.D. 1350-1520) Purépecha Empire. This National Science Foundation award will fund a program of excavation at the newly discovered city of Angamuco to test models for the development of complex societies in the region. This project develops from over 3 years of NSF sponsored full-coverage survey (2009-2011) as part of the Legacies of Resilience: The Lake Pátzcauro Basin Archaeological Project (LORE-LPB). To test the models developed from this work researchers will excavate architectural complexes within two neighborhoods that, based on surface remains, had unique time and social associations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Efforts will be focused on addressing three questions concerning the Angamuco occupation. 1) When was the predominate occupation of Angamuco and how does it relate to the development of complex societies in the region?  2) Can initial survey results concerning the function of individual structures and the spatial arrangement of these buildings be confirmed?  Do domestic, public, storage, and ceremonial functions that inferred from surface remains conform with excavation data?  3) Can social differentiation be identified through excavation?  If so, how does it evolve through time and how is this related to Empire formation.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Testing models that have been developed during the survey of Angamuco will substantially expand and deepen them and pave the way for future research. Results from this work will provide radiocarbon determinations that can help outline the timing, intensity, and location of the Angamuco occupation during the Postclassic.  Stratigraphically dated assemblages from the Postclassic period will allow the creation of a more accurate ceramic chronology for this critical time interval.  The refined temporal control will allow more accurately determination of the impact of Empire formation on the Angamuco polity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Angamuco case study can potentially yield important new insights into the development of complex societies in western Mexico, and in the process make an important contribution to anthropological understanding of the urban process.  This is far from a simple academic debate in that global environmental change is increasingly placing urban dwellers at risk of increased poverty, displacement, and health risk.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1220016</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Fisher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher T Fisher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ctfisher@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704911866</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000387195</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/30/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Leisz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen Leisz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>steve.leisz@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704913960</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000518457</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/30/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>785979618</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>948905492</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805214593</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 W. Lake St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>Archaeology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~192417</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">Cities form the core of modern society and a deeper understanding of the evolution of the urban form can potentially help us organize our modern world. One place that can make an important archaeological contribution to this debate is the newly discovered ancient city of Angamuco located within the Lake P&aacute;tzcuaro Basin, Michoac&aacute;n, Mexico (LPB), which at the time of European contact was the core of the Late Postclassic (LPC) (A.D. 1350-1520) Pur&eacute;pecha Empire.</p> <p class="Default">Cities were an important component of Pur&eacute;pecha statecraft but comparatively little is known about their general characteristics, organization, and evolution. The Legacies of Resilience: The Lake P&aacute;tzcauro Basin Archaeological Project (LORE-LPB) is a long-term effort to better understand the development of complex societies in the P&aacute;tzcuaro region. This NSF award funds two seasons of excavation (2013-2014) of excavation and associated laboratory analysis of artifacts recovered.&nbsp;</p> <p>To better understand the Angamuco occupation we chose to excavate in eight major contexts at the ancient City. This work encompassed two major seasons of excavation and several associated laboratory sessions. Contexts chosen included a large public building (Casa 5128), a cemetery, a potential palace, and several zones of commoner occupation.</p> <p>Individual excavation seasons included 2013 though which we excavated Casa 5128 &ndash; a large public building that dominates a major complex of architecture at the site &ndash; and several rooms in a palace location. During a second season in 2014 we encountered a large cemetery and recovered over 61 intact individuals. In addition we excavated at 5 other distinct locations at the settlement. Subsequent seasons of work included the laboratory analysis of artifacts, dating of carbon and other materials, and the long-term curation of the collections recovered. Analysis of these materials is on-going.</p> <p>The Angamuco case study has yeilded important insights into the development of complex societies in western Mexico, and in the process has made an important contribution to anthropological understanding of the urban process. This is far from a simple academic debate in that global environmental change is increasingly placing urban dwellers at risk of increased poverty, displacement, and health risk.&nbsp; In this sense archaeology can make an important and unique contribution to modern solutions.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/08/2017<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;T&nbsp;Fisher</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1220016/1220016_10176891_1499544392357_altar-1-excavation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1220016/1220016_10176891_1499544392357_altar-1-excavation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Excavation, Angamuco, Michoacan Mexico"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1220016/1220016_10176891_1499544392357_altar-1-excavation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Excavation, Angamuco, Michoacan Mexico"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Excavation in front of a large altar at the Angamuco cemetery, Michoacan, Mexico</div> <div class="imageCredit">Chris Fisher</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;T&nbsp;Fisher</div> <div class="imageTitle">Excavation, Angamuco, Michoacan Mexico</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1220016/1220016_10176891_1499544474809_overview4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1220016/1220016_10176891_1499544474809_overview4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Excavation, Angamuco, Michoacan Mexico"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1220016/1220016_10176891_1499544474809_overview4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Excavation, Angamuco, Michoacan Mexico"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Excavation in front of the large pyramid at Angamuco, Michoacan, Mexico</div> <div class="imageCredit">Chris Fisher</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;T&nbsp;Fisher</div> <div class="imageTitle">Excavation, Angamuco, Michoacan Mexico</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Cities form the core of modern society and a deeper understanding of the evolution of the urban form can potentially help us organize our modern world. One place that can make an important archaeological contribution to this debate is the newly discovered ancient city of Angamuco located within the Lake P&aacute;tzcuaro Basin, Michoac&aacute;n, Mexico (LPB), which at the time of European contact was the core of the Late Postclassic (LPC) (A.D. 1350-1520) Pur&eacute;pecha Empire. Cities were an important component of Pur&eacute;pecha statecraft but comparatively little is known about their general characteristics, organization, and evolution. The Legacies of Resilience: The Lake P&aacute;tzcauro Basin Archaeological Project (LORE-LPB) is a long-term effort to better understand the development of complex societies in the P&aacute;tzcuaro region. This NSF award funds two seasons of excavation (2013-2014) of excavation and associated laboratory analysis of artifacts recovered.   To better understand the Angamuco occupation we chose to excavate in eight major contexts at the ancient City. This work encompassed two major seasons of excavation and several associated laboratory sessions. Contexts chosen included a large public building (Casa 5128), a cemetery, a potential palace, and several zones of commoner occupation.  Individual excavation seasons included 2013 though which we excavated Casa 5128 &ndash; a large public building that dominates a major complex of architecture at the site &ndash; and several rooms in a palace location. During a second season in 2014 we encountered a large cemetery and recovered over 61 intact individuals. In addition we excavated at 5 other distinct locations at the settlement. Subsequent seasons of work included the laboratory analysis of artifacts, dating of carbon and other materials, and the long-term curation of the collections recovered. Analysis of these materials is on-going.  The Angamuco case study has yeilded important insights into the development of complex societies in western Mexico, and in the process has made an important contribution to anthropological understanding of the urban process. This is far from a simple academic debate in that global environmental change is increasingly placing urban dwellers at risk of increased poverty, displacement, and health risk.  In this sense archaeology can make an important and unique contribution to modern solutions.       Last Modified: 07/08/2017       Submitted by: Christopher T Fisher]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
