<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Ocean Acidification - Effects of ocean acidification on Emiliania huxleyi and Calanus finmarchicus; insights into the oceanic alkalinity and biological carbon pumps</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>999956.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>999956</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Garrison</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Ocean acidification is one of the most pressing marine science issues of our time, with potential biological impacts spanning all marine phyla and potential societal impacts affecting man's relationship to the sea. Rising levels of atmospheric pCO2 are increasing the acidity of the world oceans. It is generally held that average surface ocean pH has already declined by 0.1 pH units relative to the pre-industrial level (Orr et al., 2005), and is projected to decrease 0.3 to 0.46 units by the end of this century, depending on CO2 emission scenarios (Caldeira and Wickett, 2005). The overall goal of this research is to parameterize how changes in pCO2 levels could alter the biological and alkalinity pumps of the world ocean. Specifically, the direct and indirect effects of ocean acidification will be examined within a simple, controlled predator/prey system containing a single prey phytoplankton species (the coccolithophore, Emiliania huxleyi) and a single predator (the oceanic metazoan grazer, Calanus finmarchicus). The experiments are designed to elucidate both direct effects (i.e. effects of ocean acidification on the individual organisms only) and interactive effects (i.e. effects on the combined predator/prey system). Interactive experiments with phytoplankton prey and zooplankton predator are a critical starting point for predicting the overall impact of ocean acidification in marine ecosystems. To meet these goals, a state-of-the-art facility will be constructed with growth chambers that are calibrated and have highly-controlled pH and alkalinity levels. The strength of this approach lies in meticulous calibration and redundant measurements that will be made to ensure that conditions within the chambers are well described and tightly monitored for DIC levels. Growth and calcification rates in coccolithophores and the developmental rates, morphological and behavioral effects on copepods will be measured. The PIC and POC in the algae and the excreted fecal pellets will be monitored for changes in the PIC/POC ratio, a key parameter for modeling feedback mechanisms for rising pCO2 levels. In addition, 14C experiments are planned to measure calcification rates in coccolithophores and dissolution rates as a result of grazing. These key experiments will verify closure in the mass balance of PIC, allowing the determination of actual&lt;br/&gt;dissolution rates of PIC within the guts of copepod grazers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team of scientists in this work contributes expertise in coccolithophore ecology, biogeography and physiology (Balch) and copepod ecology and physiology (Fields). They will be joined by a post-doctoral fellow and a highly capable technical staff to provide the necessary support to cultivate and monitor cultures during experiments. Six supervised undergraduate students will have projects associated with this work. Expertise in carbonate chemistry will be provided by Dr. N. Bates (consultant, see letter of support).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact. Along with the numerous scientific and societal broader impacts of ocean acidification, there are also significant educational impacts associated with this work. This project has numerous self-contained sub-projects that will provide exceptional opportunities for motivated undergraduate students to receive hands-on research experience, learning sophisticated culturing techniques, the fundamentals of optics and micro-videography. Six supervised undergraduate students will have projects associated with this work. Students will be required to meet weekly and to give a Bigelow seminar on their respective projects. Participation at national meetings will be encouraged and supported. Balch and Fields have had great success with undergraduate students in the past with several receiving authorship on publications that incorporated their work. They will also invite several high school students into the lab to assist with basic aspects of the project. Fields is involved in the COSEE program (designed to bring ocean science to rural areas) and the "Keller Bloom" project, which provides a week-long science immersion course to gifted high school students from rural Maine. Results of the project will also contribute to the development of other BLOS educational and outreach programs, most notably weekly summer seminar series open to the public, the summer REU program and a new Colby College semester program at Bigelow Laboratory. Funds from this proposal will be used to build a state-of- the-art facility for creating, maintaining and monitoring pCO2 concentrations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1220068</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Balch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William M Balch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bbalch@bigelow.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2073152567</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000090512</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Fields</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David M Fields</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dfields@bigelow.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2073152567</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000347520</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bigelow Laboratory for Ocean Sciences</Name>
<CityName>East Boothbay</CityName>
<ZipCode>045440380</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2073152567</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>60 Bigelow Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ME01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077474757</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BIGELOW LABORATORY FOR OCEAN SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bigelow Laboratory for Ocean Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>West Boothbay Harbor</CityName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<ZipCode>045750475</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[180 McKown Point Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ME01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8001</Code>
<Text>CRI-Ocean Acidification</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1382</Code>
<Text>OCEAN ACIDIFICATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~999956</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Ocean acidification is one of the most pressing marine science issues of our time, with potential biological impacts spanning all marine phyla. Rising levels of atmospheric <em>p</em>CO2 are increasing the acidity of the world oceans. It is generally held that average surface ocean pH has already declined by ~0.1 pH units relative to the pre-industrial level (Orr et al., 2005; translating to a ~26% increase in acidity), and is projected to decrease 0.3 to 0.46 units by the end of this century, depending on CO<sub>2</sub> emission scenarios (Caldeira and Wickett, 2005; translating to a doubling to near-tripling of the acidity of sea water).&nbsp; The effects of such a change could be profound.&nbsp; The overall goal of this work was to parameterize how changes in CO<sub>2</sub> concentration could alter the biological and alkalinity pumps of the world ocean (how CO2 gets fixed and transported to the deep sea as sinking particulate matter as well as dissolved inorganic carbon species). Specifically, the direct and indirect effects of ocean acidification were examined within a simple, controlled predator/prey system containing a single prey phytoplankton species (coccolithophores) and a single predator (mesopelagic ocean grazers).&nbsp; Experiments were designed to elucidate both direct effects (i.e. effects of ocean acidification on only the individual organisms) and interactive effects (i.e. effects on the combined predator/prey system).&nbsp; Interactive experiments with phytoplankton prey and zooplankton predator were a critical starting point for predicting the overall impact of ocean acidification in marine ecosystems.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To meet these goals we designed and constructed a state-of-the-art facility with algal and copepod growth chambers and highly-controlled pH and alkalinity levels to ensure that conditions within the chambers were well described and tightly monitored for dissolved inorganic carbon levels. We measured growth and calcification rates in two species of coccolithophores (calcifying algae thought to be susceptible to ocean acidification) &nbsp;and the developmental rates, morphological and behavioral effects on three species of copepods.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp; Our results demonstrated that counter to our expectations, for the estuarine coccolithophore, <em>Pleurochrysis</em> <em>carterae</em>, increased CO<sub>2</sub> concentration had no significant impact on its growth rate or photosynthetic rate.&nbsp; Moreover, <em>P. carterae</em> calcification rates significantly increased in elevated <em>p</em>CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations of 750 ppm.&nbsp; This trend of increased calcification at higher <em>p</em>CO<sub>2</sub> conditions fits into a recently developed model, which demonstrates that coccolithophores have a calcification optima.&nbsp; Our evidence also indicated differing biological control on the water chemistry by two species of coccolithophores, <em>P. carterae</em> and <em>Emiliania huxleyi,</em> when at high cell densities.&nbsp; That is, photosynthesis of <em>P. carterae</em> tends to drive the pH up, while the calcification of <em>E. huxleyi</em> drives the pH down at high cell densities.&nbsp; Models to accurately predict future pH in a high CO<sub>2</sub> world need to factor in this diversity of response.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; For the 3 species of copepods tested, there was no significant effect of <em>p</em>CO2 on development times, lipid accumulation, feeding rate, or metabolic rate. Small but significant treatment effects were found in body length and mass (in terms of dry, carbon and nitrogen mass), notably a somewhat larger body size at the mid-pCO<sub>2</sub> treatment; that is, a putatively beneficial effect. Based on these results, and a review of other studies of <em>Calanus</em> spp, we conclude that the present parameterizations of vital rates in models of copepods population dynamics, used to generate scenarios of abundance and distribution of this species under future conditions, do not require an &ldquo;ocean acidification effect&rdquo; adjustment.</p> <p><strong>Research Team</strong>. The team of scientists in this work comprised expertise in coccolithophore ecology, biogeography and physiology (Balch) and copepod ecology and physiology (Fields). The project also had a post-doctoral fellow (White) and a highly capable technical staff to provide the necessary support to cultivate and monitor cultures during experiments. Eleven supervised undergraduate students had projects associated with this work.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default"><strong>Broader Impact. </strong>Our finding have been disseminated through five primary mechanisms: (a) 13 peer-reviewed publications published plus one legislative document for the state of Maine on the effects of ocean acidification on Maine&rsquo;s marine economy, (b) 17 presentations were made at national and international scientific conferences, (c) student projects (11 undergraduate students+ 2 MS students) (d) public outreach (Bigelow Open House, Other public venues &ndash; &gt;1000 &nbsp;people were exposed to information about ocean acidification), and (e)involvement with policy stakeholders (NERACOOS, NECAN, Maine OA Commission). Data are publically available from the Biological and Chemical Oceanography Data Management Office (<em>BCO</em>-<em>DMO</em>) at http://www.bco-dmo.org/project/514415.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/17/2017<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;M&nbsp;Balch</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      Ocean acidification is one of the most pressing marine science issues of our time, with potential biological impacts spanning all marine phyla. Rising levels of atmospheric pCO2 are increasing the acidity of the world oceans. It is generally held that average surface ocean pH has already declined by ~0.1 pH units relative to the pre-industrial level (Orr et al., 2005; translating to a ~26% increase in acidity), and is projected to decrease 0.3 to 0.46 units by the end of this century, depending on CO2 emission scenarios (Caldeira and Wickett, 2005; translating to a doubling to near-tripling of the acidity of sea water).  The effects of such a change could be profound.  The overall goal of this work was to parameterize how changes in CO2 concentration could alter the biological and alkalinity pumps of the world ocean (how CO2 gets fixed and transported to the deep sea as sinking particulate matter as well as dissolved inorganic carbon species). Specifically, the direct and indirect effects of ocean acidification were examined within a simple, controlled predator/prey system containing a single prey phytoplankton species (coccolithophores) and a single predator (mesopelagic ocean grazers).  Experiments were designed to elucidate both direct effects (i.e. effects of ocean acidification on only the individual organisms) and interactive effects (i.e. effects on the combined predator/prey system).  Interactive experiments with phytoplankton prey and zooplankton predator were a critical starting point for predicting the overall impact of ocean acidification in marine ecosystems.        To meet these goals we designed and constructed a state-of-the-art facility with algal and copepod growth chambers and highly-controlled pH and alkalinity levels to ensure that conditions within the chambers were well described and tightly monitored for dissolved inorganic carbon levels. We measured growth and calcification rates in two species of coccolithophores (calcifying algae thought to be susceptible to ocean acidification)  and the developmental rates, morphological and behavioral effects on three species of copepods.        Our results demonstrated that counter to our expectations, for the estuarine coccolithophore, Pleurochrysis carterae, increased CO2 concentration had no significant impact on its growth rate or photosynthetic rate.  Moreover, P. carterae calcification rates significantly increased in elevated pCO2 concentrations of 750 ppm.  This trend of increased calcification at higher pCO2 conditions fits into a recently developed model, which demonstrates that coccolithophores have a calcification optima.  Our evidence also indicated differing biological control on the water chemistry by two species of coccolithophores, P. carterae and Emiliania huxleyi, when at high cell densities.  That is, photosynthesis of P. carterae tends to drive the pH up, while the calcification of E. huxleyi drives the pH down at high cell densities.  Models to accurately predict future pH in a high CO2 world need to factor in this diversity of response.       For the 3 species of copepods tested, there was no significant effect of pCO2 on development times, lipid accumulation, feeding rate, or metabolic rate. Small but significant treatment effects were found in body length and mass (in terms of dry, carbon and nitrogen mass), notably a somewhat larger body size at the mid-pCO2 treatment; that is, a putatively beneficial effect. Based on these results, and a review of other studies of Calanus spp, we conclude that the present parameterizations of vital rates in models of copepods population dynamics, used to generate scenarios of abundance and distribution of this species under future conditions, do not require an "ocean acidification effect" adjustment.  Research Team. The team of scientists in this work comprised expertise in coccolithophore ecology, biogeography and physiology (Balch) and copepod ecology and physiology (Fields). The project also had a post-doctoral fellow (White) and a highly capable technical staff to provide the necessary support to cultivate and monitor cultures during experiments. Eleven supervised undergraduate students had projects associated with this work.  Broader Impact. Our finding have been disseminated through five primary mechanisms: (a) 13 peer-reviewed publications published plus one legislative document for the state of Maine on the effects of ocean acidification on Maine?s marine economy, (b) 17 presentations were made at national and international scientific conferences, (c) student projects (11 undergraduate students+ 2 MS students) (d) public outreach (Bigelow Open House, Other public venues &ndash; &gt;1000  people were exposed to information about ocean acidification), and (e)involvement with policy stakeholders (NERACOOS, NECAN, Maine OA Commission). Data are publically available from the Biological and Chemical Oceanography Data Management Office (BCO-DMO) at http://www.bco-dmo.org/project/514415.       Last Modified: 11/17/2017       Submitted by: William M Balch]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
