<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Exploring the Efficacy of Engineering is Elementary (E4)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2999827.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2999827</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Catherine L. Eberbach</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ceberbac@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924960</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is developing evidence about the efficacy of the Engineering is Elementary curriculum under ideal conditions by studying the student and teacher-level effects of implementation. The rigorous level of evidence that is developed in this study has significant utility as a support for the kinds of elementary engineering curricula that are needed as the Next Generation Science Standards come online and emphasize engineering design. The study is a randomized control trial where the assignment of teachers will be to the EiE curricular materials or to a counterfactual condition, the use of more standard design engineering curricular materials. The project studies the impact of the use of the curriculum on student learning and on teachers' use of the curriculum in a fidelity of implementation study to determine the core elements of the curriculum that support successful use. The study examines the implementation of the curricular materials in a number of contexts to more fully understand the conditions under which they work best and to explicate what aspects of such project-based inquiry materials most support student learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study uses a randomized cluster trial to examine the efficacy of the EiE curriculum across 75 schools in the treatment and 75 schools in the control group samples. Two teachers per school are included in one treatment/control condition per school. Outcome measures for students include performances on project-specific measures that have been examined for technical quality of validity and reliability. A set of additional research-based survey instruments validated for use in the EiE context are also used to collect data about students' attitudes, perceptions, interest and motivation toward science and engineering. A robust fidelity of implementation research plan is being implemented that will include teachers surveys, pre and post assessments, teacher logs,  as well as student engineering journals and student work from classroom implementation. The fidelity of implementation is further studied with forty treatment and ten control teachers through classroom observations and interviews.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The findings from this study have broad implications for how engineering design curricular can be developed and implemented at the elementary level. Engineering design has not been emphasized in the elementary classroom, lagging behind instruction in science with which teachers are more familiar. The results of this study inform practitioners and policy makers about what works, for whom and under what conditions. Information about the different contexts in which the curriculum has been implemented supports the dissemination of evidence-based research and development practices to strengthen STEM learning for all students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1220305</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Carlsen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William S Carlsen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wcarlsen@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148655664</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000148086</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
<LastName>Cunningham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christine M Cunningham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ccunningham@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148650861</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000312559</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pamela</FirstName>
<LastName>Lottero-Perdue</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pamela Lottero-Perdue</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>plotteroperdue@towson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4107042236</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000545063</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cathy</FirstName>
<LastName>Lachapelle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cathy P Lachapelle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cathy@stemedinsights.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5083951810</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000584208</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Parry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth A Parry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>liz@stemedinsights.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9194137313</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000678288</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Museum of Science</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>021141099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175890118</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 Science Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076606334</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MUSEUM OF SCIENCE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>076606334</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Museum of Science, Boston]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021141099</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Science Park]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1726155</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~694214</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~579458</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Exploring the Efficacy of Engineering is Elementary (E4) is a research study that examined whether and how students benefit from a set of critical components for engineering curriculum design. These components are fundamental to the award-winning elementary engineering curriculum, Engineering is Elementary (EiE). They include that the curricular materials:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>start with a story to help students understand how and why people solve problems using engineering; </li> <li>help students to talk about and use the engineering design process; </li> <li>challenge students&nbsp; to solve a problem while attending to important criteria and constraints; </li> <li>encourage students to use math and science to solve their engineering challenge; </li> <li>require students to test their solutions, figure out how to make them better, and improve them; </li> <li>feature design challenges that can be solved in many different ways; and </li> <li>have teacher guides with tools and hints that help teachers model good engineering for their students. </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To investigate the impact of these components on student outcomes, the E4 study compared the outcomes of students who used curricular units with these critical components (EiE) to a group of students who used a control curriculum. The control curriculum taught the same engineering content for the same amount of time but that did not include the critical components. Our study worked with more than 300 teachers at 150 schools who taught students in grades 3-5. All teachers participated in engineering professional development, and were given all the materials they needed to implement their assigned curriculum.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Over two years, we collected assessments and surveys from all teachers as well as 14,015 students. We used statistical methods to analyze the data and found that:</p> <ul> <li>EiE students learned more science and engineering than students using the control curriculum. </li> <li>Classes in which the teacher had students complete their engineering journal more carefully and thoughtfully did better in science and engineering.</li> <li>Students who completed more of their engineering journal performed better on assessments.</li> <li>Girls improved more than boys on the engineering assessment.</li> <li>EiE students became more positive about girls&rsquo; ability to do engineering compared to boys.</li> <li>Hispanic students, and those who speak a language other than English at home, did as well as other students on the science and engineering assessments.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We also collected video from 24 classrooms participating in the study, so we could observe what teachers and students were doing during engineering, and how they were learning. Our findings from the observation and video analysis include:</p> <ul> <li>Teachers hold students accountable for quality engineering work at an age-appropriate level by modeling how to do good engineering work, and by asking thought-provoking questions.</li> <li>Students and teachers manage engineering failure in different ways&mdash;and some ways are more productive, and lead to more learning and improvement, than others.</li> <li>Student engineering journals scaffold student engineering learning by focusing students&rsquo; attention, writing, and communication on engineering principles. </li> <li>Teachers support students&rsquo; identity and affiliation with engineering through engagement in engineering design processes and metadiscourse about participation.</li> <li>Engineering design provides unique ways to include epistemic tools to support collaborative scientific sense-making, inquiry processes, and reasoning with evidence. </li> <li>Carefully constructed engineering activities can provide opportunities for students to use science concepts as they solve engineering design problems. </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The results of the E4 study provide evidence that the design features in engineering curricula impact student outcomes related to science, engineering, and attitudes. Districts and schools might consider whether their teachers are implementing engineering lessons that ask students to use science in their engineering activities and that engage students in engineering practices. The research found that <em>all </em>students did better with curricula that included the critical components (EiE); students who were female, Hispanic, and/or who spoke a language other than English at home performed as well as other students. The E4 research team has disseminated its evidence-based findings through articles in practitioner and research journals, through presentations at a number of practitioner and research based conferences, and with a book that supports elementary educators who might be interested in implementing engineering with their students: <em>Engineering in Elementary STEM Education: Curriculum Design, Instruction, Learning, and Assessment</em>. E4 has also developed new assessments that teachers and researchers can use to examine student learning, interests, and attitudes in engineering.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/21/2018<br>      Modified by: Christine&nbsp;M&nbsp;Cunningham</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542732597393_CleaninganOilSpill_90--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542732597393_CleaninganOilSpill_90--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Environmental Engineering"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542732597393_CleaninganOilSpill_90--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Environmental Engineering"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students test a process they designed to clean up an oil spill in the water along a rocky shore.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Christopher San Antonio</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cathy&nbsp;P&nbsp;Lachapelle</div> <div class="imageTitle">Environmental Engineering</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542730008093_IMG_2337--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542730008093_IMG_2337--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Civil Engineering"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542730008093_IMG_2337--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Civil Engineering"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students work together to design a bridge that toy cars can cross--and that a toy boat can pass under.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Christopher San Antonio</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cathy&nbsp;P&nbsp;Lachapelle</div> <div class="imageTitle">Civil Engineering</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542732242660_Coresample--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542732242660_Coresample--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Geotechnical Engineering"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542732242660_Coresample--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Geotechnical Engineering"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students take a core sample as they learn about how the foundations of skyscrapers interact with layers of the Earth.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Engineering is Elementary</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cathy&nbsp;P&nbsp;Lachapelle</div> <div class="imageTitle">Geotechnical Engineering</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542732349147_Plantpackages--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542732349147_Plantpackages--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Package Engineering"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542732349147_Plantpackages--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Package Engineering"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students design a package to contain and protect a plant--keeping it alive and healthy on a shelf for at least 2 days.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Engineering is Elementary</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cathy&nbsp;P&nbsp;Lachapelle</div> <div class="imageTitle">Package Engineering</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542732477978_Teacherworkshop--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542732477978_Teacherworkshop--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Teachers Learn EiE"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542732477978_Teacherworkshop--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Teachers Learn EiE"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Teachers participate in a hands-on professional development workshop to practice and learn to implement Engineering is Elementary units.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Christopher San Antonio</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cathy&nbsp;P&nbsp;Lachapelle</div> <div class="imageTitle">Teachers Learn EiE</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542729787331_AH0A0229-1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542729787331_AH0A0229-1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Electrical Engineering"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1220305/1220305_10211898_1542729787331_AH0A0229-1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Electrical Engineering"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students work together to build and test an alarm circuit that another team of students designed.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Christopher San Antonio</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cathy&nbsp;P&nbsp;Lachapelle</div> <div class="imageTitle">Electrical Engineering</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Exploring the Efficacy of Engineering is Elementary (E4) is a research study that examined whether and how students benefit from a set of critical components for engineering curriculum design. These components are fundamental to the award-winning elementary engineering curriculum, Engineering is Elementary (EiE). They include that the curricular materials:     start with a story to help students understand how and why people solve problems using engineering;  help students to talk about and use the engineering design process;  challenge students  to solve a problem while attending to important criteria and constraints;  encourage students to use math and science to solve their engineering challenge;  require students to test their solutions, figure out how to make them better, and improve them;  feature design challenges that can be solved in many different ways; and  have teacher guides with tools and hints that help teachers model good engineering for their students.       To investigate the impact of these components on student outcomes, the E4 study compared the outcomes of students who used curricular units with these critical components (EiE) to a group of students who used a control curriculum. The control curriculum taught the same engineering content for the same amount of time but that did not include the critical components. Our study worked with more than 300 teachers at 150 schools who taught students in grades 3-5. All teachers participated in engineering professional development, and were given all the materials they needed to implement their assigned curriculum.     Over two years, we collected assessments and surveys from all teachers as well as 14,015 students. We used statistical methods to analyze the data and found that:  EiE students learned more science and engineering than students using the control curriculum.  Classes in which the teacher had students complete their engineering journal more carefully and thoughtfully did better in science and engineering. Students who completed more of their engineering journal performed better on assessments. Girls improved more than boys on the engineering assessment. EiE students became more positive about girls? ability to do engineering compared to boys. Hispanic students, and those who speak a language other than English at home, did as well as other students on the science and engineering assessments.      We also collected video from 24 classrooms participating in the study, so we could observe what teachers and students were doing during engineering, and how they were learning. Our findings from the observation and video analysis include:  Teachers hold students accountable for quality engineering work at an age-appropriate level by modeling how to do good engineering work, and by asking thought-provoking questions. Students and teachers manage engineering failure in different ways&mdash;and some ways are more productive, and lead to more learning and improvement, than others. Student engineering journals scaffold student engineering learning by focusing students? attention, writing, and communication on engineering principles.  Teachers support students? identity and affiliation with engineering through engagement in engineering design processes and metadiscourse about participation. Engineering design provides unique ways to include epistemic tools to support collaborative scientific sense-making, inquiry processes, and reasoning with evidence.  Carefully constructed engineering activities can provide opportunities for students to use science concepts as they solve engineering design problems.       The results of the E4 study provide evidence that the design features in engineering curricula impact student outcomes related to science, engineering, and attitudes. Districts and schools might consider whether their teachers are implementing engineering lessons that ask students to use science in their engineering activities and that engage students in engineering practices. The research found that all students did better with curricula that included the critical components (EiE); students who were female, Hispanic, and/or who spoke a language other than English at home performed as well as other students. The E4 research team has disseminated its evidence-based findings through articles in practitioner and research journals, through presentations at a number of practitioner and research based conferences, and with a book that supports elementary educators who might be interested in implementing engineering with their students: Engineering in Elementary STEM Education: Curriculum Design, Instruction, Learning, and Assessment. E4 has also developed new assessments that teachers and researchers can use to examine student learning, interests, and attitudes in engineering.                Last Modified: 11/21/2018       Submitted by: Christine M Cunningham]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
