<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Efficacy of Informal Science Education (ISE) Practices to Develop Hispanic Citizen Scientists in the Watershed of the Rio Grande of Manati, Puerto Rico</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1637345.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1637345</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ellen McCallie</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emccalli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925115</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Conservation Trust of Puerto Rico is creating citizen science projects in five research areas (insect monitoring; coastal/river system management; bird communities; bat assemblages; and cultural resources) that allow 140 Hispanic residents of Puerto Rico (age 14 and older) to move along a continuum of research involvement from contributor to collaborator to co-creator. As citizen scientists engage in scientific research that measures the effects of urban development on the Manati River watershed in northern Puerto Rico, the project team is evaluating the degree to which participants show changes in science knowledge, skills, attitudes, communication, and behavior.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project is accelerating the development of citizen science activities in Puerto Rico. New scientific knowledge generated by citizen scientists will have practical importance within and beyond the Manati watershed because Puerto Rico is undergoing rapid urban development, resulting in the loss of biodiversity and emergence of environmental problems such as lower water quality. Environmental data collected by citizen scientists will form an environmental database that permits long-term watershed monitoring and informs land use decision making.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1223882</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lee</FirstName>
<LastName>Rodriguez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lee A Rodriguez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rodriguezl@fideicomiso.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7877225834</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000507629</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/25/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yogani</FirstName>
<LastName>Govender</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yogani Govender</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ygovender@metro.inter.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7872501912</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000596845</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/25/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The Conservation Trust of Puerto Rico</Name>
<CityName>San Juan</CityName>
<ZipCode>009023554</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7877225834</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Tetuan Street 155</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>131440901</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PUERTO RICO CONSERVATION TRUST FUND</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Conservation Trust of Puerto Rico]]></Name>
<CityName>Manati</CityName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>006740074</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Carr. 616 (final) Km 6.5]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~574052</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~466272</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~597021</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project evaluated the effectiveness of an Informal Science Education (ISE) Model designed to engage citizens in STEM research to generate a change in knowledge, skills, and behavior of participants. The formative evaluation indicates that the project has a successful framework to attract the public and engage large numbers of citizens in STEM investigations. Coordinated project planning, design, implementation, appropriate communication strategies and evaluation approaches that adapted and evolved through a cyclic learning process allowed the three levels of citizen science engagement (contributor, collaborator and co-creator) for the collection, analysis and dissemination of scientific data.</p> <p>A total of 1,389 citizens participated in 755 activities for data collection and analysis of new scientific information related to the r&iacute;o Grande de Manat&iacute; Watershed. The development of 12 community-based citizen projects allowed 18 participants at collaborator and co-creator levels of engagement in science to analyze and disseminate information about their community projects at local, national and international forums, some receiving awards and were invited to submit manuscripts on their work. Types of co-creator projects developed in the communities reflects the varied in age, education, interest and motivation to participate of the participants. Projects developed through bottom-up processes include the use of shrimp and crabs to determine water quality; the understanding the value of bats to the ecosystem; understanding the importance of state forests as bird habitats; evaluation and assessment tourism and climate change on beach processes. As co-creators increased their engagement in citizen science projects, they gained knowledge and skills increasing their confidence in disseminating projects results. Various formats were used to disseminate information about this ISE project including exhibit booths (7), television (4), radio (8), poster session (18), peer review manuscripts (5), digital media (25), videos (10), tool kits (6), how to kits (3), findings (4) and oral and poster presentations at conferences (27). Integration appropriate media and dissemination strategies engaged participants beyond the research activities, an estimated 170,187 users visited the project webpage <a href="http://www.ciudadanocientifico.org">www.ciudadanocientifico.org</a>, while 2,873 likes were obtained on the Facebook page https://www.facebook.com/Ciudadano-Cient&iacute;fico-Para-La-Naturaleza.</p> <p>Multiple techniques and evaluation instruments were used and triangulated to evaluate the gain in knowledge and skills of participants at the three levels of engagement. Majority (75%, n=390) of participants had little to no prior knowledge or skills of the research themes they engaged in. Majority (&gt; 75%, n=390) of participants self-reported more confidence to talk about the scientific theme after participating in field activities. Meanwhile 54% to 63% of participants could correctly describe the 8 steps in scientific process. Of the 599 participants evaluated on the learning experience, 80 to 100% indicated they could understand the most important ideas of the scientific project, could summarize them, and apply what they learned during the activity in their community. Majority of participants, 78% to 95% stated they learned new ideas and increased their knowledge about the scientific themes.&nbsp; Co-creators showed increase in knowledge and skills, from 95 % to 100 %; however, evaluators found no significant change in participant&rsquo;s attitude towards conservation because most participants already had prior interest and motivation towards the protection of nature. Although the summative evaluation demonstrated the learning processes of the participant is not resulting in citizens taking specific conservation action relevant to the watershed, repeated exposure to interconnected ISE experiences was effective for participants to develop science process skills that they can apply to real-world situations.</p> <p>The emergent ISE model identified in this project was hierarchal in nature with interchangeable roles, as the levels of engagement of participants increased from contributor to co-creator levels of engagement. The roles identified in the emergent model include the administrators, researchers, and research assistants forming the highest tier, followed by certified environmental interpreters and volunteer leaders; at the lowest tier were the public participants involved in collecting scientific data. The additional unique pedagogy approach used in the STEM investigations followed the principles of environmental interpretation. As the participants increased their knowledge and skills, and developed their own community based projects, their roles moved to a higher tier until the co-creators converted into researchers.</p> <p>This ISE hierarchal model has created an educational niche for intergenerational interaction and families to learn science together, providing opportunities for participants to develop long lasting relationships with their communities and nature. It resulted in some participants pursuing post-secondary studies in STEM fields; while others evolved to gain employment. &nbsp;Furthermore, the ISE model transformed researchers&rsquo; plans, design and implementation of STEM projects to engage Hispanic citizens, facilitating the development of teaching instruments, communication tools and institutional approaches on citizen engagement in natural protected areas. This ISE project has propelled multidisciplinary collaboration and contributed to the advancement of evaluation of citizen science projects for Hispanic audiences. This ISE model due to its transverse nature is useful to Hispanic audiences for the collective organization of STEM learning through multiple pedagogy.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/14/2017<br>      Modified by: Yogani&nbsp;Govender</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497279789514_Figure2_ParticipantsinISEproject-1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497279789514_Figure2_ParticipantsinISEproject-1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Participants of ISE project"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497279789514_Figure2_ParticipantsinISEproject-1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Participants of ISE project"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A total of 1,389  citizens participated in approximately 755 activities contributing to data collection and analysis of new scientific information related to the río Grande de Manatí Watershed</div> <div class="imageCredit">Para la Naturaleza</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yogani&nbsp;Govender</div> <div class="imageTitle">Participants of ISE project</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497279484793_Figure1_ISE_Hierachial_model--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497279484793_Figure1_ISE_Hierachial_model--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hierarchal ISE model"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497279484793_Figure1_ISE_Hierachial_model--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hierarchal ISE model"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Hierarchal Informal Science Education Model with interchangeable roles</div> <div class="imageCredit">Para la Naturaleza</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yogani&nbsp;Govender</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hierarchal ISE model</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497280061244_Figure3_MapofStudyArea--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497280061244_Figure3_MapofStudyArea--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Map of Study Area-r&iacute;o Grande de Manat&iacute;"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497280061244_Figure3_MapofStudyArea--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Map of Study Area-r&iacute;o Grande de Manat&iacute;"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Exploring the biodiversity of the río Grande de Manatí watershed</div> <div class="imageCredit">Para la Naturaleza</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yogani&nbsp;Govender</div> <div class="imageTitle">Map of Study Area-río Grande de Manatí</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497280301981_Figure4_Collage_Core_participants--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497280301981_Figure4_Collage_Core_participants--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Co-creators at work in community citizen science projects"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497280301981_Figure4_Collage_Core_participants--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Co-creators at work in community citizen science projects"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Photographic documentation of co-creators working in community based citizen science projects</div> <div class="imageCredit">Para la Naturaleza</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yogani&nbsp;Govender</div> <div class="imageTitle">Co-creators at work in community citizen science projects</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497280754258_Figure5_Social_media_outreach_graphic--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497280754258_Figure5_Social_media_outreach_graphic--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Socila Media Benchmark"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497280754258_Figure5_Social_media_outreach_graphic--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Socila Media Benchmark"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Social media benchmark to show the impact of communication strategies: Facebook likes</div> <div class="imageCredit">Para la Naturaleza</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yogani&nbsp;Govender</div> <div class="imageTitle">Socila Media Benchmark</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497281227555_Figure6_Inforgraphic--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497281227555_Figure6_Inforgraphic--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Adaptation and evolution of ISE through cyclic learning processes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1223882/1223882_10218484_1497281227555_Figure6_Inforgraphic--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Adaptation and evolution of ISE through cyclic learning processes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The project planning, design, implementation, communication strategies and evaluation approaches adapted and evolved through a cyclic science learning process to include the three levels of citizen science engagement.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Para la Naturaleza</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yogani&nbsp;Govender</div> <div class="imageTitle">Adaptation and evolution of ISE through cyclic learning processes</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project evaluated the effectiveness of an Informal Science Education (ISE) Model designed to engage citizens in STEM research to generate a change in knowledge, skills, and behavior of participants. The formative evaluation indicates that the project has a successful framework to attract the public and engage large numbers of citizens in STEM investigations. Coordinated project planning, design, implementation, appropriate communication strategies and evaluation approaches that adapted and evolved through a cyclic learning process allowed the three levels of citizen science engagement (contributor, collaborator and co-creator) for the collection, analysis and dissemination of scientific data.  A total of 1,389 citizens participated in 755 activities for data collection and analysis of new scientific information related to the r&iacute;o Grande de Manat&iacute; Watershed. The development of 12 community-based citizen projects allowed 18 participants at collaborator and co-creator levels of engagement in science to analyze and disseminate information about their community projects at local, national and international forums, some receiving awards and were invited to submit manuscripts on their work. Types of co-creator projects developed in the communities reflects the varied in age, education, interest and motivation to participate of the participants. Projects developed through bottom-up processes include the use of shrimp and crabs to determine water quality; the understanding the value of bats to the ecosystem; understanding the importance of state forests as bird habitats; evaluation and assessment tourism and climate change on beach processes. As co-creators increased their engagement in citizen science projects, they gained knowledge and skills increasing their confidence in disseminating projects results. Various formats were used to disseminate information about this ISE project including exhibit booths (7), television (4), radio (8), poster session (18), peer review manuscripts (5), digital media (25), videos (10), tool kits (6), how to kits (3), findings (4) and oral and poster presentations at conferences (27). Integration appropriate media and dissemination strategies engaged participants beyond the research activities, an estimated 170,187 users visited the project webpage www.ciudadanocientifico.org, while 2,873 likes were obtained on the Facebook page https://www.facebook.com/Ciudadano-Cient&iacute;fico-Para-La-Naturaleza.  Multiple techniques and evaluation instruments were used and triangulated to evaluate the gain in knowledge and skills of participants at the three levels of engagement. Majority (75%, n=390) of participants had little to no prior knowledge or skills of the research themes they engaged in. Majority (&gt; 75%, n=390) of participants self-reported more confidence to talk about the scientific theme after participating in field activities. Meanwhile 54% to 63% of participants could correctly describe the 8 steps in scientific process. Of the 599 participants evaluated on the learning experience, 80 to 100% indicated they could understand the most important ideas of the scientific project, could summarize them, and apply what they learned during the activity in their community. Majority of participants, 78% to 95% stated they learned new ideas and increased their knowledge about the scientific themes.  Co-creators showed increase in knowledge and skills, from 95 % to 100 %; however, evaluators found no significant change in participant?s attitude towards conservation because most participants already had prior interest and motivation towards the protection of nature. Although the summative evaluation demonstrated the learning processes of the participant is not resulting in citizens taking specific conservation action relevant to the watershed, repeated exposure to interconnected ISE experiences was effective for participants to develop science process skills that they can apply to real-world situations.  The emergent ISE model identified in this project was hierarchal in nature with interchangeable roles, as the levels of engagement of participants increased from contributor to co-creator levels of engagement. The roles identified in the emergent model include the administrators, researchers, and research assistants forming the highest tier, followed by certified environmental interpreters and volunteer leaders; at the lowest tier were the public participants involved in collecting scientific data. The additional unique pedagogy approach used in the STEM investigations followed the principles of environmental interpretation. As the participants increased their knowledge and skills, and developed their own community based projects, their roles moved to a higher tier until the co-creators converted into researchers.  This ISE hierarchal model has created an educational niche for intergenerational interaction and families to learn science together, providing opportunities for participants to develop long lasting relationships with their communities and nature. It resulted in some participants pursuing post-secondary studies in STEM fields; while others evolved to gain employment.  Furthermore, the ISE model transformed researchers? plans, design and implementation of STEM projects to engage Hispanic citizens, facilitating the development of teaching instruments, communication tools and institutional approaches on citizen engagement in natural protected areas. This ISE project has propelled multidisciplinary collaboration and contributed to the advancement of evaluation of citizen science projects for Hispanic audiences. This ISE model due to its transverse nature is useful to Hispanic audiences for the collective organization of STEM learning through multiple pedagogy.       Last Modified: 06/14/2017       Submitted by: Yogani Govender]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
