<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Water for Life: Community Education for Water Conservation and Rainwater Harvesting in the United States Affiliated Pacific Islands</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2638743.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2842492</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ellen McCallie</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emccalli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925115</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Water for Life (WfL) is a full scale development youth and community based program; centered on freshwater literacy, water conservation and rainwater harvesting led by the Pacific Resources for Education Learning (PREL) in Hawaii. The goals of the project are to: (a) promote an understanding of water conservation and stewardship in areas lacking adequate quality water supplies and (b) build local capacity among rural communities to develop and employ site specific freshwater harvesting strategies proven to improve water quality. Rural communities within four Pacific Island entities in the U.S. affiliated Freely Associated States (FAS) will participate in WfL activities. PREL will work collaboratively with a host of organizations such as the Federated States of Micronesia National Department of Education, Marshall Islands Conservation Society, and the Micronesian Conservation Trust, to develop and implement all phases of the initiative. This work could potentially impact the quality of life for hundreds of people in the FAS through water conversation education and improved water quality in local areas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Working closely with PREL staff and local water resource managers, a core team of 15-20 individuals, primarily teachers and community leaders, will participate in a 5 day short training course to develop and facilitate onsite and web-based water conservation and encatchment activities at the four target sites in the FAS. Three core team members per site will train local implementation teams of approximately 10 individuals per year (n=160) to redeliver the program and rainwater encatchment system strategies within their local communities. The implementation teams will redeliver the program to local youth and community groups (n=640). In addition, youth and community groups will be given opportunities to address specific needs through site specific service learning activities.  These activities may vary and might include: new encatchment systems, repair/upgrade of existing catchment systems, community education of decontaminated collected or stored water, and groundwater contamination reduction efforts. Each individual will participate in WfL learning experiences for a minimum of 24 hours over the course of a year. The experiences of all project participants will be captured, analyzed, and reported in front-end, formative, and summative evaluations conducted by David Heil &amp; Associates.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project deliverables include: onsite and distance learning programs, professional development short courses for teachers and community leaders, and service learning opportunities for community and youth groups. Over 800 individuals will be directly impacted by the project. The results of this work may be applicable to other remote and rural communities outside of the Pacific distressed by poor water quality and ineffective freshwater harvesting systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1224185</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ethan</FirstName>
<LastName>Allen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ethan Allen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>allene@prel.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8084411392</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000266971</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Danko</FirstName>
<LastName>Taborosi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Danko Taborosi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>taborosi@islandresearch.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6913204037</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000614046</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pacific Resources for Education and Learning</Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<ZipCode>968132719</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8084411334</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1136 Union Mall, Suite PH 1A</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>797172798</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PACIFIC RESOURCES FOR EDUCATION AND LEARNING</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pacific Resources for Education and Learning]]></Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968133718</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[900 Fort Street Mall, Suite 1300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~524747</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~480527</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~504111</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~792918</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~540189</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Water for Life (WfL) has fostered robust, community-based, self-sustaining science learning across four sites &ndash; Palau, the Republic of the Marshall Islands (RMI), and Chuuk and Yap states in the Federated States of Micronesia (FSM) &ndash; focused on issues of drinking water. Most residents on these small, remote, isolated islands must rely on rainwater catchment systems (RWCSs), wells, or springs for drinking water; in many sites, municipal systems are non-existent or provide water only intermittently, and the water provided is often non-potable. Using a contextually-appropriate approach, WfL has bootstrapped regional informal science education (ISE) capacity among a range of local organizations in these underserved regions. Core Teams of educators and environmental and water resource professionals now lead and facilitate community efforts to build water security. WfL activities have raised awareness of water-related issues, provided innovative hands-on application of STEM learning, and fostered the development of water stewardship, conservation, and advocacy. The project has bolstered the capacity of the citizens of these communities to address critical environmental and societal challenges and increase their water self-sufficiency and resiliency. One game-changing outcome from WfL has been the development and spread of the Water Quality Monitoring Team (WQMT) model. Originally developed on Majuro (in RMI), WQMTs now help ensure that the nearly 9,000 students and teachers in all public schools there have access to regularly monitored drinking water. WQMTs consist of students, parents, and school staff (now &gt;170), trained by staff from the Environmental Protection Agency and College of the Marshall Islands Land Grant program to maintain their school RWCSs--including roofs, gutters, leaf screens, downspouts, first flush diverters, and tanks--to regularly test the water quality in all dispensers, and to send water quality data monthly to the EPA. WQMTs now keep their school RWCSs cleaner, so there are fewer episodes of poor quality water. Families that live near the schools also access these water sources, extending the impact even further. The current situation stands in stark contrast to what existed prior to WfL, when schools did not provide drinking water to their students and staff, and about 75% of all of the RWCSs tested on Majuro had unacceptable levels of coliform bacterial contamination. Based on its success in RMI, the WQMT model is being adapted and implemented in Yap and Palau. And, with further funding from NSF's INCLUDES program, the WQMT approach is now being inaugurated in outlying atolls of RMI and in Pohnpei, FSM. In other WfL sites, beyond helping upgrade and maintain RWCSs, WfL has engaged communities in improving groundwater springs and surface water sources used for drinking. Community members have learned why and how to protect such vulnerable sources from contamination. A model of spring protection infrastructure has been replicated at six sites around Chuuk, engaging many dozens of residents in active learning of key STEM principles related to water stewardship, many hundreds more in community workshops based around these installations, and providing access to cleaner water to thousands of people. More residents have learned water-related STEM through participating in installing 100 first flush diverters and 115 bob bag RWCSs. WfL has helped others learn through introducing broadly applicable decontamination technologies such as solar pasteurization and MadiDrops (www.madidrop.com), and desalinization methods such as building passive solar stills. WfL has engaged tens of thousands of regional residents in learning water-related STEM through events such as World Water day activities and challenge bowl competitions for students, and from vehicles such as billboards, murals, posters, signage, and radio programs. Formal workshops and training sessions have engaged thousands more in deeper learning. WfL staff serve on national water policy panels, shaping regional water conservation and stewardship practices. WfL educational materials, including school-based and out-of-school lessons, as well as flyers, booklets, videos, and 3,000 copies of a 280-page Handbook, have enriched the local resource bases. Hundreds of teachers have been trained using the Water for Life Handbook, and now incorporate water science and clean water technology topics into their curricula, so future generations of island residents will have the knowledge and capacity to maintain, conserve, and provide stewardship for their water sources. A Facebook page (facebook.comPREL.WfL) and website (w4l.prel.org) provide further resources. Working collaboratively with numerous local partner agencies, the lead WfL organizations of Pacific Resources for Education and Learning (PRELprel.org) and Island Research and Education Initiative (iREiislandresearch.org) have nurtured collective impact,building the capabilities of diverse arrays of community-based organizations to collaboratively develop and lead the application of STEM practices toward enhancing access to higher quality and a greater quantity of drinking water. In short, through its innovative approach of engaging communities in applying STEM practices as a path to learning STEM concepts, WfL has helped nurture locally-relevant, broad-based, self-sustaining water literacy among significant proportions of both youth and adult populations in a range of Western Pacific island nations.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2017<br>      Modified by: Ethan&nbsp;Allen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Water for Life (WfL) has fostered robust, community-based, self-sustaining science learning across four sites &ndash; Palau, the Republic of the Marshall Islands (RMI), and Chuuk and Yap states in the Federated States of Micronesia (FSM) &ndash; focused on issues of drinking water. Most residents on these small, remote, isolated islands must rely on rainwater catchment systems (RWCSs), wells, or springs for drinking water; in many sites, municipal systems are non-existent or provide water only intermittently, and the water provided is often non-potable. Using a contextually-appropriate approach, WfL has bootstrapped regional informal science education (ISE) capacity among a range of local organizations in these underserved regions. Core Teams of educators and environmental and water resource professionals now lead and facilitate community efforts to build water security. WfL activities have raised awareness of water-related issues, provided innovative hands-on application of STEM learning, and fostered the development of water stewardship, conservation, and advocacy. The project has bolstered the capacity of the citizens of these communities to address critical environmental and societal challenges and increase their water self-sufficiency and resiliency. One game-changing outcome from WfL has been the development and spread of the Water Quality Monitoring Team (WQMT) model. Originally developed on Majuro (in RMI), WQMTs now help ensure that the nearly 9,000 students and teachers in all public schools there have access to regularly monitored drinking water. WQMTs consist of students, parents, and school staff (now &gt;170), trained by staff from the Environmental Protection Agency and College of the Marshall Islands Land Grant program to maintain their school RWCSs--including roofs, gutters, leaf screens, downspouts, first flush diverters, and tanks--to regularly test the water quality in all dispensers, and to send water quality data monthly to the EPA. WQMTs now keep their school RWCSs cleaner, so there are fewer episodes of poor quality water. Families that live near the schools also access these water sources, extending the impact even further. The current situation stands in stark contrast to what existed prior to WfL, when schools did not provide drinking water to their students and staff, and about 75% of all of the RWCSs tested on Majuro had unacceptable levels of coliform bacterial contamination. Based on its success in RMI, the WQMT model is being adapted and implemented in Yap and Palau. And, with further funding from NSF's INCLUDES program, the WQMT approach is now being inaugurated in outlying atolls of RMI and in Pohnpei, FSM. In other WfL sites, beyond helping upgrade and maintain RWCSs, WfL has engaged communities in improving groundwater springs and surface water sources used for drinking. Community members have learned why and how to protect such vulnerable sources from contamination. A model of spring protection infrastructure has been replicated at six sites around Chuuk, engaging many dozens of residents in active learning of key STEM principles related to water stewardship, many hundreds more in community workshops based around these installations, and providing access to cleaner water to thousands of people. More residents have learned water-related STEM through participating in installing 100 first flush diverters and 115 bob bag RWCSs. WfL has helped others learn through introducing broadly applicable decontamination technologies such as solar pasteurization and MadiDrops (www.madidrop.com), and desalinization methods such as building passive solar stills. WfL has engaged tens of thousands of regional residents in learning water-related STEM through events such as World Water day activities and challenge bowl competitions for students, and from vehicles such as billboards, murals, posters, signage, and radio programs. Formal workshops and training sessions have engaged thousands more in deeper learning. WfL staff serve on national water policy panels, shaping regional water conservation and stewardship practices. WfL educational materials, including school-based and out-of-school lessons, as well as flyers, booklets, videos, and 3,000 copies of a 280-page Handbook, have enriched the local resource bases. Hundreds of teachers have been trained using the Water for Life Handbook, and now incorporate water science and clean water technology topics into their curricula, so future generations of island residents will have the knowledge and capacity to maintain, conserve, and provide stewardship for their water sources. A Facebook page (facebook.comPREL.WfL) and website (w4l.prel.org) provide further resources. Working collaboratively with numerous local partner agencies, the lead WfL organizations of Pacific Resources for Education and Learning (PRELprel.org) and Island Research and Education Initiative (iREiislandresearch.org) have nurtured collective impact,building the capabilities of diverse arrays of community-based organizations to collaboratively develop and lead the application of STEM practices toward enhancing access to higher quality and a greater quantity of drinking water. In short, through its innovative approach of engaging communities in applying STEM practices as a path to learning STEM concepts, WfL has helped nurture locally-relevant, broad-based, self-sustaining water literacy among significant proportions of both youth and adult populations in a range of Western Pacific island nations.       Last Modified: 10/27/2017       Submitted by: Ethan Allen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
