<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Just-in-Time-Teaching with Interactive Frequent Formative Feedback (JiTTIFFF) for Cyber Learning in Core Materials Courses</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>44122.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>44122</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Crosby</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Just-in-Time-Teaching with Interactive Frequent Formative Feedback (JiTTIFFF or JTF) project uses engagement, assessment, and reflection tools developed in a prior NSF project and adapts them to an interactive cyber-enabled web environment. Using the tools in and out of class has the potential to increase the effectiveness and efficiency of learning using frequent formative feedback to students. New strategies include: 1) instruction informed by a multi-level, assessment-driven frequent formative feedback loops; 2) formative feedback from pre-class class preparation problems, 3) feedback during in-class engagement activities; 4) next class feedback discussion on confusing points from the previous class and 5) contextualization of activities and assessments with real-world applications. Compared to lecture-based pedagogy, constructivist pedagogy: increased average conceptual gain (measured by the Materials Concept Inventory) from 18% to 42%; increased class persistence from 85% to 95%; and decreased female withdrawal rate from 40% to 10%.  The web environment facilitates ease of implementation and creates the potential for broad dissemination of instructional strategies and tools developed. The project is also investigating issues in implementation and how instructors use assessment results to adjust instruction. Such knowledge and insight is shaping the development of tutorials, workshops, webinars and you-tube videos for instruction for faculty interested in adapting the JTF pedagogy in their own instruction. The JTF pedagogy is being implemented and assessed in four settings with diverse populations: Arizona State University,  North Carolina A&amp;T, Oregon Institute of Technology, and Oregon State University. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is producing 1) an updated sets of instructional resources in the web-based JTF Learning Tool Kit; 2) an understanding of the barriers and benefits of JTF implementation in diverse settings; 3) an understanding of how instructors use results of multi-level assessment to adjust instruction to address student learning issues; and 4) an assessment of the impact of JTF on student attitude, learning and retention, and differences arising from use in different settings and diverse populations. It is also investigating the potential for broad application of the general features of JTF strategies and tools in other engineering domains through dissemination and diffusion of JTF strategies, findings, and products to a wide audience. This study is informing the engineering education community of the potential for use of the types of JTF strategies and learning tools in other engineering domains. This project is testing the effectiveness of the JTF pedagogy in different settings with diverse populations when implemented on the cyber-enabled web platforms</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1225692</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joe</FirstName>
<LastName>Stuart</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joe Stuart</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>joe.stuart@oit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5418515262</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000150368</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Klamath Falls</CityName>
<ZipCode>976018801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5418851743</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3201 Campus Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>055968499</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>055968499</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Same]]></Name>
<CityName>Klamath Falls</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>976018801</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3021 Campus Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7511</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 2 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~44122</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The overall goal of the project was to implement and extend successful strategies, resources, and practices in teaching with Just-in-Time-Teaching tools, student Just-in-Time-Learning resources as catalyzed by faculty-student interactions through Frequent Formative Feedback mechanisms(JTF). A JTF interactive web-environment enabled more effective instruction by providing &nbsp;an instructor with ease-of-implementation, impact, and effectiveness with the JTF pedagogy that was tested in a collaboration between faculty in diverse settings at Arizona State University (ASU), North Carolina A&amp;T University (NCAT), Oregon Institute of Technology (OIT), and Oregon State University (OSU). The six major outcomes of the project are described below:&nbsp;</span></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;#1 - Web-enabled resources</strong></p> <p>Web-enable successful engagement, feedback, and assessment resources. Resources were expanded into web-based suites of instructor Just-in-Time-Teaching tools and student Just-in-Time-Learning resources for interactive instruction that supports and facilitates use of JTF pedagogy for more effective teaching and learning. <span>A new web tool &nbsp;the "pencast" was used by faculty, which uses a smart pen to record voice and writing on a special paper which can then be converted into an audio PDF. This audio PDF can be used to create tutorials, problem solutions or even class lectures. The audio PDF pencast can then be posted and accessed through Blackboard or on YouTube after converting to MP4 format.&nbsp;<span>Muddiest Point student feedback was also collected before class and used to inform instruction in the class. Another technique used&nbsp;<span>Camtasia recordings turned into MP4 videos that are being posted on a YouTube channel. Another technique is using<span>&nbsp;YouTube Muddiest Point videos and Quizlet.com e-vocabulary definitions.&nbsp;</span></span></span></span>This outcome has proved very useful and successful.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>#2 -&nbsp;Community of Practice</strong></p> <p>Built a community of practice that supports implementation of JTF pedagogy through instructor discussions, web meetings, and workshops to understand JTF barriers and benefits and the change in teaching beliefs and classroom practice that occurs over time. This was accomplished by monthly meetings and faculty workshops sharing techniques. This outcome is successful and continutes to grow.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;#3 - Instructor JTF Usage</strong></p> <p>Instructors now use JTF feedback and assessment to identify and diagnose student learning issues and the teaching strategies used to address them.&nbsp; This outcome continues to grow and be successful.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;#4 - JTF Impact on Students</strong></p> <p>The effect of the JTF pedagogy on student attitude, learning, and persistence, as well as effectiveness in resolving student learning issues has been studied and has proved to be very useful in understanding and modifying teaching techniques and improving teaching effectiveness. Student surveys reflected performance and attitudes and proviced excellent feedback to enhance the effectiveness of this outcome.</p> <p><strong>#5 - JTF Other Domain Potential</strong></p> <p>A broader adaptation of JTF pedagogy in other engineering domains has been studied and continues to be utilized and successful.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>#6 &ndash; Dissemination</strong></p> <p>JTF strategies and resources have been&nbsp;broadly disseminated and diffused to a wide audience and this has facilitated greater adaptation of JTF pedagogy.&nbsp;<span>Wiley Publishing continues to use the three types of JTF teaching and learning resources for the Wiley Plus e-learning student resource, which is linked to two widely used materials texts with new editions published.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>These outcomes have proved to be transformational for many faculty exposed to these teaching techniques and moreover have illustrated that students can learn more effectively and efficiently when the tools described are implemented.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/16/2016<br>      Modified by: Joe&nbsp;Stuart</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall goal of the project was to implement and extend successful strategies, resources, and practices in teaching with Just-in-Time-Teaching tools, student Just-in-Time-Learning resources as catalyzed by faculty-student interactions through Frequent Formative Feedback mechanisms(JTF). A JTF interactive web-environment enabled more effective instruction by providing  an instructor with ease-of-implementation, impact, and effectiveness with the JTF pedagogy that was tested in a collaboration between faculty in diverse settings at Arizona State University (ASU), North Carolina A&amp;T University (NCAT), Oregon Institute of Technology (OIT), and Oregon State University (OSU). The six major outcomes of the project are described below:    #1 - Web-enabled resources  Web-enable successful engagement, feedback, and assessment resources. Resources were expanded into web-based suites of instructor Just-in-Time-Teaching tools and student Just-in-Time-Learning resources for interactive instruction that supports and facilitates use of JTF pedagogy for more effective teaching and learning. A new web tool  the "pencast" was used by faculty, which uses a smart pen to record voice and writing on a special paper which can then be converted into an audio PDF. This audio PDF can be used to create tutorials, problem solutions or even class lectures. The audio PDF pencast can then be posted and accessed through Blackboard or on YouTube after converting to MP4 format. Muddiest Point student feedback was also collected before class and used to inform instruction in the class. Another technique used Camtasia recordings turned into MP4 videos that are being posted on a YouTube channel. Another technique is using YouTube Muddiest Point videos and Quizlet.com e-vocabulary definitions. This outcome has proved very useful and successful.   #2 - Community of Practice  Built a community of practice that supports implementation of JTF pedagogy through instructor discussions, web meetings, and workshops to understand JTF barriers and benefits and the change in teaching beliefs and classroom practice that occurs over time. This was accomplished by monthly meetings and faculty workshops sharing techniques. This outcome is successful and continutes to grow.    #3 - Instructor JTF Usage  Instructors now use JTF feedback and assessment to identify and diagnose student learning issues and the teaching strategies used to address them.  This outcome continues to grow and be successful.   #4 - JTF Impact on Students  The effect of the JTF pedagogy on student attitude, learning, and persistence, as well as effectiveness in resolving student learning issues has been studied and has proved to be very useful in understanding and modifying teaching techniques and improving teaching effectiveness. Student surveys reflected performance and attitudes and proviced excellent feedback to enhance the effectiveness of this outcome.  #5 - JTF Other Domain Potential  A broader adaptation of JTF pedagogy in other engineering domains has been studied and continues to be utilized and successful.   #6 &ndash; Dissemination  JTF strategies and resources have been broadly disseminated and diffused to a wide audience and this has facilitated greater adaptation of JTF pedagogy. Wiley Publishing continues to use the three types of JTF teaching and learning resources for the Wiley Plus e-learning student resource, which is linked to two widely used materials texts with new editions published.     These outcomes have proved to be transformational for many faculty exposed to these teaching techniques and moreover have illustrated that students can learn more effectively and efficiently when the tools described are implemented.        Last Modified: 11/16/2016       Submitted by: Joe Stuart]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
