<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBP-Creating a Diverse Society that Works: Investigating the Role of Social Identity Threat in Interracial Interactions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven J. Breckler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sbreckle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927369</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The lack of positive contact between members of different racial groups has constituted a major social problem throughout American history. Even though racial and ethic diversity in the United States is growing, interracial contact remains relatively rare. Positive interracial contact is important because it has been linked to reductions in prejudice and discrimination and to greater access to intellectual, social and economic capital. When interracial contact occurs, however, research has demonstrated that it is rife with anxiety and discomfort for both racial majority and minority group members. Furthermore, people's anxiety and discomfort during interracial contact has been associated with decreased interest in pursuing future interracial contact. The present research examines how two factors - the racial diversity of an interaction partner's friendship network and the goals that he or she adopts for the interaction - influence people's experiences during interracial interactions. This research proposes a novel, theoretically based model for how these factors independently and collectively influence people's comfort and anxiety when engaged in interracial interactions and their desire to engage in future interracial interactions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While previous research has examined how racially diverse (vs. homogenous) friendship networks affects interracial interaction expectations, this work examines the role of friendship networks in the context of another situational factor - people's goals for the interaction. Five experimental studies will test whether an interaction partner's racial friendship network (racially diverse or racial homogeneous) and the partner's goals for the interaction (learning or performance goals) influence ethnic minority and White individuals' interaction experiences. In particular, we will measure Black, Hispanic and White college students' experiences of social identity threat, anxiety, and avoidant behavior prior to and during the interaction, as well as their interest in engaging in future interracial interactions. It is hypothesized that an interaction partner who has a racially diverse friend network and who also adopts a learning goal prior to the interaction will reduce participants' social identity threat, anxiety and avoidance behavior, and will foster a more positive interaction. Thus the research will test whether shifts in people's goals within the interaction context can reduce identity threat, opening the door for positive interracial contact?even in the absence of a diverse friendship network. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By exploring the perspectives of majority and minority group members, this research will provide novel theoretical and empirical contributions to the existing literatures on interracial contact and social identity threat by broadening our understanding of the challenges faced by people engaged in interracial contact. Moreover, this research will provide practical guidance on how to better structure interracial interactions to facilitate smoother exchanges and greater enjoyment for both minority and majority group members. This understanding is essential as we enter an age of increased globalization and intergroup contact and as we strive to maintain our competitiveness both at home and internationally. As faculty of color, both PIs are committed to broadening diversity with the sciences and thus serve as role models and mentors for graduate and undergraduate students from disadvantaged and underrepresented backgrounds that will be involved in the planning, execution, dissemination, and publication of the research findings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1226562</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daryl</FirstName>
<LastName>Wout</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daryl A Wout</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dwout@jjay.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6465574652</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000331995</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Murphy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary C Murphy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcmpsych@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128554581</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000525315</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY John Jay College of Criminal Justice</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100191069</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2122378449</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>524 West 59th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>620128863</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY John Jay College of Criminal Justice]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100191104</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>Social Psychology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8050</Code>
<Text>Science of Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~93657</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~266343</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overarching goal of the project was to further examine the role of an interaction partner&rsquo;s racial friendship network on people&rsquo;s experiences of social identity threat (concerns about being negatively stereotyped and treated). Our previous research demonstrated that Blacks experience more social identity threat when they anticipated interacting with a White person who has a homogeneous White friendship network compared to a White person with a racially diverse friendship network (Wout, Murphy, &amp; Steele, 2010). These findings suggested that people use their interaction partner&rsquo;s racial friendship network as a cue of either social identity threat or social identity safety. The studies we conducted during this project were designed to identify other contextual factors that could interact with friendship networks to either heighten or reduce people&rsquo;s social identity threat concerns. This research was divided into three specific research areas: 1) the effects of an interaction partner&rsquo;s racial friendship networks and interaction goals on people&rsquo;s social identity threat concerns prior to interracial interactions, 2) how people integrate the cue of racial friendship networks with other contextual cues when determining social identity threat, and 3) how people perceive and racially categorize a biracial interaction partner based on that person&rsquo;s racial friendship network.</p> <p>The primary focus of this project was to explore the effects of racial friendship networks and interaction goals on people&rsquo;s social identity threat concerns. Across a series of experiments we had either White people or people of color (Black or Hispanic) anticipate interacting with a racial outgroup member. We then manipulated both the race of the interaction partner&rsquo;s friends (either racially homogeneous friends or racially diverse friends) and the goals that the interaction partner brought to the interaction (either to learn from the interaction or to demonstrate their knowledge during the interaction). The results of our studies demonstrated that people&rsquo;s social identity threat concerns can be significantly reduced when either their interaction partner had a racially diverse network of friends or when their partner expressed a desire to learn from the interaction. Additional studies demonstrated that these social identity threat concerns could be reduced if the participants themselves adopted the goal of learning from the interaction. Collectively, these findings suggest that both an interaction partner&rsquo;s racial network of friends, as well as the goals that people bring to an interracial interaction can have a profound impact on how people expect to be perceived and treated during that interaction.</p> <p>A secondary research area focused on how people incorporate multiple cues of safety and threat when anticipating an interracial interaction. As we previously demonstrated, people interpret the race of an interaction partner&rsquo;s friends as a cue of either social identity safety (racial diverse friends) or social identity threat (racially homogeneous friends). Across two studies we investigated how Black people incorporated a White interaction partner&rsquo;s friends with other cues of either safety or threat. The results of these studies demonstrated that cues of threat could override cues of safety such that when people of color are exposed to both types of cues, they place more weight and emphasis on the threat cue. Thus, when people are exposed to conflicting cues of threat and safety, they are more concerned about being negatively stereotyped and mistreated, and have a more negative perception of their interaction partner.</p> <p>The final research area explored how people categorize and perceive biracial individuals. Much of the research on categorization of biracials has focused on testing the principle of hypodescent, which suggests that a mixed-race person is racially categorized as a member of the lower status parent&rsquo;s race (Harris, 1964). Thus, if a person has a White parent and a Black parent, that person would be categorized as Black. The two studies that we conducted demonstrated that a Black-White biracial individual&rsquo;s racial network of friends could impact how they are categorized and perceived by White people. Specifically, Whites categorized and perceived a Black-White biracial individual with predominantly Black friends as &ldquo;Blacker&rdquo; in terms of group membership and skin tone than a Black-White biracial individual with predominantly White friends. Furthermore, White had greater social identity threat concern when anticipating an interaction with a Black-White biracial person with predominantly Black friends than one with predominantly White friends. The results of these studies suggest that the racial composition of biracials can impact how they are categorized and perceived as well as how other people expect to be perceived and treated by them.</p> <p>Collectively, our projected highlights the role of racial friendships on interracial interactions. Specifically, having a racially diverse network of friends and entering an interaction with a focus on learning can foster more positive interracial interactions. In our future research, we plan to expand on the present research to explore how friendship networks can impact interactions between other social categories (e.g., political groups, religious group).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/28/2016<br>      Modified by: Daryl&nbsp;A&nbsp;Wout</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overarching goal of the project was to further examine the role of an interaction partner?s racial friendship network on people?s experiences of social identity threat (concerns about being negatively stereotyped and treated). Our previous research demonstrated that Blacks experience more social identity threat when they anticipated interacting with a White person who has a homogeneous White friendship network compared to a White person with a racially diverse friendship network (Wout, Murphy, &amp; Steele, 2010). These findings suggested that people use their interaction partner?s racial friendship network as a cue of either social identity threat or social identity safety. The studies we conducted during this project were designed to identify other contextual factors that could interact with friendship networks to either heighten or reduce people?s social identity threat concerns. This research was divided into three specific research areas: 1) the effects of an interaction partner?s racial friendship networks and interaction goals on people?s social identity threat concerns prior to interracial interactions, 2) how people integrate the cue of racial friendship networks with other contextual cues when determining social identity threat, and 3) how people perceive and racially categorize a biracial interaction partner based on that person?s racial friendship network.  The primary focus of this project was to explore the effects of racial friendship networks and interaction goals on people?s social identity threat concerns. Across a series of experiments we had either White people or people of color (Black or Hispanic) anticipate interacting with a racial outgroup member. We then manipulated both the race of the interaction partner?s friends (either racially homogeneous friends or racially diverse friends) and the goals that the interaction partner brought to the interaction (either to learn from the interaction or to demonstrate their knowledge during the interaction). The results of our studies demonstrated that people?s social identity threat concerns can be significantly reduced when either their interaction partner had a racially diverse network of friends or when their partner expressed a desire to learn from the interaction. Additional studies demonstrated that these social identity threat concerns could be reduced if the participants themselves adopted the goal of learning from the interaction. Collectively, these findings suggest that both an interaction partner?s racial network of friends, as well as the goals that people bring to an interracial interaction can have a profound impact on how people expect to be perceived and treated during that interaction.  A secondary research area focused on how people incorporate multiple cues of safety and threat when anticipating an interracial interaction. As we previously demonstrated, people interpret the race of an interaction partner?s friends as a cue of either social identity safety (racial diverse friends) or social identity threat (racially homogeneous friends). Across two studies we investigated how Black people incorporated a White interaction partner?s friends with other cues of either safety or threat. The results of these studies demonstrated that cues of threat could override cues of safety such that when people of color are exposed to both types of cues, they place more weight and emphasis on the threat cue. Thus, when people are exposed to conflicting cues of threat and safety, they are more concerned about being negatively stereotyped and mistreated, and have a more negative perception of their interaction partner.  The final research area explored how people categorize and perceive biracial individuals. Much of the research on categorization of biracials has focused on testing the principle of hypodescent, which suggests that a mixed-race person is racially categorized as a member of the lower status parent?s race (Harris, 1964). Thus, if a person has a White parent and a Black parent, that person would be categorized as Black. The two studies that we conducted demonstrated that a Black-White biracial individual?s racial network of friends could impact how they are categorized and perceived by White people. Specifically, Whites categorized and perceived a Black-White biracial individual with predominantly Black friends as "Blacker" in terms of group membership and skin tone than a Black-White biracial individual with predominantly White friends. Furthermore, White had greater social identity threat concern when anticipating an interaction with a Black-White biracial person with predominantly Black friends than one with predominantly White friends. The results of these studies suggest that the racial composition of biracials can impact how they are categorized and perceived as well as how other people expect to be perceived and treated by them.  Collectively, our projected highlights the role of racial friendships on interracial interactions. Specifically, having a racially diverse network of friends and entering an interaction with a focus on learning can foster more positive interracial interactions. In our future research, we plan to expand on the present research to explore how friendship networks can impact interactions between other social categories (e.g., political groups, religious group).          Last Modified: 12/28/2016       Submitted by: Daryl A Wout]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
