<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Network Dynamics and Corporate Strategies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>142556.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>142556</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SES - 1226489&lt;br/&gt;Bruce Kogut&lt;br/&gt;Columbia University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SES - 1226834&lt;br/&gt;David Lazer&lt;br/&gt;Northeastern University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Collaborative Research: Network Dynamics and Organizational Strategies&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;We know that, in general, people tend to share similar world views of other individuals around them -- a classic principle known as homophily. Yet, we know surprisingly little about the effects of network dynamics beyond individuals within a specific organizational context.  As a case in point, this research project uses advanced statistical and computational methods to analyze network data regarding ties among and between individuals.  Of course, people might hold views or make choices independent of their ties to other members in the same group or organization.  Alternatively, individuals might share views with their peers.  In this latter case, shared perspectives may simply reflect classic homophily (aka selection bias), or true peer influence channeled by the new network ties developed with peers.  The research focuses (a) on the degree to which organizations or normative entities recruit and/or influence people's choices and (b) on ways in which this creates broader effects beyond organizational boundaries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;Until recently, the needed fine-grained data and analytical techniques were not available to answer these questions empirically.  Findings from this research have the potential to advance our understanding of group processes generally.  Findings may be of interest to a variety of stakeholders, including public officials, the media, the business community, and the general public.  In addition, findings from this study have the potential to advance social science methodologically and provide valuable quantitative methodological training opportunities for students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1226489</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Kogut</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce M Kogut</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bruce.kogut@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128546851</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000576017</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7726</Code>
<Text>Data Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>SoO-Science Of Organizations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~142556</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Title: Collaborative Research:</p> <p>Network Dynamics and Corporate Strategies</p> <p>PI: Bruce Kogut</p> <p>Awardee: Columbia University</p> <p>Award Number: 1226489</p> <p>If firms could have the opportunity to spend large sums of money on influencing political campaigns, would they make the investment as part of their strategy?&nbsp; This is one of the questions we have addressed through the data we were able collect thanks to the National Science Foundation.</p> <p>The perennial belief since the reforms instigated by President Teddy Roosevelt and other reformers in the first decades of the 20th century is that business buys politicians.&nbsp; Over the last century, Congress sequentially expanded the regulation of campaign financing, imposing caps on how much money corporations, unions, and people could give a candidate and also funding an option for candidates to rely on public finances rather than be beholden to private donors. The last Congressional act that advanced further this reformist agenda was the so-called McCain-Feingold Act, a bipartisan legislation passed in 2002 that limited the use of soft money for financing campaigns and also limited issue advertising that encouraged the election of selective candidates.</p> <p>Since then, the Supreme Court has actively struck down some, but not all, of the regulatory limits on campaign financing, particularly the McCain-Feingold restrictions on issue advertising.&nbsp; The Citizens United decision in 2010 ruled that corporations were juridical persons who had first amendment rights to express their political opinions as any citizen.&nbsp; The Speechnow.org decision by the U.S. Court of Appeals also of 2010 expanded upon Citizen's United ruling to strike down restrictions on donations to so-called Super PACs who were not limited in their expenditures. Finally, in 2014, the McCutcheon decision eliminated caps on an individual&rsquo;s total contributions.</p> <p>Our focus in this study is on the decisions of corporations and their boards and executives to participate in campaign contributions.&nbsp; For this purpose, we constructed a balanced panel dataset on 770 of the S&amp;P 500 composites from 2001 to 2016, with more than 12,00 directors (including about 2,000 CEOs). Our unit of analysis is individual contribution in two-year period election cycles: 6 cycles, from 2001 to 2016.</p> <p>We employed a statistical model that estimates whether these legal decisions influenced the amount of money spent by corporate PACs, the corporate elite &ndash;meaning the directors on boards and CEOs, and by the very wealthy.&nbsp; The figures below provide graphically a very simple response.</p> <p>Contributions per director and CEO clearly increased after the Citizen United and Speechnow.org and the 2014 McCutcheon decisions.&nbsp; The directors who were &ldquo;maxed&rdquo; out in the previous election by how much money they could give were able in the 2012 Presidential cycle to give a lot more.&nbsp; All three trends merge after 2008: constrained, the very wealthy, and the very wealthy and also &nbsp;ideological. This raises the question of which of these factors is really explaining the rise in donations.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>We estimate next a statistical difference-in-differences model to sort out these effects.&nbsp; We find that individuals who are very wealthy and very ideological (i.e. either score near 1 or -1 on our political color index) give considerably more than anyone else.&nbsp; What happens to those who are no longer constrained by the regulatory limits on donations?&nbsp; The constrained donors tend to be wealthy and also very ideological.&nbsp; Once the McCutcheon decisions came along, the very wealthy and very ideological directors increased their giving dramatically.</p> <p>This is only one study that emerged from the NSF-funded research we did on the political color of boards.&nbsp; We chose this one because it describes a very important feature of politics in the United States.&nbsp; Because of the very high inequality in wealth and income, there are a few people who have a lot more money than other people.&nbsp; Interesting enough, most wealthy people don&rsquo;t give a lot more donations than other corporate elites who are much less wealthy.&nbsp; A few, though, give a lot, and these individuals are also the least bipartisan in their contributions.&nbsp;</p> <p>We see this very clearly in the attached figure.&nbsp; These show the most money contributed by the corporate elite come from the most ideological, either democratic or republican.&nbsp; And most of the money in the extremes are given by ideological very wealthy people.</p> <p>So what happened then to the corporations that many legal scholars thought would rapidly increase their contributions to political candidates after Citizens United?&nbsp; In fact, they did not give much more money through their corporate PACs.&nbsp; And when they gave, corporations were much more bipartisan than the wealthy corporate elite contributors.&nbsp; To our surprise, corporations pursue strategies that are relatively centrist (though surely leaning to the political right). That&rsquo;s why research is good to do.&nbsp; We found out that Teddy Roosevelt&rsquo;s world is no longer our world. Corporations are not buying the politicians through campaign donations.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Bruce&nbsp;M&nbsp;Kogut</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1226489/1226489_10206769_1543619309916_PoliticalColorofIndividualDonations--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1226489/1226489_10206769_1543619309916_PoliticalColorofIndividualDonations--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Political Color of Individual Donations"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1226489/1226489_10206769_1543619309916_PoliticalColorofIndividualDonations--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Political Color of Individual Donations"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Donations by individuals are ideological. Most people give either to the right or to the left, but not in-between. On the other hand, public companies are center-right and less ideological in their political donations.</div> <div class="imageCredit">@authors</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bruce&nbsp;M&nbsp;Kogut</div> <div class="imageTitle">Political Color of Individual Donations</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Title: Collaborative Research:  Network Dynamics and Corporate Strategies  PI: Bruce Kogut  Awardee: Columbia University  Award Number: 1226489  If firms could have the opportunity to spend large sums of money on influencing political campaigns, would they make the investment as part of their strategy?  This is one of the questions we have addressed through the data we were able collect thanks to the National Science Foundation.  The perennial belief since the reforms instigated by President Teddy Roosevelt and other reformers in the first decades of the 20th century is that business buys politicians.  Over the last century, Congress sequentially expanded the regulation of campaign financing, imposing caps on how much money corporations, unions, and people could give a candidate and also funding an option for candidates to rely on public finances rather than be beholden to private donors. The last Congressional act that advanced further this reformist agenda was the so-called McCain-Feingold Act, a bipartisan legislation passed in 2002 that limited the use of soft money for financing campaigns and also limited issue advertising that encouraged the election of selective candidates.  Since then, the Supreme Court has actively struck down some, but not all, of the regulatory limits on campaign financing, particularly the McCain-Feingold restrictions on issue advertising.  The Citizens United decision in 2010 ruled that corporations were juridical persons who had first amendment rights to express their political opinions as any citizen.  The Speechnow.org decision by the U.S. Court of Appeals also of 2010 expanded upon Citizen's United ruling to strike down restrictions on donations to so-called Super PACs who were not limited in their expenditures. Finally, in 2014, the McCutcheon decision eliminated caps on an individual?s total contributions.  Our focus in this study is on the decisions of corporations and their boards and executives to participate in campaign contributions.  For this purpose, we constructed a balanced panel dataset on 770 of the S&amp;P 500 composites from 2001 to 2016, with more than 12,00 directors (including about 2,000 CEOs). Our unit of analysis is individual contribution in two-year period election cycles: 6 cycles, from 2001 to 2016.  We employed a statistical model that estimates whether these legal decisions influenced the amount of money spent by corporate PACs, the corporate elite &ndash;meaning the directors on boards and CEOs, and by the very wealthy.  The figures below provide graphically a very simple response.  Contributions per director and CEO clearly increased after the Citizen United and Speechnow.org and the 2014 McCutcheon decisions.  The directors who were "maxed" out in the previous election by how much money they could give were able in the 2012 Presidential cycle to give a lot more.  All three trends merge after 2008: constrained, the very wealthy, and the very wealthy and also  ideological. This raises the question of which of these factors is really explaining the rise in donations.     We estimate next a statistical difference-in-differences model to sort out these effects.  We find that individuals who are very wealthy and very ideological (i.e. either score near 1 or -1 on our political color index) give considerably more than anyone else.  What happens to those who are no longer constrained by the regulatory limits on donations?  The constrained donors tend to be wealthy and also very ideological.  Once the McCutcheon decisions came along, the very wealthy and very ideological directors increased their giving dramatically.  This is only one study that emerged from the NSF-funded research we did on the political color of boards.  We chose this one because it describes a very important feature of politics in the United States.  Because of the very high inequality in wealth and income, there are a few people who have a lot more money than other people.  Interesting enough, most wealthy people don?t give a lot more donations than other corporate elites who are much less wealthy.  A few, though, give a lot, and these individuals are also the least bipartisan in their contributions.   We see this very clearly in the attached figure.  These show the most money contributed by the corporate elite come from the most ideological, either democratic or republican.  And most of the money in the extremes are given by ideological very wealthy people.  So what happened then to the corporations that many legal scholars thought would rapidly increase their contributions to political candidates after Citizens United?  In fact, they did not give much more money through their corporate PACs.  And when they gave, corporations were much more bipartisan than the wealthy corporate elite contributors.  To our surprise, corporations pursue strategies that are relatively centrist (though surely leaning to the political right). That?s why research is good to do.  We found out that Teddy Roosevelt?s world is no longer our world. Corporations are not buying the politicians through campaign donations.       Last Modified: 11/30/2018       Submitted by: Bruce M Kogut]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
