<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Time-Sharing Experiments for the Social Sciences (TESS): Proposal for Renewed Support, 2012-2015</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2787617.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2787617</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brian Humes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhumes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927284</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Time-sharing Experiments for the Social Sciences (TESS) is a platform for conducting social science survey experiments fielded on probability-based samples of United States adults. TESS was established in 2001 and capitalizes on economies of scale to enable scholars from across the social sciences, on a competitive basis, to conduct ground-breaking research on issues of broad theoretical and practical importance. The intellectual merit of TESS is closely connected to its successes in enabling social scientists to collect original population-based experimental data in a timely manner; promoting better understanding of fundamental social, political and economic questions; maximizing financial efficiency by pooling expenses for otherwise separate studies; and offering mentoring and educational resources. The new initiatives extend educational aspects of TESS, broaden TESS' population of proposers, enable TESS to contribute to assessing the value of probability sampling for experimental inference, and enhance the review process to ensure the highest quality studies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of TESS are wide-ranging. Since its inception, TESS has provided more than 400 social, behavioral, and economic researchers with the opportunity to conduct original experiments, testing a broad range of innovative hypotheses. Proposals are solicited on a continuous basis, undergo rigorous peer review, and involve Internet-based data collection with a representative national sample. The project provides an enormous gain in efficiency since costs of sampling, data collection, and data management are distributed across studies. To date, TESS has conducted over 270 population-based experiments, across disciplines including sociology, psychology, political science, communication, economics, judgment and decision making, law, public health, communication, psychiatry, and others.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By providing a common platform for population based experiments, TESS efficiently enables innovative scholars to identify causal dynamics that advance knowledge on topics such as investment behavior, judicial legitimacy, voting turnout, trust, and many more. TESS also facilitates methodological advances to topics such as the effects of web-tracking on survey response and the optimal ways to measure sensitive attitudes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TESS promotes teaching, training, and learning at the undergraduate and graduate levels. Students regularly submit proposals, many of which are funded. Even when not funded, however, students receive detailed feedback on their research at the critical design stage. TESS broadens the participation of underrepresented groups, both as investigators and research participants. At the heart of TESS' mission is the democratization of access to high quality, original experimental data, thereby putting the power of population-based experiments in the hands of researchers from all backgrounds, all academic institutions, and all career stages. And because the TESS data collection platform involves a representative sample, the results of TESS projects reflect the broad diversity of the United States.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1227179</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Druckman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James N Druckman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>druckman@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474755089</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000110424</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Dennis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John M Dennis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dennis-michael@norc.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6504212048</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000373476</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/30/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Freese</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeremy Freese</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jfreese@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507231881</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000083654</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wendy</FirstName>
<LastName>Mansfield</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wendy Mansfield</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wendy.mansfield@gfk.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2026860933</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000670044</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602081006</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 University Pl., #241]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>Social Psychology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1333</Code>
<Text>Methodology, Measuremt &amp; Stats</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1371</Code>
<Text>Political Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7726</Code>
<Text>Data Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>SoO-Science Of Organizations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~2787617</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goal of Time-sharing Experiments for the Social Sciences (TESS) is to facilitate the implementation of survey experiments across the social sciences (<a href="http://tessexperiments.org/">http://tessexperiments.org/</a>).. It does this by running studies using a nationally representative probability sample. Researchers submit applications to conduct experiments; we send them out for review and accept those that are most compelling. We also had a number of special competitions that particularly targeted younger scholars. Finally, there is a substantial teaching aspect as many students are involved.</p> <p>The project implemented 121 distinct survey experiments. Studies ran the full gamut of the social sciences (e.g., cognitive science, anthropology, economics, health, communication studies, psychology, political science, sociology, etc.).&nbsp; The studies have resulted in dozens of publications throughout the social and cognitive sciences. As part of the project, the PIs also compared various types of samples in order to advance our knowledge about when a probability sample is worth the investment. Another accomplishment comes the infrastructure. TESS is unique because it has a record of all applications (failed and successful) and a record of what accepted projects led to a publication.&nbsp; This has enabled researchers to explore publication bias in the social sciences &ndash; that is, a bias towards only publishing successful results.</p> <p>TESS also makes all stimuli, surveys, and data public one year after data collection. This offers researchers an unparalleled resource for developing studies that build on past work, re-analyzing data, and replicating extant work. We are aware of multiple graduate courses around the country that have made use of these resources by having students replicate past studies or re-analyze extant TESS data. In this sense, TESS has been at the forefront of the trend in social science towards transparency and replication.</p> <p>The project has employed nearly a dozen students who have learned about social science experimentation. In sum, TESS has generated an enormous amount of publically available data for social scientists, targeted younger scholars in particular, and helped educate students about social science research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/02/2017<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;N&nbsp;Druckman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goal of Time-sharing Experiments for the Social Sciences (TESS) is to facilitate the implementation of survey experiments across the social sciences (http://tessexperiments.org/).. It does this by running studies using a nationally representative probability sample. Researchers submit applications to conduct experiments; we send them out for review and accept those that are most compelling. We also had a number of special competitions that particularly targeted younger scholars. Finally, there is a substantial teaching aspect as many students are involved.  The project implemented 121 distinct survey experiments. Studies ran the full gamut of the social sciences (e.g., cognitive science, anthropology, economics, health, communication studies, psychology, political science, sociology, etc.).  The studies have resulted in dozens of publications throughout the social and cognitive sciences. As part of the project, the PIs also compared various types of samples in order to advance our knowledge about when a probability sample is worth the investment. Another accomplishment comes the infrastructure. TESS is unique because it has a record of all applications (failed and successful) and a record of what accepted projects led to a publication.  This has enabled researchers to explore publication bias in the social sciences &ndash; that is, a bias towards only publishing successful results.  TESS also makes all stimuli, surveys, and data public one year after data collection. This offers researchers an unparalleled resource for developing studies that build on past work, re-analyzing data, and replicating extant work. We are aware of multiple graduate courses around the country that have made use of these resources by having students replicate past studies or re-analyze extant TESS data. In this sense, TESS has been at the forefront of the trend in social science towards transparency and replication.  The project has employed nearly a dozen students who have learned about social science experimentation. In sum, TESS has generated an enormous amount of publically available data for social scientists, targeted younger scholars in particular, and helped educate students about social science research.          Last Modified: 09/02/2017       Submitted by: James N Druckman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
