<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Geographic and Occupational Mobility During the Great Depression</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>119816.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>119816</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kgyimahb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927466</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In the aftermath of the recent financial crisis, housing market bust, and recession, there has been increased scholarly interest in trends in geographic mobility in the U.S., and especially in the behavior of mobility during times of economic fluctuation. Mounting evidence points to a downward trend in geographic mobility in the U.S. exacerbated in multiple ways by the economic downturn. Recent work indicates that, since World War II, mobility has typically declined during recessions and that over the past several years housing market factors such as negative equity, mortgage lock-in, and property tax lock-in exert a strong negative effect on household mobility.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If indeed the "Great Recession" has seen a cyclical fall in geographic mobility, it would shed light on the slow nature of the current recovery in employment growth and carry important implications for policy-making. For instance, since late 2009, there has been in increase in the ratio of job openings to unemployed workers. In normal times, an increase in the number of job openings would be accompanied by a fall in the unemployment rate, but for the past two years there has been essentially no associated fall in unemployment. One hypothesis suggests that this may be evidence of "mismatch" in the labor market: an inability of firms to hire workers who would otherwise move to find work, due to an unusually strong reduction in mobility rates brought on by the unusually strong recession. Determining the importance of mismatch in explaining the slow recovery of unemployment rates in the past three recessions, and especially the Great Recession, is a significant ongoing subject of economic research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aim of this research project is to understand the effects of the Great Depression on geographic and occupational mobility in the U.S. during the 1930s. This research project will contribute to our understanding of the economics and history of the Depression itself and to our understanding of the effect of economic fluctuations on mobility generally by exploring the effects of the Great Depression on geographic and occupational mobility in the U.S. during the decade of the 1930s. To achieve these goals, the PI along with a team of undergraduate research collaborators will construct and analyze a rich new data source that will allow us to explore these issues in fundamentally new ways. What is currently known about geographic mobility during the Depression comes from the population censuses of the early twentieth century, an imperfect source for studying mobility and migration, as it depends on the observation of children's birthplaces to infer changes of location; and is therefore restricted to married men with young children. This group is not representative of the entire population, or of the sub-population with highest mobility rates: the young, single, and/or childless.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recently, new data sources and empirical techniques have dramatically increased our ability to study mobility in an historical time frame. The research project proposed here would exploit these new techniques and new data from the 1940 census that has become available in the spring of 2012 in order to construct linked panel datasets spanning the Depression decade and the two previous decades.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1227295</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Long</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason M Long</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jason.long@wheaton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6307525033</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000219208</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wheaton College</Name>
<CityName>Wheaton</CityName>
<ZipCode>601874919</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6307525833</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>501 College Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068605054</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF WHEATON COLLEGE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068605054</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wheaton College]]></Name>
<CityName>Wheaton</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>601875593</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[501 College Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~119816</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this research project is to understand broadly the impact of the Great Depression on geographic and occupational mobility in the U.S. A particular point of emphasis has been to provide the first rigorous, systematic empirical study of the Dust Bowl migration, certainly the most famous episode of internal migration within the U.S. during the Depression and perhaps in all of U.S. history. While research on the national impact of the Depression is ongoing, our analysis of the Dust Bowl migration is complete. Most of our findings contradict long-standing perceptions.</p> <p>As expected, we find that migration rates were much higher in the Dust Bowl than elsewhere in the U.S. This difference is due to the fact that individuals who were typically unlikely to move (e.g., those with young children, those living in their birth state) were equally likely to move in the Dust Bowl. While this result of elevated mobility conforms to expectation, our other principal findings contradict prevalent and durable perceptions of the Dust Bowl. First, relative to other occupations, farmers in the Dust Bowl were the least likely to move; this relationship between mobility and occupation was unique to that region. Second, out-migration rates from the Dust Bowl region were only slightly higher than they were in the 1920s. Hence, the depopulation of the Dust Bowl was due largely to a sharp drop in migration inflows. Dust Bowl migrants were no more likely to move to California than migrants from other parts of the U.S., or those from the same region ten years prior. In this sense, the westward push from the Dust Bowl to California was unexceptional. Finally, migration from the Dust Bowl was not associated with long-lasting negative labor market effects, and for farmers, the effects were positive.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;Further exploration of the impact of the Great Depression on mobility in the U.S. will be possible with the five significant new datasets that were constructed through this project. Nationally representative samples of men were linked across four decades of census data &ndash; 27,835 individuals in all, linked from 1910 to 1920, 1920 to 1930, and 1930 to 1940. To study the Dust Bowl, an additional 4,839 men from the most severely affected counties were linked from the 1930 to the 1940 census, and 2,090 men living in those same counties in 1920 were linked to the 1930 census.</p> <p>&nbsp;The project has had broader impact beyond the research findings. This research was very much undergraduate-oriented. Research carried out by eleven different undergraduate students at Wheaton over the course of the project was integral to the project. Student research collaborators, under the supervision and instruction of the PI, were responsible for the nominal linkage of individuals between the censuses, using existing samples of individual records from the 1930 and 1920 censuses and a Web-based resource allowing the researcher to search for individuals in the censuses from 1910-1940. Creating new data is a hallmark of original research in economic history; working on this project allowed students to engage directly in the process of economic history research and augmented their education in a way not possible inside the traditional classroom setting. All of the students gained valuable experience, and two have or are planning to continue on to graduate education in economics.</p> <p>&nbsp;An important contribution of the research is the creation of the five new datasets, which eventually will be made available to the broader academic community and will be useful to scholars in a variety of disciplines. The cross-disciplinary nature of this research should be of interest not only to a wide audience of economists &ndash; in particular to economic historians, macroeconomists, and labor economists &ndash; but also to scholars outside of economics, particularly American historians and sociologists. The Dust Bowl is a famous, enduring part of the story of American history. It is an episode of broad interest outside academia. We hope that eventually our research will change the way the Dust Bowl and Great Depression are understood broadly by Americans.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Jason&nbsp;M&nbsp;Long</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this research project is to understand broadly the impact of the Great Depression on geographic and occupational mobility in the U.S. A particular point of emphasis has been to provide the first rigorous, systematic empirical study of the Dust Bowl migration, certainly the most famous episode of internal migration within the U.S. during the Depression and perhaps in all of U.S. history. While research on the national impact of the Depression is ongoing, our analysis of the Dust Bowl migration is complete. Most of our findings contradict long-standing perceptions.  As expected, we find that migration rates were much higher in the Dust Bowl than elsewhere in the U.S. This difference is due to the fact that individuals who were typically unlikely to move (e.g., those with young children, those living in their birth state) were equally likely to move in the Dust Bowl. While this result of elevated mobility conforms to expectation, our other principal findings contradict prevalent and durable perceptions of the Dust Bowl. First, relative to other occupations, farmers in the Dust Bowl were the least likely to move; this relationship between mobility and occupation was unique to that region. Second, out-migration rates from the Dust Bowl region were only slightly higher than they were in the 1920s. Hence, the depopulation of the Dust Bowl was due largely to a sharp drop in migration inflows. Dust Bowl migrants were no more likely to move to California than migrants from other parts of the U.S., or those from the same region ten years prior. In this sense, the westward push from the Dust Bowl to California was unexceptional. Finally, migration from the Dust Bowl was not associated with long-lasting negative labor market effects, and for farmers, the effects were positive.    Further exploration of the impact of the Great Depression on mobility in the U.S. will be possible with the five significant new datasets that were constructed through this project. Nationally representative samples of men were linked across four decades of census data &ndash; 27,835 individuals in all, linked from 1910 to 1920, 1920 to 1930, and 1930 to 1940. To study the Dust Bowl, an additional 4,839 men from the most severely affected counties were linked from the 1930 to the 1940 census, and 2,090 men living in those same counties in 1920 were linked to the 1930 census.   The project has had broader impact beyond the research findings. This research was very much undergraduate-oriented. Research carried out by eleven different undergraduate students at Wheaton over the course of the project was integral to the project. Student research collaborators, under the supervision and instruction of the PI, were responsible for the nominal linkage of individuals between the censuses, using existing samples of individual records from the 1930 and 1920 censuses and a Web-based resource allowing the researcher to search for individuals in the censuses from 1910-1940. Creating new data is a hallmark of original research in economic history; working on this project allowed students to engage directly in the process of economic history research and augmented their education in a way not possible inside the traditional classroom setting. All of the students gained valuable experience, and two have or are planning to continue on to graduate education in economics.   An important contribution of the research is the creation of the five new datasets, which eventually will be made available to the broader academic community and will be useful to scholars in a variety of disciplines. The cross-disciplinary nature of this research should be of interest not only to a wide audience of economists &ndash; in particular to economic historians, macroeconomists, and labor economists &ndash; but also to scholars outside of economics, particularly American historians and sociologists. The Dust Bowl is a famous, enduring part of the story of American history. It is an episode of broad interest outside academia. We hope that eventually our research will change the way the Dust Bowl and Great Depression are understood broadly by Americans.       Last Modified: 11/29/2016       Submitted by: Jason M Long]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
