<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Justice During Civil Conflict</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>74575.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74575</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan Gould</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Justice and rule-of-law measures have often been touted as a solution to prevent the resumption&lt;br/&gt;of violence following conflict; yet little work has been undertaken to understand the prevalence&lt;br/&gt;of these practices while conflict remains ongoing. These measures include trials, truth&lt;br/&gt;commissions, reparations, as well as alternative accountability processes such as amnesties,&lt;br/&gt;purges, and exiles. While existing research has focused on the implementation of justice&lt;br/&gt;processes once conflict has ended, pilot data by the PIs suggests that these same practices are&lt;br/&gt;often implemented during violence. The current state of the literature provides little theoretical&lt;br/&gt;understanding as to when and why during-conflict justice processes are implemented and their&lt;br/&gt;likely effect on the duration of conflict and durability of peace.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates the implementation of during-conflict justice to understand which&lt;br/&gt;processes, if any, a government implements during internal armed conflicts and in which&lt;br/&gt;contexts such processes are pursued. Through the collection of a new cross-national dataset&lt;br/&gt;covering the implementation of justice measures during all civil wars since the Second World&lt;br/&gt;War, this research greatly improves our understanding of the presence of during-conflict justice&lt;br/&gt;and expands the current state of research on both the implementation of justice processes and the&lt;br/&gt;dynamics of conflict more broadly. This project provides an evidentiary basis to determine the&lt;br/&gt;conditions under which implementation is more likely, to facilitate the development of these&lt;br/&gt;conditions in countries that may benefit from justice measures and to prevent the development of&lt;br/&gt;circumstances detracting from these goals. Furthermore, the results of this research will be used&lt;br/&gt;to understand the potential misuses of justice measures for goals not related to conflict resolution&lt;br/&gt;and promotion of the rule-of-law, leading to more effective conflict termination strategies and&lt;br/&gt;shortening the duration of civil conflict.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1227985</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cyanne</FirstName>
<LastName>Loyle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cyanne E Loyle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cel5432@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148657515</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000610621</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>West Virginia University Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Morgantown</CityName>
<ZipCode>265066845</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3042933998</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 6845</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>WV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>191510239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WEST VIRGINIA UNIVERSITY RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[West Virginia University]]></Name>
<CityName>Morgantown</CityName>
<StateCode>WV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>265066317</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[316 Woodburn Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LSS-Law And Social Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~74575</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our research has provided important knowledge about how, why and when governments and rebel groups implement justice processes during armed conflict. To this end we have collected the definitive global, cross-national dataset on the use of during-conflict justice (DCJ). By DCJ we refer to a judicial or quasi-judicial process initiated during an internal armed conflict that attempts to address wrongdoings that have taken or are taking place as part of that conflict. In particular, we examined processes such as human rights trials, truth commissions, reparation programs, amnesties, exiles and purges. Whereas these processes commonly have been expected to be implemented after armed conflict has ended, as a means to establish accountability and rule-of-law in post-conflict societies, our research has demonstrated that similar processes are initiated in the midst of armed conflict, occasionally with less noble aims.</p> <p>The During-Conflict Justice dataset catalogues justice processes across 204 internal armed conflicts in 108 countries between 1946 and 2011. The dataset includes a total of 2205 during-conflict justice processes. Among the countries experiencing conflict, 76% used at least one form of DCJ and 65% initiated two or more processes. Given the level of detail in our coding of DCJ processes, we also know what types of processes are used, who and how many individuals are targeted, whether the process was only promised or in fact implemented, in addition to specific descriptions of each DCJ process. For example, we know that 25% of all trials initiated during armed conflict involved a death sentence, 20% of the registered truth commissions and commissions of inquiry never released any report describing their findings, and half (49%) of all amnesties granted were limited to certain crimes, time periods, or perpetrators.</p> <p>This knowledge can be used to examine the impact of the justice processes, in particular on conflict intensity and duration, willingness to negotiate, reconciliation and general level of hostility in conflict-ridden societies. In our analyses we find that the decision to use DCJ during conflict is impacted by regime type and the relative strength of the government vis-&agrave;-vis the rebel group. We also find evidence that the government and rebel use of DCJ is correlated with a reduction in battle deaths while the conflict is ongoing and some DCJ lead to an increased likelihood of the conflict being terminated with a negotiated settlement. Ultimately, our research project provides practitioners and policy makers with information necessary to assist war torn countries to bring a more rapid end conflict.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/15/2015<br>      Modified by: Cyanne&nbsp;Loyle</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our research has provided important knowledge about how, why and when governments and rebel groups implement justice processes during armed conflict. To this end we have collected the definitive global, cross-national dataset on the use of during-conflict justice (DCJ). By DCJ we refer to a judicial or quasi-judicial process initiated during an internal armed conflict that attempts to address wrongdoings that have taken or are taking place as part of that conflict. In particular, we examined processes such as human rights trials, truth commissions, reparation programs, amnesties, exiles and purges. Whereas these processes commonly have been expected to be implemented after armed conflict has ended, as a means to establish accountability and rule-of-law in post-conflict societies, our research has demonstrated that similar processes are initiated in the midst of armed conflict, occasionally with less noble aims.  The During-Conflict Justice dataset catalogues justice processes across 204 internal armed conflicts in 108 countries between 1946 and 2011. The dataset includes a total of 2205 during-conflict justice processes. Among the countries experiencing conflict, 76% used at least one form of DCJ and 65% initiated two or more processes. Given the level of detail in our coding of DCJ processes, we also know what types of processes are used, who and how many individuals are targeted, whether the process was only promised or in fact implemented, in addition to specific descriptions of each DCJ process. For example, we know that 25% of all trials initiated during armed conflict involved a death sentence, 20% of the registered truth commissions and commissions of inquiry never released any report describing their findings, and half (49%) of all amnesties granted were limited to certain crimes, time periods, or perpetrators.  This knowledge can be used to examine the impact of the justice processes, in particular on conflict intensity and duration, willingness to negotiate, reconciliation and general level of hostility in conflict-ridden societies. In our analyses we find that the decision to use DCJ during conflict is impacted by regime type and the relative strength of the government vis-&agrave;-vis the rebel group. We also find evidence that the government and rebel use of DCJ is correlated with a reduction in battle deaths while the conflict is ongoing and some DCJ lead to an increased likelihood of the conflict being terminated with a negotiated settlement. Ultimately, our research project provides practitioners and policy makers with information necessary to assist war torn countries to bring a more rapid end conflict.           Last Modified: 12/15/2015       Submitted by: Cyanne Loyle]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
