<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Graphics Processor Unit-Accelerated High Performance Computer for Astrophysics, Computer Science, and Broad Numerical Research at the University of Arizona</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1270933.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1270933</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Neff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jneff@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922475</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Due to the ongoing rapid increase in computing power, computer simulations and models of large numbers of particles (from atoms to stars) has become a powerful means of verifying theories of how large aggregates of matter form and evolve.  It is now possible for literally trillions of objects to be followed in a computer as they are influenced by varying environmental conditions (gravity, pressure, density, temperature as well as the presence of dust, gas, strong magnetic fields, and even dark matter). These simulations show us how stars, planets, and galaxies may have formed, evolved, and died either quietly or in a violent explosion such as a Super Nova.  These computer simulations are valuable tools for scientists and they also enable the computer programmers to produce "visualizations" (essentially movies, in 2- or 3-D) of these same phenomenon that are now widely used to show complex interactions on a computer monitor or projector screen to be enjoyed by all.  Highly popular computer games and science fiction movies have driven the digital electronics industry to create "graphics processing units" that can very rapidly and efficiently manipulate digital pictures.  Such GPUs are now common in smart phones, game consoles, and personal computers.  On a much larger scale, scientists are now using GPUs in addition to the more traditional Central Processing Units (CPUs) of early computer days, to make large parallel processing machines (with hundreds of GPUs and CPUs) of very high power and speed to perform these complex calculations and manipulations. Dr. Brant Robertson of the University of Arizona is leading a team who will put together such a computer cluster to answer questions in theoretical astrophysics. The new high performance computer will also be available for general use by faculty and students at the University.  Funding for this computer is provided by NSF's Division of Astronomical Sciences through the Major Research Instrumentation program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1228509</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Feryal</FirstName>
<LastName>Ozel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Feryal Ozel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fozel@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206217096</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000154615</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dimitrios</FirstName>
<LastName>Psaltis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dimitrios Psaltis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dpsaltis@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206268846</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000297505</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Cohen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul R Cohen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cohen@sista.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206262818</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000460339</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Derek</FirstName>
<LastName>Masseth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Derek A Masseth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmasseth@suncorridor.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6025433291</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000614823</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brant</FirstName>
<LastName>Robertson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brant E Robertson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brant@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8314594903</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000605623</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072459266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7697</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1270933</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1"><span class="s1">The NSF-funded El Gato supercomputer has enabled a new era of computational science for more than a hundred researchers at the University of Arizona (UA). The project led by Principal Investigator Brant Robertson (now at University of California, Santa Cruz) provided a Top500 supercomputer to UA students, staff, and faculty in disciplines ranging from astrophysics to DNA sequencing. The El Gato system was based on cutting edge computational architectures, including NVIDIA graphics processing units and Intel Xeon Phi coprocessors, and allowed for the engineering of massively parallel scientific codes. Notably, the El Gato facility incubated the development of the Computational Hydrodynamics On paraLLel Architectures (CHOLLA) code by Robertson&rsquo;s student Evan Schneider, who created CHOLLA as part of her thesis work at UA. CHOLLA has been proven as one of the fastest and most scalable codes for simulating astrophysical hydrodynamics yet devised, and has been deployed on the world&rsquo;s largest supercomputers to perform some of the largest astrophysical hydrodynamical simulations to date. In astrophysical applications, PI Robertson has used El Gato to study topics from the formation of dark matter structures to supersonic turbulence. These simulations performed on El Gato will provide crucial new insight to important astrophysical phenomena. El Gato has also served as a training ground for researchers to learn massively parallel computing techniques, furthering both their research and extending the broader impact of El Gato project by preparing scientists for new discoveries with advanced future computational facilities.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/03/2015<br>      Modified by: Brant&nbsp;E&nbsp;Robertson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1228509/1228509_10205877_1441310918259_kh--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1228509/1228509_10205877_1441310918259_kh--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Ultra High Definition Simulation of the Kelvin Helmoltz Instability"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1228509/1228509_10205877_1441310918259_kh--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Ultra High Definition Simulation of the Kelvin Helmoltz Instability"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This Ultra High Definition simulation (3840 x 2160 cells) of the Kelvin-Helmholtz instability demonstrates the power of the El Gato supercomputer and the CHOLLA hydrodynamics code. Massively parallel calculations will enable new insights into long-standing astrophysical problems.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Evan Schneider (UA) and Brant Robertson (UCSC)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Brant&nbsp;E&nbsp;Robertson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Ultra High Definition Simulation of the Kelvin Helmoltz Instability</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1228509/1228509_10205877_1441310586601_elgato--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1228509/1228509_10205877_1441310586601_elgato--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The El Gato Supercomputer at the University of Arizona"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1228509/1228509_10205877_1441310586601_elgato--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The El Gato Supercomputer at the University of Arizona"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The El Gato superco...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The NSF-funded El Gato supercomputer has enabled a new era of computational science for more than a hundred researchers at the University of Arizona (UA). The project led by Principal Investigator Brant Robertson (now at University of California, Santa Cruz) provided a Top500 supercomputer to UA students, staff, and faculty in disciplines ranging from astrophysics to DNA sequencing. The El Gato system was based on cutting edge computational architectures, including NVIDIA graphics processing units and Intel Xeon Phi coprocessors, and allowed for the engineering of massively parallel scientific codes. Notably, the El Gato facility incubated the development of the Computational Hydrodynamics On paraLLel Architectures (CHOLLA) code by RobertsonÆs student Evan Schneider, who created CHOLLA as part of her thesis work at UA. CHOLLA has been proven as one of the fastest and most scalable codes for simulating astrophysical hydrodynamics yet devised, and has been deployed on the worldÆs largest supercomputers to perform some of the largest astrophysical hydrodynamical simulations to date. In astrophysical applications, PI Robertson has used El Gato to study topics from the formation of dark matter structures to supersonic turbulence. These simulations performed on El Gato will provide crucial new insight to important astrophysical phenomena. El Gato has also served as a training ground for researchers to learn massively parallel computing techniques, furthering both their research and extending the broader impact of El Gato project by preparing scientists for new discoveries with advanced future computational facilities.          Last Modified: 09/03/2015       Submitted by: Brant E Robertson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
