<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a State-of-the-Art Small Angle X-Ray Scattering (SAXS) Instrument for Research and Education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>568398.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>568398</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leonard Spinu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lspinu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922665</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award to the University of Connecticut is for the acquisition of a versatile Small-angle X-ray Scattering (SAXS) instrument that can also be used for wide-angle and grazing-angle scattering measurements.  SAXS is a powerful tool for the characterization of structures at length scales from a few to a few hundred nanometers.  It provides information on the shape, size, molecular weight, polydispersity, and interparticle interactions of materials.  This instrument will further ongoing research in polymer science, molecular biology, pharmaceutical science, nanomaterials, and energy research.  It will be used to answers fundamental questions, such as: What is the ordering of inorganic templates and catalysts?  How does the structure of various targeted drug carriers affect their function?  What factors control the associations of bio-derived building blocks?  And, how do structures form in molecular assemblies? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The SAXS instrument will be housed in a shared user facility, which provides access to researchers across campus as well as local industry.  It will enable research projects that improve health care, develop more efficient sources of energy, and produce materials with superior properties. The instrument will be used to train the next generation of scientists through hands-on research experiences for undergraduate students, graduate students, and post-docs, as well as classroom demonstrations in structural characterization courses.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1228817</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Cole</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James L Cole</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>james.cole@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8604864333</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000184637</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Adamson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas H Adamson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Adamson@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8604864716</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000294315</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mu-Ping</FirstName>
<LastName>Nieh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mu-Ping Nieh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mu-ping.nieh@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8604868708</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000575732</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Unit 1133]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>614209054</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004534830</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Connecticut]]></Name>
<CityName>storrs</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[438 Whitney Road Ext.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1750</Code>
<Text>MPS DMR INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~568398</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The&nbsp;newly acquired small/wide angle X-ray scattering (S/WAXS) instrument, Bruker NANOSTAR, acquired through the NSF MRI grant, is a rotating-anode high-flux machine with a high-resolution 2-D detector, and an image plate detecting system. The NANOSTAR contains versatile sample environments including a temperature-controlled stage, shear and tensile cells, and a grazing-incident SAXS stage. SAXS reveals the global (i.e, whole-sample), instead of the local, nano-structures of the examined materials; allowing it to serve as a complementary method for electron microscopy. The NANOSTAR is currently located at and maintained by the Institute of Materials Science (IMS) at the University of Connecticut (UCONN). The acquisition of the NANOSTAR has served many functions.</p> <p>First, the instrument&nbsp;provides the in-house&nbsp;capability&nbsp;for faculty members at UCONN to perform material nano-structural characterization to further their understanding in many scientific disciplines (e.g., materials, biology, physics and chemistry). Interdisciplinary collaborations were fostered due to the accessibility of this new technique, allowing experts in different research fields to work with scattering experts in structural analysis. Therefore, structure-function relationships can be better understood. Moreover, this capability allows the researchers to screen the samples, avoiding unnecessary trips to national synchrotron scattering facilities, resulting in more efficient use of the faculty&rsquo;s research time and the resources provided by the infrastructures. As of now, the SAXS instrument has benefited more than 25 graduate students in their research activities supported by at least 5 grant proposals.</p> <p>Another major function of this SAXS instrument is to enhance the UCONN facilities for education and equip next generation scientists and engineers with the experience of utilizing advanced instruments. Every year, there are four UCONN courses, which discuss and introduce the scattering techniques, offered by the faculty, to the students (mostly graduate students). Prior to acquisition of the SAXS instrument, scattering was only taught in the classroom without practice. After receiving this new instrument, students can now obtain hands-on experience through usage of the instrument. Ever since the instrument was procured, the total number of students enrolled in the four courses has exceeded 100. There are at least 3 master theses and 1 PhD thesis associated with the application of SAXS.</p> <p>Moreover, IMS has an outreach program to help companies called the Affiliate Program. The new SAXS capability has strengthened the relationship between UCONN and its industrial partners. The PI (Nieh) initiated the first webinar (<a href="http://www.ims.uconn.edu/2015/08/17/ims-holds-first-webinar-concerning-small-angle-x-ray-scattering/">http://www.ims.uconn.edu/2015/08/17/ims-holds-first-webinar-concerning-small-angle-x-ray-scattering/</a>) introducing how to apply SAXS for material characterization to the industry in Aug. 2015. As of now, more than 5 companies have used the UCONN SAXS facility to investigate the nanostructure of their products. Consequently, the obtained results are used to improve their manufacturing processes and material designs.</p> <p>This UCONN SAXS capability facilitates many important research topics which are often disseminated to national and international scientific communities through presentations and publications. Since 2013, there have been at least 5 journal publications,16 invited talks, and 15 conference contributions associated with the application of the SAXS capability.</p> <p>IMS will continue to commit in research and educational efforts in the area of structural characterization through existing instruments including this MRI-funded NANOSTAR. The future objectives are to utilize these techniques to attract more users (both academic ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The newly acquired small/wide angle X-ray scattering (S/WAXS) instrument, Bruker NANOSTAR, acquired through the NSF MRI grant, is a rotating-anode high-flux machine with a high-resolution 2-D detector, and an image plate detecting system. The NANOSTAR contains versatile sample environments including a temperature-controlled stage, shear and tensile cells, and a grazing-incident SAXS stage. SAXS reveals the global (i.e, whole-sample), instead of the local, nano-structures of the examined materials; allowing it to serve as a complementary method for electron microscopy. The NANOSTAR is currently located at and maintained by the Institute of Materials Science (IMS) at the University of Connecticut (UCONN). The acquisition of the NANOSTAR has served many functions.  First, the instrument provides the in-house capability for faculty members at UCONN to perform material nano-structural characterization to further their understanding in many scientific disciplines (e.g., materials, biology, physics and chemistry). Interdisciplinary collaborations were fostered due to the accessibility of this new technique, allowing experts in different research fields to work with scattering experts in structural analysis. Therefore, structure-function relationships can be better understood. Moreover, this capability allows the researchers to screen the samples, avoiding unnecessary trips to national synchrotron scattering facilities, resulting in more efficient use of the facultyÆs research time and the resources provided by the infrastructures. As of now, the SAXS instrument has benefited more than 25 graduate students in their research activities supported by at least 5 grant proposals.  Another major function of this SAXS instrument is to enhance the UCONN facilities for education and equip next generation scientists and engineers with the experience of utilizing advanced instruments. Every year, there are four UCONN courses, which discuss and introduce the scattering techniques, offered by the faculty, to the students (mostly graduate students). Prior to acquisition of the SAXS instrument, scattering was only taught in the classroom without practice. After receiving this new instrument, students can now obtain hands-on experience through usage of the instrument. Ever since the instrument was procured, the total number of students enrolled in the four courses has exceeded 100. There are at least 3 master theses and 1 PhD thesis associated with the application of SAXS.  Moreover, IMS has an outreach program to help companies called the Affiliate Program. The new SAXS capability has strengthened the relationship between UCONN and its industrial partners. The PI (Nieh) initiated the first webinar (http://www.ims.uconn.edu/2015/08/17/ims-holds-first-webinar-concerning-small-angle-x-ray-scattering/) introducing how to apply SAXS for material characterization to the industry in Aug. 2015. As of now, more than 5 companies have used the UCONN SAXS facility to investigate the nanostructure of their products. Consequently, the obtained results are used to improve their manufacturing processes and material designs.  This UCONN SAXS capability facilitates many important research topics which are often disseminated to national and international scientific communities through presentations and publications. Since 2013, there have been at least 5 journal publications,16 invited talks, and 15 conference contributions associated with the application of the SAXS capability.  IMS will continue to commit in research and educational efforts in the area of structural characterization through existing instruments including this MRI-funded NANOSTAR. The future objectives are to utilize these techniques to attract more users (both academic and industrial) and to eventually form a center for nano-structural characterization in the New England area.          Last Modified: 11/27/2015       Submitted by: Mu-Ping Nieh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
