<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Utilizing smartphones as experimental interventions for job search and employment at reentry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>32200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>32200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan Gould</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Finding work in the immediate months after release from prison has been identified as a key factor for reducing recidivism and promoting successful reentry. Scholarship has documented the extensive barriers that individuals with criminal records likely encounter while searching for work; however, we know little about actual job search experiences at reentry and what factors lead to successful employment. Prior research has been limited by traditional data collection methods, which are particularly inadequate for studying poor and mobile groups. Using smartphones, this project will collect detailed information about reentry and job search experiences among men recently released from prison. Surveys will be sent to participants via smartphones twice a day for three months and an Android-based application will passively collect information on participants? geographic mobility and call logs. The project will experimentally test the importance of participating in a peer-based text forum for job leads and social support via the smartphones, as opposed to receiving job leads directly from the researcher. Prior scholarship has established the importance of social contacts for providing information and influence during job search; for individuals with fewer ties to the formal labor market, social support and motivation provided by peers may be particularly important for search persistence. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is timely and policy-relevant, considering the scale of mass incarceration, the numerous challenges faced by individuals recently released from prison, and the mixed outcomes of employment reentry programs. The study capitalizes on recent advances in smartphone technology to study a traditionally hard-to-reach population. The experimental treatment - participation in a group-based text application - tests a potentially important and cost-effective intervention that employment reentry organizations can easily adopt. As part of the project, the researcher will develop an Android application, which includes a web-based interface for nonprogrammers, and will make the application available to social science researchers interested in non-traditional data collection methods.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1228333</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Devah</FirstName>
<LastName>Pager</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Devah Pager</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>devah_pager@harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174960824</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000473576</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Naomi</FirstName>
<LastName>Sugie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Naomi F Sugie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nsugie@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6467344900</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000610866</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085441005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office Pop. Res. Wallace Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LSS-Law And Social Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~32200</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This project utilizes smartphones as experimental interventions to examine job search and employment among individuals recently released from prison. Prior literature describes extensive barriers to employment at reentry; however, we know little about actual job search and work experiences due to the methodological challenges of studying recently released individuals at reentry. Using smartphones, this project collects novel, detailed self-report and observed behavioral information from 135 individuals for three months after prison. It experimentally tests the importance of assignment to a peer-based, text messaging forum for job leads and social support, and it hypothesizes that peer-based support will improve job search persistence and employment outcomes.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Analyses of in-depth self-report and observed behavioral measures suggest that the nature of work among reentering individuals is irregular, precarious, and poor-quality, to a degree that is under-recognized in current scholarship.&nbsp; The findings identify distinct typologies of individuals, where older and disadvantaged jobseekers sustain high levels of search effort with little success at finding employment.&nbsp; In contrast to prevailing notions in reentry scholarship, individuals are not social isolates or deeply distraught about their job searches; rather, they are highly connected to others and feel happier while searching for work.&nbsp; Results from the experimental design suggest that job-seeking peers can potentially provide important sources of social support, motivation, and information for parolees searching for work.&nbsp; Individuals assigned to the peer forum felt happier about their job search and they spent more time searching for work and working.&nbsp; These findings challenge conventional beliefs in the literature on reentry and low-skill jobseekers, which propose that third-party intermediaries are the best sources of job search support.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The project also produced an open-source Android smartphone application for data collection (available at https://github.com/aewalker/Survey-Droid).&nbsp; Unlike most other existing smartphone survey applications, Survey Droid not only sends surveys at designated times but also triggers surveys after observed behaviors (e.g., receiving certain types of phone calls).&nbsp; It also collects observed behaviors through encrypted call logs and location estimates.&nbsp; Social scientists can set the parameters of these functions and design their own data collection projects using a website interface.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong>The project makes several contributions that have the potential to benefit jobseekers who are recently released from prison and reentry service providers, as well as policymakers, stakeholders, and society members who might indirectly profit from improved reentry outcomes.&nbsp; The findings identify three distinct typologies of individuals with uniquely different demographic backgrounds, reentry situations, search patterns, and work experiences.&nbsp; Based on this new knowledge, the project suggests that specific types of reentry employment services should be targeted to these different subgroups, in order to improve the effectiveness of services in a cost-constrained reentry context.&nbsp; The findings from the experimental design further propose that reentry practitioners adopt a specific and low-cost service intervention&mdash;a group-based, text-messaging forum&mdash;that can provide job information in real-time to job-seeking parolees and can potentially offer an impo...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[             This project utilizes smartphones as experimental interventions to examine job search and employment among individuals recently released from prison. Prior literature describes extensive barriers to employment at reentry; however, we know little about actual job search and work experiences due to the methodological challenges of studying recently released individuals at reentry. Using smartphones, this project collects novel, detailed self-report and observed behavioral information from 135 individuals for three months after prison. It experimentally tests the importance of assignment to a peer-based, text messaging forum for job leads and social support, and it hypothesizes that peer-based support will improve job search persistence and employment outcomes.  Intellectual Merit              Analyses of in-depth self-report and observed behavioral measures suggest that the nature of work among reentering individuals is irregular, precarious, and poor-quality, to a degree that is under-recognized in current scholarship.  The findings identify distinct typologies of individuals, where older and disadvantaged jobseekers sustain high levels of search effort with little success at finding employment.  In contrast to prevailing notions in reentry scholarship, individuals are not social isolates or deeply distraught about their job searches; rather, they are highly connected to others and feel happier while searching for work.  Results from the experimental design suggest that job-seeking peers can potentially provide important sources of social support, motivation, and information for parolees searching for work.  Individuals assigned to the peer forum felt happier about their job search and they spent more time searching for work and working.  These findings challenge conventional beliefs in the literature on reentry and low-skill jobseekers, which propose that third-party intermediaries are the best sources of job search support.               The project also produced an open-source Android smartphone application for data collection (available at https://github.com/aewalker/Survey-Droid).  Unlike most other existing smartphone survey applications, Survey Droid not only sends surveys at designated times but also triggers surveys after observed behaviors (e.g., receiving certain types of phone calls).  It also collects observed behaviors through encrypted call logs and location estimates.  Social scientists can set the parameters of these functions and design their own data collection projects using a website interface.  Broader Impacts              The project makes several contributions that have the potential to benefit jobseekers who are recently released from prison and reentry service providers, as well as policymakers, stakeholders, and society members who might indirectly profit from improved reentry outcomes.  The findings identify three distinct typologies of individuals with uniquely different demographic backgrounds, reentry situations, search patterns, and work experiences.  Based on this new knowledge, the project suggests that specific types of reentry employment services should be targeted to these different subgroups, in order to improve the effectiveness of services in a cost-constrained reentry context.  The findings from the experimental design further propose that reentry practitioners adopt a specific and low-cost service intervention&mdash;a group-based, text-messaging forum&mdash;that can provide job information in real-time to job-seeking parolees and can potentially offer an important source of social support and motivation for job search.  The intervention uses a freely available smartphone application&mdash;GroupMe (www.groupme.com)&mdash;that can be relatively easily implemented by reentry service providers.       Last Modified: 10/28/2014       Submitted by: Naomi F Sugie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
