<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI Collaborative: Development of an Intelligent, Autonomous, Unmanned, Mobile Sensor</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1645350.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1645350</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rita Rodriguez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rrodrigu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Proposal #:12- 29236           Collaborative          Proposal #:   12-29250&lt;br/&gt;PI(s): Valavanis, Kimon P.; Gao,David Wenzhong; Mahoor,Mohammad;Rutherford,Matthew J;Yi,Yun-Bo&lt;br/&gt;                                                    and Collab PI(s):  Boussalis, Helen R.; Guillaume, Darrell; Wu, Chivey &lt;br/&gt;Institution:University of Denver     &amp;          and     Collab Institution:      California State-LA University&lt;br/&gt;Title: MRI: Collaborative: Dev. of an Integrated, Intelligent, Autonomous, Unmanned, Mobile Sensor&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project Proposed:&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on the development of an integrated, intelligent, autonomous unmanned mobile sensor will enable research into the foundations of the next generation of autonomous Unmanned Aerial Systems (UAS). The objective of this proposal is to develop an unmanned helicopter (about 150 kg weight) along with a mobile landing platform for refueling purposes. The aircraft would be able to operate with both electric and fuel. The instrument will be composed of two tightly coupled components, a&lt;br/&gt;(i) Novel light-weight unmanned helicopter (&lt;150 Kg), and,&lt;br/&gt;(ii) General purpose landing platform that will also serve as a refueling/recharging station and             data relay/repository. &lt;br/&gt;This composition of the instrument is expected to pave the way for the next generation of multi-purpose/cost-effective UAS into civilian and public domain applications.  The proposed integrated two component instrument development is not considered as an extension of existing technology. It will enable heterogeneous networked unmanned systems operating in unison in traditional/extreme environment. The following specific research projects will be enabled through the instrument:  &lt;br/&gt;- Fault-Tolerant and Emergency Landing Navigation and Control Systems&lt;br/&gt;- RADAR-based Sense-and-Avoid System&lt;br/&gt;- Prognosis and Structural Health Monitoring of UAVs&lt;br/&gt;- Networked Unmanned Systems (NUS)&lt;br/&gt;- Integration: Software Reliability and Security&lt;br/&gt;- Unmanned Helicopters for Civilian/Public and Industrial Applications&lt;br/&gt;The University of Denver (DU) and California State University Los Angeles (CalStU-LA), a predominantly minority-serving institution, collaborate in the project. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;The impact should be felt both regionally and nationally. At the national level, the instrument should initiate transformative advances in the computational algorithms proposed. The results will be made available to the broader research community in the form of open-source codes. Simulations made possible by these algorithms will have broad national and societal impact ranging from climate change scenarios to wind power generation to plant biotechnology and improved animal breeding.&lt;br/&gt;At the institutional and regional levels, DU faculty/students will collaborate with CalStU-LA faculty/students to enhance the ethnic and gender diversity of the student population, especially recruiting minority students.  Project goal include increasing the educational/training opportunities for underrepresented students, and  the number of graduates in STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1229236</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimon</FirstName>
<LastName>Valavanis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimon P Valavanis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kimon.valavanis@du.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3038712586</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000176874</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David Wenzhong</FirstName>
<LastName>Gao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Wenzhong Gao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Wenzhong.Gao@du.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3038713570</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000261962</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yun-Bo</FirstName>
<LastName>Yi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yun-Bo Yi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yyi2@du.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3038712228</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000396603</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohammad</FirstName>
<LastName>Mahoor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mohammad Mahoor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mmahoor@du.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3038713745</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000511471</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Rutherford</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew J Rutherford</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mjr@cs.du.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3038713309</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513064</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Denver</Name>
<CityName>Denver</CityName>
<ZipCode>802104711</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3038712000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2199 S. University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Ofc of Research & Sponsored Prog]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431760</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO SEMINARY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431760</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Denver]]></Name>
<CityName>Denver</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>802105345</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2390 S. York Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1645350</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This MRI-Development proposal focused on custom-building an integrated multi-functional <strong><em>enhanced intelligent mobile sensor</em></strong>, composed of two tightly coupled components, <em>a prototype novel light-weight unmanned helicopter </em>and<em> a general purpose landing platform</em><em> </em>that will also serve as a recharging and data exchange station. The end-result of the project includes: i.) Two different scale landing platforms instead of one. The Generation-2 landing platform, smaller size, is a completely custom-built platform capable of leveling horizontally within 1 degree and operating in slopes up to 25 degrees. It has (solar) panels that open and close for recharging, and is also capable of omni directional motion. Generation-3 landing platform includes an ARGO base vehicle on which a custom-made platform is built. It has payload capability of close to 500 pounds and levels within 1 degree of the environment. ii.) Three different types of UAVs (fuel helicopter, electric helicopter, quadrotor) have been customized. They include onboard sensor suite, flight control system with autopilot and they are capable of vision-based landing, too. As such, the enhanced intelligent mobile sensor ensemble offers flexibility in chosing either one of the landing platforms and UAVs.</p> <p>The intellectual merits of the project center on the developed real-time hardware and software flight control architecture that uses the XMOS technology family of processors, capability of autonomous flight and landing, design and modeling of the landing platforms and providing a coupled and fully functional integrated system.</p> <p>Broader impacts center on promoting the idea of a UGV-UAV mobile sensor for civilian/public domain applications like search and rescue and emergency response, on allowing other groups to use and experiment with the developed prototypes, on engaging undergraduate students in the prjects and on disseminating findings through publications.</p> <p>A major impact of this project is patented technology and patent filing, and also producing a research monograph (book).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2016<br>      Modified by: Kimon&nbsp;P&nbsp;Valavanis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1229236/1229236_10213950_1477596640025_IMG_1048CR--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1229236/1229236_10213950_1477596640025_IMG_1048CR--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Integrated landing platform and electric helicopter"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1229236/1229236_10213950_1477596640025_IMG_1048CR--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Integrated landing platform and electric helicopter"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Figure depicts the Generation-2 in house custom built landing platform with (solar) panels that open and close for recharging, on which helicopters and quadrotors may autonomously land.</div> <div class="imageCredit">MRI-NSF-CNS 1229236</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kimon&nbsp;P&nbsp;Valavanis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Integrated landing platform and electric helicopter</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1229236/1229236_10213950_1477596775884_IMG_1365--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1229236/1229236_10213950_1477596775884_IMG_1365--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Quadrotor autonomous landing"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1229236/1229236_10213950_1477596775884_IMG_1365--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Quadrotor autonomous landing"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Figure depicts autonomous landing on the Generation-2 platform of a custom built quadrotor.</div> <div class="imageCredit">MRI-NSF-CNS 1229236</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kimon&nbsp;P&nbsp;Valavanis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Quadrotor autonomous landing</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1229236/1229236_10213950_1477597029301_IMG_0086--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1229236/1229236_10213950_1477597029301_IMG_0086--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Turbine Industrial Bergen Helicopter"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1229236/1229236_10213950_1477597029301_IMG_0086--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Turbine Industrial Bergen Helicopter"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Figure depicts the fully autonomous Bergen helicopter with the DU2SRI flight control system and autopilot</div> <div class="imageCredit">MRI-NSF-CNS 1229236</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kimon&nbsp;P&nbsp;Valavanis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Turbine Industrial Bergen Helicopter</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1229236/1229236_10213950_1477597739234_20161006_164457--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1229236/1229236_10213950_1477597739234_20161006_164457--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Generation-3 Landing Platform"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1229236/1229236_10213950_1477597739234_20161006_164457--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Generation-3 Landing Platform"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Figure depicts an ARGO UGV base robot on which a landing platform is custom was custom built. The UGV-based landing platform has close to 500 pounds payload capability; helicopters / quadrotors up to 170 Kg may safely land on the platform.</div> <div class="imageCredit">MRI-NSF-CNS 1229236</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kimon&nbsp;P&nbsp;Valavanis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Generation-3 Landing Platform</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This MRI-Development proposal focused on custom-building an integrated multi-functional enhanced intelligent mobile sensor, composed of two tightly coupled components, a prototype novel light-weight unmanned helicopter and a general purpose landing platform that will also serve as a recharging and data exchange station. The end-result of the project includes: i.) Two different scale landing platforms instead of one. The Generation-2 landing platform, smaller size, is a completely custom-built platform capable of leveling horizontally within 1 degree and operating in slopes up to 25 degrees. It has (solar) panels that open and close for recharging, and is also capable of omni directional motion. Generation-3 landing platform includes an ARGO base vehicle on which a custom-made platform is built. It has payload capability of close to 500 pounds and levels within 1 degree of the environment. ii.) Three different types of UAVs (fuel helicopter, electric helicopter, quadrotor) have been customized. They include onboard sensor suite, flight control system with autopilot and they are capable of vision-based landing, too. As such, the enhanced intelligent mobile sensor ensemble offers flexibility in chosing either one of the landing platforms and UAVs.  The intellectual merits of the project center on the developed real-time hardware and software flight control architecture that uses the XMOS technology family of processors, capability of autonomous flight and landing, design and modeling of the landing platforms and providing a coupled and fully functional integrated system.  Broader impacts center on promoting the idea of a UGV-UAV mobile sensor for civilian/public domain applications like search and rescue and emergency response, on allowing other groups to use and experiment with the developed prototypes, on engaging undergraduate students in the prjects and on disseminating findings through publications.  A major impact of this project is patented technology and patent filing, and also producing a research monograph (book).       Last Modified: 10/27/2016       Submitted by: Kimon P Valavanis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
