<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Field Emission Gun Energy Filtered Transmission Electron Microscope</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1050000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1050000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leonard Spinu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lspinu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922665</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award to the University of Massachusetts at Amherst is for the acquisition of a 200kV, field emission gun, in-column energy filtered transmission electron microscope (FEG-EFTEM).   Energy filtering enables superior image contrast by zero-loss filtering and element specific imaging, representing the state-of-the-art in electron microscopy characterization.   The hardware and software components of the proposed FEG-EFTEM include electron tomography capabilities for 3D-reconstruction of nanoscale structures.  Moreover, the instrument includes capabilities for examining cryogenically prepared samples from aqueous solution, appealing for biologically-derived nanostructures and synthetic soft materials in water.  The FEG-EFTEM will impact a broad range of researchers at UMass and partner institutions, and will be available broadly for U.S. and international researchers in numerous disciplines, including polymers, nanocomposites, soft materials, biology, and related topics.  Graduate, undergraduate, and postdoctoral researchers at UMass, representing well over 30 different research groups, will use the FEG-EFTEM in numerous projects, including: characterizing ordered block copolymers as templates for nanostructured materials; imaging polymer aggregation and phase behavior directly in non-volatile ionic liquids; studying helical morphologies of polymer nanorods and wires; understanding phase separation in conjugated polymers and nanocomposites for photovoltaics; imaging bacterial-based fuel cells; and direct imaging of DNA replication. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The new FEG-EFTEM will have extensive impact across numerous communities.  The instrument will be accessible broadly to researchers across the UMass campus, as well as to the local undergraduate Colleges, including all-women's Mt Holyoke and Smith Colleges, and to partner institutions such as Howard University and the University of Puerto Rico - Rio Piedras.   Through the NSF-funded Materials Research Facilities Network (MRFN), the instrument will be accessible to researchers across the U.S., significantly enhancing accessible TEM capabilities of the MRFN.  The instrument will enhance education greatly by serving as a central teaching tool through its integration into core courses in Polymer Characterization and Polymer Morphology, while allowing expansion of curricula with the introduction of a graduate course in Electron Microscopy with extensive hands-on training on the FEG-EFTEM.  Moreover, the FEG-EFTEM will benefit K-12 and Research Experience for Teachers (RET) outreach activities of various NSF and DOE centers at UMass, with electron tomography for 3D-image reconstruction providing an engaging and instructive view of materials that is suitable for integration into classroom instruction for young students.  ASPIRE (A Student-led Program In Research and Education), which brings high school students to campus on Saturdays for a laboratory-based program on polymers, will showcase the 3D-tomographic capabilities of the FEG-EFTEM, thus greatly enhancing the long standing electron microscopy unit for this program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1229302</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Gido</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel P Gido</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gido@mail.pse.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135771216</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000209750</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Russell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas P Russell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>russell@mail.pse.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135771516</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000093208</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
<LastName>Emrick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Todd Emrick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tsemrick@mail.pse.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135771613</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000210963</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Ribbe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander E Ribbe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aeribbe@polysci.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4136587415</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000291443</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michele</FirstName>
<LastName>Klingbeil</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michele M Klingbeil</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>klingbeil@microbio.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135773823</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000550508</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039242</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[70 Butterfield Terrace]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1050000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Transmission Electron Microscopy (TEM) is one of the indispensable tools in modern sciences and technology, allowing the visualization of structure and morphology down to the atomic level. Soft materials as for example synthetic or bio-polymers pose a particular challenge due to their low contrast in high voltage electron microscopy. In order to address those challenges the University of Massachusetts Amherst purchased an Energy Filtered Transmission Electron Microscope (EFTEM), which was installed in the campus wide Electron Microscopy Center. The Microscope was designed as a truly interdisciplinary tool covering applications from soft polymeric materials, which includes both synthetic or biological materials, to hard materials as found in for example semi-conductor or geoscientific research. The field emission electron source provides both high image and spectroscopic resolution. The in-column electron energy loss spectrometer (EELS) and energy dispersive x-ray spectrometer (EDS) on the other hand provide superb analytical capabilities allowing element mapping of both light and heavy elements.</p> <p>The energy filter's probably most remarkable strength is the impact on the contrast of an electron microscopic image. Figure 1 shows an example of the difference in contrast of graphene, a single sheet of carbon atoms, when acquired in unfiltered or zero-loss filtered mode. Zero-loss filtering, which removes so called inelastically scattered electrons, greatly increases the contrast of these atomically thin graphene sheets. This also has far reaching applications in cryo-microscopy where biological samples are imaged in vitrious ice, which naturally have very low contrast.</p> <p>Another unique features of the electron energy loss spectrometer is the ability of determining thicknesses of ultrathin films. Since transmission electron microscopy (TEM) requires film thicknesses on the nanometer scale, it is very difficult to determine the exact thickness of such a film. As an example Figure 2 shows the thickness distribution of a free-standing film of a so-called ionic liquid. The film which is suspended on a carbon mesh (lacey carbon) shows two characteristic structures: A biconcave layer with a thickness of only 15nm in the center and up to 100nm at the edges or a biconvex layer with thicknesses of up to 300nm at the center. These free-standing liquid films can for example be used as medium for molecular dynamics studies.</p> <p>The instrument is further capable of generating electron tomography, which allow for a 3-dimensional reconstruction of the morphology of a thin film through rotating the sample while exposed to the electron beam and recoding a series of projection images, which are used to calculate a space filling model. Figure 3 shows the distribution of gold nanoparticles at the interface of a Polymethylmaethacrylate/Polystyrene blend. The overview images shows the 2-dimnesional projection of the film while the inset shows a perspective view clearly locating the nanparticles at the PMMA/PS interface.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/26/2015<br>      Modified by: Alexander&nbsp;E&nbsp;Ribbe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1229302/1229302_10209312_1443910590173_Figure2IonicLiquid--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1229302/1229302_10209312_1443910590173_Figure2IonicLiquid--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Thickness ma...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Transmission Electron Microscopy (TEM) is one of the indispensable tools in modern sciences and technology, allowing the visualization of structure and morphology down to the atomic level. Soft materials as for example synthetic or bio-polymers pose a particular challenge due to their low contrast in high voltage electron microscopy. In order to address those challenges the University of Massachusetts Amherst purchased an Energy Filtered Transmission Electron Microscope (EFTEM), which was installed in the campus wide Electron Microscopy Center. The Microscope was designed as a truly interdisciplinary tool covering applications from soft polymeric materials, which includes both synthetic or biological materials, to hard materials as found in for example semi-conductor or geoscientific research. The field emission electron source provides both high image and spectroscopic resolution. The in-column electron energy loss spectrometer (EELS) and energy dispersive x-ray spectrometer (EDS) on the other hand provide superb analytical capabilities allowing element mapping of both light and heavy elements.  The energy filter's probably most remarkable strength is the impact on the contrast of an electron microscopic image. Figure 1 shows an example of the difference in contrast of graphene, a single sheet of carbon atoms, when acquired in unfiltered or zero-loss filtered mode. Zero-loss filtering, which removes so called inelastically scattered electrons, greatly increases the contrast of these atomically thin graphene sheets. This also has far reaching applications in cryo-microscopy where biological samples are imaged in vitrious ice, which naturally have very low contrast.  Another unique features of the electron energy loss spectrometer is the ability of determining thicknesses of ultrathin films. Since transmission electron microscopy (TEM) requires film thicknesses on the nanometer scale, it is very difficult to determine the exact thickness of such a film. As an example Figure 2 shows the thickness distribution of a free-standing film of a so-called ionic liquid. The film which is suspended on a carbon mesh (lacey carbon) shows two characteristic structures: A biconcave layer with a thickness of only 15nm in the center and up to 100nm at the edges or a biconvex layer with thicknesses of up to 300nm at the center. These free-standing liquid films can for example be used as medium for molecular dynamics studies.  The instrument is further capable of generating electron tomography, which allow for a 3-dimensional reconstruction of the morphology of a thin film through rotating the sample while exposed to the electron beam and recoding a series of projection images, which are used to calculate a space filling model. Figure 3 shows the distribution of gold nanoparticles at the interface of a Polymethylmaethacrylate/Polystyrene blend. The overview images shows the 2-dimnesional projection of the film while the inset shows a perspective view clearly locating the nanparticles at the PMMA/PS interface.          Last Modified: 10/26/2015       Submitted by: Alexander E Ribbe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
