<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Neuroeconomics and risk-sensitivity in movement adaptation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>406650.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>406650</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan Leland</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project the Principal Investigator will use a combined experimental and theoretical approach to understand the role of risk-sensitivity in movement adaptation. Movements will be analyzed within a decision-theoretic framework. The central hypothesis is that risk-sensitivity is a fundamental determinant of movement adaptation. Young and older adults will perform whole-body movement tasks that involve adaptation to novel reaching dynamics under increasing conditions of risk. Risk will be modulated by altering the subjective value associated with a given movement error. Risk-sensitivity will be quantified based on the relationship between movement error and movement-to-movement adaptation. Older adults are an ideal population to test model predictions because the subjective value of an error is greater. They have a reduced capacity to produce rapid corrections when an error elicits an unwanted action and have a greater prevalence of injurious falls. Together, these studies will determine whether risk-sensitivity provides a mechanistic explanation for the effect of the subjective value of movement error on adaptation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In terms of broader impacts, this research will test the idea that risk influences movement adaptation. It articulates a conceptual framework that could potentially transform current analyses of the decision-making processes underlying movement adaptation. The proposed work will develop a decision-theoretic, risk-sensitive model of movement adaptation that can be broadly used in the field of motor control to investigate learning in a range of movements and movement contexts, to inform studies on the generalization of risk-sensitive behavior to non-motor tasks, and how this behavior changes across the lifespan. It can inspire future studies that leverage risk-sensitivity to facilitate adaptation, and significantly advance the state-of-the-art in the areas of sensorimotor control, rehabilitation, and decision making.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1230933</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alaa</FirstName>
<LastName>Ahmed</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alaa A Ahmed</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alaa@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034926063</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000556602</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803090572</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine St Rm 481 572 UCB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7252</Code>
<Text>Perception, Action &amp; Cognition</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7956</Code>
<Text>SBE Interdisciplinary Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8605</Code>
<Text>SBE 2020</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~406650</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Effective movements depend critically on adaptation, an error-driven process that corrects control from movement to movement (e.g., aim left after a rightward miss). Importantly, the stimulus for adaptation is movement error. However, not all movement errors have the same cost. For example, a 5cm error in step placement when walking along the edge of a street curb is not the same as a 5cm error while walking along the edge of the Grand Canyon. Clearly, the stimulus for adaptation of the next step in response to each error will be different. In this case, adaptation is not only dependent on the absolute magnitude of the movement error experienced, but on an individual&rsquo;s perception of the cost of the error, i.e., its subjective value. This distortion between the absolute magnitude and subjective value of an error suggests a risk-sensitive adaptation process in the brain. In this context risk is defined as the variance over potential outcomes. Despite widely observed risk-sensitive phenomena, there has been no quantitative description of the principles underlying decision making in movement adaptation.</p> <p>This research project tested the idea that risk influences movement adaptation. We proposed a conceptual framework that has transformed current analyses of the decision-making processes underlying movement adaptation. Our findings demonstrate that human movement adaptation is indeed risk-sensitive and that this risk-sensitivity can be leveraged to improve the learning process. We found that reward feedback accelerates movement adaptation without compromising the learned neural representation. This suggests that reward feedback is a promising, yet thus far largely untapped, tool for neurorehabilitation. Additionally, we observed that stress in the form of physical threat leads to risk-averse movement decisions. Thirdly, our results demonstrate that postural stability has a significant effect on the neural representation of learning. Learning a new movement in an unstable setting can lead to reduced generalization of learning to novel contexts. Based on our findings we recommend that, in order to maximize generalization of learning, training should occur in stable, low-threat environments. Altogether, these findings have inspired ongoing studies that leverage risk-sensitivity to facilitate adaptation, and significantly advance the state-of-the-art in the areas of sensorimotor control, rehabilitation, and decision making.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/08/2017<br>      Modified by: Alaa&nbsp;A&nbsp;Ahmed</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Effective movements depend critically on adaptation, an error-driven process that corrects control from movement to movement (e.g., aim left after a rightward miss). Importantly, the stimulus for adaptation is movement error. However, not all movement errors have the same cost. For example, a 5cm error in step placement when walking along the edge of a street curb is not the same as a 5cm error while walking along the edge of the Grand Canyon. Clearly, the stimulus for adaptation of the next step in response to each error will be different. In this case, adaptation is not only dependent on the absolute magnitude of the movement error experienced, but on an individual?s perception of the cost of the error, i.e., its subjective value. This distortion between the absolute magnitude and subjective value of an error suggests a risk-sensitive adaptation process in the brain. In this context risk is defined as the variance over potential outcomes. Despite widely observed risk-sensitive phenomena, there has been no quantitative description of the principles underlying decision making in movement adaptation.  This research project tested the idea that risk influences movement adaptation. We proposed a conceptual framework that has transformed current analyses of the decision-making processes underlying movement adaptation. Our findings demonstrate that human movement adaptation is indeed risk-sensitive and that this risk-sensitivity can be leveraged to improve the learning process. We found that reward feedback accelerates movement adaptation without compromising the learned neural representation. This suggests that reward feedback is a promising, yet thus far largely untapped, tool for neurorehabilitation. Additionally, we observed that stress in the form of physical threat leads to risk-averse movement decisions. Thirdly, our results demonstrate that postural stability has a significant effect on the neural representation of learning. Learning a new movement in an unstable setting can lead to reduced generalization of learning to novel contexts. Based on our findings we recommend that, in order to maximize generalization of learning, training should occur in stable, low-threat environments. Altogether, these findings have inspired ongoing studies that leverage risk-sensitivity to facilitate adaptation, and significantly advance the state-of-the-art in the areas of sensorimotor control, rehabilitation, and decision making.           Last Modified: 02/08/2017       Submitted by: Alaa A Ahmed]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
