<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Novel Peritoneal Dialysis Catheter to Reduce Infections</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1105000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is aimed at improving the quality of life of dialysis patients through the development if a new disinfection process of the peritoneal dialysis (PD) catheter connection that will reduce infections related to PD. The prevalence of PD among dyaliss patients is increasing and infection rate has become a target for critical improvement. Since PD is a self-administered treatment, patient adherence to the set-up protocol is vital to ensure that sterility is observed. Unfortunately, this is not always the case - infection remains a pressing concern. The objective of this research is to circumvent the need to for complete patient compliance, and introduce a device that will decontaminate the interfaces of PD catheters that are at most risk of contamination. Research objectives focus on enhancing the device design in an effort to achieve a multifold logarithmic bacterial reduction on multiple pathogens, including bacterial and fungal. Other objectives of this project are to optimize product design, from both performance and usability standpoints. When implemented into the clinic, the disinfection device will allow peritoneal dialysis patients to safely receive the full benefit associated with this mode of treatment.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to develop a new standard of care for all catheters suffering from catheter-related infections at ports. The total addressable market for dialysis, central venous, and peripheral venous lines is $13 Billion. Catheter-related infections still presents as a dangerous health hazard for many markets and as of yet, no disinfectant has emerged to successfully address this issue. The "No Pay" rule implemented in recent years prevents hospitals from being reimbursed from infection-related cases with catheters. The disinfection device will enable the decontamination of catheters and the prevention of luminal infections, thereby greatly reducing the risk of secondary infection. For peritoneal dialysis specifically, this technology allows for home dialysis to be a more attractive option compared to hemodialysis by adding safety, reducing patient morbidity and mortality, while permitting more patients to take advantage of the quality of life benefits that peritoneal dialysis provides.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1230432</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
<LastName>Rasooly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julia Rasooly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>julia@puracath.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4153054134</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000580138</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Puracath Medical Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>945603445</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4153054134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>37600 Central Ct Suite 210</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>963236661</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURACATH MEDICAL, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CatheNect Medical Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>941045428</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[564 Market Street, Suite 424]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1591</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~505000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>PuraCath Medical has made a signicant impact on employment, increasing intellectual knowledge of science for society, and in helping patient lives through the help of the National Science Foundation SBIR program.</p> <p>In terms of employment, PuraCath has since throughout the life of the Phase I, IB, II, and IIB rounds been able to also raise a seed and Series A round of venture capital investment which has helped contribute to hiring engineers and scientists from top universities such as MIT, Stanford, and U.C. Berkeley. In addition to an R&amp;D staff, PuraCath has also hired business development, marketing and sales, and finance/ accounting specialists as well. PuraCath has also throughout the past few years offered several R&amp;D and engineering internship positions to students in various local universities as well.</p> <p>In terms of intellectual merit, PuraCath has since then filed on numerous patents domestically and internationally on its disinfection device with multiple applications. PuraCath was the first medical device in the dialysis industry with a 99.99% (or 4 log) disinfection claim for multiple known microorganisms that cause peritonitis infection including MRSA, Staph aureus, E Coli, Streptococcus pneumoniae, Candida albicans, and Pseudomonas aeroginosa. Also, advantages to the Firefly system are that it is antibiotic and chemical-free. PuraCath feels strongly that the Firefly disinfection system is well-positioned to become the standard of care for all peritoneal dialysis patients.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/19/2016<br>      Modified by: Julia&nbsp;Rasooly</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ PuraCath Medical has made a signicant impact on employment, increasing intellectual knowledge of science for society, and in helping patient lives through the help of the National Science Foundation SBIR program.  In terms of employment, PuraCath has since throughout the life of the Phase I, IB, II, and IIB rounds been able to also raise a seed and Series A round of venture capital investment which has helped contribute to hiring engineers and scientists from top universities such as MIT, Stanford, and U.C. Berkeley. In addition to an R&amp;D staff, PuraCath has also hired business development, marketing and sales, and finance/ accounting specialists as well. PuraCath has also throughout the past few years offered several R&amp;D and engineering internship positions to students in various local universities as well.  In terms of intellectual merit, PuraCath has since then filed on numerous patents domestically and internationally on its disinfection device with multiple applications. PuraCath was the first medical device in the dialysis industry with a 99.99% (or 4 log) disinfection claim for multiple known microorganisms that cause peritonitis infection including MRSA, Staph aureus, E Coli, Streptococcus pneumoniae, Candida albicans, and Pseudomonas aeroginosa. Also, advantages to the Firefly system are that it is antibiotic and chemical-free. PuraCath feels strongly that the Firefly disinfection system is well-positioned to become the standard of care for all peritoneal dialysis patients.       Last Modified: 09/19/2016       Submitted by: Julia Rasooly]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
