<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SEP: Sustainable Forest-Based Biofuel Pathways to Hydrocarbon Transportation Fuels: Biomass Production, Torrefaction, Pyrolysis, Catalytic Upgrading, and Combustion</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1800000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1800000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927066</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The NSF Sustainable Energy pathways (SEP) Program, under the umbrella of the NSF Science, Engineering and Education for Sustainability (SEES) initiative, will support the research program of Prof. David Shonnard and co-workers at Michigan Technological University. Drop-in, renewable replacements for petroleum-based liquid transportation fuels is a national strategic goal for energy security. The four-year Wood to Wheels (W2W) SEP project will achieve this goal by conducting transformative, multidisciplinary, comprehensive, and integrated research in the area of forest-based infrastructure-compatible liquid biofuel for vehicular transportation. Hypothesis-driven research is to be organized into three main thrusts plus a cross-cutting thrust integration activity; 1) Sustainable Forest Systems, 2) Two-Stage Torrefaction/Pyrolysis-Based Conversion Processes, 3) Energy Utilization of Advanced Biofuels, and 4) Integrated Sustainability Assessment and Decision Making. The Sustainable Forest Systems research thrust will feature research in forest productivity modeling, ecosystem nutrition and productivity, and genomics-guided feedstock (poplar) improvement. The Conversion Processes thrust will investigate a novel two-stage torrefaction and pyrolysis based processing strategy to prepare an improved bio-oil for multi-functional catalytic upgrading to a hydrocarbon green diesel fuel product. The Energy Utilization thrust will incorporate a surrogate fuels approach to determine the relationship between fuel component classes and combustion characteristics, and to provide feedback to the Conversion thrust team on targets for optimal GD composition.  The Sustainability Assessment thrust will produce decision support tools including indicator sets, perform process simulation and optimization, technoeconomic analyses, life cycle assessments, greenhouse gas analyses, and energy balances.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to achieve scientific and engineering breakthroughs for production of an infrastructure-compatible green diesel (GD) with system-wide benefits; such as clean combustion in engines (low particulates and NOx), reduced life-cycle greenhouse gas emissions compared to fossil fuel, low cost per gallon, rural job creation, increased energy independence, high productivity per acre of forest biomass, plant genotypes with favorable composition for conversion, and engines optimized to use the prescribed component makeup of the GD. Researchers, including 11 faculty, 7 PhD students, and one postdoc from Forestry, Social Sciences, Chemical Engineering, Mechanical Engineering, will develop new knowledge about complex coupled natural/industrial/societal systems. This SEP project will create a diverse highly skilled biofuels workforce with the technical research experiences and broad sustainability education needed to  support a renewable transportation fuels industry. The research team will interact with local communities to gain information on what they believe to be important measures of sustainability in their communities. Through this interaction, these communities will receive education on biofuel production technologies and what sustainability means, how it can be measured, and whether trade-offs among goals are necessary to institute sustainable biofuel systems in their area. The team will implement a W2W SEP diversity plan to: (1) recruit women, under-represented minorities, and persons with disabilities as graduate students, and (2) implement integrated practices that enable the academic and professional success of the SEP students and postdoc.   Results from the Sustainability Assessments research thrust will be fed back to the other thrust teams in order to guide research and overcome sustainability challenges that arise at key processing stages along the life cycle.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will contribute to the development of biomass-based biofuel production in the US in order to displace nearly all imported petroleum, to support domestic jobs, and to reduce greenhouse gas emissions. Project deliverables will help establish a new forest-based biofuels industry featuring high productivity forest energy crops, sustainable forest management practices, catalysts and process technologies, innovations in engine systems, sustainable decision-making databases, and analysis methods/software tools.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1230803</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Shonnard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David R Shonnard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>drshonna@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064873468</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000426524</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Burton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew J Burton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ajburton@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064872566</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000323214</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Naber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey D Naber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jnaber@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064871938</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000338251</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Audrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Mayer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Audrey L Mayer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>almayer@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064873448</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000530964</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ezra</FirstName>
<LastName>Bar Ziv</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ezra Bar Ziv</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ebarziv@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064873151</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574461</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan Technological University</Name>
<CityName>Houghton</CityName>
<ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9064871885</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 Townsend Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065453268</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN TECHNOLOGICAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065453268</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan Technological University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8026</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Energy Pathways</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1800000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The four-year<strong>&nbsp;Wood to Wheels (W2W) SEP project</strong>&nbsp;conducted transformative, multidisciplinary, comprehensive, and integrated research in the area of forest-based infrastructure-compatible liquid biofuel for vehicular transportation. Project deliverables helped establish a new forest-based biofuels industry featuring high productivity forest energy crops, sustainable forest management practices, catalysts and process technologies, innovations in engine systems, sustainable decision-making databases, and analysis methods/software tools. Hypothesis-driven research was organized into three main thrusts plus a cross-cutting thrust integration activity; 1) Sustainable Forest Systems, 2) Two-Stage Torrefaction/Pyrolysis-Based Conversion Processes, 3) Energy Utilization of Advanced Biofuels, and 4) Integrated Sustainability Assessment and Decision Making. The goal for this project is conduct research and education in support of producing infrastructure-compatible green gasoline and diesel with system-wide benefits; such as clean combustion in engines (low particulates and NOx), reduced life-cycle greenhouse gas emissions compared to fossil fuel, low cost per gallon, rural job creation, increased energy independence, high productivity per acre of forest biomass, plant genotypes with favorable composition for conversion, and engines optimized to use the prescribed component make-up of the biofuel. There were eleven tenured or tenure track faculty participants, two postdoctoral researchers, and eleven Ph.D. graduate student researchers involved. We conducted a set of activities that that allowed for collaboration between the teams in research, education, and professional development.</p> <p>The Sustainable Forest Systems research thrust featureed research in forest productivity modeling, ecosystem nutrition and productivity, and genomics-guided feedstock (poplar) improvement. The Conversion Processes thrust investigated a novel two-stage torrefaction and pyrolysis based processing strategy to prepare an improved bio-oil for multi-functional catalytic upgrading to a hydrocarbon green gasoline and diesel fuel blend product. Micro-scale experiments uncovered thermal degradation reaction mechanisms leading to improved models of these reactions. This thrust investigated the effects of feedstock biomass composition on bio-oil composition and properties. The Energy Utilization thrust incorporated a surrogate fuels approach to determine the relationship between fuel component classes and combustion characteristics, and provided feedback to the Conversion thrust team on targets for optimal biofuel composition. The Sustainability Assessment thrust produced decision support tools including indicator sets, performed process simulation and optimization, technoeconomic analyses, environmental life cycle assessments, greenhouse gas analyses, and energy balances. Results fed back to the other thrust teams in order to guide research and overcome sustainability challenges that arise at key processing stages along the life cycle. &nbsp;For example, higher lignin content in the energy crop poplar produced higher yields of char compared to liquid bio-oil. &nbsp;At a pyrolysis temperature of 500 &deg;C, an increase in poplar lignin content from 17% to 22% decreased the relative bio-oil yield from 73% to 65%, increased the char yield from 17.5% to 27.2%, and decreased the yield of lignin-derived phenolic species in the bio-oil by 3%. &nbsp;At the higher pyrolysis temperature of 600 &deg;C, there was neither a decrease in the yield of bio-oil nor an increase in the char yield, and there was an increase in the relative abundance of bio-oil phenolics compared to the results obtained at 500 &deg;C. According to these results, higher temperatures are needed to increase the yield of bio-oil and the content of phenolic species in bio-oil.</p> <p>This SEP project contributed to technology development for realizing the full potential of lignocellulosic-based biofuel production in the US, with the potential for displacing nearly all imported petroleum, support domestic jobs numbering perhaps 2-3 million out of a total 135 million employed, and reduce greenhouse gas emissions of nearly 1 billion metric tons CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;equivalents / yr assuming full implementation of the &ldquo;billion ton vision&rdquo; (as compared to the &nbsp;current total emissions of 6 billion metric tons CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;eq./yr). This SEP project created a diverse highly skilled biofuels workforce with deep technical research experiences and the broad sustainability education needed to help create a future renewable transportation fuels industry in the United States of America.&nbsp;</p> <p>A number of other deliverables contributing to broader impacts were achieved. We implemented a W2W SEP diversity plan to: (1) secure participation of women, under-represented minorities, and persons with disabilities among the recruited graduate students that reflects the great breadth of our nation&rsquo;s diversity and signifies a culture that values and seeks diversity, and (2) implement integrated practices that enable the academic and professional success of the SEP students and postdoc. .As a result of these efforts, 7 of the 13 suppoted MS, PhD, and postdocs were women and one was of native american heritage. &nbsp;One of the PhD graduates, Bethany Klemtsrud, has accepted a faculty position at the University of North Dakota in Chemical Engineering where she will continue sustainable biofuel research and outreach to native american communities. Other students have accepted positions as postdocs, and as professionals in industry, and government.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/17/2017<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;R&nbsp;Shonnard</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1230803/1230803_10209505_1505677962702_ShonnardSEPSlideforOutcomesReport--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1230803/1230803_10209505_1505677962702_ShonnardSEPSlideforOutcomesReport--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SEP Wood-to-Wheels Program"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1230803/1230803_10209505_1505677962702_ShonnardSEPSlideforOutcomesReport--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SEP Wood-to-Wheels Program"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A multidisciplinary integrated research program to improve forest-based biofuel economic, environmental, and societal performance.</div> <div class="imageCredit">David R. Shonnard</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David&nbsp;R&nbsp;Shonnard</div> <div class="imageTitle">SEP Wood-to-Wheels Program</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The four-year Wood to Wheels (W2W) SEP project conducted transformative, multidisciplinary, comprehensive, and integrated research in the area of forest-based infrastructure-compatible liquid biofuel for vehicular transportation. Project deliverables helped establish a new forest-based biofuels industry featuring high productivity forest energy crops, sustainable forest management practices, catalysts and process technologies, innovations in engine systems, sustainable decision-making databases, and analysis methods/software tools. Hypothesis-driven research was organized into three main thrusts plus a cross-cutting thrust integration activity; 1) Sustainable Forest Systems, 2) Two-Stage Torrefaction/Pyrolysis-Based Conversion Processes, 3) Energy Utilization of Advanced Biofuels, and 4) Integrated Sustainability Assessment and Decision Making. The goal for this project is conduct research and education in support of producing infrastructure-compatible green gasoline and diesel with system-wide benefits; such as clean combustion in engines (low particulates and NOx), reduced life-cycle greenhouse gas emissions compared to fossil fuel, low cost per gallon, rural job creation, increased energy independence, high productivity per acre of forest biomass, plant genotypes with favorable composition for conversion, and engines optimized to use the prescribed component make-up of the biofuel. There were eleven tenured or tenure track faculty participants, two postdoctoral researchers, and eleven Ph.D. graduate student researchers involved. We conducted a set of activities that that allowed for collaboration between the teams in research, education, and professional development.  The Sustainable Forest Systems research thrust featureed research in forest productivity modeling, ecosystem nutrition and productivity, and genomics-guided feedstock (poplar) improvement. The Conversion Processes thrust investigated a novel two-stage torrefaction and pyrolysis based processing strategy to prepare an improved bio-oil for multi-functional catalytic upgrading to a hydrocarbon green gasoline and diesel fuel blend product. Micro-scale experiments uncovered thermal degradation reaction mechanisms leading to improved models of these reactions. This thrust investigated the effects of feedstock biomass composition on bio-oil composition and properties. The Energy Utilization thrust incorporated a surrogate fuels approach to determine the relationship between fuel component classes and combustion characteristics, and provided feedback to the Conversion thrust team on targets for optimal biofuel composition. The Sustainability Assessment thrust produced decision support tools including indicator sets, performed process simulation and optimization, technoeconomic analyses, environmental life cycle assessments, greenhouse gas analyses, and energy balances. Results fed back to the other thrust teams in order to guide research and overcome sustainability challenges that arise at key processing stages along the life cycle.  For example, higher lignin content in the energy crop poplar produced higher yields of char compared to liquid bio-oil.  At a pyrolysis temperature of 500 &deg;C, an increase in poplar lignin content from 17% to 22% decreased the relative bio-oil yield from 73% to 65%, increased the char yield from 17.5% to 27.2%, and decreased the yield of lignin-derived phenolic species in the bio-oil by 3%.  At the higher pyrolysis temperature of 600 &deg;C, there was neither a decrease in the yield of bio-oil nor an increase in the char yield, and there was an increase in the relative abundance of bio-oil phenolics compared to the results obtained at 500 &deg;C. According to these results, higher temperatures are needed to increase the yield of bio-oil and the content of phenolic species in bio-oil.  This SEP project contributed to technology development for realizing the full potential of lignocellulosic-based biofuel production in the US, with the potential for displacing nearly all imported petroleum, support domestic jobs numbering perhaps 2-3 million out of a total 135 million employed, and reduce greenhouse gas emissions of nearly 1 billion metric tons CO2 equivalents / yr assuming full implementation of the "billion ton vision" (as compared to the  current total emissions of 6 billion metric tons CO2 eq./yr). This SEP project created a diverse highly skilled biofuels workforce with deep technical research experiences and the broad sustainability education needed to help create a future renewable transportation fuels industry in the United States of America.   A number of other deliverables contributing to broader impacts were achieved. We implemented a W2W SEP diversity plan to: (1) secure participation of women, under-represented minorities, and persons with disabilities among the recruited graduate students that reflects the great breadth of our nation?s diversity and signifies a culture that values and seeks diversity, and (2) implement integrated practices that enable the academic and professional success of the SEP students and postdoc. .As a result of these efforts, 7 of the 13 suppoted MS, PhD, and postdocs were women and one was of native american heritage.  One of the PhD graduates, Bethany Klemtsrud, has accepted a faculty position at the University of North Dakota in Chemical Engineering where she will continue sustainable biofuel research and outreach to native american communities. Other students have accepted positions as postdocs, and as professionals in industry, and government.           Last Modified: 09/17/2017       Submitted by: David R Shonnard]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
