<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Liquid Crystal-based Next Generation e-paper Devices by Micro-engineered Surfaces</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project focuses on development of low power consumption, bistable memory nematic liquid crystal display (LCD) devices for e-book and mobile applications, based on the micro-engineered surface alignment (MESA) technology. The MESA-LCD innovatively implements new photoaligment materials and processes, combined with unique maskless UV pattern generator, to achieve bistability and performance requirements for portable devices. It is suitable for mass production and also on flexible substrates, also compatible with existing manufacturing infra-structure of LCDs.  In Phase-I, the controlled weak anchoring have been successfully demonstrated, and the process has been developed to reduce the driving voltage by one order of magnitude. The main challenge in Phase-II is to reduce the driving voltage down to 0.1v/ìm. The main objectives and approaches in Phase-II are: (1) to develop a passive matrix MESA-LCD prototype (the first generation) for presenting to the potential investors; (2) to optimize the photoalignment process for driving voltage reduction, (3) to develop an active matrix MESA-LCD prototype (second generation) with the optimized photoalignment material and process, with establishment of large scale manufacturing processes. Anticipated Phase-II results would be the successful development of MESA-LCD prototypes for commercialization. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts/commercial potential will be that the MESA-LCD related technologies will benefit from the low power, high contrast ratio and high resolution. Success of this project will enable a high performance and low cost MESA-LCD that have a significant market opportunity in mobile devices to bring users information and Entertainment, offer users a convergent display experience, with paper-like readability, significantly less power consumption, and video-rate response times. The most important market the MESA-LCD addresses is e-paper and e-book market. When the MESA-LCD based e-book and e-paper are fully developed, one device can hold tens or hundreds of books or content, decreasing the burden of students' backpacks, saving bookshelf space, and reducing shipping costs. Also huge amount of paper will be saved, which is a good contribution to the environment. Besides the e-book and e-paper market, MESA-LCD can also be used in various applications such as price tag and sale-announcement displays on shelves and throughout the retail stores, cell phones and other hand-hold devices, display products for security and hospitality, and display for industrial controls.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/24/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1230389</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hailiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hailiang Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hailiang@hitron-technologies.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3108688072</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000551129</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/24/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hitron Technologies Inc.</Name>
<CityName>lexington</CityName>
<ZipCode>405174066</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3108688072</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3151 Custer Drive suite C</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965189124</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HITRON TECHNOLOGIES INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hitron Technologies Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Kent</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>442420001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1425 University Esplanade]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to develop and commercialize the low power consumption, bistable memory nematic liquid crystal display (LCD) devices for e-book and mobile applications based on the micro-engineered surface alignment (MESA) technology.</p> <p>During the Phase II project period, we have met most of the Phase II objectives and demonstrated the feasibility of MESA technology through:</p> <ul> <li>We developed an innovative electrode pattern and a simplified driving scheme for enabling bistable MESA-LCD.</li> <li>We fabricated MESA-LCD samples with micro patterns (Fig. 1) through use of maskless pattern generator (MPG) and various photoalignment materials. &nbsp;</li> <li>We developed a driver for amplifying the voltage for driving the MESA-LCD. </li> <li>We successfully solved the problem of the auto-focus error of the MPG. </li> <li>With the improved performance of MPG, we have successfully fabricated the MESA-LCD sample and have demonstrated the bistable display at the domain boundary. (Fig.2)</li> <li>Through further optimization of the MPG and the fabrication process, we have demonstrated the bistable display with micro-domain boundary down to ~2 &micro;m.</li> </ul> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>The broader impacts/commercial potential</strong> will be that will be that the MESA-LCD related technologies will benefit from high resolution of the display with low power consumption due to its bistability feature. Further commercialization of this technology may enable a high performance and low cost MESA-LCD that have a significant market opportunity in e-book and other mobile devices to bring users information and entertainment, offer users a convergent display experience, with paper-like readability, full color display, significantly less power consumption, video-rate response times. Also through the Phase-II development, the maskless photolithography technology is demonstrated through the improvement and optimization of the MPG. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/05/2015<br>      Modified by: Hailiang&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1230389/1230389_10218171_1446743897035_Fig.1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1230389/1230389_10218171_1446743897035_Fig.1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="photoalignment pattern"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1230389/1230389_10218171_1446743897035_Fig.1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="photoalignment pattern"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig.1. The typical stability of photoalignment pattern induced by the linear polarized UV light. The size of each sub-domain is 10 micron. The black and white states changes to each other when the polarizer is rotated by 90 degree.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jintae Yuh, James Jeffers, Hailiang Zhang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hailiang&nbsp;Zhang</div> <div class="imageTitle">photoalignment pattern</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1230389/1230389_10218171_1446745007618_Fig.2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1230389/1230389_10218171_1446745007618_Fig.2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Bi-stability display demonstration"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1230389/1230389_10218171_1446745007618_Fig.2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to develop and commercialize the low power consumption, bistable memory nematic liquid crystal display (LCD) devices for e-book and mobile applications based on the micro-engineered surface alignment (MESA) technology.  During the Phase II project period, we have met most of the Phase II objectives and demonstrated the feasibility of MESA technology through:  We developed an innovative electrode pattern and a simplified driving scheme for enabling bistable MESA-LCD. We fabricated MESA-LCD samples with micro patterns (Fig. 1) through use of maskless pattern generator (MPG) and various photoalignment materials.   We developed a driver for amplifying the voltage for driving the MESA-LCD.  We successfully solved the problem of the auto-focus error of the MPG.  With the improved performance of MPG, we have successfully fabricated the MESA-LCD sample and have demonstrated the bistable display at the domain boundary. (Fig.2) Through further optimization of the MPG and the fabrication process, we have demonstrated the bistable display with micro-domain boundary down to ~2 &micro;m.      The broader impacts/commercial potential will be that will be that the MESA-LCD related technologies will benefit from high resolution of the display with low power consumption due to its bistability feature. Further commercialization of this technology may enable a high performance and low cost MESA-LCD that have a significant market opportunity in e-book and other mobile devices to bring users information and entertainment, offer users a convergent display experience, with paper-like readability, full color display, significantly less power consumption, video-rate response times. Also through the Phase-II development, the maskless photolithography technology is demonstrated through the improvement and optimization of the MPG.            Last Modified: 11/05/2015       Submitted by: Hailiang Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
