<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  CCSS:  Cyber-Enabled Smart Systems for Seamless Secure Monitoring and Communications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149868.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>181868</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>akbar sayeed</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Objective:            &lt;br/&gt;The objective of this program is to address the security and capacity requests raised in cyber-enabled secure monitoring and control, and to accomplish a human-device interaction platform by conjoining the communication capability and computational resources of the ubiquitous wireless networks with general physical components and devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit:        &lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit is the development of practical multi-layer techniques that enable seamless, secure mobile-based device monitoring and control, and of the analytical and design tools that are broadly applicable to related engineering problems. More specifically: (i)  For security enhancement and privacy protection, the innovative access control and  privacy protection schemes can achieve secure authentication without providing non-repudiation evidence; (ii) For capacity improvement, efficient and inherently reliable wireless systems  are developed through network-centric airlink interface design and spectrum sharing; (iii) For  system development and integration, the multi-layer design strategy is realized through penetration of high layer techniques into lower layer physical system design, which greatly reduces the system complexity, management overhead and security risks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts:   &lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts are: (i) It will lead to a seamless and secure mobile-based device monitoring and control mechanism which can be utilized for a broad scope of applications critical to national competitiveness and homeland security; (ii) By integrating the technological advances resulting from this project into the undergraduate/graduate curricula, and through outreach activities, significant impacts are expected from this project on training a highly-skilled and diverse workforce in the area of cyber-enabled systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1231461</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jie</FirstName>
<LastName>Wu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jie Wu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jiewu@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2152048450</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000519190</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191221234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>153E</Code>
<Text>Wireless comm &amp; sig processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>154E</Code>
<Text>Computat systems &amp; security</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~149868</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="h7 hn"> <div class="Bk"> <div class="G3 G2 afm"> <div id=":1aa"> <div class="adn ads"> <div class="gs"> <div id=":1ac" class="ii gt adP adO"> <div id=":1ab" class="a3s aXjCH m16018916c660d392"> <div><dl class="m_-2887119283355874461clearing"><dd> <div class="m_-2887119283355874461tinyMCEContent"> <p>1.&nbsp;<strong>Cryptographic algorithm design</strong>: Our research on cryptographic algorithm design includes two areas:&nbsp;</p> <p>a)&nbsp;<strong>Anonymous Hop-by-Hop Authentication Algorithm</strong>: We developed cryptographic algorithms that maintains message source anonymity while enabling network-level message content authentication. Our scheme is secure against no-message attacks and adaptive chosen- message attacks in the random oracle model. &nbsp;</p> <p>b)&nbsp;<strong>Secure Network Authentication</strong>: We developed secure one-time login name and one-time password schemes for smart grid and smart home systems. Our theoretical analysis and evaluation demonstrated that the proposed scheme can achieve our proposed security goal and have very low computational and communication efficiency. &nbsp;</p> <p>2.&nbsp;<strong>Source&nbsp;Privacy</strong>: We designed active techniques to combat location privacy attacks. Our results can be divided into the following categories:&nbsp;</p> <p>a)&nbsp;<strong>Privacy Characterization</strong>: We developed numerical measurement criteria for location privacy measurement. Based on our proposed measurement, we designed secure location privacy protection modules for multi-hop networks. &nbsp;</p> <p>b)&nbsp;<strong>Fake Location Updating</strong>: We discovered that simply omitting location updates does not provide adequate privacy protections, especially in situations where the friendship relationships between users are known. Based on this research, we proposed a fake location update algorithm that allows user's location informated be protectedwithout involving any third party, making it more flexible and practical. &nbsp;</p> <p>c)&nbsp;<strong>Cost-Aware Security Characterization</strong>: We developed techniques to numerical desgin tradeoffs between security and cost. This problem includes two opposite questions: (i) For a given security design, how to determine the associate cost? and (ii) For a given cost level, how to determine the best security implementation? &nbsp;</p> <p>d)&nbsp;<strong>Privacy and Creditability Tradeoff</strong>: Threshold ring signature schemes provide a nice tradeoff between anonymity and creditability since it allows multiple ring members to sign a message jointly. In this research, we developed an efficient (t, n)-threshold ring signature scheme. This scheme can provide unconditional signer ambiguity, threshold unforgeability and provable security in the random oracle model. &nbsp;</p> <p>4.&nbsp;<strong>Study of multiband communication system capacity under cognitive jamming</strong>:&nbsp;We considered a communication system with a power-limited authorized user and a power-limited jammer. The jammer is assumed to be intelligent and can switch its patterns fast enough, such that it is impossible for the authorized user to detect and react in real time. We found that under additive white Gaussian (AWGN) channels, the best strategy for both of them is to distribute the signal power or jamming power uniformly over all the available spectrum.&nbsp;</p> <p>4.&nbsp;<strong>Software and Hardware Integration</strong>: We developed an integrated evaluate platform for our proposed algorithms and solutions, which includes cryptographic algorithm design, database management, Android smartphone application, secure acces gateway hardware design and integration of ZigBee interface to manged devices. Our analysis shows that we can achieve all our proposed security and network design goals.&nbsp;</p> </div> </dd></dl> <div></div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/02/2017<br>      Modified by: Jie&nbsp;Wu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[           1. Cryptographic algorithm design: Our research on cryptographic algorithm design includes two areas:   a) Anonymous Hop-by-Hop Authentication Algorithm: We developed cryptographic algorithms that maintains message source anonymity while enabling network-level message content authentication. Our scheme is secure against no-message attacks and adaptive chosen- message attacks in the random oracle model.    b) Secure Network Authentication: We developed secure one-time login name and one-time password schemes for smart grid and smart home systems. Our theoretical analysis and evaluation demonstrated that the proposed scheme can achieve our proposed security goal and have very low computational and communication efficiency.    2. Source Privacy: We designed active techniques to combat location privacy attacks. Our results can be divided into the following categories:   a) Privacy Characterization: We developed numerical measurement criteria for location privacy measurement. Based on our proposed measurement, we designed secure location privacy protection modules for multi-hop networks.    b) Fake Location Updating: We discovered that simply omitting location updates does not provide adequate privacy protections, especially in situations where the friendship relationships between users are known. Based on this research, we proposed a fake location update algorithm that allows user's location informated be protectedwithout involving any third party, making it more flexible and practical.    c) Cost-Aware Security Characterization: We developed techniques to numerical desgin tradeoffs between security and cost. This problem includes two opposite questions: (i) For a given security design, how to determine the associate cost? and (ii) For a given cost level, how to determine the best security implementation?    d) Privacy and Creditability Tradeoff: Threshold ring signature schemes provide a nice tradeoff between anonymity and creditability since it allows multiple ring members to sign a message jointly. In this research, we developed an efficient (t, n)-threshold ring signature scheme. This scheme can provide unconditional signer ambiguity, threshold unforgeability and provable security in the random oracle model.    4. Study of multiband communication system capacity under cognitive jamming: We considered a communication system with a power-limited authorized user and a power-limited jammer. The jammer is assumed to be intelligent and can switch its patterns fast enough, such that it is impossible for the authorized user to detect and react in real time. We found that under additive white Gaussian (AWGN) channels, the best strategy for both of them is to distribute the signal power or jamming power uniformly over all the available spectrum.   4. Software and Hardware Integration: We developed an integrated evaluate platform for our proposed algorithms and solutions, which includes cryptographic algorithm design, database management, Android smartphone application, secure acces gateway hardware design and integration of ZigBee interface to manged devices. Our analysis shows that we can achieve all our proposed security and network design goals.                    Last Modified: 12/02/2017       Submitted by: Jie Wu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
