<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Epigenetic alterations and stress among new mothers and neonates in the Democratic Republic of Congo:   A biocultural investigation of the intergenerational effects of war</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>353328.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>353328</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>It has been known for decades that a mother's health impacts the health of her children. Moreover, it is known that a mother's experiences while she is pregnant (i.e., peri-natal experiences) affect her children's health, both when they are born and throughout their lives. What is unknown is how information about the mother's health is transmitted to the developing fetus and, furthermore, how this information impacts children's health throughout their lives. This project is one of the first to test the possibility that extreme environmental or psychosocial stressors may result in altered health outcomes, possibly in a heritable, multigenerational manner. Specifically, the investigators will determine if epigenetic changes, which are inherited changes in gene expression that do not affect the underlying DNA sequence, translate the impact of stress and trauma to mothers into altered health outcomes in newborns. The investigators are working in the Democratic Republic of Congo, where ongoing civil war and the use of rape as a weapon has created one of the most stressful and traumatic environments for women on the planet. Culturally relevant measures of stress will be developed through extensive interviews with mothers and these data will be tested against patterns of epigenetic variation detected in DNA samples collected from mothers and their newborns. Cutting-edge DNA sequencing techniques will be used to generate the largest epigenetic dataset ever on a unique set of mother-newborn samples. Investigators will look for a connection between maternal stress and newborn health outcome that is mediated by epigenetic alterations in gene expression. Ongoing research in other laboratories indicate that it may be possible to devise treatment to reverse epigenetic alterations made in response to stress exposures, which has profound implications for our ability to address some of society's most taxing problems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   The proposed study is the first to investigate epigenetic alterations (changes in gene expression that do not change the underlying DNA sequence) in humans as a possible response to peri-natal stress and trauma to mothers that results in altered health outcomes in offspring. The idea that violence and stress exposure can create changes in newborn health outcome, presumably through changes in gene expression, has immediate relevance to global public health issues. Seen from the broadest perspective, this proposal and similar research has profound implications for our understanding and attempts to ameliorate society's most vexing problems, including multigenerational cycles of violence, abuse and poverty.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   The proposed research will improve our understanding of the link between stress and health in humans and has broad implications for the increasing prevalence of stress-related disorders in the United States. The project takes a broad, interdisciplinary perspective that integrates human genetics, cultural anthropology and sociology, biology and psychology, as well as political realities and public health policy. Furthermore, a graduate training program has been developed in collaboration with the University of Florida's Scientific Thinking and Education Partnership in which anthropology students will act as production assistants to develop communication materials to disseminate research results to the general public. Students will receive training in news writing, print layout, and video production to prepare them to better communicate their research to a non-science audience.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1231264</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Connie</FirstName>
<LastName>Mulligan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Connie J Mulligan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cmulligan@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3522738092</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000310340</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Clarence</FirstName>
<LastName>Gravlee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Clarence C Gravlee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cgravlee@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523922253</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000483633</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alyson</FirstName>
<LastName>Young</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alyson G Young</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alys.yng@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3522948128</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000570249</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326100001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2033 Mowry Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7956</Code>
<Text>SBE Interdisciplinary Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8605</Code>
<Text>SBE 2020</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~353328</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;My colleagues and I are conducting research in the Democratic Republic of Congo on the effects of maternal stress on the DNA methylation patterns of mothers and their newborns. DNA methylation is a chemical modification to DNA that can change the way genes are expressed to make proteins. Our research addresses an important question because changes in methylation patterns may be associated with disease risk (see our model in Figure 1).</p> <p>In this study, we found that maternal war-related stress is associated with widespread (genome-wide) changes in methylation patterns in the mothers but not in their newborns (Rodney and Mulligan 2014) (Figure 2). We have also found that maternal war stress is associated with lower newborn birth weights (an indicator of maternal nutrition or stress) and changes in newborn methylation at specific genes (Mulligan et al. 2012). This is of special interest because lower birth weights in newborns increase the risk of disease later in life. One particular gene whose methylation pattern in newborns is significantly correlated with maternal war stress is the glucocorticoid receptor <em>NR3C1</em>, which codes for a protein involved in newborn birth weight (Mulligan et al. 2012) (Figure 3).&nbsp;</p> <p>Our results suggest that stress may influence gene expression across a broad spectrum in the individual who directly experiences the stress&mdash;that is, the mother&mdash;whereas effects in the newborn may be focused on specific genes that are uniquely sensitive to environmental cues, such as <em>NR3C1</em>. It is interesting to note that war-stressed mothers and newborns do not share identical methylation patterns at <em>NR3C1 </em>(Mulligan et al. 2012). This suggests that methylation patterns at <em>NR3C1 </em>are not strictly inherited and may be susceptible to environmental influences. This characteristic of the <em>NR3C1</em> gene (and possibly other genes) may provide humans with an increased capacity for rapid change and adaptation to environmental stressors without producing long-lasting evolutionary change.</p> <p>Our research has important implications for health and well-being in the United States  because many Americans experience high levels of stress (49% of Americans  report a major stressful event over the past year and 26% report a  "great deal" of stress over the previous month; poll by Harvard  University School of Public Health). We hope to provide a better understanding of the underlying mechanism of the biological impacts of stress.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2016<br>      Modified by: Connie&nbsp;J&nbsp;Mulligan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1231264/1231264_10217479_1472742667607_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1231264/1231264_10217479_1472742667607_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1231264/1231264_10217479_1472742667607_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Proposed model of psychosocial stress influencing a phenotype via an epigenetic mechanism that alters gene expression</div> <div class="imageCredit">Connie Mulligan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Connie&nbsp;J&nbsp;Mulligan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1231264/1231264_10217479_1472743658597_Figure4copy--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1231264/1231264_10217479_1472743658597_Figure4copy--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1231264/1231264_10217479_1472743658597_Figure4copy--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Correlation of maternal methylation and war stress</div> <div class="imageCredit">Connie Mulligan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Connie&nbsp;J&nbsp;Mulligan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1231264/1231264_10217479_1472743735327_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1231264/1231264_10217479_1472743735327_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1231264/1231264_10217479_1472743735327_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Correlation of newborn (A and B) and maternal (C and D) methylation with war stress and birthweight</div> <div class="imageCredit">Connie Mulligan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Connie&nbsp;J&nbsp;Mulligan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  My colleagues and I are conducting research in the Democratic Republic of Congo on the effects of maternal stress on the DNA methylation patterns of mothers and their newborns. DNA methylation is a chemical modification to DNA that can change the way genes are expressed to make proteins. Our research addresses an important question because changes in methylation patterns may be associated with disease risk (see our model in Figure 1).  In this study, we found that maternal war-related stress is associated with widespread (genome-wide) changes in methylation patterns in the mothers but not in their newborns (Rodney and Mulligan 2014) (Figure 2). We have also found that maternal war stress is associated with lower newborn birth weights (an indicator of maternal nutrition or stress) and changes in newborn methylation at specific genes (Mulligan et al. 2012). This is of special interest because lower birth weights in newborns increase the risk of disease later in life. One particular gene whose methylation pattern in newborns is significantly correlated with maternal war stress is the glucocorticoid receptor NR3C1, which codes for a protein involved in newborn birth weight (Mulligan et al. 2012) (Figure 3).   Our results suggest that stress may influence gene expression across a broad spectrum in the individual who directly experiences the stress&mdash;that is, the mother&mdash;whereas effects in the newborn may be focused on specific genes that are uniquely sensitive to environmental cues, such as NR3C1. It is interesting to note that war-stressed mothers and newborns do not share identical methylation patterns at NR3C1 (Mulligan et al. 2012). This suggests that methylation patterns at NR3C1 are not strictly inherited and may be susceptible to environmental influences. This characteristic of the NR3C1 gene (and possibly other genes) may provide humans with an increased capacity for rapid change and adaptation to environmental stressors without producing long-lasting evolutionary change.  Our research has important implications for health and well-being in the United States  because many Americans experience high levels of stress (49% of Americans  report a major stressful event over the past year and 26% report a  "great deal" of stress over the previous month; poll by Harvard  University School of Public Health). We hope to provide a better understanding of the underlying mechanism of the biological impacts of stress.       Last Modified: 09/01/2016       Submitted by: Connie J Mulligan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
