<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Piezoresistive Effects in Single Molecule Devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mahmoud Fallahi</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this program is to understand the effects of mechanical stresses and perturbations on the electronic properties of single molecule systems. By exploring the impacts of contact geometry, molecule-electrode coupling strength, tensile and compressive forces, and electron-phonon interactions on the charge transport properties of these devices this project will provide new information about how the detailed, atomic-level configuration of molecular systems affects the electronic properties.&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this proposal is that developing a comprehensive understanding of the intricate interplay between the mechanical and electrical properties of single-molecule systems will provide important information about controlling charge transport in these systems and enable transformative progress in the development of functional molecular-electronic systems. This includes the exploration of new functional paradigms for electromechanical computational schemes and transducers that can convert mechanical stimuli into electrical signals for use in sensor systems.&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts are that knowledge about the interaction between mechanical structure and charge transport will affect a variety of fields beyond molecular-scale electronics. This includes biology and chemistry where these interactions are extremely important for understanding protein systems like photosynthetic reactions centers.  This research will also impact the study of both bulk organic and nanoscale electronics since controlling charge transport mechanically may allow for novel sensors, devices, and applications. Furthermore, the interdisciplinary research and educational program in this program will be three tiered with efforts focused on exposing K-12 students to engineering disciplines, undergraduate research opportunities, and graduate training and education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1231915</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Hihath</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua Hihath</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhihath@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307547700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000612904</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UC Davis]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956165294</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>103E</Code>
<Text>Energy efficient electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>104E</Code>
<Text>MEMS/NEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8028</Code>
<Text>Sensor Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~113332</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~117428</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~129240</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The goal of this project is to understand how mechanical perturbations affect the electronic properties of molecular-scale systems and devices. &nbsp;There are several factors that contribute to electronic changes in a molecular system when a strain is applied, this includes changes in the molecule-electrode contact, force dispersion within molecular bonds, electronic instabilities due to effects such as the Peierls transition, and charge density redistribution in response to a structural modification. &nbsp;In this project we have explored each of these effects to determine which processes influence the electromechanical properties of molecular devices. &nbsp;One major outcome of this project has been the development of a new electromechanical spectroscopy that is able to provide atomic-level information about the configuration of the molecule, contact, and electrode within a single-molecule device. This spectroscopy works by applying a high-frequency mechanical modulation to the molecular junction and measuring the current response at that frequency. By repeating these measurements thousands of times to obtain statistical information, and systematically examining families of related molecules, it is possible to determine the most probable configuration of a single-molecule device. &nbsp;A second major outcome of this work is a direct demonstration that environment can be used to control the structure, and thereby the transport properties of DNA (see Figure).&nbsp; By changing the solution environment around a double-stranded DNA duplex it is possible to transition it from the normal, ubiquitous, B-form conformation to a more compact A-form. This change in conformation causes a change in the conductance of about 10 times. This change is fully reversible, thus opening the possibility for creating DNA-based electromechanical switches.</span></p> <p><span>Understanding the interplay between mechanical/structural changes and the electronic properties of molecular devices will aide in the development of robust molecular-electronic devices with potentially novel electromechanical functionality. Such systems are may broadly impact the electronics industry, and understanding the charge transport properties of DNA may also enable the development of novel sensing platforms which would broadly impact the biological sciences and health-care. Further, this project has provided the students and post-doctoral researchers involved with a broad, transdisciplinary training opportunity.</span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/15/2016<br>      Modified by: Joshua&nbsp;Hihath</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1231915/1231915_10212666_1479232662658_Featured_img_Light1000X1000--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1231915/1231915_10212666_1479232662658_Featured_img_Light1000X1000--rgov-800width.jpg" title="DNA Conductance Properties"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1231915/1231915_10212666_1479232662658_Featured_img_Light1000X1000--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="DNA Conductance Properties"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic Representation of a single A-form DNA bound between two electrodes. The wavefunction for the the Highest Occupied Molecular Orbital is superimposed on the DNA.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Juan Manuel Artes</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joshua&nbsp;Hihath</div> <div class="imageTitle">DNA Conductance Properties</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project is to understand how mechanical perturbations affect the electronic properties of molecular-scale systems and devices.  There are several factors that contribute to electronic changes in a molecular system when a strain is applied, this includes changes in the molecule-electrode contact, force dispersion within molecular bonds, electronic instabilities due to effects such as the Peierls transition, and charge density redistribution in response to a structural modification.  In this project we have explored each of these effects to determine which processes influence the electromechanical properties of molecular devices.  One major outcome of this project has been the development of a new electromechanical spectroscopy that is able to provide atomic-level information about the configuration of the molecule, contact, and electrode within a single-molecule device. This spectroscopy works by applying a high-frequency mechanical modulation to the molecular junction and measuring the current response at that frequency. By repeating these measurements thousands of times to obtain statistical information, and systematically examining families of related molecules, it is possible to determine the most probable configuration of a single-molecule device.  A second major outcome of this work is a direct demonstration that environment can be used to control the structure, and thereby the transport properties of DNA (see Figure).  By changing the solution environment around a double-stranded DNA duplex it is possible to transition it from the normal, ubiquitous, B-form conformation to a more compact A-form. This change in conformation causes a change in the conductance of about 10 times. This change is fully reversible, thus opening the possibility for creating DNA-based electromechanical switches.  Understanding the interplay between mechanical/structural changes and the electronic properties of molecular devices will aide in the development of robust molecular-electronic devices with potentially novel electromechanical functionality. Such systems are may broadly impact the electronics industry, and understanding the charge transport properties of DNA may also enable the development of novel sensing platforms which would broadly impact the biological sciences and health-care. Further, this project has provided the students and post-doctoral researchers involved with a broad, transdisciplinary training opportunity.           Last Modified: 11/15/2016       Submitted by: Joshua Hihath]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
