<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Flexible Silicon Photonics on Plastic Substrates</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>346245.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>346245</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dominique Dagenais</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddagenai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922980</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Summary: The objective of this research is to demonstrate a new flexible form of silicon photonics integrated on plastic substrates, using a bond-and-transfer method. The new silicon-on-plastic photonics combines the high performance of silicon devices and the flexibility of plastic materials. The thin film format and its mechanical compliance will enable this unconventional form of photonic devices to be mechanically tunable and to be applied as optomechanical sensors. Furthermore, the plastic substrate provides a versatile platform for heterogeneous integration of passive silicon devices with active, non-silicon devices &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: Despite extensive research in flexible electronics, flexible form of integrated photonics has not been widely explored. The proposed research will demonstrate highly integrated silicon photonic devices on plastic substrates with unprecedented flexibility, tunability and compatibility. Integration of flexible photonics with microelectronics will yield a multifunctional optoelectronic system in a soft format, leading to transformative advances in areas ranging from optical communication to fundamental metrology and mechanical measurement.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The project will impact industry and the scientific community by providing a new class of optical sensors that is flexible and conformal.  The education and outreach activities will encourage high-schools students to pursue a career in science and engineering and recruit minority students to participate in research. In collaboration with the Science Museum of Minnesota, a series of experimental demonstrations of optical science (named ?The Light Fantastic?) will be presented during the Nanodays events to foster public awareness, engagement and understanding of nanoscale science, engineering and technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1232064</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mo</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mo Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>moli96@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066166966</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000572441</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554550160</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 Union St Se]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094E</Code>
<Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~346245</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of the project is to develop processes to fabricate&nbsp;flexible silicon photonic devices on plastic substrates and develop applications in flexible optical sensors, tunable photonic devices, and biophotonic sensors. During the four year period of the project, we have successfully developed several methods to fabricate and transfer integrated silicon photonic circuit from the original rigid substrate to flexible, plastic substrate. One fabrication method was developed to critically under-cut etch the silicon photonic circuit fabricated on a&nbsp;silicon-on-insulator&nbsp;substrate and peel them off with a PDMS elastomer rubber stamp. We demonstrate that this transfer process can have a very high yield and maintain the critical dimensions of the original photonic devices with unaffected performance. We further&nbsp;show&nbsp;that the characteristics of the photonic devices, including interferometers and ring resonators, on the flexible PDMS substrate can be mechanically tuned over a very wide range that is unattainable with other methods. We have also developed a second method to transfer a whole membrane of silicon or silicon nitride along with integrated photonic devices on to plastic substrates. This method does not limit the dimensions of the devices so a wider category of photonic devices, including photonic crystal cavities, can be transferred. We have shown that both silicon and silicon nitride devices can be transferred to a wide variety of plastic substrates such as PET. Finally, we use this transfer method to transfer silicon photonic devices on to unconventional substrate materials to enable new device functions. For example, we successfully transferred silicon ring resonators from SOI to calcium difluoride (CaF2) substrate, which is transparent over a wide infrared spectral range. We have used such silicon on CaF2 photonic devices to demonstrate cavity enhanced infrared spectroscopic sensing of organic analytes with comparable sensitivity and resolution to the conventional Fourier Transform Infrared (FT-IR) Spectroscopy instruments but on integrated, chip-scale devices.&nbsp;</p> <p>In summary, the outcome of this project includes the successful development of the method to fabricate flexible photonic devices that can be mechanically tuned and applied as mechanical sensors; and a transfer method that in principle can be used to make integrated photonic devices on arbitrary substrates including plastic and solid materials. The research will have a broad impact on optical sensor technology.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/09/2017<br>      Modified by: Mo&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1232064/1232064_10190026_1510243984016_IMG_2948_ps--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1232064/1232064_10190026_1510243984016_IMG_2948_ps--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Silicon on CaF2 photonics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1232064/1232064_10190026_1510243984016_IMG_2948_ps--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Silicon on CaF2 photonics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Silicon photonic circuits are transferred on to CaF2 substrate to enable chip-scale cavity enhanced IR spectroscopic sensing of chemicals.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Yu Chen</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mo&nbsp;Li</div> <div class="imageTitle">Silicon on CaF2 photonics</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of the project is to develop processes to fabricate flexible silicon photonic devices on plastic substrates and develop applications in flexible optical sensors, tunable photonic devices, and biophotonic sensors. During the four year period of the project, we have successfully developed several methods to fabricate and transfer integrated silicon photonic circuit from the original rigid substrate to flexible, plastic substrate. One fabrication method was developed to critically under-cut etch the silicon photonic circuit fabricated on a silicon-on-insulator substrate and peel them off with a PDMS elastomer rubber stamp. We demonstrate that this transfer process can have a very high yield and maintain the critical dimensions of the original photonic devices with unaffected performance. We further show that the characteristics of the photonic devices, including interferometers and ring resonators, on the flexible PDMS substrate can be mechanically tuned over a very wide range that is unattainable with other methods. We have also developed a second method to transfer a whole membrane of silicon or silicon nitride along with integrated photonic devices on to plastic substrates. This method does not limit the dimensions of the devices so a wider category of photonic devices, including photonic crystal cavities, can be transferred. We have shown that both silicon and silicon nitride devices can be transferred to a wide variety of plastic substrates such as PET. Finally, we use this transfer method to transfer silicon photonic devices on to unconventional substrate materials to enable new device functions. For example, we successfully transferred silicon ring resonators from SOI to calcium difluoride (CaF2) substrate, which is transparent over a wide infrared spectral range. We have used such silicon on CaF2 photonic devices to demonstrate cavity enhanced infrared spectroscopic sensing of organic analytes with comparable sensitivity and resolution to the conventional Fourier Transform Infrared (FT-IR) Spectroscopy instruments but on integrated, chip-scale devices.   In summary, the outcome of this project includes the successful development of the method to fabricate flexible photonic devices that can be mechanically tuned and applied as mechanical sensors; and a transfer method that in principle can be used to make integrated photonic devices on arbitrary substrates including plastic and solid materials. The research will have a broad impact on optical sensor technology.       Last Modified: 11/09/2017       Submitted by: Mo Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
