<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Selecting and Applying an Inverse Method to Infer Particle Dynamics from GEOTRACES Data</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>529388.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>529388</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henrietta Edmonds</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hedmonds@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927427</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Processes affecting ocean particles have important consequences for the marine biogeochemical cycles of trace elements; however, our present understanding of these processes is incomplete, as shown by the very large uncertainties (spanning orders of magnitude) of current estimates of particle cycling rates in the ocean. The extensive trace element dataset being generated as part of the GEOTRACES program provides an opportunity to enhance our knowledge of particle processes in a variety of oceanic environments.  A scientist from Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution plans to determine the adequacy of different inverse methods to constrain particle processes such as solid-solution exchange and particle processes in the water column from measurements of thorium isotope activity, particle composition, and particle concentration in different size fractions. To attain this goal, the researcher would first assess the adequacy of different inverse methods to infer, from such an eclectic dataset, rate constants of sorption reactions (adsorption and desorption) and particle dynamics (aggregation, disaggregation, sinking, and remineralization). The second step would involve applying the selected method to estimate these constants and their uncertainties at the "superstations" of the GEOTRACES North Atlantic Zonal Section. Once the model is in place, the scientist would test the hypotheses that the rate constants varied (1) vertically within the mesopelagic layer and the deeper layers at these stations and (2) horizontally across the diverse environments sampled along the section.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:  The software to be developed would be archived with the Biological and Chemical Oceanography Data Management Office with instructions so other scientist can use it. One graduate student would be trained on the use of inverse methods in data analyses.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1232578</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Olivier</FirstName>
<LastName>Marchal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Olivier Marchal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>omarchal@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5082893374</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000101925</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<ZipCode>025431535</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082892623</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>266 Wood Hole Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Fenno House, MS#39]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001766682</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WOODS HOLE OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTITUTION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001766682</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution]]></Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[266 Woods Hole Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1670</Code>
<Text>Chemical Oceanography</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6892</Code>
<Text>CI REUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~529388</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project, we have applied inverse methods to analyze measurements of metal and particle concentrations in oceanic samples collected during the GEOTRACES program. Inverse methods are techniques that can be used to make inferences about natural phenomena from the quantitative combination of observations and theories. Whilst such phenomena may not be directly observable, their very occurrence, and the rates at which they occur, can be inferred from other observations in the presence of a model (a classical example is the inference of the structure of the Earth interior from surface observations in the presence of a geodynamical model). In our project, inverse methods were used to extract information about the interactions of dissolved metals with solid particles in ocean waters. Phenonema of particular interest included (i) the attachment of metals onto the surfaces of particles ("adsorption") and (ii) the subsequent removal of particles by gravitational settling. Both phenomena are responsible for the removal of metals from the ocean to the sediment and are collectively called "particle scavenging". Whereas they cannot easily be observed in situ, the rates at which they occur can be determined by fitting particle scavenging models to measurements of metal and particle concentrations in seawater samples.</p> <p>Our project relied on three ingredients: a dataset, a model, and an inverse method. The dataset consisted in radiochemical and particle measurements at several stations occupied during the GEOTRACES North Atlantic transect GA03 (Fig. 1). We used measurements of the concentrations of three radio-isotopes of thorium (Th-228, Th-230, and Th-234) and particles, in three different particulate size fractions. Thorium (Th) is a chemical element that is known to be very particle-reactive in seawater, hence the use of Th data for this project. We also used measurements of the concentration of radium-228 (the radioactive parent of Th-228) as well as observational estimates of the concentrations of uranium-234 (parent of Th-230) and uranium-238 (parent of Th-234).</p> <p>The model considered for our project constituted a relatively simple description of particle scavenging in the oceanic water column (Fig. 2). It included two components: a Th cycling model and a particle cycling model. The Th cycling model represented the effects of radioactive production and decay, Th adsorption onto particles, Th desorption (i.e., detachment) from particles, particle degradation, and particle settling. The particle model represented the effects of particle degradation and particle settling.</p> <p>Different inverse methods were applied to combine the Th and particle data with the Th and particle cycling model. Each of these methods is a least-squares technique, aimed at a model solution that minimizes the sum of the squared deviations from the measurements, given the measurement errors.</p> <p>Intellectual merit. Our major results are the following. (1) A model that allows variations of rate constants of Th and  particle cycling along the water column provides a  significantly better fit to the data than a model that does not. (2) The specific rate at which Th attaches to particles relative to  that at which it is released from particles is higher in the upper ocean  than in the deep ocean (Fig. 3). (3) Noticeable variations in the rate constants of Th cycling and particle cycling were found along GA03 (Fig. 4). (4) The rate constant of Th adsorption (k1) generally decreases with depth (Fig. 5) and increases with particle concentration (Fig. 6), consistent with the notion that Th attachment onto particles increases with the number of surface sites available for adsorption. (5) Among the various components of the marine particulate matter, particulate  organic matter is the major agent responsible for the spatial variability of k1 along GA03, consistent with an important role of organic molecules in Th adsorption experiments conducted in the laboratory.</p> <p>Broader impacts. (1) This project provided full support to a graduate student. This student has been involved in virtually all facets of this project (ranging from the development of computer codes to the writing of manuscripts for peer review), has prepared and presented posters at multiple conferences, has attended a summer school on marine particles, and has interacted with a number of established scientists. (2) This project has brought together two researchers with distinct experience: an ocean modeler (O. Marchal) and a chemical oceanographer (P. Lam). (3) By enhancing our understanding of the spatial variability of particle scavenging in the ocean, this project should contribute to refined representations of this process in global ocean models and to the interpretation of deep-sea sediment records of particle-reactive elements, in particular records of the ratio of protactinium-231 to thorium-230. (4) The computational software developed over the course of this project together with a manual will be submited in Fall 2016 to the Biological and Chemical Oceanography Data Management Office. This way, our approach of data analysis could be applied by other researchers to study the cycle of other particle-reactive substances in the ocean.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Olivier&nbsp;Marchal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472495523905_image_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472495523905_image_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The U.S. GEOTRACES North Atlantic transect"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472495523905_image_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The U.S. GEOTRACES North Atlantic transect"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Stations of GEOTRACES North Atlantic transect GA03. The grey (black) circles show stations occupied during the first (second) leg. The open circle shows the cross-station occupied during the two legs. The stations labelled with a red star are those for which data have been analyzed for this project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lerner et al. (unpublished manuscript)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Olivier&nbsp;Marchal</div> <div class="imageTitle">The U.S. GEOTRACES North Atlantic transect</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472496219647_image_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472496219647_image_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Schematic of Th and particle cycling model"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472496219647_image_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Schematic of Th and particle cycling model"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic diagram of Th and particle cycling model considered for this project. "A" and "P" stand for Th isotope activity and particle concentration, respectively. "d" and "p" stand for dissolved and particulate fractions, respectively. The other symbols represent the various processes of the model.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lerner et al. (DSR, 2016)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Olivier&nbsp;Marchal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Schematic of Th and particle cycling model</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472496417337_image_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472496417337_image_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Scavenging intensity at station GT11-22"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472496417337_image_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Scavenging intensity at station GT11-22"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Vertical distribution of the rate constant ratio K = k1/(k_1+b_1) at station GT11-22 of the GA03 transect. Here k1, k_1, and b_1 are the rate constants for Th adsorption, Th desorption, and particle degradation, respectively. The error bars represent one standard deviation.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lerner et al. (DSR, 2016)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Olivier&nbsp;Marchal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Scavenging intensity at station GT11-22</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472496628081_image_4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472496628081_image_4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Distribution of rate constants of Th and particle cycling along GA03 transect"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472496628081_image_4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Distribution of rate constants of Th and particle cycling along GA03 transect"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Rate constants of Th adsorption (k1), Th desorption (k_1), particle degradation (b_1), and particle settling (w) along the GA03 transect.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lerner et al. (unpublished manuscript)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Olivier&nbsp;Marchal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Distribution of rate constants of Th and particle cycling along GA03 transect</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472497053153_image_5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472497053153_image_5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Vertical distribution of Th adsorption rate constant at GA03 stations"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472497053153_image_5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Vertical distribution of Th adsorption rate constant at GA03 stations"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Stations GT11-10 (a), GT11-12 (b), GT11-14 (c), GT11-16 (d), GT11-18 (e), GT11-20 (f), GT11-22 (g), GT11-24 (h), GT10-12 (i), GT10-11 (j), and GT10-10 (k). Grey asterisks are prior estimates (vertically uniform values) and horizontal bars represent one standard deviation.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lerner et al. (unpublished manuscript)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Olivier&nbsp;Marchal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Vertical distribution of Th adsorption rate constant at GA03 stations</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472497425039_image_6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472497425039_image_6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Variation of Th adsorption rate constant with particle concentration along GA03 transect"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1232578/1232578_10197849_1472497425039_image_6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Variation of Th adsorption rate constant with particle concentration along GA03 transect"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The values of Th adsorption rate constant (k1) are inferred by inversion, and the values of particle concentration (P) are measurements. The horizontal and vertical bars show one standard deviation. The solid line is a least-squares fit that accounts for the errors in both k1 and P.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lerner et al. (unpublished manuscript)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Olivier&nbsp;Marchal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Variation of Th adsorption rate constant with particle concentration along GA03 transect</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project, we have applied inverse methods to analyze measurements of metal and particle concentrations in oceanic samples collected during the GEOTRACES program. Inverse methods are techniques that can be used to make inferences about natural phenomena from the quantitative combination of observations and theories. Whilst such phenomena may not be directly observable, their very occurrence, and the rates at which they occur, can be inferred from other observations in the presence of a model (a classical example is the inference of the structure of the Earth interior from surface observations in the presence of a geodynamical model). In our project, inverse methods were used to extract information about the interactions of dissolved metals with solid particles in ocean waters. Phenonema of particular interest included (i) the attachment of metals onto the surfaces of particles ("adsorption") and (ii) the subsequent removal of particles by gravitational settling. Both phenomena are responsible for the removal of metals from the ocean to the sediment and are collectively called "particle scavenging". Whereas they cannot easily be observed in situ, the rates at which they occur can be determined by fitting particle scavenging models to measurements of metal and particle concentrations in seawater samples.  Our project relied on three ingredients: a dataset, a model, and an inverse method. The dataset consisted in radiochemical and particle measurements at several stations occupied during the GEOTRACES North Atlantic transect GA03 (Fig. 1). We used measurements of the concentrations of three radio-isotopes of thorium (Th-228, Th-230, and Th-234) and particles, in three different particulate size fractions. Thorium (Th) is a chemical element that is known to be very particle-reactive in seawater, hence the use of Th data for this project. We also used measurements of the concentration of radium-228 (the radioactive parent of Th-228) as well as observational estimates of the concentrations of uranium-234 (parent of Th-230) and uranium-238 (parent of Th-234).  The model considered for our project constituted a relatively simple description of particle scavenging in the oceanic water column (Fig. 2). It included two components: a Th cycling model and a particle cycling model. The Th cycling model represented the effects of radioactive production and decay, Th adsorption onto particles, Th desorption (i.e., detachment) from particles, particle degradation, and particle settling. The particle model represented the effects of particle degradation and particle settling.  Different inverse methods were applied to combine the Th and particle data with the Th and particle cycling model. Each of these methods is a least-squares technique, aimed at a model solution that minimizes the sum of the squared deviations from the measurements, given the measurement errors.  Intellectual merit. Our major results are the following. (1) A model that allows variations of rate constants of Th and  particle cycling along the water column provides a  significantly better fit to the data than a model that does not. (2) The specific rate at which Th attaches to particles relative to  that at which it is released from particles is higher in the upper ocean  than in the deep ocean (Fig. 3). (3) Noticeable variations in the rate constants of Th cycling and particle cycling were found along GA03 (Fig. 4). (4) The rate constant of Th adsorption (k1) generally decreases with depth (Fig. 5) and increases with particle concentration (Fig. 6), consistent with the notion that Th attachment onto particles increases with the number of surface sites available for adsorption. (5) Among the various components of the marine particulate matter, particulate  organic matter is the major agent responsible for the spatial variability of k1 along GA03, consistent with an important role of organic molecules in Th adsorption experiments conducted in the laboratory.  Broader impacts. (1) This project provided full support to a graduate student. This student has been involved in virtually all facets of this project (ranging from the development of computer codes to the writing of manuscripts for peer review), has prepared and presented posters at multiple conferences, has attended a summer school on marine particles, and has interacted with a number of established scientists. (2) This project has brought together two researchers with distinct experience: an ocean modeler (O. Marchal) and a chemical oceanographer (P. Lam). (3) By enhancing our understanding of the spatial variability of particle scavenging in the ocean, this project should contribute to refined representations of this process in global ocean models and to the interpretation of deep-sea sediment records of particle-reactive elements, in particular records of the ratio of protactinium-231 to thorium-230. (4) The computational software developed over the course of this project together with a manual will be submited in Fall 2016 to the Biological and Chemical Oceanography Data Management Office. This way, our approach of data analysis could be applied by other researchers to study the cycle of other particle-reactive substances in the ocean.       Last Modified: 08/29/2016       Submitted by: Olivier Marchal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
