<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: US GEOTRACES Pacific Section - Measurement of the organic complexation of dissolved iron, copper and cobalt, and total dissolved cobalt</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>217000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>217000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henrietta Edmonds</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hedmonds@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927427</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Dissolved iron (Fe), copper (Cu), and cobalt (Co) are essential elements for phytoplankton growth which in turn influences the marine carbon cycle; however, despite this important role, the cycling, distribution, and bioavailability of these bioactive elements remains poorly understood.  For example, strong organic ligands influence bioavailability and solubility, but it is unclear how interactions change throughout the water column under variable conditions. Recognizing a need for this data, researchers from the Bermuda Institute of Ocean Sciences, Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, and Scripps Institute of Oceanography will measure the organic complexation of dissolved Fe, Cu, and Co as well as total dissolved Co concentrations during the 2013 GEOTRACES cruise which will transect the coastal upwelling zone off Peru, an intense oxygen minimum zone, the East Pacific Rise hydrothermal plume, and the oligotrophic waters near Tahiti.  This study will result in a significant dataset on the speciation of these bioactive elements throughout the water column which will help assess the relationships between dissolved Fe, Cu, and Co distributions and ligand concentration gradients and will likely reveal large chemical gradients over this dynamic oceanographic region.  As regards dissolved Co concentrations, these measurements should provide new insights on the marine biogeochemistry of the element, especially in relation to oxygen minimum zones and hydrothermal plumes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In terms of the broader impacts, for the outreach efforts, the researchers plan to disseminate results from their work to the public via the web, during tours at the Bermuda Institute of Ocean Sciences (BIOS), and at the annual BIOS Marine Science Service Day open house, as well as through a five-part webinar series produced in collaboration with the Center for Ocean Sciences Education Excellence-Ocean Systems at the University of Maine and classroom curricula.  One graduate student from Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution and one graduate student from Scripps Institute of Oceanography would be trained and supported as part of this project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1233733</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Barbeau</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katherine Barbeau</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kbarbeau@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8588224339</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000116479</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Univ of California-San Diego]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>175104595</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UCSD - Scripps Inst of Oceanography]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1670</Code>
<Text>Chemical Oceanography</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9198</Code>
<Text>OTHER ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~108346</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~62299</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~46355</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Copper is a trace metal of interest in the marine environment because it can affect the health of marine microbes, for example phytoplankton at the base of the marine food web. Copper can be toxic to phytoplankton at elevated concentrations, and can also act as a limiting nutrient in ocean regions where its concentrations are very low. The biological impact and cycling of copper are largely controlled by the interaction of copper with dissolved organic ligands in seawater, which bind to (i.e. form complexes with) the copper and affect its biological availability and particle reactivity, among other properties. In this study we applied a competitive ligand exchange voltammetric technique to learn about the organic complexation of dissolved copper along the GEOTRACES Eastern tropical Pacific GP16 transect. The data set that we have produced is the largest data set thus far produced on the chemical species of copper in the ocean. Our data indicate that ligands occur in excess of copper throughout the transect, keeping the levels of biologically available free copper below toxicity, especially in surface waters. In the far eastern, iron-limited surface waters of the transect, free copper is extremely low, which may be related to the iron limitation of phytoplankton in that region. Free copper levels are also very low in the low productivity western surface waters of the transect. Highest levels of free copper are found in the deepest parts of the water column, in water that has been isolated from the surface for hundreds of years. Free copper concentrations in these deep waters do approach levels that are toxic to some sensitive microorganisms. The presence of copper binding ligands in deep waters is likely important in controlling the concentration of total dissolved copper.&nbsp; Our data set has greatly expanded the amount of data available on copper chemistry in ocean waters.</p> <p>In addition to producing a valuable dataset this project also funded the PhD research of graduate student Angel Ruacho, an under-represented minority student. The PI also participated in a collaborative webinar series on GEOTRACES sponsored by the Center for Ocean Sciences Education Excellence-Ocean Systems (COSEE-OS) group based at the University of Maine.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Katherine&nbsp;Barbeau</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1233733/1233733_10235774_1530140156242_FreeCu--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1233733/1233733_10235774_1530140156242_FreeCu--rgov-800width.jpg" title="GP16 inorganic copper"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1233733/1233733_10235774_1530140156242_FreeCu--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="GP16 inorganic copper"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Free copper ion concentrations along the GEOTRACES GP16 transect</div> <div class="imageCredit">Katherine Barbeau</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Katherine&nbsp;Barbeau</div> <div class="imageTitle">GP16 inorganic copper</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Copper is a trace metal of interest in the marine environment because it can affect the health of marine microbes, for example phytoplankton at the base of the marine food web. Copper can be toxic to phytoplankton at elevated concentrations, and can also act as a limiting nutrient in ocean regions where its concentrations are very low. The biological impact and cycling of copper are largely controlled by the interaction of copper with dissolved organic ligands in seawater, which bind to (i.e. form complexes with) the copper and affect its biological availability and particle reactivity, among other properties. In this study we applied a competitive ligand exchange voltammetric technique to learn about the organic complexation of dissolved copper along the GEOTRACES Eastern tropical Pacific GP16 transect. The data set that we have produced is the largest data set thus far produced on the chemical species of copper in the ocean. Our data indicate that ligands occur in excess of copper throughout the transect, keeping the levels of biologically available free copper below toxicity, especially in surface waters. In the far eastern, iron-limited surface waters of the transect, free copper is extremely low, which may be related to the iron limitation of phytoplankton in that region. Free copper levels are also very low in the low productivity western surface waters of the transect. Highest levels of free copper are found in the deepest parts of the water column, in water that has been isolated from the surface for hundreds of years. Free copper concentrations in these deep waters do approach levels that are toxic to some sensitive microorganisms. The presence of copper binding ligands in deep waters is likely important in controlling the concentration of total dissolved copper.  Our data set has greatly expanded the amount of data available on copper chemistry in ocean waters.  In addition to producing a valuable dataset this project also funded the PhD research of graduate student Angel Ruacho, an under-represented minority student. The PI also participated in a collaborative webinar series on GEOTRACES sponsored by the Center for Ocean Sciences Education Excellence-Ocean Systems (COSEE-OS) group based at the University of Maine.          Last Modified: 06/27/2018       Submitted by: Katherine Barbeau]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
