<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Ultrasonic Vibration Assisted NanoMachining for High-rate Tunable 2D and 3D Nanofabrication</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>358017.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>358017</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>khcooper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927017</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this research is to investigate a low cost, high speed, tunable NanoMachining approach using sharp cantilever tips with the help of ultrasonic vibration. The controllable ultrasonic vibration between the tip and the sample enables tunable fabrication of features across a wide dimensional range in one pass with high efficiency. This research incorporates process innovation and process modeling (empirical models for analysis of the nanomachining process with respect to material, geometric and process parameters) to create a novel manufacturing process for high rate nanofabrication. A high speed, high precision nanopositioning stage will be explored to fully utilize the high rate capabilities of the ultrasonic vibration assisted nanomachining process to create a novel manufacturing system, capable of high-throughput fabrication of 2D and 3D nanoscale features.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results of this research will advance the emerging nanomanufacturing industry by providing a low-cost, high-throughput method for the fabrication of 2D and 3D nanostructures. Considering the cost and high investment of other nanofabrication approaches (e.g. e-beam lithography, EUV-lithography), the results from this research will provide a transformative and efficient framework for the fabrication of nanoscale features and devices with the potential to contribute to many evolutionary products, such as nano-electronics, solar cells, photonics, and biomedical devices. Moreover, this research will integrate broad discoveries in nanotechnologies, nanofabrication, mechanics, process modeling, and instrumentation into a high rate, cost effective nanomanufacturing system. Meanwhile, the planned multidisciplinary research-based education program will link the research outcomes and students? activities to the needs of contemporary industry for nanotechnology, nanofabrication, and instrumentation. The research results will be broadly disseminated through technical publications, workshops, regular and short courses, and K-12 outreach program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1233176</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Cohen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul H Cohen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pcohen@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195132857</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000109378</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jingyan</FirstName>
<LastName>Dong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jingyan Dong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jdong@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195157196</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000307339</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957906</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[111 Lampe Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1788</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>084E</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8025</Code>
<Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~358017</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this project is to investigate a low-cost high-speed tunable nanofabrication approach using sharp cantilever tips with the help of ultrasonic vibration on an AFM platform. The controllable ultrasonic vibration of the sample enables tunable fabrication of features across a wide dimensional range in one pass with high efficiency. This project incorporates process innovation and process modeling to create a novel manufacturing system capable of high-rate fabrication of 2D and 3D nanoscale features.</p> <p>In this project, we developed an ultrasonic vibration assisted nanomachining process, and successfully applied this process in the fabrication of 2D and 3D nanoscale features on polymer and metal substrates. In this process, an ultrasonic frequency z-vibration was generated to regulate the fabrication depth, and a high frequency circular motion between the tip and the sample in <em>xy-</em>plane was added to achieve reliable control of feature width and increase material remove rate. Nano features can be machined on PMMA and aluminum surfaces with both depth and width regulated in one machining pass. With the help of ultrasonic z-vibration, the fabrication depth is predominantly controlled by the amplitude of the ultrasonic z-vibration, and is insensitive to substrate materials and other process conditions, which indicate great potential of using ultrasonic z-vibration in regulating the feature depth. We developed an 3D nanomachining approach by integrating ultrasonic vibration assisted nanomachining process with proper pattern design and control of machining procedure. Complex 3D nanostructures were fabricated successfully using the ultrasonic vibration assisted nanomachining process.</p> <p>Besides fabricating patterns directly on many substrates, ultrasonic vibration assisted nanomachining can be used as a nanolithography process to fabricating features on polymer films, and then transfer to other functional substrates. After fabricating 2D or 3D nanostructures on polymer film (i.e. resist), RIE process can be further utilized to transfer these 2D and 3D nanostructures from polymer films onto a silicon substrate. The patterns can be reliably transferred from features that are machining on PMMA film to silicon substrate with sub-100 nm resolution.</p> <p>A theoretical analysis of the sample contact stiffness and dynamic stiffness of the cantilever was used to explain the observed depth regulation from ultrasonic z-vibration. After applying ultrasonic tip-sample vibration in z- direction, significant reduction of the normal force and lateral force (friction) was observed during nanomachining. The reduced machining force by ultrasonic vibration significantly reduces tip wear and elongate tip life for nanomachining process. To understand and plan the nanomachining process, process models were developed to predict the feature dimensions with respect to the machining parameters including setpoint force, XY vibration amplitude and feed rate. we also developed a machining force model that is directly related to the instant material removal in each vibration cycle, and validated this model for the effectiveness in predicting the dynamic machining force through experiments.</p> <p>This research will advance the emerging nanomanufacturing industry by providing a low-cost high-throughput method for the fabrication of 2D and 3D nanostructures. Considering the cost and high investment of other nanofabrication approaches (e.g. e-beam lithography), this research will provide a transformative and efficient framework for the fabrication and rapid prototyping of nanoscale features and devices with low cost. The research results have been broadly disseminated through technical publications, workshops, courses, and K-12 outreach program. A lab module was developed to provide undergraduate students with hands-on experience in nanotechnology in a NUE course MAE/ISE/MSE 495 Introduction to Multidisciplinary Nanotechnology Laboratory. This project also provided demonstrations and lab tours for high school students in NCSU Summer Camp and Summer school for the undergraduate students.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Jingyan&nbsp;Dong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this project is to investigate a low-cost high-speed tunable nanofabrication approach using sharp cantilever tips with the help of ultrasonic vibration on an AFM platform. The controllable ultrasonic vibration of the sample enables tunable fabrication of features across a wide dimensional range in one pass with high efficiency. This project incorporates process innovation and process modeling to create a novel manufacturing system capable of high-rate fabrication of 2D and 3D nanoscale features.  In this project, we developed an ultrasonic vibration assisted nanomachining process, and successfully applied this process in the fabrication of 2D and 3D nanoscale features on polymer and metal substrates. In this process, an ultrasonic frequency z-vibration was generated to regulate the fabrication depth, and a high frequency circular motion between the tip and the sample in xy-plane was added to achieve reliable control of feature width and increase material remove rate. Nano features can be machined on PMMA and aluminum surfaces with both depth and width regulated in one machining pass. With the help of ultrasonic z-vibration, the fabrication depth is predominantly controlled by the amplitude of the ultrasonic z-vibration, and is insensitive to substrate materials and other process conditions, which indicate great potential of using ultrasonic z-vibration in regulating the feature depth. We developed an 3D nanomachining approach by integrating ultrasonic vibration assisted nanomachining process with proper pattern design and control of machining procedure. Complex 3D nanostructures were fabricated successfully using the ultrasonic vibration assisted nanomachining process.  Besides fabricating patterns directly on many substrates, ultrasonic vibration assisted nanomachining can be used as a nanolithography process to fabricating features on polymer films, and then transfer to other functional substrates. After fabricating 2D or 3D nanostructures on polymer film (i.e. resist), RIE process can be further utilized to transfer these 2D and 3D nanostructures from polymer films onto a silicon substrate. The patterns can be reliably transferred from features that are machining on PMMA film to silicon substrate with sub-100 nm resolution.  A theoretical analysis of the sample contact stiffness and dynamic stiffness of the cantilever was used to explain the observed depth regulation from ultrasonic z-vibration. After applying ultrasonic tip-sample vibration in z- direction, significant reduction of the normal force and lateral force (friction) was observed during nanomachining. The reduced machining force by ultrasonic vibration significantly reduces tip wear and elongate tip life for nanomachining process. To understand and plan the nanomachining process, process models were developed to predict the feature dimensions with respect to the machining parameters including setpoint force, XY vibration amplitude and feed rate. we also developed a machining force model that is directly related to the instant material removal in each vibration cycle, and validated this model for the effectiveness in predicting the dynamic machining force through experiments.  This research will advance the emerging nanomanufacturing industry by providing a low-cost high-throughput method for the fabrication of 2D and 3D nanostructures. Considering the cost and high investment of other nanofabrication approaches (e.g. e-beam lithography), this research will provide a transformative and efficient framework for the fabrication and rapid prototyping of nanoscale features and devices with low cost. The research results have been broadly disseminated through technical publications, workshops, courses, and K-12 outreach program. A lab module was developed to provide undergraduate students with hands-on experience in nanotechnology in a NUE course MAE/ISE/MSE 495 Introduction to Multidisciplinary Nanotechnology Laboratory. This project also provided demonstrations and lab tours for high school students in NCSU Summer Camp and Summer school for the undergraduate students.       Last Modified: 11/29/2016       Submitted by: Jingyan Dong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
