<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Design, Analysis and Evaluation of Battery-Changing Infrastructure for Electric Vehicles</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>340000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>340000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Georgia-Ann Klutke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gaklutke@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922443</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>While higher use of electric vehicles (EV) is a goal of governments and organizations conscious of energy conservation and environmental sustainability, EVs still have to attract owners. This project hypothesizes that the proper placement and sizing of battery-exchange (BE) facilities will make EVs more appealing since the driver's anxiety that the vehicle will run out of charge before reaching the destination will be decreased. Optimal location of BE facilities decrease the detouring required for swapping batteries, while optimal sizing of facilities improves quality of service of the facilities. This project comprehensively addresses the "Design, Analysis and Evaluation of Battery-Changing Infrastructure for Electric Vehicles" from a systems perspective.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Greater attraction and higher market penetration of EVs will lead to a cleaner environment and less dependence on oil and gasoline. The project will be useful to automobile companies that manufacture EVs, urban and transportation planners, energy grid operators, service companies that offer recharged batteries, and, last but not least, the Denmark Technical University where the project team's collaborates with researchers who are studying to fast-track EV penetration in Denmark. Also, besides the direct relevance to EV-based transportation, the several new models and methods developed intellectually contribute to the fields of operations research, computer science, industrial engineering, transportation, geographical analysis, and related fields. They also are applicable to alternative fueled vehicles where empty tanks or canisters are exchanged for full ones, such as for hydrogen-powered vehicles. The project's educational impacts include enhancements of curricula and laboratory experiences, workforce development, and student diversity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1234584</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pitu</FirstName>
<LastName>Mirchandani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pitu Mirchandani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pitu@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809655479</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000573996</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/17/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. BOX 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1631</Code>
<Text>CIS-Civil Infrastructure Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1787</Code>
<Text>SERVICE ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>076E</Code>
<Text>SERVICE ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>078E</Code>
<Text>ENTERPRISE DESIGN &amp; LOGISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~340000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project &ldquo;<em>Design, Analysis and Evaluation of Battery-Changing Infrastructure for Electric Vehicles (EV)</em>&rdquo; studied, from a systems perspective, the logistics and management issues related to battery charging infrastructures with a special focus on battery-swapping infrastructure (BSI). In the BSI, when a vehicle can gets a charged battery it leaves its spent battery for recharging, to be used by a future battery swap. Models and algorithms were developed for four problem areas:</p> <ul> <li>(A1) How can a vehicle be routed from an origin (O) to a destination (D) without running out of charge given that a fully charged battery has a maximum range of, say, R miles and battery swaps can only occur within the range;</li> <li>(A2) Using the routing algorithms from area A1, how can we route and schedule EV bus trips, or EV pickup/delivery truck trips, given now battery swaps must take place within a given range R;</li> <li>(A3) Again, using the routing algorithms from A1, route large numbers of trips form many origins to many destinations, still respecting the range constraints, while allowing vehicles to reserve a charged battery at specific facilities along the way from each O to corresponding D; and</li> <li>(A4) While facility locations are given for areas A1-A3, this last area explored algorithms to optimally locate facilities to optimize respective measures of performance.</li> </ul> <p>Some examples illustrating project results are given in Figures 1 &ndash; 5.</p> <ul> <li>For A1 area, we show in Figure 1 that because of detouring for recharging, we show the optimal route may contain cycles and hence we refer to this route as the <em>shortest EV walk</em> on the network.</li> <li>For A2 area, because of limited battery charge, or limited vehicle range, the bus in Figure 2 needs recharging to complete time-compatible service trips. The project developed integer programming models and column generation approaches to solve realistic problems.</li> <li>Computational experiments with the approximate dynamic programming based algorithms for area A3, where routing from O to D considers anticipated total OD demands, which may be referred to as <em>systems optimal routing</em>, performs better than a policy where each vehicle uses its own shortest walk, which may be referred to as greedy, or <em>user optimal routing</em>. As Figure 3 shows, systems optimal routing is most effective, up to 23% improvements in average delay, but when either there are too many batteries in the system, or when there are too few batteries system optimal is very close to user optimal.</li> <li>Finally, regarding optimal location of recharging facilities, several versions of the problem were studied; Figure 4 shows the problems researched. The research team has developed algorithms for optimally locating on lines and trees, Figure 5 shows an example of a comb tree with discrete demand points; with localization regions for optimal location of five, the minimum necessary, facilities. The optimization problem of exactly locations within the localization set can be formulated as a shortest path problem.</li> </ul> <p>The project results can be used in the design and operations of an infrastructure for recharging batteries. These results also apply to other alternative fueled vehicles such as Compressed Natural Gas and Hydrogen fuel cells</p> <p>INTELLECTUAL CONTRIBUTIONS<br /> The research team has broken new ground in Operations Research and Industrial Engineering through the development of new models and methodologies. The complexities of EV logistics, where the vehicle is range limited and refueling (or recharging) points are sparse, adds new dimensions to the planning and operating EV based systems.</p> <p>Specific pedagogical contributions to OR/IE are</p> <ol> <li>Development of polynomial algorithms for a special case of constrained shortest path problem, where the constraints are due to (a) limited driving range, and/or (b) limiting the number of refueling stops.</li> <li>Developing new vehicle scheduling and recharging facility location models for fleets of EVs, for example electric buses, and developing exact solution methods for small problems, and approximate polynomial approaches for large problems.</li> <li>Developing a Markovian model for the following problem: vehicle request for a route from origin to destination, including reservation of refuel quantities, and then solving this problem using approximate dynamic programming.</li> <li>Development of graph theoretic results on the location of refueling points (Battery Swapping Stations) on lines and trees considering both one-way and round-trip demands. The extension of this work when the network becomes dense leads to interesting asymptotic results.</li> </ol> <p>BROADER IMPACTS<br />The results of this work will be useful to</p> <ul> <li><strong>Automobile companies</strong> who are developing or plan to develop electric vehicles,</li> <li><strong>State and local agencies</strong> that must plan for battery swapping or recharging infrastructures, as well as for alternative fuel infrastructure, and</li> <li><strong>Federal and regulatory organizations</strong> that need to permit the operations of battery swapping facilities based on potential impacts to congestion, environment and sustainability.</li> </ul> <p>Last but not least, the OR/IE results from this project have permeated into the <strong>classroom</strong>; the PI uses cases and problems based on this work in his courses.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/20/2018<br>      Modified by: Pitu&nbsp;Mirchandani</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526808250845_Figure1forNSF--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526808250845_Figure1forNSF--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Shortest Walk"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526808250845_Figure1forNSF--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Shortest Walk"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1: Shortest route from s to t is s-a-d-g-l-n-t with cost 39 units. The optimal route with charging is s-a-d-e(charge)-d-g-m(charge)-n-t with cost 43 units.</div> <div class="imageCredit">MIrchandani</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pitu&nbsp;Mirchandani</div> <div class="imageTitle">Shortest Walk</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526808538004_BusRoutingwithRefueling--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526808538004_BusRoutingwithRefueling--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Bus Routing with Refueling"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526808538004_BusRoutingwithRefueling--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Bus Routing with Refueling"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2: In order to service Trip 1 and Trip 2, the bus  finishes Trip 1 then needs detouring for recharging, and then goes to service Trip 2 and then it needs to recharge at another station to reach the depot.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mirchandani</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pitu&nbsp;Mirchandani</div> <div class="imageTitle">Bus Routing with Refueling</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526809189442_RoutingwithCentralizedReservation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526809189442_RoutingwithCentralizedReservation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Routing with Centralized Reservation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526809189442_RoutingwithCentralizedReservation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Routing with Centralized Reservation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3. Compared to greedy policy (user optimal where drivers always act in their own best interest and choose their shortest walks), one can get up to 23% shorter delays with system optimal.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mirchandani</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pitu&nbsp;Mirchandani</div> <div class="imageTitle">Routing with Centralized Reservation</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526809608548_ContinuosLocationProblems--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526809608548_ContinuosLocationProblems--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Continuous Location Problems"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526809608548_ContinuosLocationProblems--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Continuous Location Problems"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 4: Locating Refueling Points (RP) on Continuous Lines & Tree Networks</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mirchandani</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pitu&nbsp;Mirchandani</div> <div class="imageTitle">Continuous Location Problems</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526809966011_LocalizationSetforCombTree--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526809966011_LocalizationSetforCombTree--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Localization Set for Comb Tree"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1234584/1234584_10215787_1526809966011_LocalizationSetforCombTree--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Localization Set for Comb Tree"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 5: Example for a Comb Tree with discrete demand points. Localization set for 5 facilities. An optimization problem for locating facilities can be solved in polynomial time</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mirchandani</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pitu&nbsp;Mirchandani</div> <div class="imageTitle">Localization Set for Comb Tree</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project "Design, Analysis and Evaluation of Battery-Changing Infrastructure for Electric Vehicles (EV)" studied, from a systems perspective, the logistics and management issues related to battery charging infrastructures with a special focus on battery-swapping infrastructure (BSI). In the BSI, when a vehicle can gets a charged battery it leaves its spent battery for recharging, to be used by a future battery swap. Models and algorithms were developed for four problem areas:  (A1) How can a vehicle be routed from an origin (O) to a destination (D) without running out of charge given that a fully charged battery has a maximum range of, say, R miles and battery swaps can only occur within the range; (A2) Using the routing algorithms from area A1, how can we route and schedule EV bus trips, or EV pickup/delivery truck trips, given now battery swaps must take place within a given range R; (A3) Again, using the routing algorithms from A1, route large numbers of trips form many origins to many destinations, still respecting the range constraints, while allowing vehicles to reserve a charged battery at specific facilities along the way from each O to corresponding D; and (A4) While facility locations are given for areas A1-A3, this last area explored algorithms to optimally locate facilities to optimize respective measures of performance.   Some examples illustrating project results are given in Figures 1 &ndash; 5.  For A1 area, we show in Figure 1 that because of detouring for recharging, we show the optimal route may contain cycles and hence we refer to this route as the shortest EV walk on the network. For A2 area, because of limited battery charge, or limited vehicle range, the bus in Figure 2 needs recharging to complete time-compatible service trips. The project developed integer programming models and column generation approaches to solve realistic problems. Computational experiments with the approximate dynamic programming based algorithms for area A3, where routing from O to D considers anticipated total OD demands, which may be referred to as systems optimal routing, performs better than a policy where each vehicle uses its own shortest walk, which may be referred to as greedy, or user optimal routing. As Figure 3 shows, systems optimal routing is most effective, up to 23% improvements in average delay, but when either there are too many batteries in the system, or when there are too few batteries system optimal is very close to user optimal. Finally, regarding optimal location of recharging facilities, several versions of the problem were studied; Figure 4 shows the problems researched. The research team has developed algorithms for optimally locating on lines and trees, Figure 5 shows an example of a comb tree with discrete demand points; with localization regions for optimal location of five, the minimum necessary, facilities. The optimization problem of exactly locations within the localization set can be formulated as a shortest path problem.   The project results can be used in the design and operations of an infrastructure for recharging batteries. These results also apply to other alternative fueled vehicles such as Compressed Natural Gas and Hydrogen fuel cells  INTELLECTUAL CONTRIBUTIONS  The research team has broken new ground in Operations Research and Industrial Engineering through the development of new models and methodologies. The complexities of EV logistics, where the vehicle is range limited and refueling (or recharging) points are sparse, adds new dimensions to the planning and operating EV based systems.  Specific pedagogical contributions to OR/IE are  Development of polynomial algorithms for a special case of constrained shortest path problem, where the constraints are due to (a) limited driving range, and/or (b) limiting the number of refueling stops. Developing new vehicle scheduling and recharging facility location models for fleets of EVs, for example electric buses, and developing exact solution methods for small problems, and approximate polynomial approaches for large problems. Developing a Markovian model for the following problem: vehicle request for a route from origin to destination, including reservation of refuel quantities, and then solving this problem using approximate dynamic programming. Development of graph theoretic results on the location of refueling points (Battery Swapping Stations) on lines and trees considering both one-way and round-trip demands. The extension of this work when the network becomes dense leads to interesting asymptotic results.   BROADER IMPACTS The results of this work will be useful to  Automobile companies who are developing or plan to develop electric vehicles, State and local agencies that must plan for battery swapping or recharging infrastructures, as well as for alternative fuel infrastructure, and Federal and regulatory organizations that need to permit the operations of battery swapping facilities based on potential impacts to congestion, environment and sustainability.   Last but not least, the OR/IE results from this project have permeated into the classroom; the PI uses cases and problems based on this work in his courses.          Last Modified: 05/20/2018       Submitted by: Pitu Mirchandani]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
