<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Uncooled Semiconductor Nuclear Radiation Detectors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>317601.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>327468</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Irina Dolinskaya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>idolinsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927078</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research objective of this award is to test the hypothesis that the electromagnetic field associated with the nuclear radiation incident on semiconductor channels will interact with the spin of the electrons via the Rashba spin-orbit interaction mechanism. The approach will be to design 4-terminal non-local spin-valve devices comprised of wide band-gap semiconductor channels over which four electrodes will be deposited. Inner two electrodes will be made out of a ferromagnetic metal while the outer two electrodes will be made out of a nonmagnetic metal. Geometry of the magnetic electrodes will be kept different deliberately in order to make their coercivities dissimilar so that their relative orientation (parallel or antiparallel) could be changed independently. These spin-valve sensors will be exposed to controlled radiation environments and non-local measurements of magneto-resistance and Hanle-effect will be performed. Experimental research will be supported by Monte Carlo simulation and theoretical modeling to understand the mechanism of radiation-spin interaction in semiconductors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this research will lead to room-temperature nuclear radiation detectors which will find applications in various civil, mechanical, manufacturing, medical imaging and security systems. The research outcomes will greatly reduce nuclear and radiological threats and benefit the society at large. The project will promote learning and education by involving K-12, undergraduate and graduate students in the inherently interdisciplinary cooperative research activities. The discoveries of this project will be presented at related technical conferences by the principal investigators and graduate students. Research results will be published in high impact peer-reviewed journals.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1234338</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ashutosh</FirstName>
<LastName>Tiwari</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ashutosh Tiwari</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tiwari@eng.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015851666</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000063917</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Haori</FirstName>
<LastName>Yang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Haori Yang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>haori.yang@utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015816229</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000592925</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Second Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF UTAH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Utah]]></Name>
<CityName>Salt Lake City</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[122 S. Central Campus Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1639</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>032E</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND ACTUATORS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1059</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSOR SYSTEMS FOR CIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1639</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5919</Code>
<Text>INDIA (COOPERATIVE SCIENCE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7234</Code>
<Text>SENSORS NON-SOLICITATION RESEA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~317601</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~9867</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>An overarching challenge in semiconductor nuclear radiation detection technology is to surmount the thermal background problem that hinders the room temperature functionality of semiconductor detectors. Specifically, in present semiconductor detectors, radiation detection is achieved via the interaction of radiation with the detector material and subsequent creation and separation of charge carriers. For realizing high energy-resolution, it is necessary that the detector material be such that for a given energy deposition by radiation it generates a large number of charge carriers. This requirement demands the application of high atomic-weight and low band-gap semiconductors such as Germanium. Nuclear detectors utilizing low band-gap semiconductors own higher resolution compared to other detectors. However, low band-gap detectors hurt from the problem of enormous thermal background. So for reliable operation, these detectors need to be cooled to liquid nitrogen temperature. This increases the over-all cost and complexity of semiconductor detectors significantly. Moreover, the need of liquid cryogen renders semiconductor nuclear detectors useless for operation in remote areas. It is generally accepted that the incremental advances to the current semiconductor nuclear detector technology will not be sufficient for developing next generation ultra-sensitive and cost-effective detectors. Such development requires the exploration of entirely new and transformative approaches. This project has explored one such approach utilizing the concept of spintronics. Some specific outcomes of the project are summarized below:</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">&nbsp;</span></strong></p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit:</span></strong></p> <p>(i)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; It has been shown that the electromagnetic field associated with the incident nuclear radiation can interact with the spin of the electrons via the Rashba spin-orbit interaction mechanism. This interaction results in a precession in the spin of the electrons and as a result the current collected by a ferromagnetic electrode (which is aligned either parallel or antiparallel to the spin injector electrode) changes. So in contrast to semiconductor detectors, where the radiation sensing mechanism depends on the generation and collection of charge carriers, in spintronic detectors, the radiation sensing mechanism is based on the quantum mechanical de-coherence of the spins of electrons. Since the absorption of the incident radiation in the semiconductor, and subsequent generation of additional carriers, is not a requirement, wide band-gap semiconductors can be used as sensing media. This can significantly reduce the thermal background problem encountered in conventional semiconductor detectors.</p> <p>(ii)&nbsp; It has been shown that a fundamental difference between the traditional semiconductor detectors and the spintronic detectors is that the performance of traditional semiconductor detectors depends on how efficiently the charge carriers are generated by the incident radiation and then how efficiently those are separated and collected; on the other hand, the performance of a spintronic detector depends only on how efficiently the spin of the electrons (already present in the semiconductor channel) is randomized by the incoming radiation.</p> <p>(iii) The project also employed the phenomena of spin-Seebeck effect (SSE) and inverse spin-Hall effect (ISHE) for radiation detection. The SSE phenomenon is the spin analogue to the Seebeck effect, in which an applied temperature gradient results in the movement of charge carriers from the hot side to the cold side of the device. When the SSE is induced in a magnetic insulator, (i.e. bismuth doped yttrium iron garnet, Bi-YIG) it causes a magnon current to move along the temperature gradient. By depositing platinum strips atop the Bi-YIG, the magnon motion excites a spin current in the platinum due to spin transfer torque at the interface. Platinum has a large spin-orbit coupling, which means the spin current can result in a large ISHE voltage along the length of the platinum. By placing the device in the presence of gamma radiation, magnons were generated in the Bi-YIG, which in turn induced an ISHE voltage in the platinum. These results showed that, at room temperature, the detection of gamma radiation is possible through the exploitation of spin-based effects in magnetic insulators.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impact:</span></strong></p> <p>(i)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The Project supported 3 Ph.D. and 1 M.S. students.</p> <p>(ii)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Two undergraduate students got opportunity to work in the project.</p> <p>(iii)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The project resulted in several scientific papers and presentations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/21/2018<br>      Modified by: Ashutosh&nbsp;Tiwari</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ An overarching challenge in semiconductor nuclear radiation detection technology is to surmount the thermal background problem that hinders the room temperature functionality of semiconductor detectors. Specifically, in present semiconductor detectors, radiation detection is achieved via the interaction of radiation with the detector material and subsequent creation and separation of charge carriers. For realizing high energy-resolution, it is necessary that the detector material be such that for a given energy deposition by radiation it generates a large number of charge carriers. This requirement demands the application of high atomic-weight and low band-gap semiconductors such as Germanium. Nuclear detectors utilizing low band-gap semiconductors own higher resolution compared to other detectors. However, low band-gap detectors hurt from the problem of enormous thermal background. So for reliable operation, these detectors need to be cooled to liquid nitrogen temperature. This increases the over-all cost and complexity of semiconductor detectors significantly. Moreover, the need of liquid cryogen renders semiconductor nuclear detectors useless for operation in remote areas. It is generally accepted that the incremental advances to the current semiconductor nuclear detector technology will not be sufficient for developing next generation ultra-sensitive and cost-effective detectors. Such development requires the exploration of entirely new and transformative approaches. This project has explored one such approach utilizing the concept of spintronics. Some specific outcomes of the project are summarized below:     Intellectual Merit:  (i)    It has been shown that the electromagnetic field associated with the incident nuclear radiation can interact with the spin of the electrons via the Rashba spin-orbit interaction mechanism. This interaction results in a precession in the spin of the electrons and as a result the current collected by a ferromagnetic electrode (which is aligned either parallel or antiparallel to the spin injector electrode) changes. So in contrast to semiconductor detectors, where the radiation sensing mechanism depends on the generation and collection of charge carriers, in spintronic detectors, the radiation sensing mechanism is based on the quantum mechanical de-coherence of the spins of electrons. Since the absorption of the incident radiation in the semiconductor, and subsequent generation of additional carriers, is not a requirement, wide band-gap semiconductors can be used as sensing media. This can significantly reduce the thermal background problem encountered in conventional semiconductor detectors.  (ii)  It has been shown that a fundamental difference between the traditional semiconductor detectors and the spintronic detectors is that the performance of traditional semiconductor detectors depends on how efficiently the charge carriers are generated by the incident radiation and then how efficiently those are separated and collected; on the other hand, the performance of a spintronic detector depends only on how efficiently the spin of the electrons (already present in the semiconductor channel) is randomized by the incoming radiation.  (iii) The project also employed the phenomena of spin-Seebeck effect (SSE) and inverse spin-Hall effect (ISHE) for radiation detection. The SSE phenomenon is the spin analogue to the Seebeck effect, in which an applied temperature gradient results in the movement of charge carriers from the hot side to the cold side of the device. When the SSE is induced in a magnetic insulator, (i.e. bismuth doped yttrium iron garnet, Bi-YIG) it causes a magnon current to move along the temperature gradient. By depositing platinum strips atop the Bi-YIG, the magnon motion excites a spin current in the platinum due to spin transfer torque at the interface. Platinum has a large spin-orbit coupling, which means the spin current can result in a large ISHE voltage along the length of the platinum. By placing the device in the presence of gamma radiation, magnons were generated in the Bi-YIG, which in turn induced an ISHE voltage in the platinum. These results showed that, at room temperature, the detection of gamma radiation is possible through the exploitation of spin-based effects in magnetic insulators.  Broader Impact:  (i)             The Project supported 3 Ph.D. and 1 M.S. students.  (ii)           Two undergraduate students got opportunity to work in the project.  (iii)          The project resulted in several scientific papers and presentations.          Last Modified: 09/21/2018       Submitted by: Ashutosh Tiwari]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
