<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DMREF/Collaborative Research: Multi-Scale Modeling and Characterization of Twinning-Induced Plasticity and Fracture in Magnesium Alloys</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>285293.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>285293</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexis Lewis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alewis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922624</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this Designing Materials to Revolutionize and Engineer our Future (DMREF) collaborative research grant is to identify fundamentally validated mean-field and full-field models capable of predicting failure in Mg alloys. This is a critical step for developing materials design concepts to enable the use of lightweight Mg alloys in safety critical applications or development of deformation processing strategies.  A critical, fundamental gap in the understanding of Mg alloy deformation relates to dislocation-dislocation, dislocation-twin, twin-twin, and twin-grain boundary (GB) interactions and their effects on strain hardening and damage initiation. It is now understood that (i) interactions between twin variants, such "autotwinning" and double twinning, catalyze macroscopic shear localization and (ii) crack nucleation takes place at twin-GB and twin-twin intersections. The ability to predict and mitigate these behaviors lags. Unless these issues are solved, Mg alloys will be relegated to cast components in non-safety critical applications.  A multi-scale approach is required, because key mechanisms operate at different length scales: 1. atomistic (dislocation core interactions with other dislocations and with twin boundaries, and decohesion); 2. microscopic (dislocation-dislocation, dislocation-twin, and twin-twin interactions); 3. mesoscopic (twin-parent grain and grain-grain compatibility interactions leading to backstress and crack initation); and 4. macroscopic (applications to forming simulation or performance prediction design incorporating shear localization). The partners will employ TEM, in situ SEM and electron backscattered diffraction (EBSD) serial imaging techniques, and neutron and synchrotron X ray-based characterization to guide and validate models of the behavior at the corresponding length scales.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These models will greatly aid efforts to render lightweight Mg alloys "formable" and "crushable," so that society can exploit performance and efficiency benefits. This could help reduce potentially harmful greenhouse gas emissions by broader application of lightweight Mg alloys in the transportation sector. Additionally, the multiscale modeling concepts under development can be modified for application to numerous other materials, which deform by similar mechanisms of twinning or martensitic transformation: such as Be, Co, Ti, U, and Zr alloys, Advanced High Strength Steels (e.g. TWIP and TRIP), and shape memory alloys. Finally, the collaboration seeks to develop young scientists and engineers, trained to work in a cutting-edge research environment, providing them with an excellent preparation for future industrial or academic research, which increasingly requires a working knowledge of both theory and experiment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1235009</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Haitham</FirstName>
<LastName>El Kadiri</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Haitham El Kadiri</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>elkadiri@me.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623254777</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000354568</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mississippi State University</Name>
<CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
<ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6623257404</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>PO Box 6156</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MS03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075461814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MISSISSIPPI STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075461814</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mississippi State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Mississippi State</CityName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[133 Etheredge Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MS03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1633</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS AND SURFACE ENG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1444</Code>
<Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~285293</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project has come to an excellent end with great individual, pairwise, and collective achievements. The three teams from Mississippi State University, University of Virginia, and Georgia Institute of Technology have made substantial strides in the following areas which directly tie-in with the specific objectives set originally for this project:</p> <ol> <li>MSU &ndash; interfacial defect theory and MD simulations on twin nucleation and mobility, twin-slip interactions, and twin-twin interactions, crystal plasticity of twin nucleation, &nbsp;and EBSD of twin-twin, interactions, with input from UVA.</li> <li>UVA &ndash; crystal plasticity-based work on twinning (together with McMaster, Waterloo, and MSU), effects of twin boundaries on slip (TEM work and single crystal collaborators at MSU, Drexel, andFraunhofer), and work on pyramidal slip with GIT</li> <li>GIT &ndash; Finite element modeling of warm formed AZ31 "turkey pan" with input from MSU and GT</li> </ol> <p>Intellectual Merit:</p> <p>From the Mississippi State University perspective, the cross disciplinary collaboration has displaced&nbsp;traditional views on the concept of hardening and disruptively catapulted novel ICME methods and areas in the world of interfacial defect theory, twin nucleation twin propagation, dislocation transmutation by twinning, and in situ EBSD characterization. There were at least 12&nbsp;peer-reviewed&nbsp;papers published in top &nbsp;journals magazines with high impact factor. Some of these articles have been highly cited (e.g. 79) despite their very recent publication date.&nbsp;</p> <p>The limited room temperature Mg ductility is a long-standing problem in the world of mechanical metallurgy, which stalls humanity from reaping a huge energy-saving benefit from the lightest metal on earth, four times less heavier than steel. This collaborative project, combining various types of expertise spanning from characterization, testing, to multiscale modeling, allowed discovering that slip and twinning are in strong conflict with each other, as alien dislocations and faults form in the wake of their slip-twin interactions to prompt premature damage. These mechanisms leading to failure have been identified and described by novel theoretical and modeling methods which are expected to substantially impact other materials including hexagonal and cubic structures.&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts:</p> <p>Three MSU graduate students benefited from this project. Dr. Christopher Barrett is now a Post Doc at MSU working under Dr. El Kadiri&rsquo;s supervision, Dr. Vahid Tari is now a Post Doc at Carnegie Mellon working under Professor Anthony Rollet, and Aidin Imandoust is now preparing for his final PhD dissertation defense. Exposed to this cross-disciplinary collaboration with several meetings at conferences and beyond, Christopher Barrett who has spent an internship in LANL thanks to this grant has been able to innovate a new concept which impacted the field of interfacial defect theory. This concept, dubbed trichromatic complex (see primary image) is based on the three-colored symmetry group theory and was deemed invaluable to formally understand the role of disclinations in faceting mechanisms of interfaces of the likes seen when a dislocation strikes a twin boundary.&nbsp;</p> <p>As a result, Christopher Barrett has won significant research awards at Mississippi State University. A picture attached here shows Barrett with Dean Achille Messac and Associate Dean Masoud Rais-Rohani. receiving the Bagley 2014 research publication award. He has developed a robust ICME software, dubbed MPC tool, which for the first time allows automatic fitting of MEAM potentials using DFT. The MPC tool is publically available at:</p> <p><a href="https://icme.hpc.msstate.edu/mediawiki/index.php/MPC">https</a><a href="https://icme.hpc.msstate.edu/mediawiki/index.php/MPC">://icme.hpc.msstate.edu/mediawiki/index.php/MPC</a></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/18/2016<br>      Modified by: Haitham&nbsp;El Kadiri</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474235712969_Trichromatic_Complex_Twin_Slip_Interactions--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474235712969_Trichromatic_Complex_Twin_Slip_Interactions--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Trichromatic_Pattern_Twin_Slip_Interactions"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474235712969_Trichromatic_Complex_Twin_Slip_Interactions--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Trichromatic_Pattern_Twin_Slip_Interactions"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Natural trichromatic pattern (NTP) for the basal slip interaction with the {10-12} twin boundary showing the decomposition of the perfect basal into i number of twinning disconnections, a basal-prismatic (BP) disclination dipole.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Acta Materialia 70 (2014) 137?161</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Haitham&nbsp;El Kadiri</div> <div class="imageTitle">Trichromatic_Pattern_Twin_Slip_Interactions</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474236168015_Two_Variant_2pct--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474236168015_Two_Variant_2pct--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Two-Variant Twinning in Mg"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474236168015_Two_Variant_2pct--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Two-Variant Twinning in Mg"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">In situ EBSD of a Mg grain undergoing nucleation of two twinning variants at 2% of plastic deformation</div> <div class="imageCredit">Acta Materialia 61 (2013) 3549?3563</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Haitham&nbsp;El Kadiri</div> <div class="imageTitle">Two-Variant Twinning in Mg</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474236242920_Two_Variants_3pct--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474236242920_Two_Variants_3pct--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Two-Variant Twinning in Mg 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474236242920_Two_Variants_3pct--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Two-Variant Twinning in Mg 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">In situ EBSD of a Mg grain undergoing nucleation of two twinning variants at 3% of plastic deformation</div> <div class="imageCredit">Acta Materialia 61 (2013) 3549?3563</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Haitham&nbsp;El Kadiri</div> <div class="imageTitle">Two-Variant Twinning in Mg 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474236310375_Two_Variants_4pct--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474236310375_Two_Variants_4pct--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Two-Variant Twinning in Mg 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474236310375_Two_Variants_4pct--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Two-Variant Twinning in Mg 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">In situ EBSD of a Mg grain undergoing nucleation of two twinning variants at 4% of plastic deformation</div> <div class="imageCredit">Acta Materialia 61 (2013) 3549?3563</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Haitham&nbsp;El Kadiri</div> <div class="imageTitle">Two-Variant Twinning in Mg 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474236464052_Barrett_Award--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474236464052_Barrett_Award--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Barrett Research Award"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474236464052_Barrett_Award--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Barrett Research Award"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">From the right, Dean Achille Messac, Christopher Barrett, and Associate Dean Masoud Rais-Rohani.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Christopher D. Barrett</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Haitham&nbsp;El Kadiri</div> <div class="imageTitle">Barrett Research Award</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474235936056_Slip-Twin_Generation_Transmuted_Dislocation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474235936056_Slip-Twin_Generation_Transmuted_Dislocation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Slip-Twin_Generation_Transmuted_Dislocation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1235009/1235009_10203363_1474235936056_Slip-Twin_Generation_Transmuted_Dislocation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Slip-Twin_Generation_Transmuted_Dislocation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Snopshot of an MD simulations unveiling the transmutation of two basal a dislocations to a prismatic c+a dislocation in the twin, disconnections, and a prismatic-basal facet</div> <div class="imageCredit">El Kadiri, Agnew, Barrett, and Wang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Haitham&nbsp;El Kadiri</div> <div class="imageTitle">Slip-Twin_Generation_Transmuted_Dislocation</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project has come to an excellent end with great individual, pairwise, and collective achievements. The three teams from Mississippi State University, University of Virginia, and Georgia Institute of Technology have made substantial strides in the following areas which directly tie-in with the specific objectives set originally for this project:  MSU &ndash; interfacial defect theory and MD simulations on twin nucleation and mobility, twin-slip interactions, and twin-twin interactions, crystal plasticity of twin nucleation,  and EBSD of twin-twin, interactions, with input from UVA. UVA &ndash; crystal plasticity-based work on twinning (together with McMaster, Waterloo, and MSU), effects of twin boundaries on slip (TEM work and single crystal collaborators at MSU, Drexel, andFraunhofer), and work on pyramidal slip with GIT GIT &ndash; Finite element modeling of warm formed AZ31 "turkey pan" with input from MSU and GT   Intellectual Merit:  From the Mississippi State University perspective, the cross disciplinary collaboration has displaced traditional views on the concept of hardening and disruptively catapulted novel ICME methods and areas in the world of interfacial defect theory, twin nucleation twin propagation, dislocation transmutation by twinning, and in situ EBSD characterization. There were at least 12 peer-reviewed papers published in top  journals magazines with high impact factor. Some of these articles have been highly cited (e.g. 79) despite their very recent publication date.   The limited room temperature Mg ductility is a long-standing problem in the world of mechanical metallurgy, which stalls humanity from reaping a huge energy-saving benefit from the lightest metal on earth, four times less heavier than steel. This collaborative project, combining various types of expertise spanning from characterization, testing, to multiscale modeling, allowed discovering that slip and twinning are in strong conflict with each other, as alien dislocations and faults form in the wake of their slip-twin interactions to prompt premature damage. These mechanisms leading to failure have been identified and described by novel theoretical and modeling methods which are expected to substantially impact other materials including hexagonal and cubic structures.   Broader Impacts:  Three MSU graduate students benefited from this project. Dr. Christopher Barrett is now a Post Doc at MSU working under Dr. El Kadiri?s supervision, Dr. Vahid Tari is now a Post Doc at Carnegie Mellon working under Professor Anthony Rollet, and Aidin Imandoust is now preparing for his final PhD dissertation defense. Exposed to this cross-disciplinary collaboration with several meetings at conferences and beyond, Christopher Barrett who has spent an internship in LANL thanks to this grant has been able to innovate a new concept which impacted the field of interfacial defect theory. This concept, dubbed trichromatic complex (see primary image) is based on the three-colored symmetry group theory and was deemed invaluable to formally understand the role of disclinations in faceting mechanisms of interfaces of the likes seen when a dislocation strikes a twin boundary.   As a result, Christopher Barrett has won significant research awards at Mississippi State University. A picture attached here shows Barrett with Dean Achille Messac and Associate Dean Masoud Rais-Rohani. receiving the Bagley 2014 research publication award. He has developed a robust ICME software, dubbed MPC tool, which for the first time allows automatic fitting of MEAM potentials using DFT. The MPC tool is publically available at:  https://icme.hpc.msstate.edu/mediawiki/index.php/MPC       Last Modified: 09/18/2016       Submitted by: Haitham El Kadiri]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
