<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI-AIR:  Advanced SiNWs: Partnerships for Innovative Research in Energy (ASPIRE)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>800000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>800000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Barbara H. Kenny</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This NSF Accelerating Innovation Research (AIR) project will build on an existing novel and emerging nanotechnology platform that integrates patent pending branched-SiNWs, obliquely aligned nanorods and lithographically patterned nanostructures into high energy density batteries, solar cells with improved absorption and wire grid polarizers for smart windows, respectively; all with lower cost and improved performance. Additionally, the project will leverage its broader incubation and commercialization efforts that connects university-based research and development activities with private enterprise, funding and expertise; thereby helping to increase the rate and scale of clean energy technology market deployment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The world needs short-, medium-, and long-term solutions to the global energy challenge, and innovative programs such as this AIR project that develops an energy ecosystem is one such answer to that challenge.  By introducing a new paradigm of open, circular communication amongst partners, the AIR project will routinely make existing nanostructured-materials platforms accessible to its partners, allowing them to expand on and remix the core product in surprising new ways such as clean energy applications.  The most important innovation that will be built within this ecosystem is a network of companies, working collaboratively together, to maximize technological research advances and to identify new opportunities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1237734</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pradeep</FirstName>
<LastName>Haldar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pradeep Haldar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>phaldar@sunypoly.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5184378684</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000107903</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Hartley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Hartley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhartley1@albany.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5184378686</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000212722</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Albany</Name>
<CityName>Albany</CityName>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5184374974</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 WASHINGTON AVE MSC 100A</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>152652822</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY- College of Nanoscale Science and Engineering]]></Name>
<CityName>Albany</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>122033640</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[257 Fuller Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PARTNRSHIPS FOR INNOVATION-PFI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~800000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The <em>Advanced SiNWs: Partnerships for Innovative Research in Energy</em> (ASPIRE) program, developed by the College of Nanoscale Science &amp; Engineering (CNSE) uses the application of three principal architectures: silicon nanowires (SiNW), obliquely aligned nanorods and electron-beam lithographically produced nanopatterns as its technology platform.&nbsp; Recent work has demonstrated these materials to be promising building blocks for future clean energy devices, including wire grid polarizers for smart windows, anti-reflective coatings for solar cells and high surface area anodes for lithium-ion batteries. This activity built on the work of CNSE&rsquo;s successes in highly controlled growth of nanowires, nanorods and nanopatterns at its unique nanofabrication facilities for building large area nanostructured devices, as well as leverage its broader incubation, commercialization and &ldquo;partnerships for innovation&rdquo; efforts, which focuses on connecting university-based research and development activities with private enterprise, funding and expertise; thereby helping increase the rate and scale of clean energy technology market penetration across the region and country.&nbsp;</p> <p>In the NSF AIR: ASPIRE program, CNSE worked with three companies in three technology areas: 1) High-performance silicon-based anodes for lithium ion batteries; 2) Advanced SiO2 nanorods as antireflective coatings for high efficiency solar cells; and 3) Large area nanopatterns applied to wire&nbsp; grid polarizers for smart windows.&nbsp; The program also worked with several other organizations in its outreach efforts.</p> <p>The open innovation knowledge model used by CNSE is augmented with the addition of interactive interdisciplinary collaborations and sharing of information amongst the industrial partners and other information from resource providers. This accelerates the pace of commercialization through pilot prototyping and rapid scale-up of these important innovations. The selected partnerships match the small companies&rsquo; technical innovation with CNSE&rsquo;s top scientific capacity, research and innovation focus, and unique multi-disciplinary approach to commercialize novel clean energy technologies as well as breakthrough materials and systems.</p> <p><strong>Project Outcomes:</strong></p> <p><strong>YEAR I</strong></p> <p>During the first year of the NSF AIR: ASPIRE project, CNSE made significant strides in its research in silicon nanowires and nanopatterning.&nbsp; Specific results related to this research include:</p> <ul> <li>Designed and built a prototype      manufacturing tool in order to synthesize and characterize silicon      nanowires (SiNWs), using the metal-induced growth process</li> <li>Demonstrated that SiNWs exhibit      high energy capacity and cycle life for lithium ion battery anodes</li> <li>Finalized license agreement with      B.E.S.S.-Technologies</li> <li>Demonstrated large area anti-reflection      coatings with ultra high light transmittance, beneficial for photovoltaic      energy conversion</li> <li>Patent application for      anti-reflective coating is currently in process</li> <li>Completed a feasibility study for      modifying an existing e-beam system to support exposures on large area      (450mm) wafers</li> <li>Hosted over 1,000 students at      CNSE through NSF AIR: ASPIRE K-12 clean energy outreach/knowledge      facilitation efforts</li> <li>Coordinated several targeted      events for cleantech businesses to discuss opportunities and challenges in      an open forum</li> <li>Organized the largest statewide      collegiate business plan competition with over $500K in business      assistance funds to support the innovation ecosystem</li> </ul> <p><strong>YEAR II</strong></p> <p>In the second year, CNSE focused on scaling-up SiNWs and nanorods, optimize processes for nanopatterns, and demonstrate prototype of full scale...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Advanced SiNWs: Partnerships for Innovative Research in Energy (ASPIRE) program, developed by the College of Nanoscale Science &amp; Engineering (CNSE) uses the application of three principal architectures: silicon nanowires (SiNW), obliquely aligned nanorods and electron-beam lithographically produced nanopatterns as its technology platform.  Recent work has demonstrated these materials to be promising building blocks for future clean energy devices, including wire grid polarizers for smart windows, anti-reflective coatings for solar cells and high surface area anodes for lithium-ion batteries. This activity built on the work of CNSEÆs successes in highly controlled growth of nanowires, nanorods and nanopatterns at its unique nanofabrication facilities for building large area nanostructured devices, as well as leverage its broader incubation, commercialization and "partnerships for innovation" efforts, which focuses on connecting university-based research and development activities with private enterprise, funding and expertise; thereby helping increase the rate and scale of clean energy technology market penetration across the region and country.   In the NSF AIR: ASPIRE program, CNSE worked with three companies in three technology areas: 1) High-performance silicon-based anodes for lithium ion batteries; 2) Advanced SiO2 nanorods as antireflective coatings for high efficiency solar cells; and 3) Large area nanopatterns applied to wire  grid polarizers for smart windows.  The program also worked with several other organizations in its outreach efforts.  The open innovation knowledge model used by CNSE is augmented with the addition of interactive interdisciplinary collaborations and sharing of information amongst the industrial partners and other information from resource providers. This accelerates the pace of commercialization through pilot prototyping and rapid scale-up of these important innovations. The selected partnerships match the small companiesÆ technical innovation with CNSEÆs top scientific capacity, research and innovation focus, and unique multi-disciplinary approach to commercialize novel clean energy technologies as well as breakthrough materials and systems.  Project Outcomes:  YEAR I  During the first year of the NSF AIR: ASPIRE project, CNSE made significant strides in its research in silicon nanowires and nanopatterning.  Specific results related to this research include:  Designed and built a prototype      manufacturing tool in order to synthesize and characterize silicon      nanowires (SiNWs), using the metal-induced growth process Demonstrated that SiNWs exhibit      high energy capacity and cycle life for lithium ion battery anodes Finalized license agreement with      B.E.S.S.-Technologies Demonstrated large area anti-reflection      coatings with ultra high light transmittance, beneficial for photovoltaic      energy conversion Patent application for      anti-reflective coating is currently in process Completed a feasibility study for      modifying an existing e-beam system to support exposures on large area      (450mm) wafers Hosted over 1,000 students at      CNSE through NSF AIR: ASPIRE K-12 clean energy outreach/knowledge      facilitation efforts Coordinated several targeted      events for cleantech businesses to discuss opportunities and challenges in      an open forum Organized the largest statewide      collegiate business plan competition with over $500K in business      assistance funds to support the innovation ecosystem   YEAR II  In the second year, CNSE focused on scaling-up SiNWs and nanorods, optimize processes for nanopatterns, and demonstrate prototype of full scale devices.  NSF AIR: ASPIRE continued to provide business plan, market validation, and legal support for partner companies, and assisted in raising private capital.  Fabricated and tested full cells      in both coin and pouch cell formats; the nanostructured material has shown      ~80% capacity retention ov...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
