<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RCN: Social Observatories Coordinating Network (SOCN)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cheryl Eavey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ceavey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927269</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the operations of the Social Observatories Coordinating Network (SOCN), a research coordination network that will work with a broad cross-section of scholars in the social, behavioral, and economic (SBE) scientific communities in the development and planning of a set of observatories that will transform SBE science.  The major objectives of the network are to continue exploration of ideas regarding the potential form and functioning of a network of social observatories and to actively engage individuals and groups across the SBE research community in this process.  SOCN will work with disciplinary and interdisciplinary groups to ensure that they contribute to the design of these proposed observatories and that the scientific questions the observatories might pursue will have value for basic research and for a broad range of practical uses.  SOCN will widely dissemination reports and other findings, and it will facilitate interactions among scholars, particularly at national professional meetings and other scientific conferences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The network will facilitate the consideration and development of what is expected to be a transformative set of observatories that would provide a new platform for data collection, data archiving, and data distribution; advanced cyberinfrastructure for a truly interdisciplinary SBE scientific enterprise; new approaches to training of students; and a focal point for synthesis and faculty collaboration around questions of national importance.  A coordinated suite of social observatories is expected to add new capabilities for SBE sciences by moving to fine-grained and place-based studies that address local, regional, and national concerns.  The observatories will advance understanding of individual decision making via experiments, ethnography, spatially explicit data, administrative, and social media data that, when combined over all sites, will be nationally representative.  Through its efforts to facilitate consideration of social observatories, SOCN will advance the discussion of critical new ideas and advance interdisciplinary communication and collaboration across the SBE sciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1237498</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emilio</FirstName>
<LastName>Moran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emilio F Moran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>moranef@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5178841236</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000263042</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Hofferth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sandra Hofferth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hofferth@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056269</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000589369</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1333</Code>
<Text>Methodology, Measuremt &amp; Stats</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1333</Code>
<Text>METHOD, MEASURE &amp; STATS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1664</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7956</Code>
<Text>SBE Interdisciplinary Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8605</Code>
<Text>SBE 2020</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~299999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Objectives</strong></p> <p>The major objectives of the Social Observatories Coordinating Network (SOCN) were to explore ideas regarding the potential form and functioning of a new form of infrastructure for research - a network of regional data centers - and to actively engage individuals and groups across the social, behavioral, and economic research community in this process.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Outcomes</strong></p> <p>There are four major take-away messages gained from this project:</p> <ol> <li>Behavior is so situation-      and place-specific that it is practically impossible to use widely      dispersed national samples of populations to draw conclusions about      processes in any one place.&nbsp; Populations      tend to be clustered spatially by social, economic, and demographic characteristics.&nbsp; This has implications for important      issues of national concern, such as adaptation to environmental change and      social mobility.&nbsp; Social policy,      economic conditions, race/ethnic/immigrant composition, and the size of      the middle class in a city provide a context in which individuals can      thrive or stagnate, leading to important questions about the roles of      government, nonprofits, and for-profit organizations in fostering      opportunity and mobility processes, and the impact of their policies on      individuals, families, and neighborhoods.&nbsp;</li> <li>The network considered a      new national framework or platform that is both scalable and flexible for      addressing these new challenges, one that allows for rapid response to      local crises such as the devastating impact of tornadoes and hurricanes or      social unrest, and those provoked by prolonged regional drought or      economic decline. This platform can also address national crises such as      the declining middle class and why in many schools across the country our      children are not learning optimally.</li> <li>In consultation with      statistical experts&nbsp; and based upon      earlier workshops on cyber-infrastructure, our network proposed the      development of twenty to twenty-five regional data centers located across      the United States. Each center would collect, organize, create, and      disseminate data. These regional data centers or &ldquo;social observatories&rdquo;      would follow about 400 census tracts over time and space from twenty to      twenty-five regions across the country. Working closely with local and      state governments, they would access administrative data with information      on not just a sample of the population of those several hundred census      tracts, but complete records on all the population in those tracts (i.e.,      circa two million Americans). The centers would serve as data collection      facilities wherein data are cleaned, linked, and made available for      legitimate research purposes through a secure integrated data      dissemination system. Although they would be charged with keeping data on      their particular geographic region, some of these centers may have a      national focus as well. These centers may conduct surveys but they would      also use data sources that until now have not been part of the toolbox of      the social sciences, and they would connect these data to local context      and place without losing the capacity to aggregate and serve as a national      sample of people and places in the United States. Our vision is that,      collectively, they would offer a nationally representative sample, one      that was highly clustered so as to capture local context and variability.</li> <li>Linking diverse forms of      data, including administrative and social media data, represents the most      efficient way to obtain more place-specific information in our current social      science data bases.&nbsp; This is the      focus of our edited volume (669) of the <em>Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, </em>January      2017.&nbsp; Probably the most important,      least well-addressed, and most difficult issue raised was privacy and confidentiality      in the handling of individual data.&nbsp;      This is an area recommended for future NSF initiatives.&nbsp; </li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>The observatory network explicitly responded to what is now a broad call in many scientific circles to address issues of importance with the best tools available without regard for disciplinary origins. We expect this project to have broad impact on thinking regarding research and data collection in multiple fields of scientific inquiry.&nbsp; The proposed new scientific infrastructure will enable the social, behavioral, and economic sciences (SBE) to contribute to societal needs at multiple levels and will facilitate collaboration with other sciences in addressing questions of critical importance. The proposed data centers could transform how the SBE sciences go about their work for decades to come by encouraging integration and linkage across varied forms of data by scientists from multiple disciplines representing all regions of the country.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Sandra&nbsp;Hofferth</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Objectives  The major objectives of the Social Observatories Coordinating Network (SOCN) were to explore ideas regarding the potential form and functioning of a new form of infrastructure for research - a network of regional data centers - and to actively engage individuals and groups across the social, behavioral, and economic research community in this process.     Outcomes  There are four major take-away messages gained from this project:  Behavior is so situation-      and place-specific that it is practically impossible to use widely      dispersed national samples of populations to draw conclusions about      processes in any one place.  Populations      tend to be clustered spatially by social, economic, and demographic characteristics.  This has implications for important      issues of national concern, such as adaptation to environmental change and      social mobility.  Social policy,      economic conditions, race/ethnic/immigrant composition, and the size of      the middle class in a city provide a context in which individuals can      thrive or stagnate, leading to important questions about the roles of      government, nonprofits, and for-profit organizations in fostering      opportunity and mobility processes, and the impact of their policies on      individuals, families, and neighborhoods.  The network considered a      new national framework or platform that is both scalable and flexible for      addressing these new challenges, one that allows for rapid response to      local crises such as the devastating impact of tornadoes and hurricanes or      social unrest, and those provoked by prolonged regional drought or      economic decline. This platform can also address national crises such as      the declining middle class and why in many schools across the country our      children are not learning optimally. In consultation with      statistical experts  and based upon      earlier workshops on cyber-infrastructure, our network proposed the      development of twenty to twenty-five regional data centers located across      the United States. Each center would collect, organize, create, and      disseminate data. These regional data centers or "social observatories"      would follow about 400 census tracts over time and space from twenty to      twenty-five regions across the country. Working closely with local and      state governments, they would access administrative data with information      on not just a sample of the population of those several hundred census      tracts, but complete records on all the population in those tracts (i.e.,      circa two million Americans). The centers would serve as data collection      facilities wherein data are cleaned, linked, and made available for      legitimate research purposes through a secure integrated data      dissemination system. Although they would be charged with keeping data on      their particular geographic region, some of these centers may have a      national focus as well. These centers may conduct surveys but they would      also use data sources that until now have not been part of the toolbox of      the social sciences, and they would connect these data to local context      and place without losing the capacity to aggregate and serve as a national      sample of people and places in the United States. Our vision is that,      collectively, they would offer a nationally representative sample, one      that was highly clustered so as to capture local context and variability. Linking diverse forms of      data, including administrative and social media data, represents the most      efficient way to obtain more place-specific information in our current social      science data bases.  This is the      focus of our edited volume (669) of the Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, January      2017.  Probably the most important,      least well-addressed, and most difficult issue raised was privacy and confidentiality      in the handling of individual data.       This is an area recommended for future NSF initiatives.        Broader Impacts  The observatory network explicitly responded to what is now a broad call in many scientific circles to address issues of importance with the best tools available without regard for disciplinary origins. We expect this project to have broad impact on thinking regarding research and data collection in multiple fields of scientific inquiry.  The proposed new scientific infrastructure will enable the social, behavioral, and economic sciences (SBE) to contribute to societal needs at multiple levels and will facilitate collaboration with other sciences in addressing questions of critical importance. The proposed data centers could transform how the SBE sciences go about their work for decades to come by encouraging integration and linkage across varied forms of data by scientists from multiple disciplines representing all regions of the country.            Last Modified: 03/28/2017       Submitted by: Sandra Hofferth]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
