<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research Initiation Award Grant: Modeling and Control Genetic Regulations in Biological Networks using Advanced Signal Processing and Control Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>239999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The overarching goal of this project is to provide a theoretical and computational framework for modeling and control of genetic regulation to generate effective therapeutic strategies for genetic diseases such as cancer. The accomplishment of such intervention in genetically pathological cells, such as cancer cells, would be a major step in the transformation of medicine to a mathematically grounded engineering discipline based on dynamic molecular interaction. The education goal of this project is to enhance the quality education for engineering students at PVAMU and to increase the number of African-American students pursuing careers in computational and systems biology. Three undergraduate students will be supported by this project each year to work on the research. In addition, many students will be impacted by a new course and several enhanced courses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The interdisciplinary nature of this project promises to foster crossfertilization of ideas between electrical engineering and systems biology through research and education. The project aims to model drug effects on gene regulation using hybrid systems and infer their targeted genetic regulatory networks in terms of their complex nature - in regard to network dynamics, robustness and sensitivity - thereby designing better intervention strategies. Instead of traditional techniques, such as microarrays that provide a snapshot of an aspect of the system at one time point, the dynamics of tumor cell response to drugs can be quantitatively characterized through a multi-dimensional examination of the cells' responses through drug perturbation to test different combinations of cell type, reporters, and drugs/dosages, augmented by a system identification and control theoretical approach aiming to better understand genetic regulatory network behavior in order to design effective therapeutic strategies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1238918</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lijun</FirstName>
<LastName>Qian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lijun Qian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>liqian@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9362619908</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000193829</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Prairie View A &amp; M University</Name>
<CityName>Prairie View</CityName>
<ZipCode>774460519</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9362611689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 519</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MS 1230]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>138170220</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRAIRIE VIEW A&amp;M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>138170220</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Prairie View A & M University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>774460667</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~39999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The genetic regulation mechanisms of cells are composed of many interacting complex dynamical networks. The cancer cells take advantage of such complex network through genetic aberrations to promote survival and proliferation, and evade apoptosis and immune surveillance. In this project,&nbsp;<span>theoretical and computational framework for modeling and control of genetic regulation is proposed to generate effective therapeutic strategies for genetic diseases such as cancer. The accomplishment of such intervention in genetically pathological cells, such as cancer cells, is a major step in the transformation of medicine to a mathematically grounded engineering discipline based on dynamic molecular interaction. Significant results have been generated and published in journals and refereed conferences.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>This project is interdisciplinary in nature. It complements the existing topics in Engineering and Computer Science at PVAMU. Specifically, this project introduced the exciting new field of computational and systems biology to the students and faculty in Engineering and Computer Science and encourage them to explore this emerging research topic. Many engineering students at Prairie View A&amp;M University (a&nbsp;</span>Historically Black Colleges and University, HBCU) have participated this research project and many of them have become interested to pursue careers in computational and systems biology. New courses have been created and existing courses have been updated to teach students state-of-the-art in this emerging research field.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2018<br>      Modified by: Lijun&nbsp;Qian</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The genetic regulation mechanisms of cells are composed of many interacting complex dynamical networks. The cancer cells take advantage of such complex network through genetic aberrations to promote survival and proliferation, and evade apoptosis and immune surveillance. In this project, theoretical and computational framework for modeling and control of genetic regulation is proposed to generate effective therapeutic strategies for genetic diseases such as cancer. The accomplishment of such intervention in genetically pathological cells, such as cancer cells, is a major step in the transformation of medicine to a mathematically grounded engineering discipline based on dynamic molecular interaction. Significant results have been generated and published in journals and refereed conferences.     This project is interdisciplinary in nature. It complements the existing topics in Engineering and Computer Science at PVAMU. Specifically, this project introduced the exciting new field of computational and systems biology to the students and faculty in Engineering and Computer Science and encourage them to explore this emerging research topic. Many engineering students at Prairie View A&amp;M University (a Historically Black Colleges and University, HBCU) have participated this research project and many of them have become interested to pursue careers in computational and systems biology. New courses have been created and existing courses have been updated to teach students state-of-the-art in this emerging research field.        Last Modified: 10/29/2018       Submitted by: Lijun Qian]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
