<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I/UCRC:  Center for Advanced Forestry Systems--Phase II</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>675160.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1175190</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregory Reed</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PROGRAM DIRECTOR'S RECOMMENDATION &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;IIP 1238324 &lt;br/&gt;North Carolina State University &lt;br/&gt;Goldfarb &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;IIP 1238265 &lt;br/&gt;Virginia Tech &lt;br/&gt;Fox &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;IIP 1238305 &lt;br/&gt;Oregon State University &lt;br/&gt;Howe &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;IIP 1238319 &lt;br/&gt;Purdue University &lt;br/&gt;Michler &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal seeks funding for a second five-year term (Phase II) of the NSF Industry/University Cooperative Research Center for Advanced Forestry Systems (CAFS) sites including the North Carolina State University (lead), Virginia Tech, Oregon State University and Purdue University. The collaborative research conducted under the CAFS umbrella focuses on optimizing genetic and cultural systems to produce high-quality raw materials for new and existing forest products industries. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Over the past 50 years, much forestry research has taken place in university-based, industry-supported, cooperative research programs. These "coops" continue be extraordinarily successful at achieving research and technological advances on topics of great relevance to the forest industry. However, the ability to focus on specific disciplinary topics in response to industrial guidance is also a limitation. Many of the problems and opportunities facing forestry today, bridge disciplinary and regional boundaries. For technological advances to be made, it is necessary to approach research questions on multiple spatial and temporal scales, including the molecular, cellular, individual-tree, stand, and ecosystem levels. The proposed Center (CAFS) has been successful at providing the administrative structure and funding that has allowed scientists from these existing cooperatives to initiate much need cross-disciplinary research in areas of genetics, site manipulation, and growth and yield modeling. The proposal presents a plan for the 2nd five-year phase for the four original university CAFS sites, North Carolina State, Oregon State, Purdue, and Virginia Tech. This proposal also serves as a research and administrative template for the other five university sites that have joined CAFS since its interception in late 2007. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research conducted by CAFS increases the competitiveness of forest products industries and forest landowners by solving problems on multiple temporal and spatial scales and determining fundamental solutions that transcend traditional species, regional, and disciplinary boundaries. Member organizations of the Center benefit by becoming knowledgeable about a wider range of technological capabilities. In addition, technology transfer between Center scientists and member personnel fosters rapid implementation of new technologies. The broader scientific community benefits through refereed publications and presentations at scientific meetings. During the Phase II period, graduate student training will continue to be featured in Center research and technology transfer. Aggressive recruiting for graduate students among under-represented groups will be conducted, increasing the diversity of the workforce for both academia and industry in this traditionally diversity-deficient discipline. Opportunities will continue to be sought to involve undergraduate students in Center research activities, exposing them to the excitement of forest science and encouraging them to pursue graduate education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/24/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1238324</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
<LastName>Allen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Howard L Allen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lee_allen@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196121456</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000091213</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/19/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barry</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldfarb</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barry Goldfarb</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>barry_goldfarb@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195154471</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000165556</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/24/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Michler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles H Michler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>michler@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654966016</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000345183</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
<LastName>Stape</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jose L Stape</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jlstape@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195134041</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000518294</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/29/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Jeffries</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephanie Jeffries</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ssjeffri@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195152444</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000675150</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/30/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Cook</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel L Cook</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rlcook@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195152444</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000721497</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/24/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Cook</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel L Cook</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rlcook@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195152444</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000721497</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/24/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276958008</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1049</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY-UNIV COOPERATIVE RSCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8040</Code>
<Text>Energy and Environment</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~352580</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~130637</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~548870</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~93103</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award facilitated North Carolina State University's participation as the lead site in the I/UCRC Center for Advanced Forestry Systems.&nbsp; The Center began in 2007 and this award completes the second five-year phase.&nbsp; The Center has encompassed 9 university sites and over 100 industrial, government and non-profit members in the forestry sector.</p> <p>The primary mission of the Center has been to conduct interdisciplinary and trans-regional research to solve landowner-relevant problems in managing forests in a profitable and environmentally sustainable way. Over the ten years of Center operations over 65 research projects were conducted. While individual study results are too numerous to mention, some highlights include: (1) using a stable isotope of nitrogen to understand fertilizer fate and nutrient cycling in forest plantations; (2) gaining a better understanding of how soil properties affect the response to fertilization in forest stands; (3) developing molecular markers to assist breeding and foster disease resistance in tree breeding programs; (4) developing technology to use remote sensing data to diagnose nutrient deficient forest stands; and (5) updating growth and yield models for predicting performance of elite genotypes in forest plantations.</p> <p>The Center has emphasized participation by graduate and undergraduate students in the research projects, as well as Center meetings. These opportunities have resulted in many students becoming employed by member organizations after finishing school. This strengthens the future workforce in the forestry sector, both in industry and academia.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/05/2019<br>      Modified by: Rachel&nbsp;L&nbsp;Cook</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award facilitated North Carolina State University's participation as the lead site in the I/UCRC Center for Advanced Forestry Systems.  The Center began in 2007 and this award completes the second five-year phase.  The Center has encompassed 9 university sites and over 100 industrial, government and non-profit members in the forestry sector.  The primary mission of the Center has been to conduct interdisciplinary and trans-regional research to solve landowner-relevant problems in managing forests in a profitable and environmentally sustainable way. Over the ten years of Center operations over 65 research projects were conducted. While individual study results are too numerous to mention, some highlights include: (1) using a stable isotope of nitrogen to understand fertilizer fate and nutrient cycling in forest plantations; (2) gaining a better understanding of how soil properties affect the response to fertilization in forest stands; (3) developing molecular markers to assist breeding and foster disease resistance in tree breeding programs; (4) developing technology to use remote sensing data to diagnose nutrient deficient forest stands; and (5) updating growth and yield models for predicting performance of elite genotypes in forest plantations.  The Center has emphasized participation by graduate and undergraduate students in the research projects, as well as Center meetings. These opportunities have resulted in many students becoming employed by member organizations after finishing school. This strengthens the future workforce in the forestry sector, both in industry and academia.       Last Modified: 11/05/2019       Submitted by: Rachel L Cook]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
