<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Travel Grant Support for IEEE ICCCN 2012 Conference</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marilyn McClure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmcclure@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 21st IEEE International Conference on Computer Communications and Networks (ICCCN 2012) is to be held in Munich, Germany during July 30 to August 2, 2012 (http://icccn.org/icccn12/). This award provides partial assistance to approximately 10 United States-based graduate students to attend this important conference.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1238494</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaobo</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaobo Zhou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xzhou@uccs.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7192553493</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000330885</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chuan</FirstName>
<LastName>Yue</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chuan Yue</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chuanyue@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3033842439</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000581299</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Colorado Springs</Name>
<CityName>Colorado Springs</CityName>
<ZipCode>809183733</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7192553153</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1420, Austin Bluffs Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>186192829</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Colorado Springs]]></Name>
<CityName>Colorado Springs</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>809183733</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1420, Austin Bluffs Parkway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The International Conference on Computer Communications and Networks (ICCCN) is one of the leading international conferences for presenting novel ideas and fundamental advances in the fields of computer communications and networks. ICCCN serves to foster communication among researchers and practitioners with a common interest in improving communications and networking through scientific and technological innovation.This project aimed to assist approximately 10 U.S. institute based graduate students to attend the ICCCN conferences in 2012 and 2013.</p> <p>To ensure an equal opportunity for all interested individuals to apply for the travel funds, the travel award program was advertised in several ways, including an announcement on the ICCCN 2012 web page. In 2012, seven applications were submitted to the Award Committee. Each application for a travel award consisted of the student's vita, a letter from the student, and a letter from the student's advisor. Based on the review criteria, six eligible applications were approved by the Award Committee. In 2013, the General Chair and the Technical Program Co-Chairs looked at the top ten ranked papers that were eligible and selected the top four for the travel awards. The ten recipients were from a variety of universities located in difference states, i.e., University of Texas at San Antonio, Stony Brook University, Lafayette College, The Pennsylvania State University at University Park, University of Central Florida, University of Memphis, George Mason University, University of Kentucky, Auburn University, and University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</p> <p>The support from this NSF student travel award enabled more participation of the US-based students who would otherwise be unable to attend ICCCN 2012 and ICCCN 2013. It involved minority students including one female PhD student, and also engaged one undergraduate student. Participation in high-quality conferences such as the IEEE ICCCN provided an extremely important part of the students&rsquo; research and career development. It provided the opportunity for them to present their own work, attend panel and keynote speech sessions, interact with peers and more senior researchers, and expose themselves to leading edge research work in the field of computer communication and networks.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/05/2013<br>      Modified by: Xiaobo&nbsp;Zhou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The International Conference on Computer Communications and Networks (ICCCN) is one of the leading international conferences for presenting novel ideas and fundamental advances in the fields of computer communications and networks. ICCCN serves to foster communication among researchers and practitioners with a common interest in improving communications and networking through scientific and technological innovation.This project aimed to assist approximately 10 U.S. institute based graduate students to attend the ICCCN conferences in 2012 and 2013.  To ensure an equal opportunity for all interested individuals to apply for the travel funds, the travel award program was advertised in several ways, including an announcement on the ICCCN 2012 web page. In 2012, seven applications were submitted to the Award Committee. Each application for a travel award consisted of the student's vita, a letter from the student, and a letter from the student's advisor. Based on the review criteria, six eligible applications were approved by the Award Committee. In 2013, the General Chair and the Technical Program Co-Chairs looked at the top ten ranked papers that were eligible and selected the top four for the travel awards. The ten recipients were from a variety of universities located in difference states, i.e., University of Texas at San Antonio, Stony Brook University, Lafayette College, The Pennsylvania State University at University Park, University of Central Florida, University of Memphis, George Mason University, University of Kentucky, Auburn University, and University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.  The support from this NSF student travel award enabled more participation of the US-based students who would otherwise be unable to attend ICCCN 2012 and ICCCN 2013. It involved minority students including one female PhD student, and also engaged one undergraduate student. Participation in high-quality conferences such as the IEEE ICCCN provided an extremely important part of the studentsÆ research and career development. It provided the opportunity for them to present their own work, attend panel and keynote speech sessions, interact with peers and more senior researchers, and expose themselves to leading edge research work in the field of computer communication and networks.       Last Modified: 09/05/2013       Submitted by: Xiaobo Zhou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
