<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Planning Grant: I/UCRC for joining Center for Cloud and Autonomic Computing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>13959.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>13959</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tnandago@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924550</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed planning activity seeks to undertake planning of the establishment of a new Industry/University Cooperative Research Center (I/UCRC) site at Indiana University of the existing Center for Cloud and Autonomic Computing. The center currently involves Arizona, Florida, Mississippi State and Rutgers, and industry and government partners in the field. The Indiana University site intends to provide additional capabilities for the center to cover the areas of basic cloud infrastructure including tools to support the FutureGrid testbed, security, networking, storage, programming models and applications. The site intends to explore the utility of clouds to support scientific research including infrastructure tools and development of innovations in extensions of the MapReduce programming model, identification of science applications suitable for clouds, privacy preserving algorithms for health informatics on clouds, integration of high performance networking and data architectures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The planned site, in combination with the existing center plans to help build innovation capacity in cloud computing and its supporting science and engineering through cooperatively defined research on key challenges with industry.  The outcomes from the center have the potential to broadly impact the public and private sectors. The site plans to have a significant impact on curriculum and student training at the undergraduate and graduate levels. The planned site intends to actively engage in outreach to Minority Serving Institutions through existing consortia.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1238310</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Geoffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Fox</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Geoffrey C Fox</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gcf@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128567977</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000231257</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Swany</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas M Swany</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>swany@iu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128567795</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000347755</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>XiaoFeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>XiaoFeng Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xw7@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128561862</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000219306</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judy</FirstName>
<LastName>Fox</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judy Fox</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ckw9mp@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4342975916</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000555330</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474082671</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2719 E. 10th St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8039</Code>
<Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~13959</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-162dd730-5c0d-b3c7-53b4-710861d87717"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This is a small planning project involving 5 faculty at Indiana University &nbsp;to join an NSF Industry/University cooperative research center I/UCRC in broad areas of Cloud Computing, Distributed Systems and Big Data. This is a collaboration between Indiana University, Florida University and Georgia Tech. It involved identifying and interacting with 17 potential industry and government partners. This required preparation of a brochure and many interactions between University personnel and and the partners. The research areas in center are:</span></p> <ol> <li>Future platforms &ndash; creating and understanding future hardware platforms for next generation applications and providing infrastructure for realistic tests of technology on real applications.</li> <li>Software technologies, algorithms, and solutions &ndash; developing software and algorithms for applications and systems necessary for running large scale applications on clouds and HPC.</li> <li>Application driven networks &ndash; using software defined networking (SDN) to dynamically configure the network to adapt to the needs of a specific application.</li> <li>In-network distributed infrastructure for advanced network applications &ndash; using programmable devices in the network fabric to improve performance and functionality in applications from high-performance cluster computing to the &ldquo;Internet of Things.&rdquo;</li> <li>System operation and management &ndash; automating how back-end components operate, how they deliver services to end users, how they operate efficiently with minimal human intervention, and how to scale them while maintaining high levels of resilience and availability.</li> <li>Systems security - understanding how to split applications so parts needing high security can be run separately, especially on clouds.</li> <li>Parallel algorithms &ndash; creating new batch and online algorithms for core machine learning.</li> <li>End user applications and engagement &ndash; driving all research by major simulation and data intensive applications.</li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;<br />Particularly important were interactions at a workshop <a href="http://streamingsystems.org/index.html">http://streamingsystems.org/index.html</a> held in Indianapolis STREAM2015. The final steps in this project are ongoing as it was delayed by serious medical events outside Indiana University. We expect the center to form in the next year.</p> <ul> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/19/2016<br>      Modified by: Geoffrey&nbsp;C&nbsp;Fox</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This is a small planning project involving 5 faculty at Indiana University  to join an NSF Industry/University cooperative research center I/UCRC in broad areas of Cloud Computing, Distributed Systems and Big Data. This is a collaboration between Indiana University, Florida University and Georgia Tech. It involved identifying and interacting with 17 potential industry and government partners. This required preparation of a brochure and many interactions between University personnel and and the partners. The research areas in center are:  Future platforms &ndash; creating and understanding future hardware platforms for next generation applications and providing infrastructure for realistic tests of technology on real applications. Software technologies, algorithms, and solutions &ndash; developing software and algorithms for applications and systems necessary for running large scale applications on clouds and HPC. Application driven networks &ndash; using software defined networking (SDN) to dynamically configure the network to adapt to the needs of a specific application. In-network distributed infrastructure for advanced network applications &ndash; using programmable devices in the network fabric to improve performance and functionality in applications from high-performance cluster computing to the "Internet of Things." System operation and management &ndash; automating how back-end components operate, how they deliver services to end users, how they operate efficiently with minimal human intervention, and how to scale them while maintaining high levels of resilience and availability. Systems security - understanding how to split applications so parts needing high security can be run separately, especially on clouds. Parallel algorithms &ndash; creating new batch and online algorithms for core machine learning. End user applications and engagement &ndash; driving all research by major simulation and data intensive applications.     Particularly important were interactions at a workshop http://streamingsystems.org/index.html held in Indianapolis STREAM2015. The final steps in this project are ongoing as it was delayed by serious medical events outside Indiana University. We expect the center to form in the next year.            Last Modified: 01/19/2016       Submitted by: Geoffrey C Fox]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
