<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF/FDA SIR: Quantitative Characterization of Hyperspectral Reflectance Imaging Performance for Tissue Diagnostics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>87527.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>87527</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lesterow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT &lt;br/&gt;#1238407&lt;br/&gt;Chen, Yu&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hyperspectral reflectance imaging (HRI) represents an emerging technology with a wide range of current and potential clinical applications including cancer detection  and tissue oximetry. However, there is currently a lack of standardized methods to assure the quality and consistency of HRI imaging instruments. The lack of a standard battery of well-validated methods for objective, quantitative evaluation of HRI limits innovation in academia and industry and hampers the regulatory process by increasing the burden on manufacturers to develop preclinical test methods and perform clinical studies to demonstrate the effectiveness of new products. This proposed study will result in novel, validated image quality test methods and phantom fabrication techniques as well as improved understanding of spectral imaging systems such as those that have been submitted to FDA. Thus, this project will enhance FDA?s ability to rapidly evaluate innovative technologies based on HRI that have a strong potential to improve public health.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1238407</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yu</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yu Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yuchen@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014053439</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000505109</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI Research Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>005E</Code>
<Text>Neuro-photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~87527</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><em>Background:</em></strong> Hyperspectral reflectance imaging (HRI) represents an emerging technology with a wide range of current and potential clinical applications including cancer detection and tissue oximetry. However, there is currently a lack of standardized methods to assure the quality and consistency of HRI imaging instruments. The lack of a standard battery of well-validated methods for objective, quantitative evaluation of HRI limits innovation in academia and industry and hampers the regulatory process by increasing the burden on manufacturers to develop preclinical test methods and perform clinical studies to demonstrate the effectiveness of new products.</p> <p><strong><em>Results:</em></strong> This study developed innovative phantom-based test methods for quantitative and objective evaluation of HRI performance. New technologies such as 3D printing and silicone molding with photolithography were investigated and applied in phantom fabrication. The fabricated polymer phantoms are stable, long lasting, and well-controlled, and they contain subsurface channels that can be injected with HRI contrast agents such as hemoglobin and gold nanoparticles to mimic blood vessels or contrast agents targeting tumors. These phantoms form the basis of standardized tests. Algorithms for quantitatively analyzing the performance of the HRI were developed for the experimental data obtained with the polymer phantoms. The results of the project have been presented in 4 conferences, published in 1 academic journal and 2 conference proceedings, and 2 more academic journal publications are in preparation.</p> <p><strong><em>Intellectual Merits: </em></strong>These novel, validated phantom fabrication techniques and image quality test methods as well as improved understanding of spectral imaging systems initiate the formation of standardized tests for HRI systems, which will enhance FDA&rsquo;s ability to rapidly evaluate innovative technologies based on HRI. It will also provide standardized evaluation methods for manufacturers to improve and demonstrate their product quality. These tests also provide established techniques for rapid yet rigorous quality assurance testing for clinicians. This study also provides extensive insights into the factors influencing HRI imaging of both endogenous tissue structures and nanoparticle-labeled tumors. Insights gained regarding optimal methods for image quality assessment promise to advance nanotechnology-based cancer therapy/imaging as well as other HRI applications, such as vascular imaging and assessment of tissue oximetry. The project will contribute to healthcare through its development of well-validated test phantoms that can be used by academic and industrial researchers to hasten technological advancement and translation from laboratory to clinical implementation.</p> <p><strong><em>Broader Impact: </em></strong>The project contributes to healthcare through its development of well-validated test phantoms that can be used by academic and industrial researchers to facilitate technological advancement and translation from laboratory to clinical implementation. This work leveraged the complementary expertise of two research groups at UMD and FDA to generate regulatory-relevant findings with high relevance to the biomedical engineering community. The PI organized a one-day workshop titled &ldquo;International&nbsp;Workshop&nbsp;on Tissue Phantoms and Standardization in Biophotonics&rdquo; at the University of Maryland Campus. 20 invited lectures were given by experts in the field of optical imaging and phantom development, from worldwide. 55 attendees from governmental institutions (52%), academia (42%) and industry (6%) attended the meeting and joined the discussion. The workshop marked the formation of a community of scientists and regulators in the field of regulatory science for biophotonics imaging. The discussion will...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Background: Hyperspectral reflectance imaging (HRI) represents an emerging technology with a wide range of current and potential clinical applications including cancer detection and tissue oximetry. However, there is currently a lack of standardized methods to assure the quality and consistency of HRI imaging instruments. The lack of a standard battery of well-validated methods for objective, quantitative evaluation of HRI limits innovation in academia and industry and hampers the regulatory process by increasing the burden on manufacturers to develop preclinical test methods and perform clinical studies to demonstrate the effectiveness of new products.  Results: This study developed innovative phantom-based test methods for quantitative and objective evaluation of HRI performance. New technologies such as 3D printing and silicone molding with photolithography were investigated and applied in phantom fabrication. The fabricated polymer phantoms are stable, long lasting, and well-controlled, and they contain subsurface channels that can be injected with HRI contrast agents such as hemoglobin and gold nanoparticles to mimic blood vessels or contrast agents targeting tumors. These phantoms form the basis of standardized tests. Algorithms for quantitatively analyzing the performance of the HRI were developed for the experimental data obtained with the polymer phantoms. The results of the project have been presented in 4 conferences, published in 1 academic journal and 2 conference proceedings, and 2 more academic journal publications are in preparation.  Intellectual Merits: These novel, validated phantom fabrication techniques and image quality test methods as well as improved understanding of spectral imaging systems initiate the formation of standardized tests for HRI systems, which will enhance FDAÆs ability to rapidly evaluate innovative technologies based on HRI. It will also provide standardized evaluation methods for manufacturers to improve and demonstrate their product quality. These tests also provide established techniques for rapid yet rigorous quality assurance testing for clinicians. This study also provides extensive insights into the factors influencing HRI imaging of both endogenous tissue structures and nanoparticle-labeled tumors. Insights gained regarding optimal methods for image quality assessment promise to advance nanotechnology-based cancer therapy/imaging as well as other HRI applications, such as vascular imaging and assessment of tissue oximetry. The project will contribute to healthcare through its development of well-validated test phantoms that can be used by academic and industrial researchers to hasten technological advancement and translation from laboratory to clinical implementation.  Broader Impact: The project contributes to healthcare through its development of well-validated test phantoms that can be used by academic and industrial researchers to facilitate technological advancement and translation from laboratory to clinical implementation. This work leveraged the complementary expertise of two research groups at UMD and FDA to generate regulatory-relevant findings with high relevance to the biomedical engineering community. The PI organized a one-day workshop titled "International Workshop on Tissue Phantoms and Standardization in Biophotonics" at the University of Maryland Campus. 20 invited lectures were given by experts in the field of optical imaging and phantom development, from worldwide. 55 attendees from governmental institutions (52%), academia (42%) and industry (6%) attended the meeting and joined the discussion. The workshop marked the formation of a community of scientists and regulators in the field of regulatory science for biophotonics imaging. The discussion will continue, and more collaboration and rapid advance in the field are expected to happen along the way.  This research work was also seamlessly integrated with educational, mentoring, and outreach activities to ad...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
