<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Alliance for Physics EXcellence (APEX)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>7999999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>7999999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Ford</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>miford@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925153</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Alliance for Physics Excellence (APEX) project is led by Alabama Agricultural and Mechanical University (AAMU) and includes as core partners the University of Alabama at Tuscaloosa (UA-T), Drake State Technical College, the American Association of Physics Teachers/Physics Teaching Resource Agents, and the Huntsville City School system. The partnership also includes supporting partners from the 11 Alabama Math Science and Technology Initiative (AMSTI) regional in-service centers, Madison County Schools, Scottsboro City Schools, Madison City Schools, and the Alabama State Department of Education. The vision of APEX is to promote significant gains in student learning by transforming secondary physics education throughout Alabama. APEX is serving as a comprehensive agent of change by successfully integrating cutting edge teaching practices within secondary physics programs, and it is directly impacting 25% of the physics teachers (with 41,000 students) throughout all Alabama school systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overarching goal of this project is transformation of the work of pre-service and in-service physics teachers as they gain a deeper content knowledge of physics and also employ effective pedagogical strategies based on physics education research. These teachers go on to apply that knowledge within their own classroom "action research," and this serves as a catalyst to encourage teacher experimentation within their classes - while also encouraging the sharing of these findings with physics teaching colleagues. APEX builds on three components, each with its own subset of goals relating to the overarching project goal. The first component is a physics education center for teacher training that works toward:  (1) increasing the quantity of highly qualified in-service teachers and the number of underrepresented minority pre-service teachers; (2) increasing the depth and breadth of content knowledge, pedagogy, and instructional technology knowledge and skills; (3) promoting the development of the undergraduate physics teacher education programs at AAMU and UA-T; (4) implementing a cyber infrastructure resource repository for sharing and disseminating best teaching practices and lessons learned; and (5) distributing laboratory equipment to schools via the Alabama Science in Motion program. A second component builds on a physics teaching research program to promote and guide action research in the classroom, thus enhancing evidence-based best practices in these Alabama classrooms. The third component is a physics leadership development initiative that works with policy makers and administrators to encourage their broad support of physics teachers and programs. APEX's best practices, lessons learned, and research findings are being disseminated in journals of physics education, as well as being presentated at regional and national STEM education conferences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1238192</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Manmohan</FirstName>
<LastName>Aggarwal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Manmohan D Aggarwal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mohan.aggarwal@aamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2563728132</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000350921</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mostafa</FirstName>
<LastName>Dokhanian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mostafa Dokhanian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mostafa.dokhanian@aamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2563728131</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000475983</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/17/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marius</FirstName>
<LastName>Schamschula</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marius Schamschula</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marius.schamschula@aamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2563728226</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000442603</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edward Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>edward.jones@aamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2563724834</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000353338</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/26/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vernessa</FirstName>
<LastName>Edwards</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vernessa Edwards</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vernessa.edwards@aamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2563728107</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000350222</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Cady</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara Cady</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>barbara.cady@aamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2563725675</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000350020</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cathy</FirstName>
<LastName>McNeal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cathy C McNeal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cmcneal@hsv.k12.al.us</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2564286969</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000502459</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Alabama A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>Normal</CityName>
<ZipCode>357627500</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2563728186</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research and Sponsored</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[4900 Meridian]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079121448</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ALABAMA A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079121448</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Alabama A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>Normal</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>357620285</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4900 Meridian St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1792</Code>
<Text>MSP-TARGETED AWARDS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1792</Code>
<Text>MSP-Targeted Awards</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~2966938</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~1893996</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~1747491</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~1391574</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Research shows that the United States is facing a severe shortage of qualified high school physics teachers. Compared to other science subjects, such as biology and chemistry, fewer numbers of teachers in physics classrooms have degrees or certification in physics education. Studies show that only about 47% of physics teachers in U.S. classrooms are qualified to teach the subject. This means over half of the teachers are not equipped to meet the learning needs of students. The shortage of qualified physics teachers increases the use of teachers from other content areas to facilitate physics courses. This can hamper students' interest and the learning of physics, and affect their future career choices in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics fields. According to other researchers, the shortage of physics teachers can be linked to the fact that very few university programs are currently designed to specifically prepare physics teacher candidates for challenges of everyday instruction.</p> <p>Statistics of the physics shortage in Alabama was much more prevalent when compared to the U.S. average.&nbsp; Please note the following: (1) Shortage of physics offerings - 27% of students attend school with no physics. (Alabama&nbsp; &nbsp; ranks 44 out of 50 states); (2) Shortage of students taking physics. - 19% in Alabama vs 37% in US; (3) Shortage of trained physics teachers - 10% are certified with physics major vs 34% US.&nbsp;To address this need, The Alliance for Physics Excellence (APEX) led by Alabama Agricultural and Mechanical University (AAMU) and a core of partners:The University of Alabama at Tuscaloosa, Drake State Community and Technical College, American Association of Physics Teachers/Physics Teaching Resource Agents AAPT/PTRA, Alabama Math, Science &amp; Technology Initiative and the Alabama State Department of Education launched a five-year grant project funded by the National Science Foundation to transform physics education throughout the state of Alabama.&nbsp; APEX used a three dimensional approach to transforming physics pedagogy from traditional, didactic methods to actively engaging students in the learning process. The pillars of APEX physics high school teacher preparation included deepening content knowledge in the physics discipline, its pedagogical approach, and applying technology as it applies to physics pedagogy. This integrated 3-D approach will promote better conceptual understanding, problem-solving and exploration across the entire physics curriculum. Each teacher committed to three two-week summer training sessions and three two-day academic weekend workshops over a course of three years.&nbsp; Teachers experienced 70 contact hours per summer to develop their deep knowledge and classroom leadership skills and another 42 hours per academic for a total of 336 hours over the three-year period. Opportunities included reflection, networking and continuous professional development. APEX used an innovative strategy referred to as the top-down bottom-up strategy.&nbsp; While simultaneously training high school physics teacher on content and pedagogy, administrators, policymakers and stakeholders were being informed regarding the importance and need to include physics as a mandatory subject in the high school curricula. The vision<strong>&nbsp;</strong>of APEX, to promote significant gains in student learning by transforming secondary physics education throughout Alabama, successfully addressed NSF's Intellectual Merit criterion.</p> <p>Implications of the project emphasize a need for in-service training of physics teachers in U.S. high school classrooms. There is a need to increase students' interest in STEM education and grow the STEM workforce. Physics is a required course in most STEM fields, and therefore needs quality teachers. The APEX model provides an effective way to train physics teachers and possibly inspire other professional development providers to use targeted in-service training that meets the needs of its participants. Broader implications of APEX resulted in 77 trained high school physics teachers promoting the physics three-dimensional teaching methodology to other STEM discipline teachers. Through the collaboration between an HBCU and a majority institution, the preservice teacher component at the collegiate level created an opportunity to increase the number of females and African Americans entering the physics pipeline in a state with only one highly qualified African-American physics teacher. The dissemination of lessons learned, action researched best practices and partnership with ALSDE/ASIM also institutionalizes the accessibility of technology and equipment to APEX and non-APEX students and teachers.</p> <p>The following quote from an APEX participant further supports the broader impact this project has had in the physics classrooms across Alabama.</p> <p>"<em>Thank you for instilling the love&nbsp;of physics in me through my APEX experience.&nbsp; Prior to my APEX experience, I only taught it because I had to teach it, but now I have fought for the past two years to have physics in my high school when administration&nbsp;wanted to drop the course.&nbsp; Not only have I learned to love physics, but I have learned to love teaching through discovery.&nbsp; I have used the "APEX" style of teaching in all the classes I teach and have found students to be extremely responsive to it as opposed to my former lecture style of teaching.?&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/09/2019<br>      Modified by: Manmohan&nbsp;D&nbsp;Aggarwal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1565949822226_Equipmentdonation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1565949822226_Equipmentdonation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Group Photograph of President and other participants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1565949822226_Equipmentdonation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Group Photograph of President and other participants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Photo of the Alabama A&M University President Dr Andrew Hugine (Center), Dr Kemba Chambers (Interim President of J.F. Drake State Community and Technical College) and Ms Martha Allison, Science Education Administrator, Alabama Department of Education along with other admininstrators</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mohan Aggarwal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Manmohan&nbsp;D&nbsp;Aggarwal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Group Photograph of President and other participants</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1565948820302_COHORT2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1565948820302_COHORT2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Photograph of Cohort 2 of APEX participants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1565948820302_COHORT2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Photograph of Cohort 2 of APEX participants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Alabama high school teacher scholars cohort 2 undergoing professional development training at Alabama A&M University for the APEX project</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mohan Aggarwal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Manmohan&nbsp;D&nbsp;Aggarwal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Photograph of Cohort 2 of APEX participants</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1565948995799_COHORT3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1565948995799_COHORT3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Photograph of Cohort 3 of APEX participants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1565948995799_COHORT3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Photograph of Cohort 3 of APEX participants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Alabama high school teacher-scholars cohort 3 undergoing Professional development training at Alabama A&M University for this APEX project</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mohan Aggarwal</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Manmohan&nbsp;D&nbsp;Aggarwal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Photograph of Cohort 3 of APEX participants</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1565721684792_COHORT1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1565721684792_COHORT1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Photograph of Cohort 1 of APEX participants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1565721684792_COHORT1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Photograph of Cohort 1 of APEX participants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Alabama High School teachers and Alabama Science in Motion specialist underwent APEX professional Development at Alabama A&M University</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mohan Aggarwal</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Manmohan&nbsp;D&nbsp;Aggarwal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Photograph of Cohort 1 of APEX participants</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1575634627586_Mohan7--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1575634627586_Mohan7--rgov-800width.jpg" title="APEX Alabama physics teacher scholars during professional development workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1575634627586_Mohan7--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="APEX Alabama physics teacher scholars during professional development workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Alabama high school physics teacher scholars performing hands on experiment during APEX professional development workshop</div> <div class="imageCredit">Manmohan D Aggarwal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Manmohan&nbsp;D&nbsp;Aggarwal</div> <div class="imageTitle">APEX Alabama physics teacher scholars during professional development workshop</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1575634855365_Mohan6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1575634855365_Mohan6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="APEX Alabama physics teacher scholars during professional development workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1238192/1238192_10214800_1575634855365_Mohan6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="APEX Alabama physics teacher scholars during professional development workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Alabama physics teacher scholars performing hands on experiment during Professional Development workshop</div> <div class="imageCredit">Manmohan D Aggarwal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Manmohan&nbsp;D&nbsp;Aggarwal</div> <div class="imageTitle">APEX Alabama physics teacher scholars during professional development workshop</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Research shows that the United States is facing a severe shortage of qualified high school physics teachers. Compared to other science subjects, such as biology and chemistry, fewer numbers of teachers in physics classrooms have degrees or certification in physics education. Studies show that only about 47% of physics teachers in U.S. classrooms are qualified to teach the subject. This means over half of the teachers are not equipped to meet the learning needs of students. The shortage of qualified physics teachers increases the use of teachers from other content areas to facilitate physics courses. This can hamper students' interest and the learning of physics, and affect their future career choices in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics fields. According to other researchers, the shortage of physics teachers can be linked to the fact that very few university programs are currently designed to specifically prepare physics teacher candidates for challenges of everyday instruction.  Statistics of the physics shortage in Alabama was much more prevalent when compared to the U.S. average.  Please note the following: (1) Shortage of physics offerings - 27% of students attend school with no physics. (Alabama    ranks 44 out of 50 states); (2) Shortage of students taking physics. - 19% in Alabama vs 37% in US; (3) Shortage of trained physics teachers - 10% are certified with physics major vs 34% US. To address this need, The Alliance for Physics Excellence (APEX) led by Alabama Agricultural and Mechanical University (AAMU) and a core of partners:The University of Alabama at Tuscaloosa, Drake State Community and Technical College, American Association of Physics Teachers/Physics Teaching Resource Agents AAPT/PTRA, Alabama Math, Science &amp; Technology Initiative and the Alabama State Department of Education launched a five-year grant project funded by the National Science Foundation to transform physics education throughout the state of Alabama.  APEX used a three dimensional approach to transforming physics pedagogy from traditional, didactic methods to actively engaging students in the learning process. The pillars of APEX physics high school teacher preparation included deepening content knowledge in the physics discipline, its pedagogical approach, and applying technology as it applies to physics pedagogy. This integrated 3-D approach will promote better conceptual understanding, problem-solving and exploration across the entire physics curriculum. Each teacher committed to three two-week summer training sessions and three two-day academic weekend workshops over a course of three years.  Teachers experienced 70 contact hours per summer to develop their deep knowledge and classroom leadership skills and another 42 hours per academic for a total of 336 hours over the three-year period. Opportunities included reflection, networking and continuous professional development. APEX used an innovative strategy referred to as the top-down bottom-up strategy.  While simultaneously training high school physics teacher on content and pedagogy, administrators, policymakers and stakeholders were being informed regarding the importance and need to include physics as a mandatory subject in the high school curricula. The vision of APEX, to promote significant gains in student learning by transforming secondary physics education throughout Alabama, successfully addressed NSF's Intellectual Merit criterion.  Implications of the project emphasize a need for in-service training of physics teachers in U.S. high school classrooms. There is a need to increase students' interest in STEM education and grow the STEM workforce. Physics is a required course in most STEM fields, and therefore needs quality teachers. The APEX model provides an effective way to train physics teachers and possibly inspire other professional development providers to use targeted in-service training that meets the needs of its participants. Broader implications of APEX resulted in 77 trained high school physics teachers promoting the physics three-dimensional teaching methodology to other STEM discipline teachers. Through the collaboration between an HBCU and a majority institution, the preservice teacher component at the collegiate level created an opportunity to increase the number of females and African Americans entering the physics pipeline in a state with only one highly qualified African-American physics teacher. The dissemination of lessons learned, action researched best practices and partnership with ALSDE/ASIM also institutionalizes the accessibility of technology and equipment to APEX and non-APEX students and teachers.  The following quote from an APEX participant further supports the broader impact this project has had in the physics classrooms across Alabama.  "Thank you for instilling the love of physics in me through my APEX experience.  Prior to my APEX experience, I only taught it because I had to teach it, but now I have fought for the past two years to have physics in my high school when administration wanted to drop the course.  Not only have I learned to love physics, but I have learned to love teaching through discovery.  I have used the "APEX" style of teaching in all the classes I teach and have found students to be extremely responsive to it as opposed to my former lecture style of teaching.?                 Last Modified: 12/09/2019       Submitted by: Manmohan D Aggarwal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
