<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Scaling I-Corps Training curriculum: Developing Scientific and Engineering Discoveries into Useful Technologies, Products and Processes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>398239.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>398239</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EFMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The National Collegiate Inventors &amp; Innovators Alliance (NCIIA) proposes to scale the I-Corps program by supporting the program at campuses in geographically-diverse locations across the U.S. NCIIA will work with original members of the I-Corps teaching team to implement two additional workshops. Feedback from the evaluation process will inform improvements in both the instructor-training program and the I-Corps curriculum. NCIIA Course and Program grants support the development and implementation of experiential education programs that teach engineering and science students to apply innovative and entrepreneurial thinking to their coursework. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the I-Corps program is to determine the commercial feasibility of technology derived from NSF-funded research. Participants will leave the program with an expanded skill-set that will give them the tools necessary to evaluate and translate their research into applications that can benefit society.  This program will support an initial a network of instructors who can improve and adapt the program model as it is disseminated to new institutions and regions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1239638</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Weilerstein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philip J Weilerstein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pweilerstein@nciia.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135872172</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000041172</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Collegiate Inventors and Innovators Alliance</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359682</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135872172</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 Venture Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>110907578</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL COLLEGIATE INVENTORS &amp; INNOVATORS ALLIANCE, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Collegiate Inventors and Innovators Alliance]]></Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 Venture Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>40XX</Code>
<Name>NSF TRUST FUND</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>048960</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~398239</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>While the United States remains the world&rsquo;s leader in scientific and engineering research and education, we can do much more to commercialize our best discoveries, particularly those emerging from university labs. To meet the challenge of bringing the country's best innovations into the global market -- and to increase the impact of academic research -- NSF created the Innovation Corps (I-Corps) program to help NSF-funded scientists and engineers develop skills to evaluate their research for potential practical, economically scalable applications. I-Corps training is an eight-week course designed to teach I-Corps teams the Lean Launchpad business model design and customer development process developed by Steve Blank.</p> <p>The major goals of this project entitled, "Scaling I&shy;-Corps Training Curriculum: Developing Scientific and Engineering Discoveries into Useful Technologies, Products and Processes&rdquo;, has been a two-pronged effort that entailed: (1) developing a scalable model for delivering the I-Corps&nbsp;program to a larger number of NSF grantees and (2) a faculty development component that prepares new instructors to deliver the program in geographically diverse locations across the country. &nbsp;In addition, during the course of this grant, the National Collegiate Inventors and Innovators Alliance (d/b/a VentureWell) initiated a longitudinal study of I-Corps&nbsp;teams to measure their progress with respect to scaling their venture and assessing the impact of their participation in the I-Corps&nbsp;program.</p> <p>Specific project deliverables included:</p> <ul> <li>Publication of Faculty Development Workbooks</li> <li>Development and publication of Faculty Teaching Manual</li> <li>Dissemination of I-Corps Course Administration Handbook that is updated upon completion of each new faculty training</li> <li>Interview protocol that can be adapted or adopted by others using the I-Corps curriculum</li> <li>Set of course evaluation instruments that may be adapted or adopted by others using the I-Corps curriculum</li> <li>Longitudinal survey instrument that may be adapted or adopted by others to measure long-term outcomes and program impacts on similar types of teams and participants.</li> </ul> <p>With an overarching objective to provide professional development and training for university faculty serving as I-Corps trainers and mentors, the work conducted under this grant established a template and structure for translating entrepreneurship, business model, and customer discovery concepts into powerful tools for scientists and engineers. Faculty continue to gain professional development opportunities from their participation in the National I&shy;-Corps&nbsp;training programs as they are able to observe instructors from different regional Nodes deliver the I-Corps curriculum.</p> <p>Tasked with facilitating -- and working hand&shy;-in-hand&nbsp;with -- the NSF I-Corps&nbsp;program, this project also initiated development of a National Innovation Network to provide recipients of NSF&shy;-funded&nbsp;research with the knowledge, tools, mentors and professional community to accelerate commercialization of their research and inventions to create new business and economic opportunities.&nbsp;</p> <p>This interdisciplinary project, relevant to all STEM disciplines, but particularly engineering, chemistry, education and computer science, will help expand the impact of these disciplines through improving the knowledge, skills and behaviors needed to translate STEM research into practical applications that have potential social, environmental, and economic benefits for society.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2015<br>      Modified by: Philip&nbsp;J&nbsp;Weilerstein</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ While the United States remains the worldÆs leader in scientific and engineering research and education, we can do much more to commercialize our best discoveries, particularly those emerging from university labs. To meet the challenge of bringing the country's best innovations into the global market -- and to increase the impact of academic research -- NSF created the Innovation Corps (I-Corps) program to help NSF-funded scientists and engineers develop skills to evaluate their research for potential practical, economically scalable applications. I-Corps training is an eight-week course designed to teach I-Corps teams the Lean Launchpad business model design and customer development process developed by Steve Blank.  The major goals of this project entitled, "Scaling I&shy;-Corps Training Curriculum: Developing Scientific and Engineering Discoveries into Useful Technologies, Products and Processes", has been a two-pronged effort that entailed: (1) developing a scalable model for delivering the I-Corps program to a larger number of NSF grantees and (2) a faculty development component that prepares new instructors to deliver the program in geographically diverse locations across the country.  In addition, during the course of this grant, the National Collegiate Inventors and Innovators Alliance (d/b/a VentureWell) initiated a longitudinal study of I-Corps teams to measure their progress with respect to scaling their venture and assessing the impact of their participation in the I-Corps program.  Specific project deliverables included:  Publication of Faculty Development Workbooks Development and publication of Faculty Teaching Manual Dissemination of I-Corps Course Administration Handbook that is updated upon completion of each new faculty training Interview protocol that can be adapted or adopted by others using the I-Corps curriculum Set of course evaluation instruments that may be adapted or adopted by others using the I-Corps curriculum Longitudinal survey instrument that may be adapted or adopted by others to measure long-term outcomes and program impacts on similar types of teams and participants.   With an overarching objective to provide professional development and training for university faculty serving as I-Corps trainers and mentors, the work conducted under this grant established a template and structure for translating entrepreneurship, business model, and customer discovery concepts into powerful tools for scientists and engineers. Faculty continue to gain professional development opportunities from their participation in the National I&shy;-Corps training programs as they are able to observe instructors from different regional Nodes deliver the I-Corps curriculum.  Tasked with facilitating -- and working hand&shy;-in-hand with -- the NSF I-Corps program, this project also initiated development of a National Innovation Network to provide recipients of NSF&shy;-funded research with the knowledge, tools, mentors and professional community to accelerate commercialization of their research and inventions to create new business and economic opportunities.   This interdisciplinary project, relevant to all STEM disciplines, but particularly engineering, chemistry, education and computer science, will help expand the impact of these disciplines through improving the knowledge, skills and behaviors needed to translate STEM research into practical applications that have potential social, environmental, and economic benefits for society.           Last Modified: 04/01/2015       Submitted by: Philip J Weilerstein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
