<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The 34th Midwest Probability Colloquium</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>22000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>22000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 34th Midwest Probability Colloquium at Northwestern University on October 12-14, 2012, at Northwestern University. Probability theory has been the most applicable branch of pure mathematics. During the last decade we have seen a clear surge in popularity of probabilistic tools and methods in other branches of pure and applied mathematics. This year's selection of program topics and speakers reflect the broad scope of applicability of the discipline. By maintaining a wide range of active research directions, the Midwest Probability Colloquium continues to provide a forum for the exchange of intellectual interest across a wide array of applied fields as well as for core areas of mathematics. Following the well established traditional format, the colloquium will be divided into the Tutorial Program and the Research Program. This year's topic of the Tutorial Program is Probability and Mathematical Biology and will be hosted by&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Steven Evans (University of California, Berkeley)&lt;br/&gt;David Steinsaltz (University of Oxford)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The speakers of the Research Program are:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Elizabeth Meckes (CaseWestern Research University)&lt;br/&gt;Jeremy Quastel (University of Toronto)&lt;br/&gt;Gennady Samorodnitsky (Cornell University)&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This conference will be sponsored jointly by the National Science Foundation with a conference grant and by Northwestern University with providing the venue and other local amenities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/10/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1239624</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elton</FirstName>
<LastName>Hsu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elton P Hsu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ehsu@math.northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474918541</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000453653</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/10/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602082730</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2033 Sheridan Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~22000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcomes Report for the General Public <br />Project Title: The 34th Midwest Probability Colloquium<br />Principal Investigator: Elton Hsu<br />Awardee: Northwestern University<br />Award Number: 1239624<br />Award Expires:06/30/2013<br /><br />The 34th Midwest Probability Colloquium was held with great success on October 11-13, 2012 at Northwestern University. The conference was attended by approximately 90 participants, with 65 of them registered online. The speakers were chosen by a three-member scientific committee elected at the last year's meeting. The speakers for the Tutorial Program were Steve Evans (UC Berkeley, two lectures) and David Steinsaltz (Oxford University), and the speakers of the research program were Jeremy Quastel (University of Toronto, two lectures), Elizabeth Meckes (Case Western Reserve University), and Genndy Samorodnitsky (Cornell University). <br /><br />This year's topic for the Tutorial Program was Probability Theory in Biomathematics. The topics of the Research Program included stochastic partial differential equations, Gaussian random fields, and projections of probability distributions. The lectures were well received by the members of audience, the majority of whom were young researchers and graduate students.</p> <p>The funds provided by the NSF were used to defray in full the expenses of the speakrs and to partially support the travel and lodging of the participants who had no or insufficient resources to attend the conference. Almost all of the participants supported in this category were graduate students and young researchers who have obtained their Ph. D. within 5 years.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2013<br>      Modified by: Elton&nbsp;P&nbsp;Hsu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report for the General Public  Project Title: The 34th Midwest Probability Colloquium Principal Investigator: Elton Hsu Awardee: Northwestern University Award Number: 1239624 Award Expires:06/30/2013  The 34th Midwest Probability Colloquium was held with great success on October 11-13, 2012 at Northwestern University. The conference was attended by approximately 90 participants, with 65 of them registered online. The speakers were chosen by a three-member scientific committee elected at the last year's meeting. The speakers for the Tutorial Program were Steve Evans (UC Berkeley, two lectures) and David Steinsaltz (Oxford University), and the speakers of the research program were Jeremy Quastel (University of Toronto, two lectures), Elizabeth Meckes (Case Western Reserve University), and Genndy Samorodnitsky (Cornell University).   This year's topic for the Tutorial Program was Probability Theory in Biomathematics. The topics of the Research Program included stochastic partial differential equations, Gaussian random fields, and projections of probability distributions. The lectures were well received by the members of audience, the majority of whom were young researchers and graduate students.  The funds provided by the NSF were used to defray in full the expenses of the speakrs and to partially support the travel and lodging of the participants who had no or insufficient resources to attend the conference. Almost all of the participants supported in this category were graduate students and young researchers who have obtained their Ph. D. within 5 years.       Last Modified: 08/29/2013       Submitted by: Elton P Hsu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
