<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CPS: Synergy: Achieving High-Resolution Situational Awareness in Ultra-Wide-Area Cyber-Physical Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1000000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Energy infrastructure is a critical underpinning of modern society. To ensure its reliable operation, a nation-wide or continent-wide situational awareness system is essential to provide high-resolution understanding of the system dynamics such that proper actions can be taken in real-time in response to power system disturbances and to avoid cascading blackouts. The power grid represents a typical highly dynamic cyber-physical system (CPS). The ever-increasing complexity and scale in sensing and actuation, compounded by the limited knowledge of the accurate system state have resulted in major system failures, such as the massive power blackout of August 2003 and the most recent Arizona/California blackout of September 2011. Therefore, methods and tools for monitoring and control of these and other such dynamic systems at high resolution are vital to an emergent generation of tightly coupled, physically distributed CPS. This project employs the power grid as a target application and develops a high-resolution, ultra-wide-area situational awareness system that synergistically integrates sensing, processing, and actuation. First, from the sensing perspective, high resolution is reflected in both measurement accuracy and potential for dense spatial coverage. Wide area, precise, synchronized, and affordable sensing in voltage angle and frequency measurements for large-scale observation is sorely needed to observe system disturbances and capture critical changes in the power grid. The crucial innovation of this work is to make accurate frequency measurement from low voltage distribution systems through the wide deployment of Frequency Disturbance Recorders (FDRs). Second, from a data processing perspective, high resolution is reflected in finer-scale data analysis to reveal hidden information.  In practical CPS, events seldom occur in an isolated fashion; cascading events are more common and realistic.  A new conceptual framework is presented in the study of event analysis, referred to as event unmixing, where real-world events are considered a mixture of more than one constituent root event. This concept is a key enabler for the analysis of events to go beyond what are immediately detectable in the system. The event formation process is interpreted from a linear mixing perspective and innovative sparsity-constrained unmixing algorithms are presented for multiple event separation and spatial-temporal localization.  Third, to discover the high-level spatial-temporal correlation among root events in real time, a descriptive language is developed to discover patterns on the spatial and temporal information of root events. This descriptive language allows embedding pattern descriptions on the desirable and undesirable interactions between events in the system, which will then be compiled into distributed runtime constructs to be executed in deployed systems. Fourth, from the actuation perspective, the system pushes the intelligence toward the lower level of the power grid allowing local devices to make decisions and to react quickly to contingencies based on the high-resolution understanding of the system state, enabling a more direct reconfiguration of the physical makeup of the grid. Finally, the methods and tools are implemented and validated on an existing wide-area power grid monitoring system, the North American frequency monitoring network (FNET).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Escalating demands for electricity coupled with an outdated power transmission grid pose a serious threat to the US economy. The transformative nature of this research is to turn a large volume of real-time data into actionable information and help prevent potential outages from happening. The power grid is a typical example of dynamic cyber physical system. Providing high-resolution situational awareness for the power grid has a direct and immediate impact on this and other CPS. The research is coupled with a strong educational component including active recruitment of students from underrepresented groups supported by existing programs and broad dissemination of research findings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1239478</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yilu</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yilu Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>liu@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8559744129</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000274370</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hairong</FirstName>
<LastName>Qi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hairong Qi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hqi@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659748527</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000253946</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leon</FirstName>
<LastName>Tolbert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leon M Tolbert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tolbert@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659743461</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000356175</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Qing</FirstName>
<LastName>Cao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Qing Cao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cao@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659745417</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000537804</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379163801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1331 CIR PARK DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tennessee Knoxville]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CPS-Cyber-Physical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1000000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project employs the power grid as a target application and develops a high-resolution, ultra-wide-area situational awareness system that synergistically integrates sensing (high-resolution sensing with innovative design of frequency disturbance recorder at the distribution level), processing (high-resolution online data analysis through event unmixing), and actuation (coordinated local actuation with load as resource). The objective is to turn a large volume of real-time "mixture" data into actionable information and help prevent potential outages from happening. All the designs are powered by online implementation supported through novel programming abstractions such as DataSQL.</p> <p>From sensing perspective, high resolution is reflected in both measurement accuracy and potential for dense spatial coverage. Wide area, precise, synchronized, and affordable sensing in voltage angle and frequency measurements for large-scale observation is sorely needed to observe system disturbances and capture critical changes in the power grid. The crucial innovation of this work is to make accurate frequency measurement from low voltage distribution systems through the wide deployment of Frequency Disturbance Recorders (FDR).</p> <p>From processing perspective, high resolution is reflected in finer-scale data analysis to reveal hidden information.&nbsp; In practical CPS, events seldom occur in an isolated fashion. Cascading events are more common and realistic.&nbsp; A new conceptual framework is presented in the study of event analysis, referred to as event unmixing, where real-world events are considered a mixture of more than one constituent root event. We have developed innovative cluster-based sparse coding event unmixing algorithms for multiple event separation and spatial-temporal localization.</p> <p>From online implementation perspective, we tackle the challenging problem of online data programming and processing through novel programming abstractions such as DataSQL. Probabilistic and fault-tolerant methods and compact data structures have been developed that are particularly suitable for large amount of online data processing and data programming abstractions on resource constrained platforms.</p> <p>From the actuation perspective, the system pushes the intelligence toward the lower level of the power grid allowing effective local load participation to react quickly to contingencies based on the high-resolution understanding of the system state, enabling a more direct reconfiguration of the physical makeup of the grid.</p> <p>The proposed methods and tools have been implemented and validated on an existing wide-area power grid monitoring system, the North American frequency monitoring network (FNET/GridEye), as well as the hardware testbed constructed at our partner institute, the NSF/COE CURENT Center.</p> <p>Please see more details at the project website (<a href="http://aicip.eecs.utk.edu/wiki/CPSPowerGrid)">http://aicip.eecs.utk.edu/wiki/CPSPowerGrid)</a> and the open source software for event unmixing (<a href="https://bitbucket.org/aicip/csc)">https://bitbucket.org/aicip/csc)</a>.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/11/2017<br>      Modified by: Hairong&nbsp;Qi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744250994_powercps-system2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744250994_powercps-system2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Power Grid CPS"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744250994_powercps-system2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Power Grid CPS"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">To turn a large volume of real-time ?mixture? data into actionable information and help prevent outages from happening</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Tennessee</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hairong&nbsp;Qi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Power Grid CPS</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744413850_powercps-deployment2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744413850_powercps-deployment2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FNET/GridEye"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744413850_powercps-deployment2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FNET/GridEye"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The deployment map of FNET/GridEye (A joint effort by the University of Tennessee and Oak Ridge National Laboratory)</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Tennessee</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hairong&nbsp;Qi</div> <div class="imageTitle">FNET/GridEye</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744506154_powercps-cluster2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744506154_powercps-cluster2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cluster-based processing"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744506154_powercps-cluster2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cluster-based processing"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The existence of stable clusters  with similar behavior within the cluster for various</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Tennessee</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hairong&nbsp;Qi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cluster-based processing</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744709469_powercps-unmixing2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744709469_powercps-unmixing2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Event unmixing"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744709469_powercps-unmixing2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Event unmixing"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">First row: frequency readout for single event with one generator trip (GT) (top-left) and multiple events with two GTs and three line trips (LTs) (top-right). Second row: the comparison between the original frequency signal and the reconstructed. Third row: the recognition results.</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Tennessee</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hairong&nbsp;Qi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Event unmixing</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744887471_powercps-actuation2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744887471_powercps-actuation2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Load participation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1239478/1239478_10212194_1507744887471_powercps-actuation2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Load participation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Residential power demand simulation tool (L) and HVAC demand response (load shedding) (R). Simulation of 1000 homes on Sunday June 3rd, 2012 (At 4 pm, shed 50 % of HVACs). Residential power demand decreased by ~30% for 9.5 minutes whileresidential power demand increased by ~18% for 18 minutes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Tennessee</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hairong&nbsp;Qi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Load participation</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project employs the power grid as a target application and develops a high-resolution, ultra-wide-area situational awareness system that synergistically integrates sensing (high-resolution sensing with innovative design of frequency disturbance recorder at the distribution level), processing (high-resolution online data analysis through event unmixing), and actuation (coordinated local actuation with load as resource). The objective is to turn a large volume of real-time "mixture" data into actionable information and help prevent potential outages from happening. All the designs are powered by online implementation supported through novel programming abstractions such as DataSQL.  From sensing perspective, high resolution is reflected in both measurement accuracy and potential for dense spatial coverage. Wide area, precise, synchronized, and affordable sensing in voltage angle and frequency measurements for large-scale observation is sorely needed to observe system disturbances and capture critical changes in the power grid. The crucial innovation of this work is to make accurate frequency measurement from low voltage distribution systems through the wide deployment of Frequency Disturbance Recorders (FDR).  From processing perspective, high resolution is reflected in finer-scale data analysis to reveal hidden information.  In practical CPS, events seldom occur in an isolated fashion. Cascading events are more common and realistic.  A new conceptual framework is presented in the study of event analysis, referred to as event unmixing, where real-world events are considered a mixture of more than one constituent root event. We have developed innovative cluster-based sparse coding event unmixing algorithms for multiple event separation and spatial-temporal localization.  From online implementation perspective, we tackle the challenging problem of online data programming and processing through novel programming abstractions such as DataSQL. Probabilistic and fault-tolerant methods and compact data structures have been developed that are particularly suitable for large amount of online data processing and data programming abstractions on resource constrained platforms.  From the actuation perspective, the system pushes the intelligence toward the lower level of the power grid allowing effective local load participation to react quickly to contingencies based on the high-resolution understanding of the system state, enabling a more direct reconfiguration of the physical makeup of the grid.  The proposed methods and tools have been implemented and validated on an existing wide-area power grid monitoring system, the North American frequency monitoring network (FNET/GridEye), as well as the hardware testbed constructed at our partner institute, the NSF/COE CURENT Center.  Please see more details at the project website (http://aicip.eecs.utk.edu/wiki/CPSPowerGrid) and the open source software for event unmixing (https://bitbucket.org/aicip/csc).           Last Modified: 10/11/2017       Submitted by: Hairong Qi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
