<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Expanding and Strengthening the Secondary STEM Teacher Training Program</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1199804.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1199804</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Camacho - Walter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mcamacho@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928718</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Noyce Teacher Scholar Program at Benedictine University is providing 2-year scholarships to 27 pre-service undergraduates and 33 STEM professional career changers. In addition, 23 undergraduates potentially interested in STEM teaching careers are enjoying summer internships where they become exposed to the basics of problem-based learning and then assist with the Summer Sleuths program. The project expects to produce at least 49 new mathematics/science teachers highly qualified to teach mathematics or science in grades 6-12. Building on existing campus strengths, the project is focusing on chemistry, physics, biology, and mathematics. The project is partnering with nearby school districts including Naperville Community Unit School District 203 and Chicago Academy High School, as well as the Golden Apple Foundation. The project is utilizing "Inquiry Weekend Workshops" to allow Noyce Scholars to learn the basics of inquiry pedagogy from master teachers. A required seminar course "Careers in Science" is helping to recruit students to the STEM teaching profession. Master teachers mentor the Noyce Scholars throughout their teaching internship and into their first year of teaching, in addition to allowing the Scholars observation opportunities in their high needs classrooms. Faculty from multiple disciplines are ensuring teachers are prepared with strong content knowledge, a commitment to inquiry-based science instruction, and a thorough preparation in pedagogy. The project is creating a model that includes inspirational educational experiences for future teachers, early exposure to field experiences, and interdisciplinary interactions that help students develop innovative pedagogical techniques. The project is advancing, applying, and disseminating knowledge about strategies for the recruitment, preparation, induction and retention of highly-qualified STEM teachers for high-needs schools in an urban area. Preparing scholars to be the nation's leading educational change agents who integrate inquiry, problem-based learning, and research into their mathematics and science courses will have a significant impact on increasing learning opportunities and achievement for students in high-needs schools. The project also is expected to increase their interest in and enthusiasm for science, which will result in higher numbers of these students pursuing STEM careers. Implementation of the proposed model is being documented so that it can be replicated in other urban settings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1240091</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allison</FirstName>
<LastName>Wilson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allison K Wilson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>awilson@ben.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6308296520</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000382328</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Wig</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Wig</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>awig@ben.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6308295627</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000468050</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Zigmond</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Zigmond</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jzigmond@ben.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6308296004</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000618525</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Benedictine University</Name>
<CityName>Lisle</CityName>
<ZipCode>605320900</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6308296004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5700 College Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069957298</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BENEDICTINE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069957298</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Benedictine University]]></Name>
<CityName>Lisle</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>605320900</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5700 College Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>04XX</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1199804</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Benedictine University completed the NSF Noyce Teacher Scholarship program entitled, <em>Expanding and Strengthening the Secondary STEM Teacher Training Program</em>. A total of 28 aspiring teachers were supported by the grant; 15 two-year scholarships were awarded to highly qualified undergraduates to complete a traditional teacher education program and 13 one-year stipends were awarded to STEM professionals in our alternative certification program. Fourteen women and three underrepresented minority scholars participated in the program. &nbsp;To date, 17 of these scholars are teaching in physics (6), mathematics (5), chemistry (1) or biology/chemistry (5) in a high needs school district.&nbsp; Four additional scholars are finishing earning their credentials.</p> <p>Scholars were recruited into the Noyce program in a variety of ways. Partnerships with the Brookfield Zoo, Morton Arboretum, the Jurica-Suchy Nature Museum and the DuPage Forest Preserve provided unique educational experiences in non-traditional settings. Our highly successful Learning Assistant program provided teaching and facilitating opportunities in the college classroom. &nbsp;Our <em>Careers in Science</em> alumni panels reinforced the appeal of the teaching profession and emphasized the need for highly trained and effective teachers.&nbsp; However, the most successful method of recruitment was still personal contact of individual faculty with students. &nbsp;A lesson learned was that students often became excited about the teaching profession too late to complete their STEM major and earn certification in four years. Our School of Education has recently proposed a streamlined education major that will facilitate this timeline.</p> <p>Five undergraduate scholars participated in mentored research projects that promoted the connection between the scientific method and the classroom. Other scholars created discovery boxes containing objects and a complete set of NGSS-aligned objectives and suggested lesson plans for use by elementary teachers and home schoolers. Scholars were mentored in inquiry pedagogy by master teachers of the Golden Apple Foundation's <em>Inquiry Science Institute</em>.&nbsp; As part of their training, they learned how to motivate and engage students in the classroom using minimal resources.&nbsp; Scholars had the opportunity to receive formal mentoring from master teachers during their first year of teaching.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2020<br>      Modified by: Allison&nbsp;K&nbsp;Wilson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Benedictine University completed the NSF Noyce Teacher Scholarship program entitled, Expanding and Strengthening the Secondary STEM Teacher Training Program. A total of 28 aspiring teachers were supported by the grant; 15 two-year scholarships were awarded to highly qualified undergraduates to complete a traditional teacher education program and 13 one-year stipends were awarded to STEM professionals in our alternative certification program. Fourteen women and three underrepresented minority scholars participated in the program.  To date, 17 of these scholars are teaching in physics (6), mathematics (5), chemistry (1) or biology/chemistry (5) in a high needs school district.  Four additional scholars are finishing earning their credentials.  Scholars were recruited into the Noyce program in a variety of ways. Partnerships with the Brookfield Zoo, Morton Arboretum, the Jurica-Suchy Nature Museum and the DuPage Forest Preserve provided unique educational experiences in non-traditional settings. Our highly successful Learning Assistant program provided teaching and facilitating opportunities in the college classroom.  Our Careers in Science alumni panels reinforced the appeal of the teaching profession and emphasized the need for highly trained and effective teachers.  However, the most successful method of recruitment was still personal contact of individual faculty with students.  A lesson learned was that students often became excited about the teaching profession too late to complete their STEM major and earn certification in four years. Our School of Education has recently proposed a streamlined education major that will facilitate this timeline.  Five undergraduate scholars participated in mentored research projects that promoted the connection between the scientific method and the classroom. Other scholars created discovery boxes containing objects and a complete set of NGSS-aligned objectives and suggested lesson plans for use by elementary teachers and home schoolers. Scholars were mentored in inquiry pedagogy by master teachers of the Golden Apple Foundation's Inquiry Science Institute.  As part of their training, they learned how to motivate and engage students in the classroom using minimal resources.  Scholars had the opportunity to receive formal mentoring from master teachers during their first year of teaching.              Last Modified: 03/31/2020       Submitted by: Allison K Wilson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
