<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MSPnet.org: An Online Professional Learning Network</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>4811612.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5319715</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen Bergin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kbergin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925171</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>MSPnet.org is an online professional learning network created to serve NSF's Math and Science Partnership program.  It facilitates the sharing of strategies, challenges, resources and expertise within and across MSP projects.  It is also an effective vehicle for sharing the lessons learned by MSP projects with the U.S. Department of Education's MSP program, as well as with researchers, practitioners, and the public at large.  Finally, it provides an innovative model of inter-linking e-communities of practice to others interested in developing online learning communities. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;MSPnet, which was first launched in January 2004 with 351 pre-registered members, now serves over 7,200 members who are affiliated with current or past MSP projects.  In addition, it has successfully attracted a large public user-base of over 1.5 million unique visitors, who have accessed over 7.4 million page-views.  MSPnet's professional learning network facilitates cross-project dialogue while also providing each NSF MSP project with its own project space, including interactive tools to enhance collaboration between partners. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The current effort includes new features and functionalities to insure that the network stays innovative and up-to-date with rapidly changing technology.  Changes to the site are responsive to evolving community needs, principles of Web and community design, navigational ease, and usability.  While seamlessly continuing previous activities, innovative formats and interactive events (e.g., interactive online poster sessions, interactive panels and webinars), MSPnet is supporting additional cross-project dialogue, enhancing mechanisms for users to quickly find resources relevant to their needs, and providing synthesis and research briefs of MSP-authored research.  These are accessible to a wide audience, and create new mechanisms for the sharing of resources with other resource centers and communities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1240555</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Drayton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian E Drayton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brian_drayton@terc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175470430</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000087508</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joni</FirstName>
<LastName>Falk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joni Falk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>joni_falk@terc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6178739632</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000177844</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>TERC Inc</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021401339</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6178739600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2067 Massachusetts Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071719801</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TERC, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[TERC Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambrdige</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021401364</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2067 Massachusetts Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1793</Code>
<Text>MSP-OTHER AWARDS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7345</Code>
<Text>PAEMST Pres Awrds Excell Teach</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1793</Code>
<Text>MSP-Other Awards</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0417</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1662596</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~2076466</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~1072550</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~508103</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Math and Science Partnership Network (http://MSPnet.org) was originally created in 2004 to serve multiple communities affiliated with the National Science Foundation&rsquo;s Math and Science Partnership Program. The last grant from NSF supporting the development of this project, was received in 2012. The project was actively facilitated until September 2019. Over the years, MSPnet expanded its reach and served state coordinators and evaluators involved in ED&rsquo;s Math, Science Partnership Program, leaders affiliated with NSF&rsquo;s STEM+C program, as well as other researchers, K-12 educators and administrators, higher education STEM faculty, and professional developers interested in improving Science, Technology, Engineering, Mathematics and Computer Science teaching and learning. The site provided a resource center and collegial network for those leading efforts to improve Math and Science.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;The design of MSPnet was innovative as it provided a central Hub for all projects to learn and share findings, resources, research, challenges, and strategies with each other. In addition, each participating NSF-funded project had its own interactive project space to collaborate with partners, collect research in a project specific library, share files internally, utilize a shared project calendar, and host webinars free of charge. Project spaces also enabled each project to showcase their efforts to the public, as it provided an abstract of the work, links to their publications, and bios of their senior staff. By the end of the project, MSPnet provided interactive project spaces for 274 NSF-funded projects. Material created by each of these projects contributed to the rich collection that was shared in the MSPnet Hub. Almost all of this material was made accessible to the public at large.&nbsp;</p> <p>Goals:&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li>MSPnet.org created a virtual, electronic, infrastructure for NSF and ED projects to learn with and from each other. The 274 interactive project spaces allowed each participating project to contribute resources to a Central Hub, which were then shared across all projects and with the public at large.&nbsp;</li> <li>MSPnet.org increased access to research, resources, and tools related to STEM teaching and learning, educational policy, challenging courses and curriculum, institutional change and sustainability, and effective practices of professional development.</li> <li>MSPnet.org provided an archive of the growth and products produced by&nbsp;&nbsp;the very large NSF MSP program over time. It created a digital library with over 3,000 full-text articles related to STEM education. This collection included 780 publications written by leaders of NSF-funded MSP and STEM+C projects. These articles provide a broad view of the collective impact of these programs on the field.&nbsp;</li> </ol> <p>Activities:</p> <p>The staff of MSPnet created the architecture and technical development and provided the maintenance and content management for this large on-line infrastructure that successfully supported knowledge-sharing across multiple communities. It created a vast Library that added relevant research each week, a Resources section that shared useful websites and research tools, and a Conference section, which archived each of the program&rsquo;s annual Learning Network Conferences, by providing abstracts, papers and videos of plenary events.&nbsp;&nbsp;In addition, it created interactive experiences to engage users, including the MSPnet Academy, which featured interactive webinars offered by leaders in the field, discussions on multiple topics of interest, and monthly blogs. Last, it provided a weekly newsletter to users informing them of new research, resources, and events that were also posted to the site. This was particularly effective in drawing our members back to the site often.</p> <p>Findings:</p> <p>The site has had over two million-page views and has served over 460,000 unique users from 215 countries and territories. While 81% of users originated in the US, 19% of users came from 215 countries and territories across the globe. The highest usage internationally came from Canada, China, Brazil, the Philippines, India, the UK, Australia, Germany, South Korea and Turkey.&nbsp;</p> <p>Evaluation reports found that MSPnet.org provided users with up-to-date research, news and resources related to the broad fields of STEM and computer science education. The library made them aware of, and provided access to newly published findings relevant to their project. It also enabled many in the community to expand community connections and their professional networks.&nbsp;</p> <p>Fueling new initiatives:&nbsp;</p> <p>Efforts piloted through MSPnet fueled new initiatives which now serve expanded networks and communities. The first is the STEM for All Video Showcase, which was piloted on MSPnet in 2015 and 2016, and allowed projects to share short videos about their projects and to discuss them with their colleagues and the public at large (<ins datetime="2020-01-28T13:53" cite="mailto:Joni%20Falk"><a href="https://stemforall2016.videohall.com/">https://stemforall2016.videohall.com</a></ins>). This effort now continues and involves presenters from over 30 NSF programs and 10 other federal agencies. MSPnet also allowed us to pilot a community for STEM teacher leaders. This effort now continues as the STEM Teacher Leadership Network (<a href="https://stemtlnet.org/">https://stemtlnet.org</a>).&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/28/2020<br>      Modified by: Joni&nbsp;Falk</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1240555/1240555_10217464_1580233242781_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1240555/1240555_10217464_1580233242781_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1: Interlinking Hub and Project Spaces"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1240555/1240555_10217464_1580233242781_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1: Interlinking Hub and Project Spaces"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1: Interlinking Hub and Project Spaces</div> <div class="imageCredit">TERC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joni&nbsp;Falk</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1: Interlinking Hub and Project Spaces</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1240555/1240555_10217464_1580233346364_figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1240555/1240555_10217464_1580233346364_figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2: MSPnet home page"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1240555/1240555_10217464_1580233346364_figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2: MSPnet home page"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2: MSPnet home page</div> <div class="imageCredit">TERC</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joni&nbsp;Falk</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2: MSPnet home page</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Math and Science Partnership Network (http://MSPnet.org) was originally created in 2004 to serve multiple communities affiliated with the National Science Foundation’s Math and Science Partnership Program. The last grant from NSF supporting the development of this project, was received in 2012. The project was actively facilitated until September 2019. Over the years, MSPnet expanded its reach and served state coordinators and evaluators involved in ED’s Math, Science Partnership Program, leaders affiliated with NSF’s STEM+C program, as well as other researchers, K-12 educators and administrators, higher education STEM faculty, and professional developers interested in improving Science, Technology, Engineering, Mathematics and Computer Science teaching and learning. The site provided a resource center and collegial network for those leading efforts to improve Math and Science.    The design of MSPnet was innovative as it provided a central Hub for all projects to learn and share findings, resources, research, challenges, and strategies with each other. In addition, each participating NSF-funded project had its own interactive project space to collaborate with partners, collect research in a project specific library, share files internally, utilize a shared project calendar, and host webinars free of charge. Project spaces also enabled each project to showcase their efforts to the public, as it provided an abstract of the work, links to their publications, and bios of their senior staff. By the end of the project, MSPnet provided interactive project spaces for 274 NSF-funded projects. Material created by each of these projects contributed to the rich collection that was shared in the MSPnet Hub. Almost all of this material was made accessible to the public at large.   Goals:   MSPnet.org created a virtual, electronic, infrastructure for NSF and ED projects to learn with and from each other. The 274 interactive project spaces allowed each participating project to contribute resources to a Central Hub, which were then shared across all projects and with the public at large.  MSPnet.org increased access to research, resources, and tools related to STEM teaching and learning, educational policy, challenging courses and curriculum, institutional change and sustainability, and effective practices of professional development. MSPnet.org provided an archive of the growth and products produced by  the very large NSF MSP program over time. It created a digital library with over 3,000 full-text articles related to STEM education. This collection included 780 publications written by leaders of NSF-funded MSP and STEM+C projects. These articles provide a broad view of the collective impact of these programs on the field.    Activities:  The staff of MSPnet created the architecture and technical development and provided the maintenance and content management for this large on-line infrastructure that successfully supported knowledge-sharing across multiple communities. It created a vast Library that added relevant research each week, a Resources section that shared useful websites and research tools, and a Conference section, which archived each of the program’s annual Learning Network Conferences, by providing abstracts, papers and videos of plenary events.  In addition, it created interactive experiences to engage users, including the MSPnet Academy, which featured interactive webinars offered by leaders in the field, discussions on multiple topics of interest, and monthly blogs. Last, it provided a weekly newsletter to users informing them of new research, resources, and events that were also posted to the site. This was particularly effective in drawing our members back to the site often.  Findings:  The site has had over two million-page views and has served over 460,000 unique users from 215 countries and territories. While 81% of users originated in the US, 19% of users came from 215 countries and territories across the globe. The highest usage internationally came from Canada, China, Brazil, the Philippines, India, the UK, Australia, Germany, South Korea and Turkey.   Evaluation reports found that MSPnet.org provided users with up-to-date research, news and resources related to the broad fields of STEM and computer science education. The library made them aware of, and provided access to newly published findings relevant to their project. It also enabled many in the community to expand community connections and their professional networks.   Fueling new initiatives:   Efforts piloted through MSPnet fueled new initiatives which now serve expanded networks and communities. The first is the STEM for All Video Showcase, which was piloted on MSPnet in 2015 and 2016, and allowed projects to share short videos about their projects and to discuss them with their colleagues and the public at large (https://stemforall2016.videohall.com). This effort now continues and involves presenters from over 30 NSF programs and 10 other federal agencies. MSPnet also allowed us to pilot a community for STEM teacher leaders. This effort now continues as the STEM Teacher Leadership Network (https://stemtlnet.org).                                            Last Modified: 01/28/2020       Submitted by: Joni Falk]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
