<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Thermal Controls on Ecosystem Metabolism and Function:  Scaling from Leaves to Canopies to Regions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>130977.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>130977</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Temperature exerts a primary environmental control on biological systems and processes at a range of scales in space and time. Its influence is fundamental, ranging from controls on the reaction rates of enzymes, ecosystem biogeochemical reactions, and large-scale distributions of plant and animal species. Temperature is also a fundamental characteristic of climate. Indeed, much of the concern about the impact of climate warming is motivated by the pervasive influence of temperature on organisms. Although most focus is usually on air temperature, the skin temperature of an organism, such as a plant, is actually more relevant in many cases. However, until now measurements of organismal temperature using thermal images taken from some distance away have been challenging because of sensor and computational limitations. This research project addresses this gap in understanding through three goals: (1) to assess the use of thermal imaging measurements for ecological and agricultural studies, such as monitoring the response of plant canopies to heat and drought stress; (2) to demonstrate the continuous deployment of robust thermal cameras for continuous canopy imaging for a range of ecosystems; and (3) to develop scaling algorithms to relate sparse measurements at individual canopy sites to the patterns observed at regional scales by sensors on aircraft and satellites. The work will combine temperature observations at a range of spatial resolutions with synthesis activities in an innovative manner. The results will enhance our understanding of how ecosystem structure and function are related to skin temperature patterns. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will introduce new technology and infrastructure for long-term thermal data collection that could have a large impact on our understanding of ecological functioning across multiple scales.  It will combine the diverse interdisciplinary expertise of researchers at different stages in their careers in fields including plant physiology, remote sensing, biogeography, and statistics. Results will directly inform questions concerning the link between leaf temperatures and carbon assimilation by ecosystems and the response of natural and agricultural ecosystems to drought stress. It will address scaling of properties and processes related to temperature, as is required for predicting responses to climate change. Particular focus will be on the responses of ecosystems to drought and heat waves. More tangible outcomes will be advances in understanding of plant-temperature interactions in natural and managed ecosystems, as well as the establishment of canopy thermal imaging equipment at three long-term monitoring sites. Finally, this project will integrate research and teaching through the training of post-doctoral researchers, mentoring of undergraduate students, and development of laboratory modules based on the concepts and data generated by this project for undergraduate and graduate courses in geography, earth science, ecology, and environmental science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1241616</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Richardson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew D Richardson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>andrew.richardson@nau.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9285233049</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000536468</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/14/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University, FAS Org. and Evol. Biology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021382020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[22 Divinity Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7959</Code>
<Text>MacroSysBIO &amp; NEON-Enabled Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7959</Code>
<Text>MACROSYSTEM BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~130977</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Plant canopy temperature is important for understanding how plant growth and productivity is affected by environmental conditions. Canopy temperature can deviate strongly from air temperature and therefore needs to be measured directly, instead of assumed from air temperature. To understand how canopy temperature affects plant responses like evaporative water loss, photosynthesis, leaf development, and flowering, we need to measure plant temperature for many individuals, many times throughout a day, for entire growing seasons. However, making these continuous temperature measurements of many leaves outside of a controlled environment is difficult and rarely done. This project utilized thermal cameras to continuously record images of tree canopies in a forest, and developed the tools necessary to extract temperatures from the images.</p> <p>Our project advances the application of thermal imaging to better understand ecosystem function in remote, automated and unmanned, field settings. In the coming years there will be an enormous amount of interest in ecological applications of thermal imaging. We have learned a tremendous amount about the logistical and practical challenges of trying to maintain a continuous record of thermal imagery at an unattended field site, and we have prepared a manuscript, essentially a primer on thermal imaging for the plant- and ecosystem-science community, for publication in a peer reviewed journal. We are also releasing the software we developed for processing the thermal images and calculating canopy temperature, so that others may take advantage of what we have learned and be able to deploy similar thermal cameras to other field sites.</p> <p>With regards to intellectual merit, we obtained the first multi-year, continuous, dataset of forest canopy temperature derived from high-resolution thermal images. We conducted extensive analyses to characterize the errors and uncertainties associated with calculating temperature from thermal imagery, and developed new software tools to facilitate image processing and analysis. Our analyses focused on comparing temperatures of different parts of the forest canopy at hourly and seasonal timescales and discussed how this information can be paired with additional data to further our knowledge of leaf-level biophysical processes and canopy interactions with the atmosphere and surrounding ecosystem.</p> <p>With regards to broader impacts, this project provided training for one postdoctoral scholar and two undergraduate research assistants. More generally, this project has wide implications for the understanding the biological responses of ecosystems in a warming world.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/03/2015<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;D&nbsp;Richardson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Plant canopy temperature is important for understanding how plant growth and productivity is affected by environmental conditions. Canopy temperature can deviate strongly from air temperature and therefore needs to be measured directly, instead of assumed from air temperature. To understand how canopy temperature affects plant responses like evaporative water loss, photosynthesis, leaf development, and flowering, we need to measure plant temperature for many individuals, many times throughout a day, for entire growing seasons. However, making these continuous temperature measurements of many leaves outside of a controlled environment is difficult and rarely done. This project utilized thermal cameras to continuously record images of tree canopies in a forest, and developed the tools necessary to extract temperatures from the images.  Our project advances the application of thermal imaging to better understand ecosystem function in remote, automated and unmanned, field settings. In the coming years there will be an enormous amount of interest in ecological applications of thermal imaging. We have learned a tremendous amount about the logistical and practical challenges of trying to maintain a continuous record of thermal imagery at an unattended field site, and we have prepared a manuscript, essentially a primer on thermal imaging for the plant- and ecosystem-science community, for publication in a peer reviewed journal. We are also releasing the software we developed for processing the thermal images and calculating canopy temperature, so that others may take advantage of what we have learned and be able to deploy similar thermal cameras to other field sites.  With regards to intellectual merit, we obtained the first multi-year, continuous, dataset of forest canopy temperature derived from high-resolution thermal images. We conducted extensive analyses to characterize the errors and uncertainties associated with calculating temperature from thermal imagery, and developed new software tools to facilitate image processing and analysis. Our analyses focused on comparing temperatures of different parts of the forest canopy at hourly and seasonal timescales and discussed how this information can be paired with additional data to further our knowledge of leaf-level biophysical processes and canopy interactions with the atmosphere and surrounding ecosystem.  With regards to broader impacts, this project provided training for one postdoctoral scholar and two undergraduate research assistants. More generally, this project has wide implications for the understanding the biological responses of ecosystems in a warming world.          Last Modified: 04/03/2015       Submitted by: Andrew D Richardson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
