<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: Future Directions For Formal Methods</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>84725.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>84725</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nina Amla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>namla@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927991</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The past decade has seen tremendous advances in the theory and practice of software verification, and several success stories in the transition of verification techniques from the research lab to development tools. However, despite these advances, much work remains in several directions. These include determining the best ways to applying these advances to broader, higher-level issues like reliability, and privacy in new domains like cyber-physical systems and medicine; in finding the best ways to reach out to practitioners, and to train engineers to use formal methods principles, methodologies and tools; and in finding ways for to multiply the effectiveness of researchers through the use of shared platforms and infrastructure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this workshop is to identify the future directions in research in formal methods and its transition to industrial practice. The workshop will bring together researchers from academia, industry, and government research labs working in the area of formal methods and verification, and identify primary challenges in the field, both foundational, infrastructural, and in transitioning ideas from research labs to developer tools.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1242686</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ranjit</FirstName>
<LastName>Jhala</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ranjit Jhala</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhala@cs.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585341420</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486287</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930404</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7944</Code>
<Text>SOFTWARE ENG &amp; FORMAL METHODS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~84725</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Thus, in December 2012 the National Science Foundation sponsored a workshop&nbsp;that brought together formal methods researchers and practitioners to takestock of the situtation, identify successes, the obstacles towards broaderadoption, and to chart future directions for formal methods and its effectivetransition to practice. &nbsp;The workshop brought together researchers from academia, industrial researchlaboratories, and government organizations, as well as practitioners from&nbsp;formal methods based tool vendors.</p> <p>The goal of the workshop was to reflect upon the most effective ways&nbsp;for the formal methods community to influence the computing revolution.&nbsp;To this end,&nbsp;<span style="font-size: 12px; line-height: 17px;">we structured the workshop along four (related) focus areas.</span></p> <p><br />Infrastructure &amp; Community Synergies: As the field develops, it is increasingly harder for researchers to makeprogress working in isolation. Building large scale verification tools requiresa lot of effort in developing scalable infrastructure. Often, much of the effortis duplicated across projects. &nbsp;The goal of this area was to identifycommunity synergies, for example, in defining standard intermediate formats.</p> <p><br />Education &amp; Outreach: A major stumbling block to the adoption of formal methods is often lack ofexpertise in the workforce. If formal methods are to be broadly adopted, theymust be accessible to all engineers, not only specially trained Ph.D.&rsquo;s.&nbsp;The purpose of this direction is to recommend education and outreach&nbsp;activities that will lower the bar to the adoption of new techniques,&nbsp;as well as inform tool developers about the usability requirements of&nbsp;developers and quality assurance engineers. &nbsp;</p> <p><br />Roadmap to Adoption The goal of this area was to identify effective ways of transitioning researchtools to industrial practice. Adoption requires better scalability andeffectiveness of the tools, demonstrating effectiveness, and better usability ofthe tools.</p> <p><br />Frontiers &amp; New Challenge Domains: The rapid spread of computing machinery through a variety of critical domainshas necessitated the development of specialized techniques that ensure thereliability and correctness of the software used in those domains. &nbsp;The purpose of this focus area was to identify the new domains where&nbsp;rigorous guarantees are required and which are ripe for current- or&nbsp;next-generation formal methods and tools.</p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px; line-height: 17px;">The workshop led to a report, which summarize the discussions from the four areas, in each case,identifying successes, obstacles and promising thrusts for future work. With a strong, co-ordinated and strategically chosen pushes we can significantlyinfluence all these trends for the better, allowing society to continue to reapbenefits from computing technology, while helping to build a foundation for asafer, more secure and more dependable future.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/26/2013<br>      Modified by: Ranjit&nbsp;Jhala</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Thus, in December 2012 the National Science Foundation sponsored a workshop that brought together formal methods researchers and practitioners to takestock of the situtation, identify successes, the obstacles towards broaderadoption, and to chart future directions for formal methods and its effectivetransition to practice.  The workshop brought together researchers from academia, industrial researchlaboratories, and government organizations, as well as practitioners from formal methods based tool vendors.  The goal of the workshop was to reflect upon the most effective ways for the formal methods community to influence the computing revolution. To this end, we structured the workshop along four (related) focus areas.   Infrastructure &amp; Community Synergies: As the field develops, it is increasingly harder for researchers to makeprogress working in isolation. Building large scale verification tools requiresa lot of effort in developing scalable infrastructure. Often, much of the effortis duplicated across projects.  The goal of this area was to identifycommunity synergies, for example, in defining standard intermediate formats.   Education &amp; Outreach: A major stumbling block to the adoption of formal methods is often lack ofexpertise in the workforce. If formal methods are to be broadly adopted, theymust be accessible to all engineers, not only specially trained Ph.D.Æs. The purpose of this direction is to recommend education and outreach activities that will lower the bar to the adoption of new techniques, as well as inform tool developers about the usability requirements of developers and quality assurance engineers.     Roadmap to Adoption The goal of this area was to identify effective ways of transitioning researchtools to industrial practice. Adoption requires better scalability andeffectiveness of the tools, demonstrating effectiveness, and better usability ofthe tools.   Frontiers &amp; New Challenge Domains: The rapid spread of computing machinery through a variety of critical domainshas necessitated the development of specialized techniques that ensure thereliability and correctness of the software used in those domains.  The purpose of this focus area was to identify the new domains where rigorous guarantees are required and which are ripe for current- or next-generation formal methods and tools.  The workshop led to a report, which summarize the discussions from the four areas, in each case,identifying successes, obstacles and promising thrusts for future work. With a strong, co-ordinated and strategically chosen pushes we can significantlyinfluence all these trends for the better, allowing society to continue to reapbenefits from computing technology, while helping to build a foundation for asafer, more secure and more dependable future.             Last Modified: 11/26/2013       Submitted by: Ranjit Jhala]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
