<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Easy to use clickable linker technology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is to determine the commercial value of the fluorogenic linker technology. The fluorogenic linker is defined by two functional groups that are initially non-fluorogenic chemical handles which specifically react with each other to form a fluorescent linkage. These chemical handles are readily incorporated in polymers, small molecules, proteins, nucleic acids, and other biomolecules. The result is a conjugation approach that allows for non-destructive, highly sensitive reaction monitoring, which will be necessary in screening reaction conditions, optimizing conjugations between two molecules, and determining conjugation efficiencies. The proposed project is to assess the value of a fluorogenic linker technology that provides a well defined procedure that guides any researcher with little knowledge in chemistry to link two different molecules together, and then verify the linkage through fluorescence. The procedure will not require extensive purification for downstream applications, provide higher sensitivity in determining conjugation efficiency, and shorten processing time for potential use in high throughput systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Linking two different molecules has a significant role in development of therapeutic agents and materials development. For instance, linking a disease homing signal and a therapeutic drug can yield tissue specific delivery to avoid side-effects by reducing administered drug concentrations, and increasing targeted drug delivery. Such uses are common for many biopharmaceutical and biotech companies that rely on developing new protein-based therapeutics. The proposed project provides a practical approach to monitor these linkages in a highly sensitive manner. The result will have the potential to streamline discovery process, provide more effective drug conjugates for tissue specific delivery, and reduce exposure to harmful organic solvents that can cause both medical and environmental damages.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1242237</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Qian</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Qian Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wang@mail.chem.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8037778436</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486091</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University South Carolina Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 Hampton Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 414]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>111310249</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTH CAROLINA RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Carolina]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbia</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[631 Sumter Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Major goals for this NSF Innovation Corps listed in the application were 1)identification of customers/industries that utilize the patented technology, <span><span>fluorogenic</span></span> linker; 2) a spin-off company with a website that highlights the technology and; 3) expanded product lines either as a kit or a stand-alone product. The final verdict was to pursue the commercialization of the technology.</p> <p>With the support of the NSF I-Corps award, we have successfully achieved (if not exceeded) all our goals. We have been able to performed hundreds interviews with potential customers and identified a few key potential customers/industries that utilize the patented technology, <span><span>fluorogenic</span></span> linker. In addition, a spin-off company &ndash; A&amp;Q <span><span>Nanodesigns</span></span> &ndash; was established.</p> <p>The patent license resulted in three products were launched under the trademark, <span><span>iON</span></span>-Linker, in April 2013. The startup also continues to conduct direct sales through its web portal at <a href="http://www.aqnano.com"><span><span>www</span></span>.<span><span>aqnano</span></span>.com</a>.&nbsp;The PI and co-PI of the proposal are working on further pursuing commercialization of related technologies.</p> <p>In addition, A&amp;Q <span><span>Nano</span></span> has merged apart of its technology with a local small business to tackle other issues unrelated to the initial proposal, but the new venture stems from the interviews conducted during the NSF I-Corps program. For this new venture, the founders and angel investors are committing over $300K to start a new company, <span><span>IMCS</span></span>, <span><span>LLC</span></span>. Products were launched in 2013.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/03/2014<br>      Modified by: Qian&nbsp;Wang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Major goals for this NSF Innovation Corps listed in the application were 1)identification of customers/industries that utilize the patented technology, fluorogenic linker; 2) a spin-off company with a website that highlights the technology and; 3) expanded product lines either as a kit or a stand-alone product. The final verdict was to pursue the commercialization of the technology.  With the support of the NSF I-Corps award, we have successfully achieved (if not exceeded) all our goals. We have been able to performed hundreds interviews with potential customers and identified a few key potential customers/industries that utilize the patented technology, fluorogenic linker. In addition, a spin-off company &ndash; A&amp;Q Nanodesigns &ndash; was established.  The patent license resulted in three products were launched under the trademark, iON-Linker, in April 2013. The startup also continues to conduct direct sales through its web portal at www.aqnano.com. The PI and co-PI of the proposal are working on further pursuing commercialization of related technologies.  In addition, A&amp;Q Nano has merged apart of its technology with a local small business to tackle other issues unrelated to the initial proposal, but the new venture stems from the interviews conducted during the NSF I-Corps program. For this new venture, the founders and angel investors are committing over $300K to start a new company, IMCS, LLC. Products were launched in 2013.          Last Modified: 02/03/2014       Submitted by: Qian Wang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
