<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>U.S.-Brazil Frontiers of Science and Engineering Symposium</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>183592.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>183592</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonia Ortega</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sortega@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925198</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will help to support the first U.S.-Brazil Frontiers of Science and Engineering Symposium (USBFOS&amp;E) organized by the National Academy of Science (NAS) and the National Academy of Engineering (NAE), respectively, in partnership with the National Academy of Sciences of Brazil.  The symposium, to be held in Brazil in early 2014, is designed to facilitate exchange and collaboration across scientific and engineering disciplines and to enhance networks among early-career scientists and engineers.  This would be the first bilateral Frontiers meeting involving both young scientists and engineers at the same meeting, and will also be the first to be held in Latin America. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;About 60-70 outstanding early-career scientists and engineers from the United States and Brazil (30-35 from each side) are expected to participate and attend this symposium.  A program organizing committee, led by co-chairs from the U.S. and Brazil and consisting of additional members, will identify topics and speakers.  The symposium format will include formal sessions with presentations by speakers on leading edge research, emerging technologies, and with multiple opportunities for informal interactions across science and engineering fields.  Similar symposia in other regions have fostered interdisciplinary and international collaborations, and have served as a reference point for many of the emerging frontiers in research and innovation in the U.S.  Presentations from the USBFOS&amp;E will be posted on the NAS and NAE-FOE web sites.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1242920</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Hunziker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet R Hunziker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhunzike@nae.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023341571</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000390009</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
<LastName>Patte</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edward R Patte</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>epatte@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023342254</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000619499</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 Fifth Street, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7299</Code>
<Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5913</Code>
<Text>BRAZIL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5977</Code>
<Text>AMERICAS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7299</Code>
<Text>INTERNATIONAL PLAN &amp; WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~183592</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Kavli Frontiers of Science (KFOS) and the Frontiers of Engineering (FOE) programs were started by the National Academy of Sciences and the National Academy of Engineering, respectively, to facilitate exchange and collaboration across scientific and engineering disciplines and to enhance networks among early-career scientists and engineers.&nbsp;This&nbsp;activity ultimately advances innovation and the US research enterprise.&nbsp;In addition to the annual KFOS and FOE symposia involving US-based attendees, there are KFOS programs with Germany, Japan, China, India, Indonesia, South Korea, and Israel; and FOE programs with Germany, Japan, India, China, and the European Union. The symposia are designed to bring together a select group of scientists and engineers (ages 30-45) from academia, industry, and government labs to discuss pioneering scientific and engineering research and leading-edge technical work in various scientific and engineering fields and industry sectors. The goal of the symposia is to promote an interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge and methodology that could lead to collaborative networks of scientists and engineers within the United States and between scientists and engineers from the United States and partnering countries. These same goals apply to the Brazil-US Frontiers of Science and Engineering symposium.&nbsp;</p> <p>The&nbsp;Brazil-US Frontiers of Science and Engineering Symposium was held&nbsp; March 17-19, 2014, in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. There were 60 attendees, excluding staff and guests.&nbsp;Brazilian and US scientists and engineers gave presentations on four&nbsp;topics:&nbsp;1) Bioengineering and Public Health: Biomedical Materials and Devices for Bridging the Biotic-Abiotic Interface, 2) Precision Nanotech: The Next Generation of Nanoengineering and Nanomaterials, 3) Biofuels, and 4)&nbsp;Sustainability and Resilient Cities: Challenges and Opportunities. In addition, there were poster sessions and numerous networking activities. Videos of the presentations are posted on the symposium homepage at <a href="http://www.nasonline.org/busfose14">www.nasonline.org/busfose14</a>.</p> <p>Outcomes described in the evaluation form:</p> <p>Rated good or excellent<br />Meeting format&nbsp; 100%<br />Choice of topics&nbsp; 100%<br />Quality of presentations&nbsp; 100%<br />Level of science/engineering covered&nbsp; 100%<br />Flash poster talks&nbsp; 100%<br />Your opportunity to participate&nbsp; 98%<br />Communication prior to the symposium&nbsp; 90%<br />Meeting materials&nbsp; 97%<br /><br />Range of session topics ranked "about right" vs. too broad or too narrow&nbsp; 92%</p> <p>Did you gain anything useful to your own work and research from: (answered yes or possibly)<br />Presentations and discussion in your discipline&nbsp; 95%<br />Presentations and discussion in other disciplines&nbsp; 95%<br />Informal discussions with those in your discipline&nbsp; 100%<br />Informal discussions with those in other disciplines&nbsp; 95%<br />Poster sessions&nbsp; 95%</p> <p>Rate the symposium's value in the following areas: (answered extremely valuable or valuable)<br />Establishing contacts for your research or professional development&nbsp; 90%<br />Expanding your scientific or engineering perspective by exposure to ideas related to fields other than your own&nbsp; 97%<br />Reviewing new ideas or providing inspiration application to your future research&nbsp; 100%<br />Background materials (agenda book, etc.) in preparation for this symposium&nbsp; 82%</p> <p>Have you identified potential collaborative opporutnities as a result of this symposium?&nbsp; 92% answered yes or possibly<br /><br />Have you identified potential applications of interdisciplinary approaches, tools, and/or analytical methods to your research activities?&nbsp; 92% answered yes or possibly</p> <p>How do you rate the usefulness of this symposium to your professional develo...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Kavli Frontiers of Science (KFOS) and the Frontiers of Engineering (FOE) programs were started by the National Academy of Sciences and the National Academy of Engineering, respectively, to facilitate exchange and collaboration across scientific and engineering disciplines and to enhance networks among early-career scientists and engineers. This activity ultimately advances innovation and the US research enterprise. In addition to the annual KFOS and FOE symposia involving US-based attendees, there are KFOS programs with Germany, Japan, China, India, Indonesia, South Korea, and Israel; and FOE programs with Germany, Japan, India, China, and the European Union. The symposia are designed to bring together a select group of scientists and engineers (ages 30-45) from academia, industry, and government labs to discuss pioneering scientific and engineering research and leading-edge technical work in various scientific and engineering fields and industry sectors. The goal of the symposia is to promote an interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge and methodology that could lead to collaborative networks of scientists and engineers within the United States and between scientists and engineers from the United States and partnering countries. These same goals apply to the Brazil-US Frontiers of Science and Engineering symposium.   The Brazil-US Frontiers of Science and Engineering Symposium was held  March 17-19, 2014, in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. There were 60 attendees, excluding staff and guests. Brazilian and US scientists and engineers gave presentations on four topics: 1) Bioengineering and Public Health: Biomedical Materials and Devices for Bridging the Biotic-Abiotic Interface, 2) Precision Nanotech: The Next Generation of Nanoengineering and Nanomaterials, 3) Biofuels, and 4) Sustainability and Resilient Cities: Challenges and Opportunities. In addition, there were poster sessions and numerous networking activities. Videos of the presentations are posted on the symposium homepage at www.nasonline.org/busfose14.  Outcomes described in the evaluation form:  Rated good or excellent Meeting format  100% Choice of topics  100% Quality of presentations  100% Level of science/engineering covered  100% Flash poster talks  100% Your opportunity to participate  98% Communication prior to the symposium  90% Meeting materials  97%  Range of session topics ranked "about right" vs. too broad or too narrow  92%  Did you gain anything useful to your own work and research from: (answered yes or possibly) Presentations and discussion in your discipline  95% Presentations and discussion in other disciplines  95% Informal discussions with those in your discipline  100% Informal discussions with those in other disciplines  95% Poster sessions  95%  Rate the symposium's value in the following areas: (answered extremely valuable or valuable) Establishing contacts for your research or professional development  90% Expanding your scientific or engineering perspective by exposure to ideas related to fields other than your own  97% Reviewing new ideas or providing inspiration application to your future research  100% Background materials (agenda book, etc.) in preparation for this symposium  82%  Have you identified potential collaborative opporutnities as a result of this symposium?  92% answered yes or possibly  Have you identified potential applications of interdisciplinary approaches, tools, and/or analytical methods to your research activities?  92% answered yes or possibly  How do you rate the usefulness of this symposium to your professional development relative to other meetings you have recently attended. 100% answered very useful or useful  Based on your experience at this meeting, would you attend another Frontierssymposium?  Yes 100%  Comments:  "I really enjoyed this meeting. It really expanded my science horizons and got my wheels turning in some different directions. I also made good connections that I never would have otherwise."  "I was u...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
