<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>LTREB Renewal: Fourteen years of simulated climate change in an ancient limestone grassland: connecting responses of genotypes, species, and ecosystems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>447327.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>454827</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Betsy Von Holle</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mvonholl@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924974</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project, researchers seek to understand the long-term impacts of climate change on grassland ecosystems.  They use multi-decadal simulation experiments of warmed soil and air temperatures and of summer drought or elevated rainfall to identify how well the characteristics of different plant species predict how communities and ecosystem processes will shift in coming decades.  This project also extends research on climate change impacts to the genetic level; recent evidence indicates that some ecosystems may be resistant to climate change because some species can adapt rapidly to new environments. Results to date show that individual species respond over small spatial scales and that these changes may be adaptive.  Over the next five years of a ten year project, the researchers will provide long-term data that reveal the details that underlie an apparent stability of plant community structure in response to climate change. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Temperate grasslands are a key contributor to global productivity and their response to global climate change is of critical importance to the future of human welfare.  While fertile grasslands show rapid vegetation shifts in response to simulated warming, those on less fertile soils that contain slower-growing species appear more resistant to rapid climate change.  Because the latter grasslands account for a large majority of pasture- and range-lands throughout the world, their recalcitrance to climate shifts will have significant ramifications for the future of food and fiber production.  The Buxton research site has garnered considerable media attention and will continue to increase community awareness of climate change research through visits from the interested public, now facilitated by a partnership with the Ecological Continuity Trust. The dataset accumulated annually from this study is currently available online to other researchers. Continued involvement and mentoring of undergraduate and graduate students of broad racial and ethnic representation from different nations provides valuable opportunities for education and advances international communication in climate change science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1242529</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Fridley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason D Fridley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fridley@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154433098</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000396593</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[211 Lyman Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1196</Code>
<Text>LONG-TERM RSCH IN ENVIR BIO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1196</Code>
<Text>LONG-TERM RSCH IN ENVIR BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~89615</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~89202</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~268510</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~7500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>North-temperate grasslands contribute significantly to global productivity and human welfare, and their response to climate change is a major concern of the international scientific community. Unlike other grasslands in more fertile or colder regions, these systems respond slowly to climate forcing due to the slow growth and long lifespan of component species. Understanding the response of these communities to climate change therefore requires experimentation over multiple decades to capture critical shifts in system behavior. This grant supported the Buxton Climate Change Study in northern England from its 20<sup>th</sup> to its 25<sup>th</sup> year of manipulation of winter warming, summer drought, and enhanced rainfall. It is not only among the longest continuously running &lsquo;laboratories&rsquo; of grassland function in response to altered climate in the world, but a nexus of researchers from several countries working to understand linkages between plants, soil, and climate.</p> <p>Over the grant period several new scientific discoveries were made. First, certain aspects of the vegetation provide a buffer against climate impacts; chief among these is the genetic diversity of dominant plant groups that have allowed some species to evolve rapidly in response to changing climate, and particularly drought. We showed that part of the reason such diversity exists in the first place is local variation in site conditions: such heterogeneity creates a local pool of different genotypes that are able to respond in different ways to water availability (e.g., shallow versus deep soils). Second, the idea that climate is unlikely to change the function of infertile ecosystems&mdash;in this case very low soil phosphorus availability&mdash;is false, because a climate shift that alters a plant&rsquo;s energy budget (e.g., the duration of the growing season) also impacts its ability to tolerate nutrient limitation. In other words, as the growing season of north-temperate ecosystems increases with warming, plants have more energy to allocate to nutrient foraging, including soil microbial relationships. Third, there is strong evidence that the soil microbial communities themselves are changing, and those communities are likely to impact the nature of energy-nutrient exchanges in ways that change grassland productivity and stability. Finally, we also determined that a warmer, drier future climate is likely to increase grassland susceptibility to invasive species. Some of these species (e.g., heath brome) are productive but not favored by sheep or cattle, thereby creating a situation where grassland biomass may increase but not in a way conducive to livestock production.</p> <p>This grant also provided for the training of undergraduate and graduate students from several countries, and facilitated international knowledge transfer across laboratories in the U.S., UK, Switzerland, and The Netherlands. The project garnered media attention and helped to promote community awareness of climate change research through visits from the interested public and scientific community, in part via a partnership with the Ecological Continuity Trust. The dataset collected is available online to the scientific research community. Finally, the scientific advances and outreach opportunities generated by this grant helped secure continued support for the long-term experiment by a UK steering committee to ensure the study remains a nexus for international collaboration, and one of the only long-term experimental resources for predicting the future of north-temperate grassland function with continued climate change.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/13/2018<br>      Modified by: Jason&nbsp;D&nbsp;Fridley</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1242529/1242529_10195498_1515871618189_fig1_askew--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1242529/1242529_10195498_1515871618189_fig1_askew--rgov-800width.jpg" title="BCCIL"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1242529/1242529_10195498_1515871618189_fig1_askew--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="BCCIL"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Buxton Climate Change Impacts Experiment, on a steep daleside in Derbyshire, England, UK. The study, established in 1993, is one of the longest continuous manipulations of grassland climate in the world.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Andrew Askew</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jason&nbsp;D&nbsp;Fridley</div> <div class="imageTitle">BCCIL</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ North-temperate grasslands contribute significantly to global productivity and human welfare, and their response to climate change is a major concern of the international scientific community. Unlike other grasslands in more fertile or colder regions, these systems respond slowly to climate forcing due to the slow growth and long lifespan of component species. Understanding the response of these communities to climate change therefore requires experimentation over multiple decades to capture critical shifts in system behavior. This grant supported the Buxton Climate Change Study in northern England from its 20th to its 25th year of manipulation of winter warming, summer drought, and enhanced rainfall. It is not only among the longest continuously running ?laboratories? of grassland function in response to altered climate in the world, but a nexus of researchers from several countries working to understand linkages between plants, soil, and climate.  Over the grant period several new scientific discoveries were made. First, certain aspects of the vegetation provide a buffer against climate impacts; chief among these is the genetic diversity of dominant plant groups that have allowed some species to evolve rapidly in response to changing climate, and particularly drought. We showed that part of the reason such diversity exists in the first place is local variation in site conditions: such heterogeneity creates a local pool of different genotypes that are able to respond in different ways to water availability (e.g., shallow versus deep soils). Second, the idea that climate is unlikely to change the function of infertile ecosystems&mdash;in this case very low soil phosphorus availability&mdash;is false, because a climate shift that alters a plant?s energy budget (e.g., the duration of the growing season) also impacts its ability to tolerate nutrient limitation. In other words, as the growing season of north-temperate ecosystems increases with warming, plants have more energy to allocate to nutrient foraging, including soil microbial relationships. Third, there is strong evidence that the soil microbial communities themselves are changing, and those communities are likely to impact the nature of energy-nutrient exchanges in ways that change grassland productivity and stability. Finally, we also determined that a warmer, drier future climate is likely to increase grassland susceptibility to invasive species. Some of these species (e.g., heath brome) are productive but not favored by sheep or cattle, thereby creating a situation where grassland biomass may increase but not in a way conducive to livestock production.  This grant also provided for the training of undergraduate and graduate students from several countries, and facilitated international knowledge transfer across laboratories in the U.S., UK, Switzerland, and The Netherlands. The project garnered media attention and helped to promote community awareness of climate change research through visits from the interested public and scientific community, in part via a partnership with the Ecological Continuity Trust. The dataset collected is available online to the scientific research community. Finally, the scientific advances and outreach opportunities generated by this grant helped secure continued support for the long-term experiment by a UK steering committee to ensure the study remains a nexus for international collaboration, and one of the only long-term experimental resources for predicting the future of north-temperate grassland function with continued climate change.          Last Modified: 01/13/2018       Submitted by: Jason D Fridley]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
