<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Efficient Methods for Characterizing Large-Scale Network Dynamics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Many real-world phenomena can be modeled by dynamic networks whose connectivity as well as activity changes over time. Hence, there is a growing interest in elucidating the structure and dynamics of such networks. Existing approaches to this problem focus mainly on utilizing either coarse network properties or global structural features to comprehend network dynamics. Such methods often rely on extensions of network features of static networks to understand dynamic networks and fail to capture the rich dynamics of real-world networks. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This exploratory project explores  a hierarchical approach to decomposition of network structure and dynamics that can explain changing dynamics at multiple scales ranging from node-level to community-level. The  approach is novel, and because of its untested nature, somewhat risky. The research  is organized around three aims:(i) Develop information-theoretic flow based approaches that can extract multiple layers of dynamics by simultaneously optimizing for explicit community structures and partial flow dynamics in complex networks. (ii) Develop a computational framework for dynamics-aware network summarization that preserves the flow dynamics of graphs and provides a summary of the large-scale graph dynamics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project  advances the current state-of-the-art in network data analytics. The resulting tools for elucidating the structure and dynamics of complex networks at multiple scales could potentially transform the way we understand, design, engineer, and control complex networks. The project enriches research-based training and outreach activities at Wayne State University.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1242304</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chandan</FirstName>
<LastName>Reddy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chandan K Reddy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>reddy@cs.vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5718583307</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000084755</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wayne State University</Name>
<CityName>Detroit</CityName>
<ZipCode>482023622</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3135772424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5057 Woodward</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[6th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001962224</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WAYNE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001962224</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wayne State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Detroit</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>482023622</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5057 Woodward]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Understanding temporal dynamics in large-scale and complex data is a challenging yet rewarding problem. A complete and thorough recognition of the value of dynamical behavior of temporal data can provide deeper insights on the underlying characteristics of the domain and the data. In this project, the team has developed novel methods for understanding the commonalities and differences of multiple groups of documents collected at different time points. This is useful in understanding temporal document collections. To address such needs, we developed a novel topic modeling method based on joint nonnegative matrix factorization, which simultaneously discovers common as well as discriminative topics given multiple document sets.</p> <p>Another contribution of this project is in the topic of the effect of twitter dynamics in crowdfunding environment. Crowdfunding has gained widespread popularity in recent years. Despite the huge success of the crowdfunding platforms, not every project is successful in reaching its funding goal. We studied the dynamics of a crowdfunding platform and the impact of social networks on this platform. Contrary to previous studies, our analysis is not restricted to project-based features alone; instead, we expand the features into four different categories: temporal traits, personal traits, geo-location traits, and network traits. Based on the insights gained from the data, we developed a supervised learning framework to learn a model that can recommend a set of investors to Kickstarter projects. By utilizing features from the initial days of project duration alone, we showed that our results are significantly better than the previous studies.</p> <p>The third contribution of the project is in the topic of survival regression in the context of handling time-to-event data. Time-to-event outcomes based data can be modelled using survival regression methods which can predict these outcomes in different applications in diverse fields such as engineering, economics and healthcare. However, the event of interest may not always be observed during the study period due to time limitations or losing data traces. This phenomenon is known as censoring and makes survival analysis different from and more challenging than standard regression. Active learning from censored data using survival regression methods will enable model to be queried by a domain expert for the time-to-event label of the sampled instances. This offers greater advantages in the domains such as healthcare where a domain expert (clinician) can interactively refine the model with his feedback. With this motivation, we addressed this problem by providing an active learning based survival model which uses a novel model discriminative gradient based sampling scheme.</p> <p>In addition, this project also develops the "Data Miner: An Educational Tool" to teach students the basics of Data mining concepts in a simplified manner along with their real world applications for high school kids. This tool describes six data mining modules such that Recommender System, Cluster Analysis, Classification, Association Analysis, PageRank and Social Networks. This was a toolkit was used for giving demos for the kids. The tool is accessible at http://datamining.cs.wayne.edu:8080/DataMiner/</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2015<br>      Modified by: Chandan&nbsp;Reddy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/PO...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Understanding temporal dynamics in large-scale and complex data is a challenging yet rewarding problem. A complete and thorough recognition of the value of dynamical behavior of temporal data can provide deeper insights on the underlying characteristics of the domain and the data. In this project, the team has developed novel methods for understanding the commonalities and differences of multiple groups of documents collected at different time points. This is useful in understanding temporal document collections. To address such needs, we developed a novel topic modeling method based on joint nonnegative matrix factorization, which simultaneously discovers common as well as discriminative topics given multiple document sets.  Another contribution of this project is in the topic of the effect of twitter dynamics in crowdfunding environment. Crowdfunding has gained widespread popularity in recent years. Despite the huge success of the crowdfunding platforms, not every project is successful in reaching its funding goal. We studied the dynamics of a crowdfunding platform and the impact of social networks on this platform. Contrary to previous studies, our analysis is not restricted to project-based features alone; instead, we expand the features into four different categories: temporal traits, personal traits, geo-location traits, and network traits. Based on the insights gained from the data, we developed a supervised learning framework to learn a model that can recommend a set of investors to Kickstarter projects. By utilizing features from the initial days of project duration alone, we showed that our results are significantly better than the previous studies.  The third contribution of the project is in the topic of survival regression in the context of handling time-to-event data. Time-to-event outcomes based data can be modelled using survival regression methods which can predict these outcomes in different applications in diverse fields such as engineering, economics and healthcare. However, the event of interest may not always be observed during the study period due to time limitations or losing data traces. This phenomenon is known as censoring and makes survival analysis different from and more challenging than standard regression. Active learning from censored data using survival regression methods will enable model to be queried by a domain expert for the time-to-event label of the sampled instances. This offers greater advantages in the domains such as healthcare where a domain expert (clinician) can interactively refine the model with his feedback. With this motivation, we addressed this problem by providing an active learning based survival model which uses a novel model discriminative gradient based sampling scheme.  In addition, this project also develops the "Data Miner: An Educational Tool" to teach students the basics of Data mining concepts in a simplified manner along with their real world applications for high school kids. This tool describes six data mining modules such that Recommender System, Cluster Analysis, Classification, Association Analysis, PageRank and Social Networks. This was a toolkit was used for giving demos for the kids. The tool is accessible at http://datamining.cs.wayne.edu:8080/DataMiner/       Last Modified: 10/30/2015       Submitted by: Chandan Reddy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
