<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Higher-Taxon Fidelity: Comparative Taphonomy of Marine Benthic Associations in Holocene Depositional Systems of Coastal North Carolina</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>161263.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>161263</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>H. Richard Lane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Higher-Taxon Fidelity: Comparative Taphonomy of Marine Benthic Associations in Holocene Depositional Systems of Coastal North Carolina &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will compare present-day marine communities with past communities that existed in the same areas prior to the industrial revolution. The past communities will be reconstructed using shellfish remains found abundantly at or around the surface in coastal habitats. Also, the project will assess fossilization potential (probability of preservation) of major types of marine animals, with primary focus on shellfish. Using coastal habitats of the Outer Banks (North Carolina, USA), marine communities will be assessed quantitatively in terms of several major groups of animals important both in commercial and scientific terms. The targeted field area has been selected because of the presence of abundant and diverse marine animals (both live and dead), including benthic mollusks, echinoids, arthropods, annelids, and brachiopods. We will sample multiple sites to carry out quantitative comparisons of living organisms and dead shellfish remains. The project should generate a dataset of ~20,000 specimens representing ~200 samples of living and/or dead organisms.&lt;br/&gt;Two primary goals motivate this study. First goal is to quantify differences between live communities and dead shellfish accumulations in order to provide data that will allow us to interpret more reliably ecological information preserved in the fossil record (shellfish is a dominant type of organisms preserved as fossils). Namely, to develop more rigorous understanding of environmental and ecological changes recorded in the fossil record, it is necessary to determine whether death assemblages can provide meaningful estimates of biodiversity, faunal composition, and other aspects of living communities. Second, a rigorous understanding of long-term ecosystem changes in areas inhabited by present-day shellfish communities is critical for assessing human impacts on marine life. Namely, systematic sampling of extant, ecologically understood, and often economically important shellfish should contribute direct data for assessing human impacts on coastal ecosystems. This, in turn, should result in a more informed evaluation of environmental -- and, ultimately, societal -- consequences of our diverse activities in coastal areas (from industry to tourism) and improved guidelines for developing sustainable approaches to human uses of coastal areas.&lt;br/&gt;This project will offer a venue for training a post-doctoral researcher in integrating disparate data and developing transferable skills in paleontology, marine sciences, and statistical methods. In addition funding has been allocated for undergraduate student internships to be recruited from underrepresented minority groups (with assistance from the on-campus Department of Multicultural Programs and Services). These undergraduates will receive hands-on field experience and will be involved in science educational/outreach activities, which will also allow them to develop competitive portfolios for pursuing graduate education. Numerous undergraduate educational and research opportunities will also be provided by this project, including datasets suitable for developing laboratory exercise in introductory and advanced courses in natural sciences. This proposal will support one female post-doctoral researcher and initiate collaboration between Virginia Tech and Duke University Marine Laboratory. Popular online venues will be used to involve the public in an interactive manner.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1243484</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michal</FirstName>
<LastName>Kowalewski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michal J Kowalewski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mkowalewski@flmnh.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3522731907</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485045</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carrie</FirstName>
<LastName>Tyler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carrie L Tyler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ctyler@flmnh.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523923516</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000638893</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~7403</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~103263</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~50597</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Can death assemblages provide meaningful estimates of diversity, relative abundance &amp; other<strong> </strong>aspects of local communities across multiple higher taxa simultaneously? Although most fossil assemblages consist of multiple higher taxa, we lack a clear understanding of whole assemblage fidelity, i.e., relative taphonomic biases across multiple higher taxa. Studies comparing living communities to death assemblages have been fruitful in assessing biases induced by the fossilization process, &amp; quantifying the expected fidelity of the resulting fossil record. However, these types of analyses are typically restricted to a single taxon, primarily more heavily calcified organisms such as mollusks. In an effort to quantitatively assess taphonomic biases across multiple marine invertebrate groups with variable biomineralization (bivalves, gastropods, echinoids, decapods, &amp; chelicerates) we are targeting the subtidal benthos of coastal North Carolina.</p> <p>Field collections from 55 localities &amp; 221 samples resulted in the identification of 11,248 live individuals, &amp; 94,964 dead individuals, representing 231 species (Figure 1). Our data suggest that taphonomic filters can alter relative abundance of higher taxa. While mollusk-based fidelity analysis provides a powerful tool for assessing anthropogenic changes, other groups with lower fossilization potential, may be less informative or more difficult to interpret in terms of human impacts on ecosystems (Figure 2). In addition to enhancing our understanding of the quality of the fossil record, this project also provides an important reference baseline for conservation biology where the assessment of anthropogenic changes in local ecosystems is essential for reconstructing pristine communities that existed prior to human-induced disturbances.</p> <p>&nbsp;In addition to the main project outcomes described above, these data were also used to examine whether environmental conditions associated with increasing water depth such as temperature, salinity, &amp; nutrients should result in fundamental differences in invertebrate marine communities. Whether depth &amp; its related environmental parameters control faunal composition has previously not been directly tested. If depth is a widespread primary control on community structure, &amp; can be readily inferred from paleontological data, this would have significance for stratigraphic patters of fossil occurrences.</p> <p>We evaluated modern macro-faunal associations of marine invertebrates along an onshore-offshore gradient in North Carolina to determine the relationship between community composition &amp; bathymetry, compare the performance of various ordination techniques, &amp; to evaluate whether differences in resolution between modern &amp; paleontological data reduce the ability of ordinations to effectively capture ecological gradients. Communities do ordinate along an axis that primarily reflects bathymetry &amp; its environmental correlatives, producing analogous results with a variety of ordination techniques (Figure 3 &amp; 4). This relationship was strong using heavily biomineralized taxa, &amp; when excluding mollusks; Ordinations using only mollusks did not perform as well, however, limiting the analysis to robust mollusks improved the clarity of the bathymetric signal (Figure 5).</p> <p>Some types of paleontological data should, therefore, accurately capture bathymetric gradients. In coastal ecosystems of North Carolina, bathymetry appears to be a primary controlling factor. Although it is arguable that individual case studies such as this one can support broader generalizations, these results are promising &amp; consistent with multiple paleontological studies. Fossil communities may provide robust quantitative water depth estimates with applications to paleoecology &amp; stratigraphy.</p> <p>Finally, beta diversity (&beta;) is often ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Can death assemblages provide meaningful estimates of diversity, relative abundance &amp; other aspects of local communities across multiple higher taxa simultaneously? Although most fossil assemblages consist of multiple higher taxa, we lack a clear understanding of whole assemblage fidelity, i.e., relative taphonomic biases across multiple higher taxa. Studies comparing living communities to death assemblages have been fruitful in assessing biases induced by the fossilization process, &amp; quantifying the expected fidelity of the resulting fossil record. However, these types of analyses are typically restricted to a single taxon, primarily more heavily calcified organisms such as mollusks. In an effort to quantitatively assess taphonomic biases across multiple marine invertebrate groups with variable biomineralization (bivalves, gastropods, echinoids, decapods, &amp; chelicerates) we are targeting the subtidal benthos of coastal North Carolina.  Field collections from 55 localities &amp; 221 samples resulted in the identification of 11,248 live individuals, &amp; 94,964 dead individuals, representing 231 species (Figure 1). Our data suggest that taphonomic filters can alter relative abundance of higher taxa. While mollusk-based fidelity analysis provides a powerful tool for assessing anthropogenic changes, other groups with lower fossilization potential, may be less informative or more difficult to interpret in terms of human impacts on ecosystems (Figure 2). In addition to enhancing our understanding of the quality of the fossil record, this project also provides an important reference baseline for conservation biology where the assessment of anthropogenic changes in local ecosystems is essential for reconstructing pristine communities that existed prior to human-induced disturbances.   In addition to the main project outcomes described above, these data were also used to examine whether environmental conditions associated with increasing water depth such as temperature, salinity, &amp; nutrients should result in fundamental differences in invertebrate marine communities. Whether depth &amp; its related environmental parameters control faunal composition has previously not been directly tested. If depth is a widespread primary control on community structure, &amp; can be readily inferred from paleontological data, this would have significance for stratigraphic patters of fossil occurrences.  We evaluated modern macro-faunal associations of marine invertebrates along an onshore-offshore gradient in North Carolina to determine the relationship between community composition &amp; bathymetry, compare the performance of various ordination techniques, &amp; to evaluate whether differences in resolution between modern &amp; paleontological data reduce the ability of ordinations to effectively capture ecological gradients. Communities do ordinate along an axis that primarily reflects bathymetry &amp; its environmental correlatives, producing analogous results with a variety of ordination techniques (Figure 3 &amp; 4). This relationship was strong using heavily biomineralized taxa, &amp; when excluding mollusks; Ordinations using only mollusks did not perform as well, however, limiting the analysis to robust mollusks improved the clarity of the bathymetric signal (Figure 5).  Some types of paleontological data should, therefore, accurately capture bathymetric gradients. In coastal ecosystems of North Carolina, bathymetry appears to be a primary controlling factor. Although it is arguable that individual case studies such as this one can support broader generalizations, these results are promising &amp; consistent with multiple paleontological studies. Fossil communities may provide robust quantitative water depth estimates with applications to paleoecology &amp; stratigraphy.  Finally, beta diversity (&beta;) is often used to explore spatiotemporal components of biodiversity within and across habitats. Although widely used in pale...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
