<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI:   Genetic Analysis of Gurken translational Control in Drosophila</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250720.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250720</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>casonya johnson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual merit: All animals must reproducibly establish their body plan in the face of a constantly changing environment. Gurken is an evolutionarily conserved growth factor that is carefully regulated to establish the anterior / posterior and dorsal / ventral axis during oogenesis in the fruit fly Drosophila melanogaster. This project aims to identify the mechanisms by which the translation of Gurken is regulated by addressing the response of gurken mRNA to two stimuli: Nutrient limitation and DNA-damage. The first goal of the research is to understand how Drosophila maintain robust developmental patterning when confronted with an environment where the availability of nutrients is highly variable. The production of proteins is highly regulated in response to nutrient availability and ensures the efficient utilization of resources. Translation in the cell is globally repressed when nutrients are scarce; however, a small subset of essential proteins escape this repression by employing an alternative mechanism known as IRES-mediated translation. Preliminary work from the PI's lab suggests that the gurken mRNA utilizes this alternative mechanism to maintain the axis patterning when nutrients are limiting. The research will utilize a number of genetic and biochemical approaches to study the activity of the gurken mRNA both in vitro and in vivo. Specifically, the activity of regulatory regions of the gurken mRNA will be probed by joining them to light emitting luciferase reporter genes. This will facilitate the discovery of IRES elements that allow the oocyte to maintain its robust patterning. The second goal of the research is to understand how damage to the genome that occurs during meiosis affects the translation of gurken. Previous research has shown that mutations that interfere with DNA repair inhibit the translation of gurken by an unknown mechanism. Several novel mutations that affect this signaling pathway have been isolated. This project will take a genomic sequencing approach to identify these mutations and shed light on the mechanism(s) that communicates the integrity of the genome to developmental patterning molecules.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The research conducted in this project will engage students in the study of translation regulation at the State University of New York College at Fredonia, a predominantly undergraduate institution. The research will address several pressing questions in the field, as indicated above, while allowing students to be the driving force behind the activities. The students will be intimately involved in the design and execution of the experiments and have the opportunity to present the results of the project at regional and national meetings. The research will directly impact not only the students working in the PI's laboratory, but also students that are enrolled in the core genetics lab and upper level molecular genetics lab courses (approximately 70 students per year). The project will facilitate full-time research experiences for three summer students that will be recruited from Fredonia and/or regional community colleges.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1243951</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Ferguson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott B Ferguson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Scott.Ferguson@fredonia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7166734883</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000540445</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY College at Fredonia</Name>
<CityName>Fredonia</CityName>
<ZipCode>140631127</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166733528</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>280 CentralAve Reed Library 127A</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>152606182</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY College at Fredonia]]></Name>
<CityName>Fredonia</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>140631127</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Central Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~110129</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~67660</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~72931</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intelectual Merit: </strong>Oogenesis is the most energetically demanding activity that female insects perform. The biological imperative of reproduction requires that the mature eggs be produced in a viable state and significant numbers. This is accomplished through carefully regulated translation of proteins to establish a body plan that is preserved throughout development. The Drosophila <em>gurken </em>(<em>grk</em>) gene is essential to egg viability and functions to establish anterior / posterior and dorsal / ventral asymmetries during oogenesis. This occurs through careful regulation of <em>grk </em>RNA localization and translation control. This study demonstrated that <em>grk </em>can be translated by way of an Internal Ribosomal Entry Site (IRES). This atypical translation modality is commonly found in viral RNAs, however an appreciation of its importance in the regulation of cellular RNAs is growing. We believe that this is an evolutionary adaptation that enables the fly to support oogenesis in times where food is less abundant. Under these conditions the fly adapts, as do most cells, by downregulating cannonical translation to save energy. Only those mRNAs that contain an IRES can continue to be translated in such an environment. Because of its central role in oocyte development, <em>grk </em>evolved an IRES to maintain body plan patterning under all conditions. Not having an IRES would perturb the body plan leading to inviable eggs.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong>&nbsp;During the award period, the intellectual merit aims of the grant were addressed using the <span>course</span><span>-based undergraduate research experience (</span><span>CURE</span><span>)</span> model whereby many objectives were incorporated into teaching labs. Specifically it enriched the training of three master&rsquo;s students, 16 undergraduate researchers, 333 Genetics Lab (BIOL 238) students, and 78 Molecular Genetics (BIOL 437) students at SUNY Fredonia. The research students involved in this program have enrolled in some of the premier graduate programs in the US including Cornell University (Ph.D.), UC Berkeley (Ph.D.), SUNY Albany (Ph.D.), and two students at Johns Hopkins (Ph.D.).</p> <p>While the impact on training in the PI&rsquo;s lab is evident based on the student&rsquo;s success following graduation, the wider impact on the research environment at Fredonia is also significant. During the term of the grant, enrollment in the Biology Department has increased from a pre-award average of 208 to a post-award average of 241. Many students and parents cited the research opportunities in lab courses as an important determinant in their decision to attend Fredonia. The freshman to sophomore retention rate of students in the department has also risen from a pre-award average of 64.3% to a post-award average of 79.5%. If the goal of the RUI program is to increase retention and participation of students in the STEM training pipeline, this award has been extremely successful. Fredonia also serves a growing Hispanic and African American population. The summer RUI stipends have been true to the objective of including underrepresented students. We have supported two hispanic students that successfully graduated and obtained positions at Roswell Park Cancer Institute and OmniSeq in Buffalo, NY. In addition, one of two female African-American students from the program earned a Master of Public Health at NYU and the other completed her BS in Biology in the spring 2017.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/29/2018<br>      Modified by: Scott&nbsp;B&nbsp;Ferguson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1243951/1243951_10227969_1524975114729_2016ScottFergusonposter--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1243951/1243951_10227969_1524975114729_2016ScottFergusonposter--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Ferguson NSF RUI Award Poster"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1243951/1243951_10227969_1524975114729_2016ScottFergusonposter--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Ferguson NSF RUI Award Poster"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Ferguson NSF RUI promotional poster.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Charlotte R. Morse and Scott B. Ferguson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Scott&nbsp;B&nbsp;Ferguson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Ferguson NSF RUI Award Poster</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intelectual Merit: Oogenesis is the most energetically demanding activity that female insects perform. The biological imperative of reproduction requires that the mature eggs be produced in a viable state and significant numbers. This is accomplished through carefully regulated translation of proteins to establish a body plan that is preserved throughout development. The Drosophila gurken (grk) gene is essential to egg viability and functions to establish anterior / posterior and dorsal / ventral asymmetries during oogenesis. This occurs through careful regulation of grk RNA localization and translation control. This study demonstrated that grk can be translated by way of an Internal Ribosomal Entry Site (IRES). This atypical translation modality is commonly found in viral RNAs, however an appreciation of its importance in the regulation of cellular RNAs is growing. We believe that this is an evolutionary adaptation that enables the fly to support oogenesis in times where food is less abundant. Under these conditions the fly adapts, as do most cells, by downregulating cannonical translation to save energy. Only those mRNAs that contain an IRES can continue to be translated in such an environment. Because of its central role in oocyte development, grk evolved an IRES to maintain body plan patterning under all conditions. Not having an IRES would perturb the body plan leading to inviable eggs.  Broader Impacts: During the award period, the intellectual merit aims of the grant were addressed using the course-based undergraduate research experience (CURE) model whereby many objectives were incorporated into teaching labs. Specifically it enriched the training of three master?s students, 16 undergraduate researchers, 333 Genetics Lab (BIOL 238) students, and 78 Molecular Genetics (BIOL 437) students at SUNY Fredonia. The research students involved in this program have enrolled in some of the premier graduate programs in the US including Cornell University (Ph.D.), UC Berkeley (Ph.D.), SUNY Albany (Ph.D.), and two students at Johns Hopkins (Ph.D.).  While the impact on training in the PI?s lab is evident based on the student?s success following graduation, the wider impact on the research environment at Fredonia is also significant. During the term of the grant, enrollment in the Biology Department has increased from a pre-award average of 208 to a post-award average of 241. Many students and parents cited the research opportunities in lab courses as an important determinant in their decision to attend Fredonia. The freshman to sophomore retention rate of students in the department has also risen from a pre-award average of 64.3% to a post-award average of 79.5%. If the goal of the RUI program is to increase retention and participation of students in the STEM training pipeline, this award has been extremely successful. Fredonia also serves a growing Hispanic and African American population. The summer RUI stipends have been true to the objective of including underrepresented students. We have supported two hispanic students that successfully graduated and obtained positions at Roswell Park Cancer Institute and OmniSeq in Buffalo, NY. In addition, one of two female African-American students from the program earned a Master of Public Health at NYU and the other completed her BS in Biology in the spring 2017.       Last Modified: 04/29/2018       Submitted by: Scott B Ferguson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
