<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Emerging Research Questions in the Arctic</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Renee Crain</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rcrain@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924482</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal from the National Academy of Sciences is to support a planning and assessment activity by the Polar Research Board (PRB). Selected via standard NRC procedures, an ad hoc committee of 16 members will engage a broader segment of the Arctic research community in an information-gathering workshop. The workshop will assess the current state of research and supporting infrastructure and plan for emerging research questions in the Arctic over the next 10-20 years. The assessment will identify the key scientific questions in different realms of Arctic science, exploring both disciplinary realms (e.g., marine, terrestrial, atmosphere, cryosphere, and social sciences) and cross cutting realms (e.g., integrated systems science and sustainability science). Based on the emerging research questions, the study will also help identify research infrastructure needs (e.g., observation networks, computing and data management, ship requirements, shore facilities, etc.) and collaboration opportunities. The goal is to provide crisp, concise guidance for U.S. Arctic research so that research is targeted on critical scientific and societal questions and conducted as effectively as possible. An opportunity for additional, web-based community input will be offered. Existing community planning documents will be used, but synthesis and findings are the responsibility of the committee.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1243485</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chris</FirstName>
<LastName>Elfring</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chris Elfring</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>celfring@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023343426</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000312462</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 5th Street NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5201</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5202</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RES &amp; POLICY SUPPORT PR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">Once ice-bound, difficult to access, and largely ignored by the rest of the world, the Arctic is now front and center in the midst of many important questions facing the world today. Our daily weather, what we eat, and coastal flooding are all interconnected with the future of the Arctic. What happens in the Arctic also has far-reaching implications around the world. With rapid change unfolding throughout the Arctic, the need for actionable Arctic science has never been greater. A warming climate is reshaping Arctic ecosystems, bringing changes such as the loss of sea ice and glaciers, thawing of permafrost, and changing snow patterns.</p> <p>A 2014 National Research Council (NRC) report, <em>The Arctic in the Anthropocene</em>, reviews research questions previously identified by Arctic researchers, and then highlights the new questions that have emerged in the wake of and expectation of further rapid Arctic change, as well as new capabilities to address them. <em>The Arctic in the Anthropocene</em> identifies both a disciplinary and a cross-cutting research strategy for the next 10 to 20 years, and evaluates infrastructure needs and collaboration opportunities. The climate, biology, and society in the Arctic are changing in rapid, complex, and interactive ways. Understanding the Arctic system has never been more critical; thus, Arctic research has never been more important. This report will be a resource for institutions, funders, policy makers, and students. Written in an engaging style, <em>The Arctic in the Anthropocene</em> paints a picture of one of the last unknown places on this planet, and communicates the excitement and importance of the discoveries and challenges that lie ahead.</p> <p>The report can be found here: <a href="http://dels.nas.edu/Report/Arctic-Anthropocene-Emerging/18726?bname=prb">http://dels.nas.edu/Report/Arctic-Anthropocene-Emerging/18726?bname=prb</a>.</p> <p>The website also includes a listing of key messages, a report in brief, a briefing power point, a short video summary featuring the committee co-chairs (Stephanie Pfirman and Henry Huntington), and a recording of a webinar also given by the committee co-chairs.</p> <p>Overall, the broader impact of the work of the NRC is to ensure that the best possible science is available in the public policy arena. Findings and recommendations in NRC reports help to steer public policy, government programs, and academic institutions. This report could provide a valuable complement to the future planning efforts of Interagency Arctic Research Policy Committee and its individual agencies, and on the roles to be played by state, local and tribal governments, non-governmental organizations, industry, researchers from academia, other stakeholders, and traditional knowledge holders in the Arctic.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2014<br>      Modified by: Chris&nbsp;Elfring</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Once ice-bound, difficult to access, and largely ignored by the rest of the world, the Arctic is now front and center in the midst of many important questions facing the world today. Our daily weather, what we eat, and coastal flooding are all interconnected with the future of the Arctic. What happens in the Arctic also has far-reaching implications around the world. With rapid change unfolding throughout the Arctic, the need for actionable Arctic science has never been greater. A warming climate is reshaping Arctic ecosystems, bringing changes such as the loss of sea ice and glaciers, thawing of permafrost, and changing snow patterns.  A 2014 National Research Council (NRC) report, The Arctic in the Anthropocene, reviews research questions previously identified by Arctic researchers, and then highlights the new questions that have emerged in the wake of and expectation of further rapid Arctic change, as well as new capabilities to address them. The Arctic in the Anthropocene identifies both a disciplinary and a cross-cutting research strategy for the next 10 to 20 years, and evaluates infrastructure needs and collaboration opportunities. The climate, biology, and society in the Arctic are changing in rapid, complex, and interactive ways. Understanding the Arctic system has never been more critical; thus, Arctic research has never been more important. This report will be a resource for institutions, funders, policy makers, and students. Written in an engaging style, The Arctic in the Anthropocene paints a picture of one of the last unknown places on this planet, and communicates the excitement and importance of the discoveries and challenges that lie ahead.  The report can be found here: http://dels.nas.edu/Report/Arctic-Anthropocene-Emerging/18726?bname=prb.  The website also includes a listing of key messages, a report in brief, a briefing power point, a short video summary featuring the committee co-chairs (Stephanie Pfirman and Henry Huntington), and a recording of a webinar also given by the committee co-chairs.  Overall, the broader impact of the work of the NRC is to ensure that the best possible science is available in the public policy arena. Findings and recommendations in NRC reports help to steer public policy, government programs, and academic institutions. This report could provide a valuable complement to the future planning efforts of Interagency Arctic Research Policy Committee and its individual agencies, and on the roles to be played by state, local and tribal governments, non-governmental organizations, industry, researchers from academia, other stakeholders, and traditional knowledge holders in the Arctic.       Last Modified: 10/29/2014       Submitted by: Chris Elfring]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
