<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:   Center for Historical Information and Analysis (CHIA)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>79596.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>79596</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will strengthen the organizational and technical infrastructure of the Center for Historical Information and Analysis (http://chia.pitt.edu), a multi-institutional collaborative of scholars in social, natural, and information sciences structured as a Research Collaborative and a Headquarters. The Research Collaborative links participating institutions that are collecting data on population, climate, and other topics with a crowdsourcing tool to demonstrate the feasibility of building a continuously growing collection of diverse historical data and metadata. The Headquarters assembles and develops knowledge on repository design to develop a repository sufficient to house the incoming data and permit global and interactive analysis. The Center for Historical Information and Analysis?s future plans include expanding its collection and processing of historical data, broadening its community of social and natural science researchers, analyzing historical patterns of global change, and sharing its resources with researchers, policy-makers, teachers and students. CHIA is headquartered at the University of Pittsburgh with participating research groups at Boston University, Harvard University, Michigan State University, and University of California-Merced.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To understand global social patterns as they exist today, it is increasingly clear that we need to understand how they have evolved over recent centuries. The Center for Historical Information and Analysis responds to this need and takes historical analysis into the realm of Big Data. It is expected that the data resources will grow to several terabytes in size. This project will stimulate development of more efficient research collaborations, enabling systematic large-scale consolidation of diverse historical data sources. Once collected and integrated, the data repository and analytical system will allow scholars to address a wider set of questions testing hypotheses about long-term and short-term social change at the global scale and catalyzing an expansion of the evidence base in social sciences. For example, our understanding of important societal issues can advance by linking health to demography and by incorporating climate and health factors into economic studies. Disciplinary theory will advance through interaction among the various scientific fields, so that a global network of social-science researchers will emerge.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1244693</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Gerring</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Gerring</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jgerring@austin.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124715121</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000457139</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[881 Commonwealth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7726</Code>
<Text>Data Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8068</Code>
<Text>Data Infrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~79596</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Major Activities for the CHIA project as a whole (most of which was carried out at the lead campus, U. of Pittsburgh):</p> <p><strong>1.Crowdsourcing.&nbsp;</strong>Programming of the infrastructure, upgrading of the website, extensive testing of the process of ingesting data from remote sources, experimentation with parallel ingest of datasets at Harvard Dataverse Network.</p> <p>2.<strong>Distributed world-historical Archive.</strong>&nbsp;</p> <p>Reliance on newly upgraded Harvard Dataverse 4.0&nbsp; for expanding and upgrading the World-Historical Dataterse, linked from the CHIA website (chia.pitt.edu) to the Harvard Dataverse.</p> <p>3.<strong>Data integration and merging</strong>.</p> <p>Release of Col*Fusion 2.0, the infrastructure for linking and integrating individual datasets into larger groupings.</p> <p>Identification of documentation as a more substantial topic of work with data integration and merging than earlier realized. In response to earlier failures to develop systematic documentation of complex datasets, a two-step procedure was adopted. First, for any file archived on the World-Historical Dataverse, a systematic, 20-item list of entries known as Level 1 Documentation was developed, tested, and applied to all archived files. Level 1 Documentation is presented as the first sheet in the Excel format of each file. Second, Level 2 Documentation was defined as the higher order documentation of space, time, topic and scale to be developed within the CHIA work space.</p> <p>4.<strong>Prototype datasets</strong>.</p> <p>Further development of datasets took place in historical African population, inequality worldwide, and global silver production 1870-1900. Additional prototype datasets developed at Michigan State.</p> <p>5.<strong>Social-science theory</strong>.</p> <p>Matt Drwenski led in theoretical and empirical study of inequality, expanding from various types of economic inequality to address inequalities in health and in social issues. This led at once to cross-disciplinary work in social science and to information-science modeling of large-scale matrices with attention to the modeling of missing data.</p> <p><strong>6. Analysis of archived data.&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Among analyzed data were those on global inequality, especially since the year 2000. At Michigan State, additional work on the mortality due to the 1918 influenza pandemic as measured in India, Ceylon, Indonesia, and Japan.</p> <p>7.<strong>Global data-collection infrastructure</strong>.</p> <p>Collaboration continued with the CHIA Asia Office in Singapore and with CODESRIA in Senegal. The main expansion in global network was the creation of CLARIAH, a large-scale project for development of the digital humanities in the Netherlands, based at the International Institute of Social History. CHIA PI Patrick Manning became one of the five members of the Advisory Board of the &euro; 12 million project, with responsibility for the social-science section of the project.</p> <p><strong>Significant Results:</strong></p> <p><strong>1.Crowdsourcing.&nbsp;</strong>Successful utilization of crowdsourcing ingest infrastructure; addition of ingest capability in the parallel Dataverse Network system. Advance in defining future role of crowd-sourcing in ingest, editing, documentation, and analysis.</p> <p><strong>2.Distributed world-historical Archive.&nbsp;</strong>Further integration of the Poirot server, managed by the Pitt School of Information Science, into project activities; development of its initial links to Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center; further reliance on Harvard Dataverse.</p> <p><strong>3.Data integration and merging.&nbsp;</strong>Improved statement of the needs for initial metadata to facilitate data integration: Level 1 documentation template, Level 2 documentation design.</p> <p>4.<strong>Prototype datasets</strong>. further work with the disease-climate-population dataset and th...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Major Activities for the CHIA project as a whole (most of which was carried out at the lead campus, U. of Pittsburgh):  1.Crowdsourcing. Programming of the infrastructure, upgrading of the website, extensive testing of the process of ingesting data from remote sources, experimentation with parallel ingest of datasets at Harvard Dataverse Network.  2.Distributed world-historical Archive.   Reliance on newly upgraded Harvard Dataverse 4.0  for expanding and upgrading the World-Historical Dataterse, linked from the CHIA website (chia.pitt.edu) to the Harvard Dataverse.  3.Data integration and merging.  Release of Col*Fusion 2.0, the infrastructure for linking and integrating individual datasets into larger groupings.  Identification of documentation as a more substantial topic of work with data integration and merging than earlier realized. In response to earlier failures to develop systematic documentation of complex datasets, a two-step procedure was adopted. First, for any file archived on the World-Historical Dataverse, a systematic, 20-item list of entries known as Level 1 Documentation was developed, tested, and applied to all archived files. Level 1 Documentation is presented as the first sheet in the Excel format of each file. Second, Level 2 Documentation was defined as the higher order documentation of space, time, topic and scale to be developed within the CHIA work space.  4.Prototype datasets.  Further development of datasets took place in historical African population, inequality worldwide, and global silver production 1870-1900. Additional prototype datasets developed at Michigan State.  5.Social-science theory.  Matt Drwenski led in theoretical and empirical study of inequality, expanding from various types of economic inequality to address inequalities in health and in social issues. This led at once to cross-disciplinary work in social science and to information-science modeling of large-scale matrices with attention to the modeling of missing data.  6. Analysis of archived data.   Among analyzed data were those on global inequality, especially since the year 2000. At Michigan State, additional work on the mortality due to the 1918 influenza pandemic as measured in India, Ceylon, Indonesia, and Japan.  7.Global data-collection infrastructure.  Collaboration continued with the CHIA Asia Office in Singapore and with CODESRIA in Senegal. The main expansion in global network was the creation of CLARIAH, a large-scale project for development of the digital humanities in the Netherlands, based at the International Institute of Social History. CHIA PI Patrick Manning became one of the five members of the Advisory Board of the &euro; 12 million project, with responsibility for the social-science section of the project.  Significant Results:  1.Crowdsourcing. Successful utilization of crowdsourcing ingest infrastructure; addition of ingest capability in the parallel Dataverse Network system. Advance in defining future role of crowd-sourcing in ingest, editing, documentation, and analysis.  2.Distributed world-historical Archive. Further integration of the Poirot server, managed by the Pitt School of Information Science, into project activities; development of its initial links to Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center; further reliance on Harvard Dataverse.  3.Data integration and merging. Improved statement of the needs for initial metadata to facilitate data integration: Level 1 documentation template, Level 2 documentation design.  4.Prototype datasets. further work with the disease-climate-population dataset and the 20th-century world dataset (each of roughly 20 MB in size); development of datasets on global silver production (1870-1900), global inequality, and (at Michigan State) 1918 influenza pandemic.    At Boston University:  In addition to aiding in the development of infrastructure, as described above, the team at BU worked on three specific world-historical projects:  1. Demography and Democracy - a look at the re...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
