<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative RUI: Regulation of Flagellar Biogenesis in H. pylori</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>238615.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>238615</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070700</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Larry Halverson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The bacterial flagellum is a complex nanomachine responsible for motility in many species. Assembly requires coordinated control of dozens of genes and involves some of the most sophisticated regulatory mechanisms found in nature. While much has been learned from the paradigm for flagellar gene regulation in studies with Escherichia coli and Salmonella, significant gaps exist in knowledge of how other bacteria regulate biogenesis, including the epsilon-Proteobacteria, members of which have profound agricultural and environmental significance. This collaborative project seeks to better understand the mechanisms Helicobacter pylori and other epsilon-Proteobacteria use to coordinate flagellar gene expression via interactions with proteins involved in export of flagellar components. Two research groups will participate: one at Kennesaw State University and the other at the University of Georgia. The research will provide critical information about how H. pylori coordinates expression of flagellar genes. Results will also inform as to how flagellar and related pathogenic structural assembly occurs in other species. In a broader sense, the results of these studies will provide a valuable framework for gene regulation in H. pylori other epsilon-Proteobacteria and expand the value of prokaryotic genome sequences by characterizing mechanisms of gene regulation in the context of assembly of large scale macromolecular structures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;Kennesaw State University is a large and rapidly growing university that is fast becoming a destination of choice for undergraduates interested in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math (STEM) careers from basic research to high school science teaching. Its researchers are making valuable contributions to a number of fields including microbiology and biochemistry. Among the broader impacts are enhancements in the research environment through collaboration with University of Georgia, broadening of the Kennesaw State University investigator's expertise and knowledge, and exposure of students and faculty to methods they would not otherwise experience. Extensive participation of Kennesaw State University and University of Georgia students, particularly underrepresented minorities, will help train the next generation of scientists. Continued maturation of the research environment and infrastructure will help other researchers address their questions and lay the foundation for future graduate programs. Integration of research into teaching will be accomplished by development of instructional laboratories using methods and experiments arising from the proposed work as well as outreach efforts to improve science education by involving in-service teachers and science education students. Outreach efforts will help to alleviate the critical shortage of secondary science teachers in Georgia through collaboration with Kennesaw State University's Noyce II Master Teaching Fellows and Master of Arts in Teaching programs which will increase teacher recruitment and retention.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1244242</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoover</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy R Hoover</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>TRHOOVER@UGA.EDU</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7065422675</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000205795</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia</Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Tucker Hall Room 409]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>619003127</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>180655748</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306025016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 D.W. Brooks Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~238615</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>Helicobacter pylori</em> is a bacterium that colonizes the stomach of about half the world&rsquo;s population<em>.&nbsp; H. pylori</em> is the causative agent of peptic ulcer disease and is also a major risk factor for gastric cancer and mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue lymphoma. &nbsp;<em>H. pylori</em> cells typically possess one to six flagella located at one of the cell poles that they use for motility.&nbsp; Flagellum-mediated motility is required by <em>H. pylori</em> to colonize the stomach. &nbsp;Understanding the mechanisms that control biosynthesis of <em>H. pylori</em> flagellum is critical for identifying new targets for therapeutics and developing alternative strategies for treatment of <em>H. pylori</em> infections.</p> <p>Biosynthesis of the <em>H. pylori</em> flagellum is a complex process that requires the coordinated and orderly expression of dozens of genes that encode proteins that constitute the flagellum or are involved in the assembly of flagellum.&nbsp; Expression of a subset of these flagellar genes is regulated by the sensor protein FlgS, which controls the activity of the transcriptional activator FlgR.&nbsp; The cellular cue that is sensed by FlgS to activate FlgR and subsequently stimulate transcription is not known.&nbsp; Results from the project showed that FlgS binds with high affinity to FlhA, a component of the flagellar protein export apparatus.&nbsp; Assembly of the export apparatus is one of the earliest events in flagellar biogenesis, and our results suggest that binding of FlgS to FlhA is, at least part of, the signal that turns on expression of the FlgR-dependent genes.&nbsp; Consistent with this hypothesis, mutations that blocked formation of the export apparatus inhibited expression of the FlgR-dependent genes, whereas mutations that prevented formation of the flagellar rod, a step that occurs just after assembly of the export apparatus, resulted in enhanced expression of FlgR-dependent genes.&nbsp; The project generated a collection of <em>H. pylori</em> mutants that make either more or fewer flagella than normal, which were used in studies on how flagella number influence motility.&nbsp; The results of these studies showed that <em>H. pylori</em> cells that have more flagella are more motile in medium that have viscosity similar to that of the gastric mucosa.&nbsp; This observation suggests that <em>H. pylori</em> cells that have multiple flagella are more effective in colonizing the stomach.</p> <p>With regard to broad impacts, the project provided research training for four Ph.D. students and eleven undergraduates.&nbsp; Eight of the undergraduates participated in activities associated with a REU Site in Prokaryotic Biology program that operated from the Microbiology Department at the University of Georgia. &nbsp;Participants in the REU Site activities were exposed to a number of career-enriching activities, including an ethics-in-science workshop that used a case-study approach to provide a framework for identifying and resolving ethical issues as they arise in scientific situations.&nbsp; The REU Site participants also learned how to communicate scientific results effectively in a poster format, presented their research results in a poster session at the end of the program, and went on a field trip to the Centers for Disease Control in Atlanta, Georgia.&nbsp; All of the graduate and undergraduate researchers trained in the project learned about cutting-edge research in microbiology by attending scientific seminars in the Microbiology Department, and in weekly research meetings where the students presented the results of the research on a regular basis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/15/2017<br>      Modified by: Timothy&nbsp;R&nbsp;Hoover</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Helicobacter pylori is a bacterium that colonizes the stomach of about half the world?s population.  H. pylori is the causative agent of peptic ulcer disease and is also a major risk factor for gastric cancer and mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue lymphoma.  H. pylori cells typically possess one to six flagella located at one of the cell poles that they use for motility.  Flagellum-mediated motility is required by H. pylori to colonize the stomach.  Understanding the mechanisms that control biosynthesis of H. pylori flagellum is critical for identifying new targets for therapeutics and developing alternative strategies for treatment of H. pylori infections.  Biosynthesis of the H. pylori flagellum is a complex process that requires the coordinated and orderly expression of dozens of genes that encode proteins that constitute the flagellum or are involved in the assembly of flagellum.  Expression of a subset of these flagellar genes is regulated by the sensor protein FlgS, which controls the activity of the transcriptional activator FlgR.  The cellular cue that is sensed by FlgS to activate FlgR and subsequently stimulate transcription is not known.  Results from the project showed that FlgS binds with high affinity to FlhA, a component of the flagellar protein export apparatus.  Assembly of the export apparatus is one of the earliest events in flagellar biogenesis, and our results suggest that binding of FlgS to FlhA is, at least part of, the signal that turns on expression of the FlgR-dependent genes.  Consistent with this hypothesis, mutations that blocked formation of the export apparatus inhibited expression of the FlgR-dependent genes, whereas mutations that prevented formation of the flagellar rod, a step that occurs just after assembly of the export apparatus, resulted in enhanced expression of FlgR-dependent genes.  The project generated a collection of H. pylori mutants that make either more or fewer flagella than normal, which were used in studies on how flagella number influence motility.  The results of these studies showed that H. pylori cells that have more flagella are more motile in medium that have viscosity similar to that of the gastric mucosa.  This observation suggests that H. pylori cells that have multiple flagella are more effective in colonizing the stomach.  With regard to broad impacts, the project provided research training for four Ph.D. students and eleven undergraduates.  Eight of the undergraduates participated in activities associated with a REU Site in Prokaryotic Biology program that operated from the Microbiology Department at the University of Georgia.  Participants in the REU Site activities were exposed to a number of career-enriching activities, including an ethics-in-science workshop that used a case-study approach to provide a framework for identifying and resolving ethical issues as they arise in scientific situations.  The REU Site participants also learned how to communicate scientific results effectively in a poster format, presented their research results in a poster session at the end of the program, and went on a field trip to the Centers for Disease Control in Atlanta, Georgia.  All of the graduate and undergraduate researchers trained in the project learned about cutting-edge research in microbiology by attending scientific seminars in the Microbiology Department, and in weekly research meetings where the students presented the results of the research on a regular basis.          Last Modified: 08/15/2017       Submitted by: Timothy R Hoover]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
