<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: PFISR Ion-Neutral Observations in the Thermosphere (PINOT)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>94398.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>94398</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020201</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ilia Roussev</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>iroussev@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927436</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This collaborative research effort will study magnetosphere-ionosphere-thermosphere coupling through a coordinated campaign of observations and modeling using the Poker Flat Incoherent-Scatter Radar (PFISR), the Resolute Bay Incoherent-Scatter Radar (RISR), a variety of optical instruments, the Super Dual Auroral Radar Network (SuperDARN), the Homer Very High Frequency (VHF) radar, and the Global Ionospheric-Thermospheric Model (GITM).  The ionosphere, thermosphere, and magnetosphere comprise a tightly coupled system at high latitudes. The ionosphere is the mediating element in this view, facilitating the transfer of free energy generated by solar wind-magnetosphere coupling into heat and bulk motion of the neutral atmosphere. This mediation occurs through electric fields, particle precipitation, diffusion, and field-aligned currents, agents that act collectively to structure the plasma density and composition within the system. Although elements of this system have been studied in considerable detail, their nonlinear interactions, and the global implications of these regional processes, remains poorly understood and inadequately observed. The electronic steering capability of PFISR offers a unique diagnostic to fill this gap. Using a dense grid of beams, a three-dimensional, time dependent view of the ion-neutral interactions can be developed. These results, in coordination with observations by common volume optical, and VHF and HF radar observations, allow access to system dynamics and system responses which were previously unobservable. The experimental campaign, involving twenty researchers from nine institutions, will be carried out over two winter seasons. The results will be used to address fundamental questions of the physics of the upper atmosphere and its coupling to the magnetosphere and the lower atmosphere, which have remained obscured for lack of key data. As a result, although it is understood that small-scale processes play critically important roles in this coupling, they have been difficult to include in quantitative models. The new information will be implemented in the GITM model validating the new understanding of the coupled magnetosphere, ionosphere and thermosphere, and thereby providing enhanced simulation capabilities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1244675</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Semeter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua Semeter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jls@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173583498</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000100994</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022152421</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[8 Saint Mary's St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1521</Code>
<Text>AERONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~30596</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~31443</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~32359</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Between 50 and 500 km altitude lies a region of transition between the neutral atmosphere we experience and the full ionized plasma of the solar wind and magnetosphere.&nbsp; Dynamics in this outer atmospheric region are strongly influenced by interactions between the plasma and neutral gases.&nbsp; This collaborative research project used detailed measurements of this region by ground-based radar and optical methods to investigate the underlying physics at its underlying elemental scales. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Boston University&rsquo;s role in the project concerned the study of impinging beams of plasma particles, and their effects on the neutral and plasma gases in the outer atmosphere.&nbsp; These particle beams are created through the release of magnetic energy stored within Earth&rsquo;s magnetosphere. &nbsp; Auroras (the northern and southern lights) are a dramatic manifestation of these beams, but they lead to important societal consequences as well.&nbsp; These beams interact with existing plasma waves, producing regions of plasma turbulence which, in turn, interact with radio waves, affecting ground-space communications, and degrading the performance of Global Navigation Satellite Systems (GNSS systems) such as GPS. &nbsp; These particle-wave interactions also constitute a heat source for the neutral gas, which enhances satellite drag. &nbsp; The electric currents carried by these particle beams also induce electric currents in long ground-conductors, providing a threat to the stability of power grids.</p> <p>Our approach to studying the physics of beam-atmosphere interactions used a combination of Incoherent Scatter Radars (ISRs), optical imagery of the aurora, and computer simulations of the plasma environment. &nbsp; ISRs are large powerful radar systems that are highly sensitive to the presence of ionospheric turbulence. &nbsp; The specific radar system employed in this work was the Poker Flat ISR (PFISR). &nbsp; PFISR is the first electronically steerable phased-array ISR. &nbsp; Unlike dish-based radar systems where repointing requires mechanically moving an enormous dish, PFISR is repointed rapidly and arbitrarily on a pulse-by-pulse basis.&nbsp; This technology allows for a precise determination of where and when these beam-induced plasma turbulence events occur.</p> <p>The multi-instrument framework applied in this work allowed us to study the micro-scale physics of beam-atmosphere interactions in unprecedented detail.&nbsp; A major findings of this work was the identification of two distinct categories of turbulence, one related the so-called parametric decay of Langmuir waves, and the other associated with sheared plasma flow. &nbsp; The former category could be further sub-classified into cases of so-called cavitating (or &ldquo;strong&rdquo;) Langmuir turbulence in the 200 to 250 km range, and the other associated with weak Langmuir turbulence in the 300 to 700 km range. &nbsp; &nbsp; With this new understanding, we may now quantify the impacts on the local space weather environment, and extrapolate our results to the global solar-terrestrial system.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/01/2016<br>      Modified by: Joshua&nbsp;Semeter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Between 50 and 500 km altitude lies a region of transition between the neutral atmosphere we experience and the full ionized plasma of the solar wind and magnetosphere.  Dynamics in this outer atmospheric region are strongly influenced by interactions between the plasma and neutral gases.  This collaborative research project used detailed measurements of this region by ground-based radar and optical methods to investigate the underlying physics at its underlying elemental scales.     Boston UniversityÆs role in the project concerned the study of impinging beams of plasma particles, and their effects on the neutral and plasma gases in the outer atmosphere.  These particle beams are created through the release of magnetic energy stored within EarthÆs magnetosphere.   Auroras (the northern and southern lights) are a dramatic manifestation of these beams, but they lead to important societal consequences as well.  These beams interact with existing plasma waves, producing regions of plasma turbulence which, in turn, interact with radio waves, affecting ground-space communications, and degrading the performance of Global Navigation Satellite Systems (GNSS systems) such as GPS.   These particle-wave interactions also constitute a heat source for the neutral gas, which enhances satellite drag.   The electric currents carried by these particle beams also induce electric currents in long ground-conductors, providing a threat to the stability of power grids.  Our approach to studying the physics of beam-atmosphere interactions used a combination of Incoherent Scatter Radars (ISRs), optical imagery of the aurora, and computer simulations of the plasma environment.   ISRs are large powerful radar systems that are highly sensitive to the presence of ionospheric turbulence.   The specific radar system employed in this work was the Poker Flat ISR (PFISR).   PFISR is the first electronically steerable phased-array ISR.   Unlike dish-based radar systems where repointing requires mechanically moving an enormous dish, PFISR is repointed rapidly and arbitrarily on a pulse-by-pulse basis.  This technology allows for a precise determination of where and when these beam-induced plasma turbulence events occur.  The multi-instrument framework applied in this work allowed us to study the micro-scale physics of beam-atmosphere interactions in unprecedented detail.  A major findings of this work was the identification of two distinct categories of turbulence, one related the so-called parametric decay of Langmuir waves, and the other associated with sheared plasma flow.   The former category could be further sub-classified into cases of so-called cavitating (or "strong") Langmuir turbulence in the 200 to 250 km range, and the other associated with weak Langmuir turbulence in the 300 to 700 km range.     With this new understanding, we may now quantify the impacts on the local space weather environment, and extrapolate our results to the global solar-terrestrial system.       Last Modified: 02/01/2016       Submitted by: Joshua Semeter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
