<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Accessible Access Control</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199164.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199164</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vpiotrow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925141</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Access control is a last line of defense for protecting computer system resources from a compromised process. This is a primary motivation for the principle of least privilege, which requires that a process be given access to only those resources it needs in order to complete its task.  Enforcement of this principle is difficult.  A strict access control policy can contain tens of thousands of rules, while errors in the policy can interrupt service and put system resources at risk unnecessarily. This project is developing materials that facilitate education on modern access control models and systems.  A policy development system leverages visualization to enhance student learning.  The policy development system allows graphical development and analysis of access control policies.  It runs at the user-level, so that student work does not impact operation of the underlying system and so that access to a specific operating system is not required.  A set of web-based tutorials is being developed that are suitable for study out of the classroom. The project results will increase the number of institutions that offer deep coverage of access control in their curriculum and will facilitate devdrlopment of the relevant expertise by workers who are not able to pursue formal education. Computer system security breaches cost companies billions of dollars per year. By helping to create a workforce trained to use modern access control systems effectively, this project increases the ability of industry to protect electronic data.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1245310</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ching-Kuang</FirstName>
<LastName>Shene</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ching-Kuang Shene</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shene@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064872209</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000234045</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Carr</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven M Carr</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>steve.carr@wmich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2692763115</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000321908</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jean</FirstName>
<LastName>Mayo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jean Mayo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmayo@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064873157</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000240605</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chaoli</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chaoli Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chaoli.wang@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746319212</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000510655</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan Technological University</Name>
<CityName>Houghton</CityName>
<ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9064871885</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 Townsend Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065453268</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN TECHNOLOGICAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065453268</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan Technological University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~199164</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Access control is a last line of defense for protecting computer system resources from a compromised process. This is a primary motivation for the principle of least privilege, which requires that a process be given access to only those resources it needs in order to complete its task. Though necessary for system security, enforcement of this principle is difficult. It requires very fine-grained specification of the permissions a process has to system resources, which in turn leads to very large and complex policies. A very strict policy can contain tens of thousands of rules.&nbsp;</p> <p>Operating system developers have been tackling the difficult problem of designing access control systems that can enforce the principle of least privilege. A large part of this effort has been incorporation of sophisticated security models that abstract the required access to protected data, thus simplifying the development of an access control policy. &nbsp;For example, the NSA developed SELinux, which facilitates mandatory access control through the Linux Security Modules and provides support for the Multi-level Security, Role-based Access Control, and Type Enforcement security models.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong>: In order for these contemporary access control systems to be effective, a workforce must be trained to use them correctly and effectively. This project developed materials to facilitate more effective access control education. &nbsp;The Role-based Access Control (RBAC), Multilevel Security (MLS), Domain Type Enforcement (DTE) and UNIX Permissions models are supported and the materials are modularized around each model so that instructors can select the modules appropriate to a particular course.</p> <p>A user-level policy development system (PDS) was created that supports graphical analysis of access control policies. &nbsp;A publicly accessible website acv.cs.mtu.edu has been created to distribute the PDS system and tutorials. &nbsp;DTEvisual, MLSvisual, RBACvisual and UNIXvisual cover the DTE, MLS, RBAC and UNIX permission models, respectively. &nbsp;Each system leverages visualization, which is widely used for more effective learning, for access control education. &nbsp;Figure 1 depicts a visualization from the MLSvisual system. &nbsp;The MLS model abstracts control over information used within the US Military. &nbsp;Users and objects have security levels and these levels are nodes within the graph. &nbsp;Colored arrows show how information may flow in the system through a sequence of reads and writes. &nbsp;</p> <p><br />Languages were developed that allow policies to be expressed concisely in a text-based file. &nbsp;Policies can also be edited graphically through the visualization system. The resulting changes can be analyzed immediately and the resulting text-based policy can be exported. &nbsp;Figure 2 depicts a text-based DTE policy (top left) and a visualization (bottom right) from DTEvisual. &nbsp;Elliptical nodes, which represent DTE domains, and rectangular nodes, that represent DTE types, can be added through a series of clicks. &nbsp;Arcs that represent exec and auto permissions for domain changes can also be added through the graphical interface. &nbsp;</p> <p><br />The PDS system helps instructors to overcome many of the hurdles associated with teaching access control. It runs at the user-level so students can explore policies without support from system administrators or affecting other system users. It provides a simple specification language for each model to reduce the complexity of policy specifications. It leverages visualization, through model-specific policy depictions, to improve learning. It reduces instruction overhead through an ability to give homework and quizzes using the visualization system and through the simplified specification language. It is modularized so that instructors can select the models that align with their course learning goals.The software is available from the course web site. The distribution includes the source code. &nbsp;This will enable interested developers to maintain and enhance the software for their own scientific and educational goals.</p> <p>More than 200 undergraduate students have used the system. &nbsp;Classroom testing showed that a PDS significantly helped students to understand the associated underlying model and enhanced courses in which they were used.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong>:&nbsp;Computer system security breaches cost companies billions of dollars per year. The NSA led an effort to substantially improve system security nationwide through its SELinux project. The SELinux project introduced sophisticated security models into real access control systems and proved the effectiveness of these models to solve common security problems. This project built upon this effort by helping to create a workforce trained to use modern access control systems effectively. The result will be an increase in the ability of industry to protect electronic data. &nbsp;Hence, the future impact of this project promises to be substantial.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Jean&nbsp;Mayo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1245310/1245310_10274070_1480440533735_Slide1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1245310/1245310_10274070_1480440533735_Slide1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1: Poiicy Depiction in MLSvisual"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1245310/1245310_10274070_1480440533735_Slide1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1: Poiicy Depiction in MLSvisual"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A policy shown in MLSvisual.  Nodes represent security levels.  Orange arrows show levels that can be read by a user at the selected level.  Blue arrows show levels that may be written.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jean Mayo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jean&nbsp;Mayo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1: Poiicy Depiction in MLSvisual</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1245310/1245310_10274070_1480440717417_Slide2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1245310/1245310_10274070_1480440717417_Slide2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2: Graphical Policy Editing in DTEvisual"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1245310/1245310_10274070_1480440717417_Slide2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2: Graphical Policy Editing in DTEvisual"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Text policy and its depiction in DTEvisual.  Rounded nodes represent domains and square nodes represent types.  Edges show access allowed through the policy.  Type nodes, domain nodes, and access edges can be added graphically and the resulting text policy can be exported.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jean Mayo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jean&nbsp;Mayo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2: Graphical Policy Editing in DTEvisual</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Access control is a last line of defense for protecting computer system resources from a compromised process. This is a primary motivation for the principle of least privilege, which requires that a process be given access to only those resources it needs in order to complete its task. Though necessary for system security, enforcement of this principle is difficult. It requires very fine-grained specification of the permissions a process has to system resources, which in turn leads to very large and complex policies. A very strict policy can contain tens of thousands of rules.   Operating system developers have been tackling the difficult problem of designing access control systems that can enforce the principle of least privilege. A large part of this effort has been incorporation of sophisticated security models that abstract the required access to protected data, thus simplifying the development of an access control policy.  For example, the NSA developed SELinux, which facilitates mandatory access control through the Linux Security Modules and provides support for the Multi-level Security, Role-based Access Control, and Type Enforcement security models.   Intellectual Merit: In order for these contemporary access control systems to be effective, a workforce must be trained to use them correctly and effectively. This project developed materials to facilitate more effective access control education.  The Role-based Access Control (RBAC), Multilevel Security (MLS), Domain Type Enforcement (DTE) and UNIX Permissions models are supported and the materials are modularized around each model so that instructors can select the modules appropriate to a particular course.  A user-level policy development system (PDS) was created that supports graphical analysis of access control policies.  A publicly accessible website acv.cs.mtu.edu has been created to distribute the PDS system and tutorials.  DTEvisual, MLSvisual, RBACvisual and UNIXvisual cover the DTE, MLS, RBAC and UNIX permission models, respectively.  Each system leverages visualization, which is widely used for more effective learning, for access control education.  Figure 1 depicts a visualization from the MLSvisual system.  The MLS model abstracts control over information used within the US Military.  Users and objects have security levels and these levels are nodes within the graph.  Colored arrows show how information may flow in the system through a sequence of reads and writes.     Languages were developed that allow policies to be expressed concisely in a text-based file.  Policies can also be edited graphically through the visualization system. The resulting changes can be analyzed immediately and the resulting text-based policy can be exported.  Figure 2 depicts a text-based DTE policy (top left) and a visualization (bottom right) from DTEvisual.  Elliptical nodes, which represent DTE domains, and rectangular nodes, that represent DTE types, can be added through a series of clicks.  Arcs that represent exec and auto permissions for domain changes can also be added through the graphical interface.     The PDS system helps instructors to overcome many of the hurdles associated with teaching access control. It runs at the user-level so students can explore policies without support from system administrators or affecting other system users. It provides a simple specification language for each model to reduce the complexity of policy specifications. It leverages visualization, through model-specific policy depictions, to improve learning. It reduces instruction overhead through an ability to give homework and quizzes using the visualization system and through the simplified specification language. It is modularized so that instructors can select the models that align with their course learning goals.The software is available from the course web site. The distribution includes the source code.  This will enable interested developers to maintain and enhance the software for their own scientific and educational goals.  More than 200 undergraduate students have used the system.  Classroom testing showed that a PDS significantly helped students to understand the associated underlying model and enhanced courses in which they were used.  Broader Impacts: Computer system security breaches cost companies billions of dollars per year. The NSA led an effort to substantially improve system security nationwide through its SELinux project. The SELinux project introduced sophisticated security models into real access control systems and proved the effectiveness of these models to solve common security problems. This project built upon this effort by helping to create a workforce trained to use modern access control systems effectively. The result will be an increase in the ability of industry to protect electronic data.  Hence, the future impact of this project promises to be substantial.                Last Modified: 11/29/2016       Submitted by: Jean Mayo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
