<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Building BRIDGES Within the Undergraduate Major in Computer Science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>193813.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>193813</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephanie August</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project, investigators from UNC Charlotte are building a software&lt;br/&gt;infrastructure named ``BRIDGES" (Bridging Real-world Infrastructure&lt;br/&gt;Designed to Goal-align, Engage and Stimulate) to transform student&lt;br/&gt;experiences in computing education. The primary goal of the project is to&lt;br/&gt;improve retention of CS majors, especially at the sophomore level. BRIDGES&lt;br/&gt;facilitates a hands-on experience for solving traditional problems in computer&lt;br/&gt;science using real-world information systems, such as Facebook, Twitter,&lt;br/&gt;Google Maps, etc.  BRIDGES is being integrated into two computer science&lt;br/&gt;required courses, the senior capstone course and the sophomore level&lt;br/&gt;data structures and algorithms course, enabling a senior-sophomore bridge.&lt;br/&gt;Sophomore and senior students in these courses will partner in joint lab&lt;br/&gt;sessions to utilize and create new extensions to the BRIDGES infrastructure&lt;br/&gt;to support data structures programming assignments. Sophomores will act as&lt;br/&gt;customers for the new tools and data sets created by seniors and use them in&lt;br/&gt;their course programming assignments.  In this manner, BRIDGES will create a&lt;br/&gt;more connected student body by partnering sophomores and seniors, which&lt;br/&gt;should lead to improved student retention and engagement. BRIDGES is&lt;br/&gt;being built using open source and web technologies, promoting easy&lt;br/&gt;dissemination. Two workshops on the BRIDGES system will be held,&lt;br/&gt;involving educators from regional colleges and high schools, including&lt;br/&gt;minority and underrepresented institutions.  An additional workshop will be&lt;br/&gt;held associated with a major education conference. Students from the STARS Alliance (an NSF funded Broadening Participation in Computing consortium) will be given access to the learning materials and infrastructure to incorporate into their outreach and teaching activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/05/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1245841</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paula</FirstName>
<LastName>Goolkasian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paula Goolkasian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pagoolka@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046874749</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000093938</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kalpathi</FirstName>
<LastName>Subramanian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kalpathi R Subramanian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>krs@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046878579</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000376129</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Youngblood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory M Youngblood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gmyoungblood@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046877989</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000318897</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/09/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Kosara</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert Kosara</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rkosara@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046878377</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000495286</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/15/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamie</FirstName>
<LastName>Payton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jamie Payton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>payton@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046878188</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000363062</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9201 University City Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066300096</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHARLOTTE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Charlotte]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlotte</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9201 University City Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~193813</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project has resulted in <strong>BRIDGES</strong>, a software infrastructure that facilitates<br />solving traditional problems in computer science by providing easy access<br />to&nbsp; using real-world data and information systems (such as Facebook,<br />Twitter, Google Maps, IMDB Actor/Movie data, etc) as part of routine course<br />assignments.&nbsp; BRIDGES also&nbsp; provides visualization capabilities to better<br />engage students completing traditional and rigorous assignments.<br />The project targets computer science students at the sophomore level,<br />a particularly vulnerable point in computer science programs, in order to<br />improve retention and graduation.<br /><br />Outcomes from this project include the following:</p> <ol> <li>&nbsp;The BRIDGES system&nbsp; is stable and works with 3 programming languages, C++, Python and Java;</li> <li>BRIDGES has been used in over 11 courses at UNC Charlotte and&nbsp; through partner instructors in 16 courses at&nbsp; 10 universities external to UNC Charlotte</li> <li>BRIDGES has been disseminated through conferences, mailing lists, and direct contact.</li> <li>&nbsp;Over 1300 students have so far been directly impacted by the BRIDGES software. This impact has been increasing in recent years (nearly 200 student users in Spring 2019).</li> <li>&nbsp;BRIDGES has demonstrated knowledge gains in data structures courses when compared non-BRIDGES users of the same course.</li> <li>Students undergoing courses using the BRIDGES exercises have shown superior performance in 4 follow-on required courses in computer science.</li> <li>Qualitative Analysis performed on BRIDGES project surveys over 4 years show over 90%&nbsp; positive responses to BRIDGES.</li> <li>Surveys of instructors using BRIDGES in their data structures were overall positive, but also noted a moderate amount of learning curve required to use the toolkit.</li> <li>Two conference publications, numerous demonstrations and presentations and four workshops have resulted from the project.</li> <li>&nbsp;Training and mentoring of 10 students (2 PhD, 8 undergraduate) involved in the BRIDGES project; 7 of the undergraduate students have continued into graduate school. Two female students and 1 Latino student were involved in the project.</li> <li>Peer mentoring&nbsp; was implemented to&nbsp; bring&nbsp; senior level students&nbsp; to <br />connect and mentor&nbsp; sophomore level data structures students. Overall,&nbsp; results were mixed and require further investigation.</li> </ol> <p><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Kalpathi&nbsp;R&nbsp;Subramanian</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project has resulted in BRIDGES, a software infrastructure that facilitates solving traditional problems in computer science by providing easy access to  using real-world data and information systems (such as Facebook, Twitter, Google Maps, IMDB Actor/Movie data, etc) as part of routine course assignments.  BRIDGES also  provides visualization capabilities to better engage students completing traditional and rigorous assignments. The project targets computer science students at the sophomore level, a particularly vulnerable point in computer science programs, in order to improve retention and graduation.  Outcomes from this project include the following:   The BRIDGES system  is stable and works with 3 programming languages, C++, Python and Java; BRIDGES has been used in over 11 courses at UNC Charlotte and  through partner instructors in 16 courses at  10 universities external to UNC Charlotte BRIDGES has been disseminated through conferences, mailing lists, and direct contact.  Over 1300 students have so far been directly impacted by the BRIDGES software. This impact has been increasing in recent years (nearly 200 student users in Spring 2019).  BRIDGES has demonstrated knowledge gains in data structures courses when compared non-BRIDGES users of the same course. Students undergoing courses using the BRIDGES exercises have shown superior performance in 4 follow-on required courses in computer science. Qualitative Analysis performed on BRIDGES project surveys over 4 years show over 90%  positive responses to BRIDGES. Surveys of instructors using BRIDGES in their data structures were overall positive, but also noted a moderate amount of learning curve required to use the toolkit. Two conference publications, numerous demonstrations and presentations and four workshops have resulted from the project.  Training and mentoring of 10 students (2 PhD, 8 undergraduate) involved in the BRIDGES project; 7 of the undergraduate students have continued into graduate school. Two female students and 1 Latino student were involved in the project. Peer mentoring  was implemented to  bring  senior level students  to  connect and mentor  sophomore level data structures students. Overall,  results were mixed and require further investigation.                Last Modified: 05/29/2019       Submitted by: Kalpathi R Subramanian]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
