<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Flipping Calculus</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>172136.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>172136</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Haddock</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jhaddock@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922671</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The purpose of Flipping Calculus is to transform the teaching and learning of the material in Calculus. Flipping a course describes an instructional approach in which the delivery of a majority of the content is moved outside of class, via online videos, lecture notes, and readings, while homework, such as problem sets, labs, and applications, are shifted into the classroom. Instructors in Flipped Calculus are devoting class time to supporting small groups of students who are engaged in collaborative discussions and problem solving.  Senior faculty are creating a library of videotaped lessons which correspond to key calculus concepts.  In addition, they are developing and refining guided problem sets and assessments to evaluate the progress made by the students.  Eventually, a website for flipping calculus will be created, which will host the videos and course materials, available for broad dissemination.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project activities are based on research on how students learn and are designed to actively engage students in Calculus so they obtain a deeper understanding of the material, ultimately remembering and applying the skills and concepts they learn.  This project involves at least six mathematics faculty members and is having a direct impact on more than 200 students during the first year of the project and upwards of 300 students in year two. The project leaders are extending the impact by presenting their findings and materials at regional and national conferences, sharing the videotapes, problem sets, labs and discussion questions on a website dedicated to flipping Calculus, as well as publishing articles in mathematics education journals.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1245059</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John K Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jwilliams@hartford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8607684825</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000292359</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mako</FirstName>
<LastName>Haruta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mako E Haruta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>haruta@hartford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2037685261</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000218662</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Larissa</FirstName>
<LastName>Schroeder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Larissa Schroeder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schroeder@hartford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8607684083</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620557</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jean</FirstName>
<LastName>McGivney-Burelle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jean McGivney-Burelle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>burelle@hartford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8607685921</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620560</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hartford</Name>
<CityName>West Hartford</CityName>
<ZipCode>061171545</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8607685938</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 Bloomfield Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069264398</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HARTFORD, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069264398</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hartford]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>061171599</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~172136</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The need to improve the participation and performance of U.S. students majoring in STEM is well understood and is beginning to be addressed by political leaders, foundations, non-profits and professional organizations at the state and national levels. At the college level, Calculus is a course that has significant potential to serve as a pump for increasing the number students majoring in STEM fields. Unfortunately, first-semester Calculus often acts as a gatekeeper, frequently filtering students out of STEM majors. The purpose of our project, <em>Flipping Calculus, </em>was to transform the teaching and learning of Calculus I by inverting (i.e., flipping) traditional instruction and incorporating pedagogical practices that are steeped in our understanding of how students learn most effectively.</p> <p>To accomplish our goals we developed a comprehensive set of high-quality resources for Calculus I, including videos/screencasts, interesting and challenging problem sets and engaging discussion questions to be completed in class, along with multiple assessments so that students' work in class and out of class is highly structured. These materials were disseminated via a project website, journal articles, and through dozens of local, regional, national and international conference presentations, invited talks, organized contributed paper sessions, workshops, panels, and poster sessions.</p> <p>To assess the effectiveness of our flipped Calculus model we conducted a quasi-experimental study of students (n=112) enrolled in either traditional or flipped sections of Calculus I. Results of this exploratory study revealed that students enrolled in flipped sections of Calculus I spent more time outside of class working on mathematics and spent more class time working on, discussing, and presenting solutions to problems. In addition, students enrolled in the flipped sections performed significantly better than their peers on the common final exam. Furthermore, the follow-up analysis of Calculus II grades suggested that the benefits from enrolling in a flipped Calculus I course extended into performance in Calculus II. As a result of this study, all sections of Calculus I are now taught via inverted instruction. Our project has established the feasibility of flipping a mutliple section course and has changed our students&rsquo; first year experience and expectations, providing them with many of the skills needed for a successful academic and workplace career.</p> <p>Today, <em>Flipping Calculus</em> continues to impact the teaching and learning of mathematics at the University of Hartford. With flipping pedagogy implemented in Calculus I and now in Calculus II, our work directly impacts more than 800 undergraduate STEM majors each year.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Publications:</span></p> <p>Schroeder<strong>, </strong>L.B., McGivney-Burelle, J., &amp; Xue, F. (2015). To flip or not to flip? An exploratory study comparing student performance in Calculus I. <em>PRIMUS: Problems, Resources, and Issues in Undergraduate Mathematics Studies</em>, <em>25</em> (9-10), 876 &ndash; 885. DOI: 10.1080/10511970.2015.1050617</p> <p>Schroeder, L. B. &amp; Dorn, B. (2016). Enabling and integrating online formative assessment in a flipped calculus course. <em>PRIMUS: Problems, Resources, and Issues in Undergraduate Mathematics,</em> 26(6), 585 &ndash;602. DOI: 10.1080/10511970.2015.1050619.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/27/2017<br>      Modified by: Larissa&nbsp;Schroeder</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The need to improve the participation and performance of U.S. students majoring in STEM is well understood and is beginning to be addressed by political leaders, foundations, non-profits and professional organizations at the state and national levels. At the college level, Calculus is a course that has significant potential to serve as a pump for increasing the number students majoring in STEM fields. Unfortunately, first-semester Calculus often acts as a gatekeeper, frequently filtering students out of STEM majors. The purpose of our project, Flipping Calculus, was to transform the teaching and learning of Calculus I by inverting (i.e., flipping) traditional instruction and incorporating pedagogical practices that are steeped in our understanding of how students learn most effectively.  To accomplish our goals we developed a comprehensive set of high-quality resources for Calculus I, including videos/screencasts, interesting and challenging problem sets and engaging discussion questions to be completed in class, along with multiple assessments so that students' work in class and out of class is highly structured. These materials were disseminated via a project website, journal articles, and through dozens of local, regional, national and international conference presentations, invited talks, organized contributed paper sessions, workshops, panels, and poster sessions.  To assess the effectiveness of our flipped Calculus model we conducted a quasi-experimental study of students (n=112) enrolled in either traditional or flipped sections of Calculus I. Results of this exploratory study revealed that students enrolled in flipped sections of Calculus I spent more time outside of class working on mathematics and spent more class time working on, discussing, and presenting solutions to problems. In addition, students enrolled in the flipped sections performed significantly better than their peers on the common final exam. Furthermore, the follow-up analysis of Calculus II grades suggested that the benefits from enrolling in a flipped Calculus I course extended into performance in Calculus II. As a result of this study, all sections of Calculus I are now taught via inverted instruction. Our project has established the feasibility of flipping a mutliple section course and has changed our students? first year experience and expectations, providing them with many of the skills needed for a successful academic and workplace career.  Today, Flipping Calculus continues to impact the teaching and learning of mathematics at the University of Hartford. With flipping pedagogy implemented in Calculus I and now in Calculus II, our work directly impacts more than 800 undergraduate STEM majors each year.  Publications:  Schroeder, L.B., McGivney-Burelle, J., &amp; Xue, F. (2015). To flip or not to flip? An exploratory study comparing student performance in Calculus I. PRIMUS: Problems, Resources, and Issues in Undergraduate Mathematics Studies, 25 (9-10), 876 &ndash; 885. DOI: 10.1080/10511970.2015.1050617  Schroeder, L. B. &amp; Dorn, B. (2016). Enabling and integrating online formative assessment in a flipped calculus course. PRIMUS: Problems, Resources, and Issues in Undergraduate Mathematics, 26(6), 585 &ndash;602. DOI: 10.1080/10511970.2015.1050619.       Last Modified: 07/27/2017       Submitted by: Larissa Schroeder]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
