<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Studies of Waves and Circulation Features in the Antarctic Stratosphere Using Super-Pressure Balloon Data</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>296590.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>296590</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020106</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric DeWeaver</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edeweave@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928527</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project conducts research on the circulation of the Antarctic stratospheric polar vortex based on data from super pressure balloons (SPBs).  SPBs have a semi-rigid envelope which, under pressure from the gas inside, maintains constant volume and hence constant effective density regardless of heating and cooling, so that they move with the wind along a nearly horizontal surface of constant density.  Data for this project comes from two field campaigns,VORCORE (27 SPBs in 2005) and CONCORDIASI (18 SPBs in 2010), both of which launched balloons from Antarctica which rose to levels between 70 and 50mb and circulated within the polar vortex for several months.  Instruments carried by the SPBs included miniaturized dropsondes, GPS receivers for occultation soundings, ozone sensors, and cloud ice particle counters.  Research conducted under this award studies inertia-gravity waves and large-scale transport across and within the polar vortex, with four specific objectives: 1) The accurate statistical descriptions of the inertial and gravity wave fields over the Antarctic in the spatial and spectral domains, 2) The formulation of constraints for gravity wave parameterizations based on calculation of gravity wave momentum flux, 3) The influence of gravity waves on the formation of polar stratospheric clouds (PSCs, which play an important role in ozone depletion), and 4) The fundamental dynamical process at work in air exchanges and transports in relation to the polar vortex, with an emphasis on the role of Rossby wave breaking.  The work uses a combination of observational analysis and modeling, and uses novel methods motivated by dynamical systems theory to address air exchange and transport across and within the polar vortex.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The problems addressed in the proposal are of societal as well as scientific interest for two reasons.  First, the processes examined here are all relevant to the formation of the ozone hole, as ozone depletion depends on transport and mixing of stratospheric air across and within the polar vortex, and gravity wave motions may play a role in the formation of PSCs.  Second, gravity wave momentum fluxes are thought to play an important role in determining the strength of atmospheric circulation, and the effects of gravity waves are paremeterized in weather and climate models.  Thus, observational analysis of gravity wave properties may be beneficial for weather and climate modeling and prediction.  In addition, the work will support and train a graduate student, thereby providing for the next generation of scientists in this field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1245069</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
<LastName>Mechoso</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carlos R Mechoso</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mechoso@atmos.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3108251217</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000190598</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951565</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[405 Hilgard Ave., 7173]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~296590</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The present project concentrated on the stratosphere over Antarctica. Our specific objectives were the increased understanding of the wave fields over the Antarctic and emphasis on how these waves interact with the circulation and the polar vortex, and on how the presence of the vortex conditions the transport processes.&nbsp; The Antarctic polar night vortex is a key contributor to the setting the conditions required by the special chemistry that produces the Antarctic Ozone Hole.</p> <p>The research used a unique data set of the region gathered in situ by drifting super-pressure balloons launched during the field campaigns of the VORCORE and CONCORDIASI international projects sponsored by France&rsquo;s CNRS and US&rsquo;s NSF. For the wave analyses we applied formulations of wave fluxes in log-density coordinates developed in the previous funding period of this project. For the investigation of transport processes we used novel tools of Lagrangian analysis, which we were first to apply to studies on the stratospheric circulation.</p> <p>(1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Based on ERA-Interim Reanalysis data we built a 2D kinematic model capable of reproducing, by adjusting its parameters, vortex filamentation and breakdown features that are strikingly similar to the observation. Analyses of model results revealed the key kinematic mechanisms at work for the observed filamentation of the vortex (see Fig.1).</p> <p>(1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A novel definition of the stratospheric vortex boundary on isentropic surfaces was proposed and justified based on properties of dynamical systems in bounded domains (compact sets) in periodic or quasi-periodic cases. The boundary marks the poleward extension of the region of strong filamentation and mixing known as the &ldquo;surf zone&rdquo;). To our knowledge, other heuristic definitions of the vortex edge have not been similarly justified.</p> <p>(2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We introduced the new concept of normally hyperbolic invariant manifolds to the geometrical template that governs 3D transport in the stratosphere. To our knowledge, this concept had not been applied in stratospheric contexts.</p> <p>(3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The large-scale mechanisms at work for the unique splitting of the stratospheric polar vortex in the southern spring of 2002 were discussed.&nbsp; We identified the behavior of air parcels during the split (see Figs. 2 and 3). Lagrangian structures used in this project were identified in the observational data. It was also concluded that the results agree with the notion that vortex interactions together with links between troposphere and stratosphere were key to the uniqueness of the event .</p> <p>(4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Momentum fluxes over the Antarctic Peninsula comprise a main distribution maximizing at small flux values and a secondary high flux distribution exhibiting a high degree of intermittency (see Fig. 4). The high flux events account for a large part of the average flux, which suggests that drag parameterizations in GCCMs should account for the conditions that favor them.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Dr. Anirban Guha, who joined the team in 2013 as a postdoctoral scholar, was trained in stratospheric dynamics and numerical modeling of the atmosphere. Professor Jezabel Curbelo, an Assistant Professor of Mathematics, has been trained in stratospheric dynamics and transports.The work performed under this project represents a bridge between atmospheric scientists and applied mathematicians. The special Lagrangian analyses applied in the project had been used in oceanographic contexts for dynamical transports including the fate of oil spills in the ocean. The project has demonstrated their applicability to the stratosphere and the potential for future research.&nbsp;</p> <p>Refereed Publications</p> <p>Curbelo, J., V. J. Garc&iacute;a-Garrido, C. R. Mechoso, A. M. Mancho, and Stephen Wiggins, 2017a: Insights on the three-dimensional Lagrangian geometry of the Antarctic Polar Vortex. Nonlin. Processes Geophys., 24, 379- 392. &nbsp;https://doi.org/10.5194/npg-24-379-2017<br />Curbelo, J., C. R. Mechoso, A. M. Mancho, and Stephen Wiggins, 2017b: Lagrangian study of the final warming in the southern stratosphere during 2002. Climate Dynamics. &nbsp;Sub-judice.<br />Garc&iacute;a-Garrido, V. J., J. Curbelo, C. R. Mechoso, A. M. Mancho, and Stephen Wiggins, 2017: A Simple Kinematic Model for the Lagrangian Description of Relevant Nonlinear Processes in the Stratospheric Polar Vortex. Nonlin. Processes Geophys., 24, 265-278. https://doi.org/10.5194/npg-24-265-2017<br />Guha, A., C. R. Mechoso, C. S. Konor, and R. P. Heikes, 2016: Modeling Rossby wave breaking in the southern spring stratosphere. J. Atmos. Sci., 73, 393-406.&nbsp;.Mechoso, C. R, 2016: Lagrangian Studies of the Southern Stratosphere. &nbsp;Invited presentation at the Third International Workshop on Nonlinear Processes in Oceanic and Oceanic Flows. Madrid, Spain, 6-8 July 2016.<br />Walterscheid, R. L., L. J. Gelinas, C. R. Mechoso, and G. Schubert, 2016: Spectral Distribution of Gravity Wave Momentum Fluxes over the Antarctic Peninsula from Concordiasi Super-Pressure Balloon Data. &nbsp;J. Geophys. Res., 121, 7509&ndash;7527.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/05/2018<br>      Modified by: Carlos&nbsp;R&nbsp;Mechoso</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1245069/1245069_10245585_1515143477277_OutcomesFig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1245069/1245069_10245585_1515143477277_OutcomesFig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Kinematic  Model depiction of vortex split"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1245069/1245069_10245585_1515143477277_OutcomesFig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Kinematic  Model depiction of vortex split"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Left panel: The function M (? = 15) obtained at t = 3 from the Kinematic Model with a selected set of parameters. The pole is marked with a black dot and the equator with a dashed black line. Right panel: ?M magnitudes.  M is a Lagrangian descriptor: Higher values of M roughly correspond t</div> <div class="imageCredit">Curbelo et al. (2017b)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carlos&nbsp;R&nbsp;Mechoso</div> <div class="imageTitle">Kinematic  Model depiction of vortex split</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1245069/1245069_10245585_1515143875647_OutcomesFig2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1245069/1245069_10245585_1515143875647_OutcomesFig2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="3D structure of the polar vortex"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1245069/1245069_10245585_1515143875647_OutcomesFig2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="3D structure of the polar vortex"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. Representation of the 3D structure of the polar vortex during the splitting. a) and b) Longitude-height and latitude-height projection of M on a surface that contains the normally hyperbolic invariant contour (NHIC). c) Embedding of the surface displayed in (b) on the 3D space and cross se</div> <div class="imageCredit">Curbelo et al. (2017b)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carlos&nbsp;R&nbsp;Mechoso</div> <div class="imageTitle">3D structure of the polar vortex</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1245069/1245069_10245585_1515144462235_OutcomesFig3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1245069/1245069_10245585_1515144462235_OutcomesFig3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Position of particles during vortex split"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1245069/1245069_10245585_1515144462235_OutcomesFig3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Position of particles during vortex split"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3. The function M at 850K just before the vortex split. (a) The blue (red) arrows highlight (stable) unstable manifolds. (b) and (c) Position of particles before and during the split. Red (blue) dots indicate particles outside (inside) the curve determined by the maximum value of M for each l</div> <div class="imageCredit">Curbelo et al. (2017b)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carlos&nbsp;R&nbsp;Mechoso</div> <div class="imageTitle">Position of particles during vortex split</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1245069/1245069_10245585_1515144599565_OutcomesFig4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1245069/1245069_10245585_1515144599565_OutcomesFig4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Momentum fluxes above Antarctica"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1245069/1245069_10245585_1515144599565_OutcomesFig4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Momentum fluxes above Antarctica"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 4. Distribution of fluxes stratified by mean flux in 500  500 km cells. The symbol mx refers to the zonal horizontal momentum flux.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Walterscheid et al. (2016)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carlos&nbsp;R&nbsp;Mechoso</div> <div class="imageTitle">Momentum fluxes above Antarctica</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The present project concentrated on the stratosphere over Antarctica. Our specific objectives were the increased understanding of the wave fields over the Antarctic and emphasis on how these waves interact with the circulation and the polar vortex, and on how the presence of the vortex conditions the transport processes.  The Antarctic polar night vortex is a key contributor to the setting the conditions required by the special chemistry that produces the Antarctic Ozone Hole.  The research used a unique data set of the region gathered in situ by drifting super-pressure balloons launched during the field campaigns of the VORCORE and CONCORDIASI international projects sponsored by France?s CNRS and US?s NSF. For the wave analyses we applied formulations of wave fluxes in log-density coordinates developed in the previous funding period of this project. For the investigation of transport processes we used novel tools of Lagrangian analysis, which we were first to apply to studies on the stratospheric circulation.  (1)      Based on ERA-Interim Reanalysis data we built a 2D kinematic model capable of reproducing, by adjusting its parameters, vortex filamentation and breakdown features that are strikingly similar to the observation. Analyses of model results revealed the key kinematic mechanisms at work for the observed filamentation of the vortex (see Fig.1).  (1)          A novel definition of the stratospheric vortex boundary on isentropic surfaces was proposed and justified based on properties of dynamical systems in bounded domains (compact sets) in periodic or quasi-periodic cases. The boundary marks the poleward extension of the region of strong filamentation and mixing known as the "surf zone"). To our knowledge, other heuristic definitions of the vortex edge have not been similarly justified.  (2)          We introduced the new concept of normally hyperbolic invariant manifolds to the geometrical template that governs 3D transport in the stratosphere. To our knowledge, this concept had not been applied in stratospheric contexts.  (3)          The large-scale mechanisms at work for the unique splitting of the stratospheric polar vortex in the southern spring of 2002 were discussed.  We identified the behavior of air parcels during the split (see Figs. 2 and 3). Lagrangian structures used in this project were identified in the observational data. It was also concluded that the results agree with the notion that vortex interactions together with links between troposphere and stratosphere were key to the uniqueness of the event .  (4)          Momentum fluxes over the Antarctic Peninsula comprise a main distribution maximizing at small flux values and a secondary high flux distribution exhibiting a high degree of intermittency (see Fig. 4). The high flux events account for a large part of the average flux, which suggests that drag parameterizations in GCCMs should account for the conditions that favor them.    Dr. Anirban Guha, who joined the team in 2013 as a postdoctoral scholar, was trained in stratospheric dynamics and numerical modeling of the atmosphere. Professor Jezabel Curbelo, an Assistant Professor of Mathematics, has been trained in stratospheric dynamics and transports.The work performed under this project represents a bridge between atmospheric scientists and applied mathematicians. The special Lagrangian analyses applied in the project had been used in oceanographic contexts for dynamical transports including the fate of oil spills in the ocean. The project has demonstrated their applicability to the stratosphere and the potential for future research.   Refereed Publications  Curbelo, J., V. J. Garc&iacute;a-Garrido, C. R. Mechoso, A. M. Mancho, and Stephen Wiggins, 2017a: Insights on the three-dimensional Lagrangian geometry of the Antarctic Polar Vortex. Nonlin. Processes Geophys., 24, 379- 392.  https://doi.org/10.5194/npg-24-379-2017 Curbelo, J., C. R. Mechoso, A. M. Mancho, and Stephen Wiggins, 2017b: Lagrangian study of the final warming in the southern stratosphere during 2002. Climate Dynamics.  Sub-judice. Garc&iacute;a-Garrido, V. J., J. Curbelo, C. R. Mechoso, A. M. Mancho, and Stephen Wiggins, 2017: A Simple Kinematic Model for the Lagrangian Description of Relevant Nonlinear Processes in the Stratospheric Polar Vortex. Nonlin. Processes Geophys., 24, 265-278. https://doi.org/10.5194/npg-24-265-2017 Guha, A., C. R. Mechoso, C. S. Konor, and R. P. Heikes, 2016: Modeling Rossby wave breaking in the southern spring stratosphere. J. Atmos. Sci., 73, 393-406. .Mechoso, C. R, 2016: Lagrangian Studies of the Southern Stratosphere.  Invited presentation at the Third International Workshop on Nonlinear Processes in Oceanic and Oceanic Flows. Madrid, Spain, 6-8 July 2016. Walterscheid, R. L., L. J. Gelinas, C. R. Mechoso, and G. Schubert, 2016: Spectral Distribution of Gravity Wave Momentum Fluxes over the Antarctic Peninsula from Concordiasi Super-Pressure Balloon Data.  J. Geophys. Res., 121, 7509&ndash;7527.       Last Modified: 01/05/2018       Submitted by: Carlos R Mechoso]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
