<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Bridging Math and Science - Authentic Laboratory Experiences in Mathematical Biology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99693.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99693</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Haddock</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jhaddock@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922671</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>There is no precedent for math instruction using "wet" labs to engage students in mathematics through data-driven inquiry experiences. In this project, we construct Laboratory Experiences in Mathematical Biology (LEMBs) for undergraduate math classrooms. LEMBs are developed collaboratively at Utah State University and Colorado College, aimed at sophomore classrooms including both STEM and non-STEM majors. Students manipulate and interact with real-world biological mechanisms, construct their own mathematical descriptions and gain deeper understanding of underlying mathematical relationships. LEMBs are open-ended, inviting student participation and creativity. Student acquisition of modeling and problem-solving skills and the effect of LEMBs on other skills are evaluated using pre/post-tests, think-aloud exercises, and instructor/student interviews. We expect to create new knowledge about learners' construction of modeling and problem-solving skills. LEMBs invite student-centered mathematics instruction and expose faculty to alternative pedagogy. We assemble pedagogical materials to facilitate lab-based instruction, including alternate mathematical pathways rooted in the labs, multiple assessment items, and educational vignettes based on classroom observations to illustrate key pedagogical techniques. LEMBs and instructor support materials are made available to faculty nationwide via Open Access publication through USU?s Digital Commons. Presentations about LEMBs are made at conferences, and articles are also submitted to research and education journals.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1245421</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Powell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James A Powell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jim.powell@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4357971953</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000417602</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Miroslav</FirstName>
<LastName>Kummel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Miroslav Kummel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mkummel@coloradocollege.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7193896892</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000193230</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brynja</FirstName>
<LastName>Kohler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brynja Kohler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brynja.kohler@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4357972826</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000499036</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Bruder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea S Bruder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Andrea.Bruder@coloradocollege.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7193896318</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000618734</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Wesolek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Wesolek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Andrew.Wesolek@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4357972650</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620670</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Utah State University</Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<ZipCode>843221415</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4357971226</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1415 Old Main Hill ~ Room 64]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072983455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UTAH STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072983455</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Utah State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>843223900</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3900 Old Main Hill]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~99693</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview.&nbsp;</strong>While widely used in the natural sciences, labs are untypical for math classes, despite research on engaged learning and learning through experience. We&nbsp;created Laboratory Experiences in Mathematical Biology (LEMBs) for math classrooms, in which students interact with real-world biological mechanisms, construct mathematical descriptions, and gain understanding of mathematical relationships. Our labs are open-ended modeling assignments adaptable to a wide range of undergraduate&nbsp;math classes. These activities challenge students to think in detail about new concepts and prepare them for lifelong learning by making connections to scientific questions. In addition, they&nbsp;emphasize the nature of today&rsquo;s interdisciplinary research. We assessed the effectiveness of the labs through pre- and post-tests and created instructor support materials that are available at&nbsp;<a href="http://digitalcommons.usu.edu/lemb/">http://digitalcommons.usu.edu/lemb/</a>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong>. Post-secondary education depends largely on lectures and book homework problems.&nbsp; Real-world applications appear as contrived story problems with `canned&rsquo; data.&nbsp; This does a poor job of involving higher levels of student math cognition, particularly related to skills valued by STEM employers, including abilities to:</p> <ul> <li>Develop models and adapt      mathematical techniques to novel situations,</li> <li>Develop models and adapt mathematical techniques to      novel situations,</li> <li>Draw meaning from data,</li> <li>Think critically and creatively about quantitative      problems,</li> <li>Use computational tools to provide timely answers, </li> <li>Work effectively in teams, and</li> <li>Communicate results clearly and concisely. </li> </ul> <p>The learning gap is predominant in freshman/sophomore math classes required of STEM majors, calculus through linear algebra and ordinary differential equations (ODE), which are often terminal math classes for engineers, physicists and STEM teachers.</p> <p>When students are confronted with authentic, open-ended labs, requiring creative effort and teamwork in the context of instructor scaffolding, higher-level learning outcomes are multiplied.&nbsp; However, labs in collegiate math classes are problematic because:</p> <ul> <li>Actual      data collection is required for students to interact with mechanisms and      engage the full spectrum of math cognition.</li> <li>Infrastructure for labs in math classes does not exist.</li> <li>Lab subject matter is biased toward/away from differing      majors in math classes</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;LEMBs address these difficulties by:</p> <ul> <li>Creating      data collection projects which do not require specialized infrastructure.</li> <li>Using biological mechansisms, about which students have      intuitive understanding but little prior experience.</li> <li>Adapting biomath modeling, which is intrinsically      open-ended because few generally-accepted mathematical models exist for      biology.</li> </ul> <p>Six&nbsp;LEMBs span a spectrum of biological mechanisms:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Yeast      Lab</strong>:&nbsp;Yeast reproduce in a      capped ?ask, generating carbon dioxide&nbsp;which is trapped in an      inverted jar.&nbsp; Students engage in model competition with the      resulting data.&nbsp;</li> <li><strong>&nbsp;Stream Lab</strong>:&nbsp;Dead leaves&nbsp;float down a&nbsp;small      stream.&nbsp;The number of leaves passing recording stations along the      stream&nbsp;are tallied and students are asked to manipulate models to      answer questions in aquatic biology.</li> <li><strong>Zombie      Lab</strong>:&nbsp;Students play a game to      simulate the&nbsp;spread of a virus in ?xed populations and are challenged      to&nbsp;model for the resulting data.&nbsp;In advanced classes teams      proceed to model Humans vs. Zombies game data from their own campus.</li> <li><strong>Brine      Shrimp Lab</strong>:&nbsp;Brine shrimp movements      are tracked&nbsp;by students.&nbsp;Students are challenged to determine      and verify whether the brine shrimp&nbsp;move in a random walk.&nbsp; </li> <li><strong>Leaky      Bucket Lab</strong>:&nbsp;Students test a standard      model (Torricelli's law) and develop and compare their&nbsp;own      alternative models to describe the dynamics of water draining from      perforated&nbsp;containers.&nbsp; </li> <li><strong>Coffee&nbsp;to      Go! Lab</strong>:&nbsp;A layered system of      coffee and milk serves as a physical&nbsp;model for temperature gradients      in lakes or atmospheric inversions.&nbsp;      Students collect space-time temperature data and are challenged to      visualize and model complex data.&nbsp; </li> </ul> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong>.&nbsp;&nbsp;Students across many disciplines gained experience in how mathematics can be used to address science and engineering questions.&nbsp; We abstracted several lab&nbsp;design principles to help accomplish this, summarized by the <strong>PAVE</strong> framework:</p> <ul> <li><strong>P</strong>romote discovery: Labs are open-ended with opportunity      to reason inductively, explore concepts and relationships, and discover      connections.</li> <li><strong>A</strong>uthentic: Driven by real data, ideally collected by      students, labs require models and techniques used by applied      mathematicians and scientists.</li> <li><strong>V</strong>isible success: Mathematical plausibility is visualized      by model comparisons with data.</li> <li><strong>E</strong>ngaging: Labs have an accessible, original, scientific      question about natural phenomenon fitting into a broader story line.&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>The LEMBs also gave post-secondary math teachers an opportunity to review/refresh their pedagogy more generally.&nbsp; Effective teachers of LEMBs used pedagogical practices which maintained high levels of cognitive demand, including:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Scaffold      student thinking</strong>: Ask questions and minimize      direct instruction so students can work and think themselves. </li> <li><strong>Sustained      press for justification</strong>:      When students make observations and discoveries, encourage mechanistic,      mathematical or deductive explanations. </li> <li><strong>Sufficient      time to explore</strong>: Allow time for data      gathering, small group discussion and whole-class reflection on experiment      and results.</li> <li><strong>Build      on prior knowledge</strong>:      Require students to use, adapt and expand previous knowledge.&nbsp; </li> <li><strong>Students      have means to monitor their own progress</strong>:      Clear lab instructions, rubrics for evaluation and comparison with      personally-collected data.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2016<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;A&nbsp;Powell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview. While widely used in the natural sciences, labs are untypical for math classes, despite research on engaged learning and learning through experience. We created Laboratory Experiences in Mathematical Biology (LEMBs) for math classrooms, in which students interact with real-world biological mechanisms, construct mathematical descriptions, and gain understanding of mathematical relationships. Our labs are open-ended modeling assignments adaptable to a wide range of undergraduate math classes. These activities challenge students to think in detail about new concepts and prepare them for lifelong learning by making connections to scientific questions. In addition, they emphasize the nature of today?s interdisciplinary research. We assessed the effectiveness of the labs through pre- and post-tests and created instructor support materials that are available at http://digitalcommons.usu.edu/lemb/.     Intellectual Merit. Post-secondary education depends largely on lectures and book homework problems.  Real-world applications appear as contrived story problems with `canned? data.  This does a poor job of involving higher levels of student math cognition, particularly related to skills valued by STEM employers, including abilities to:  Develop models and adapt      mathematical techniques to novel situations, Develop models and adapt mathematical techniques to      novel situations, Draw meaning from data, Think critically and creatively about quantitative      problems, Use computational tools to provide timely answers,  Work effectively in teams, and Communicate results clearly and concisely.    The learning gap is predominant in freshman/sophomore math classes required of STEM majors, calculus through linear algebra and ordinary differential equations (ODE), which are often terminal math classes for engineers, physicists and STEM teachers.  When students are confronted with authentic, open-ended labs, requiring creative effort and teamwork in the context of instructor scaffolding, higher-level learning outcomes are multiplied.  However, labs in collegiate math classes are problematic because:  Actual      data collection is required for students to interact with mechanisms and      engage the full spectrum of math cognition. Infrastructure for labs in math classes does not exist. Lab subject matter is biased toward/away from differing      majors in math classes    LEMBs address these difficulties by:  Creating      data collection projects which do not require specialized infrastructure. Using biological mechansisms, about which students have      intuitive understanding but little prior experience. Adapting biomath modeling, which is intrinsically      open-ended because few generally-accepted mathematical models exist for      biology.   Six LEMBs span a spectrum of biological mechanisms:  Yeast      Lab: Yeast reproduce in a      capped ?ask, generating carbon dioxide which is trapped in an      inverted jar.  Students engage in model competition with the      resulting data.   Stream Lab: Dead leaves float down a small      stream. The number of leaves passing recording stations along the      stream are tallied and students are asked to manipulate models to      answer questions in aquatic biology. Zombie      Lab: Students play a game to      simulate the spread of a virus in ?xed populations and are challenged      to model for the resulting data. In advanced classes teams      proceed to model Humans vs. Zombies game data from their own campus. Brine      Shrimp Lab: Brine shrimp movements      are tracked by students. Students are challenged to determine      and verify whether the brine shrimp move in a random walk.   Leaky      Bucket Lab: Students test a standard      model (Torricelli's law) and develop and compare their own      alternative models to describe the dynamics of water draining from      perforated containers.   Coffee to      Go! Lab: A layered system of      coffee and milk serves as a physical model for temperature gradients      in lakes or atmospheric inversions.       Students collect space-time temperature data and are challenged to      visualize and model complex data.     Broader Impacts.  Students across many disciplines gained experience in how mathematics can be used to address science and engineering questions.  We abstracted several lab design principles to help accomplish this, summarized by the PAVE framework:  Promote discovery: Labs are open-ended with opportunity      to reason inductively, explore concepts and relationships, and discover      connections. Authentic: Driven by real data, ideally collected by      students, labs require models and techniques used by applied      mathematicians and scientists. Visible success: Mathematical plausibility is visualized      by model comparisons with data. Engaging: Labs have an accessible, original, scientific      question about natural phenomenon fitting into a broader story line.    The LEMBs also gave post-secondary math teachers an opportunity to review/refresh their pedagogy more generally.  Effective teachers of LEMBs used pedagogical practices which maintained high levels of cognitive demand, including:  Scaffold      student thinking: Ask questions and minimize      direct instruction so students can work and think themselves.  Sustained      press for justification:      When students make observations and discoveries, encourage mechanistic,      mathematical or deductive explanations.  Sufficient      time to explore: Allow time for data      gathering, small group discussion and whole-class reflection on experiment      and results. Build      on prior knowledge:      Require students to use, adapt and expand previous knowledge.   Students      have means to monitor their own progress:      Clear lab instructions, rubrics for evaluation and comparison with      personally-collected data.           Last Modified: 09/30/2016       Submitted by: James A Powell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
