<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Resolving Issues of Hydroxyl (OH) Measurements and Oxidation Chemistry in Forest Environments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>283473.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>283473</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020104</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Edgerton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sedgerto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928522</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding atmospheric oxidation chemistry is critical for establishing the links between atmospheric composition, air quality, and climate change. Hydroxyl (OH) is the atmosphere's primary oxidant. Comparisons of measurements and models provide evidence that OH and hydroperoxyl (HO2) chemistry is generally understood in clean, remote environments, but less well understood in cities when nitrogen oxide (NOx) levels are high. Other evidence indicates that OH is most poorly understood in low-NOx, high biogenic VOC (BVOC) environments, particularly forests where measured OH has greatly exceeded modeled OH by a factor of 2 to 10, well beyond the typical ±30% 2ó uncertainties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These forest environments are challenging the models, for which new oxidation mechanisms are being designed, and the measurements, which can have interferences and be near their detection limits. A previously suspected interference was recently confirmed for the combination of O3, OH, and alkenes in the Principal Investigator's (PI) laser-based Ground-based Hydrogen Oxides Sensor (GTHOS) by adding the ability to detect OH by chemical removal of OH (called OHchem) to the usual method wavelength modulation on and off an OH spectral line (called OHwave). Laboratory tests demonstrate that OHchem is the real OH for GTHOS.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will contribute measurements of OHchem, OHwave, HO2, alkene-based RO2, and OH reactivity to a multi-investigator study that will provide a consistent picture of the isoprene oxidation mechanism, demonstrate that OHchem is the real OH, and determine if the GTHOS OH interference is caused by an atmospherically relevant intermediate species. The PIs will also find the reason that GTHOS appears to be much more sensitive to this O3/OH/alkene interference than other OH-measuring instruments and to reduce that sensitivity if the interference is not atmospherically relevant. These goals of this two-year study will be accomplished primarily by participating with other groups who are proposing separately in a Focused Isoprene-chemistry eXperiment (FIX), which has a field component as part of the Secondary Organic Aerosol Study and a laboratory environmental chamber component. The results of this research will lead to improved oxidation mechanisms in the models that are used for regional and for global air quality, thus providing better guidance to policy makers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/28/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1246918</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Brune</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William H Brune</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>whb2@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148653286</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000366301</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/28/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>Atmospheric Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~283473</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Rural and remote forests have special atmospheric chemistry, one with copious emissions of biogenic volatile organic compounds (BVOC) from trees and low levels of the pollutants nitrogen oxides and ozone. Because forests cover 1/3 of Earth&rsquo;s land, this chemistry must be well understood in order to build predictive capability of the atmosphere&rsquo;s ability to cleanse itself. The atmosphere&rsquo;s main natural cleansing agent &ndash; hydroxyl (OH) &ndash; reacts rapidly with BVOCs and its abundance is reduced. Surprisingly, in several field studies, including some of ours, measured OH was several times larger than calculated with models. This disagreement led to speculation about mysterious additional OH sources in forests. Another possibility is that the OH measurements are wrong and have an interference. The Southern Oxidant and Aerosol Study (SOAS) in a rural Alabama forest and the follow-on FIX@CIT study in the Caltech environmental chamber provided excellent tests for the chemistry of isoprene, the most abundant BVOC, and for determining the identity of possible interferences. Using both our typical method for detecting OH and one in which OH is scavenged from the air before it is sampled, we show conclusively that the scavenging method measures the real OH; that measured and modeled OH are consistent; and that OH detected by our typical method has an interference. Using these data sets, we are honing in on the identity of this interference. The combined measurements of OH, hydroperoxyl (HO<sub>2</sub>), OH reactivity, and other chemical species provide evidence that there are no mysterious OH sources in this forest.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/25/2016<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;H&nbsp;Brune</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Rural and remote forests have special atmospheric chemistry, one with copious emissions of biogenic volatile organic compounds (BVOC) from trees and low levels of the pollutants nitrogen oxides and ozone. Because forests cover 1/3 of EarthÆs land, this chemistry must be well understood in order to build predictive capability of the atmosphereÆs ability to cleanse itself. The atmosphereÆs main natural cleansing agent &ndash; hydroxyl (OH) &ndash; reacts rapidly with BVOCs and its abundance is reduced. Surprisingly, in several field studies, including some of ours, measured OH was several times larger than calculated with models. This disagreement led to speculation about mysterious additional OH sources in forests. Another possibility is that the OH measurements are wrong and have an interference. The Southern Oxidant and Aerosol Study (SOAS) in a rural Alabama forest and the follow-on FIX@CIT study in the Caltech environmental chamber provided excellent tests for the chemistry of isoprene, the most abundant BVOC, and for determining the identity of possible interferences. Using both our typical method for detecting OH and one in which OH is scavenged from the air before it is sampled, we show conclusively that the scavenging method measures the real OH; that measured and modeled OH are consistent; and that OH detected by our typical method has an interference. Using these data sets, we are honing in on the identity of this interference. The combined measurements of OH, hydroperoxyl (HO2), OH reactivity, and other chemical species provide evidence that there are no mysterious OH sources in this forest.           Last Modified: 06/25/2016       Submitted by: William H Brune]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
