<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Southern Ocean in a Warming World: Winds, Carbon and Heat</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>323345.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>323345</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Milne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmilne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924714</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Southern Ocean surrounding Antarctica is the primary portal through which the vast volume of the intermediate, deep, and bottom waters of the global ocean interact with the surface and thus the global atmosphere. This region has a profound influence on the Earth's climate, oceanic circulation and ecosystems. Current modeling and observational studies suggest that, despite occupying just over a quarter of the surface ocean area:&lt;br/&gt;? the Southern Ocean accounts for up to half of the annual oceanic uptake of anthropogenic carbon dioxide from the atmosphere&lt;br/&gt;? the Southern Ocean accounts for about 70% ± 30% of the excess heat that is transferred from the atmosphere into the ocean each year; and&lt;br/&gt;? the Southern Ocean winds and buoyancy fluxes are the principal source of energy for driving the large-scale deep meridional overturning circulation throughout the global ocean.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are notable inconsistencies in the simulations of the circulation in this complex and underobserved region in the latest generation of EaSMs (earth systems models). These include the sensitivity of Southern Ocean circulation to changes in anthropogenic CO2 uptake, heat and wind variability. Westerly wind variability in turn has been linked to the state of the polar ozone hole. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project seeks to analyze the output of various IPCC-AR5 ESM runs to identify the strengths and weaknesses of the models in comparison with most recent data sources. Using two GFDL ESMs, four model sensitivity runs will also be conducted, which will seek to quantify the role of westerlies in the uptake of carbon and heat in the Southern Ocean.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1246247</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joellen</FirstName>
<LastName>Russell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joellen Russell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jrussell@geo.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206262194</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000410706</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072459266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[888 N Euclid Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANT Ocean &amp; Atmos Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~323345</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary goal of this project was to assess the role of the Southern Ocean in the global climate generally, and specifically, its role in the response of the climate system to increase greenhouse gas forcing especially with respect to the uptake of anthropogenic heat and carbon. Our main objective was to reduce our uncertainties in the projections of future climate. Our goals required activity on three separate fronts: 1) assess the suite of CMIP5 simulations and give a thorough analysis of the atmosphere, ocean, and carbon cycle in each; 2) quantify the uptake of heat and carbon by the ocean around Antarctica using new observational targets and diagnostics; and 3) carry out simulations using the GFDL ESMs to quantify and predict the role of the Westerlies on the fate of the Southern Ocean window to the deep ocean reservoir.</p> <p>We have achieved several of our goals: 1) we understand better the mechanisms that influence the uptake of heat and carbon by the Southern Ocean; and 2) we have quantified the specific details that lead to better/worse or larger/smaller changes in the uptake of anthropogenic heat and carbon in several of the CMIP5 simulations. The wind-sensitivity experiments will be completed at GFDL under the auspices of SOMIP, and due to its adoption into FAFMIP and the WCRP CMIP6 efforts, many climate modeling centers (NCAR, UKMO, CSIRO and others) have stated their intention to carry out the experiments instead of just GFDL.</p> <p>A paper titled, &ldquo;Metrics for the Evaluation of the Southern Ocean in Coupled Climate Models and Earth System Models&rdquo;, by Joellen L. Russell, Igor Kamenkovich, Cecilia Bitz, Raffaele Ferrari, Sarah Gille, Paul Goodman, Robert Hallberg, Kenneth Johnson, Karina Khazmutdinova, Irina Marinov, Matthew Mazloff, Jorge Sarmiento, Kevin Speer, Lynne Talley and Rik Wanninkhof, was accepted (pending minor revision) at the Journal of Geophysical Research &ndash; Oceans.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/13/2017<br>      Modified by: Joellen&nbsp;Russell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1246247/1246247_10264645_1510572300644_zonal_winds_final--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1246247/1246247_10264645_1510572300644_zonal_winds_final--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Annual-mean zonal wind stress (N/m2)"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1246247/1246247_10264645_1510572300644_zonal_winds_final--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Annual-mean zonal wind stress (N/m2)"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Annual-mean zonal wind stress (N/m2) from the reanalysis, the state estimate and from several of the coupled climate models submitted as part of the CMIP5/IPCC-AR5 process.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. Russell</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joellen&nbsp;Russell</div> <div class="imageTitle">Annual-mean zonal wind stress (N/m2)</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of this project was to assess the role of the Southern Ocean in the global climate generally, and specifically, its role in the response of the climate system to increase greenhouse gas forcing especially with respect to the uptake of anthropogenic heat and carbon. Our main objective was to reduce our uncertainties in the projections of future climate. Our goals required activity on three separate fronts: 1) assess the suite of CMIP5 simulations and give a thorough analysis of the atmosphere, ocean, and carbon cycle in each; 2) quantify the uptake of heat and carbon by the ocean around Antarctica using new observational targets and diagnostics; and 3) carry out simulations using the GFDL ESMs to quantify and predict the role of the Westerlies on the fate of the Southern Ocean window to the deep ocean reservoir.  We have achieved several of our goals: 1) we understand better the mechanisms that influence the uptake of heat and carbon by the Southern Ocean; and 2) we have quantified the specific details that lead to better/worse or larger/smaller changes in the uptake of anthropogenic heat and carbon in several of the CMIP5 simulations. The wind-sensitivity experiments will be completed at GFDL under the auspices of SOMIP, and due to its adoption into FAFMIP and the WCRP CMIP6 efforts, many climate modeling centers (NCAR, UKMO, CSIRO and others) have stated their intention to carry out the experiments instead of just GFDL.  A paper titled, "Metrics for the Evaluation of the Southern Ocean in Coupled Climate Models and Earth System Models", by Joellen L. Russell, Igor Kamenkovich, Cecilia Bitz, Raffaele Ferrari, Sarah Gille, Paul Goodman, Robert Hallberg, Kenneth Johnson, Karina Khazmutdinova, Irina Marinov, Matthew Mazloff, Jorge Sarmiento, Kevin Speer, Lynne Talley and Rik Wanninkhof, was accepted (pending minor revision) at the Journal of Geophysical Research &ndash; Oceans.          Last Modified: 11/13/2017       Submitted by: Joellen Russell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
