<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: CC-NIE Integration: An Open Cloud Infrastructure for Scalable Data Intensive Collaboration</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>569522.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>569522</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>By all accounts, the size of the data flows pulsing out of new instruments, sensor networks and massive simulations continues to escalate dramatically. Consequently many researchers in large national and international collaborations, sitting in different administrative domains, spread across the wide area network, and using diverse local resources, are likely to find that the data sets of most current interest are not where they need to be, when they need to be there, for their work to proceed efficiently. It is clear that an adequate cyberinfrastructure strategy for campus level bridging must address such critical problems in the area of data logistics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project creates a Data Logistics Toolkit (DLT) - an easy to install package of production quality software for building WAN-enabled storage nodes that dramatically improve the ability of data intensive research communities to collaborate in the wide area. DLT-enabled services (e.g. a global "drop box" for research that supports automatic data positioning) enable the automation and optimization of the timely placement of data across a wide range of scenarios, using policy-controlled sharing, replication, caching, control loop optimization and overlay multicast. Offering familiar user and programming interfaces, and backed by a solid but scalable security framework, the DLT transforms global data-intensive collaboration by providing a generic interface to an essential logistical resource - storage - and by giving campuses with DLT-enabled nodes the network awareness and adaptivity needed to maximize the productivity of their wide area links to distributed data and computing resources.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1246282</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Swany</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas M Swany</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>swany@iu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128567795</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000347755</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[509 E. 3rd St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~569522</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The escalation of data intensive research, and the proliferation of highly distributed collaboration in nearly every field of science have combined to make data management and movement increasingly problematic.&nbsp; The goal of this project was the production of an easy-to-install, easy-to-use software system for data logistics, called the Data Logistics Toolkit (DLT).&nbsp; Logistics is defined as &ldquo;the time sensitive positioning of goods and services&rdquo; or the &ldquo;detailed coordination of a complex operation involving many people, facilities, or supplies&rdquo;.&nbsp; The basis of our data logistics approach is to consider network-centric cyberinfrastructure in which the &ldquo;goods&rdquo; are data.&nbsp; As such, we have developed models and software infrastructure for the coordination, positioning and distribution of data for various applications, packaged in a set of building blocks that comprise the DLT.</p> <p>Various data logistics software components were integrated to become the DLT and the system was packaged for distribution in "shrink-wrapped" form. The Toolkit has guided installers and can configure itself to be usable as a platform for high-performance data sharing over high-speed research and education networks, as well as providing components that can be leveraged by other science applications and frameworks.&nbsp; Instances of the Toolkit will boot, automatically configure themselves, register themselves with a global discovery service, and become immediately useable as logistical data resources.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong> The DLT integrates a set of storage and networking technologies to create network-aware storage nodes that dramatically improve the ability of data intensive research communities to collaborate in the wide area.&nbsp; The components of the DLT, and the research embodied in those components, decomposes storage software systems into fundamental elements and enables those components to be synthesized into many different types of storage services.&nbsp; DLT-enabled services, like a global &ldquo;drop box&rdquo; for research that supports automatic data positioning, enable automation and optimization of rapid movement and timely placement of data, across a wide range of scenarios, through policy-controlled sharing, replication, caching, control loop optimization and overlay multicast. The impact of the DLT on data-intensive campus bridging infrastructure builds on the fact that its components have been created and tested over several years of largely NSF funded research and infrastructure building by PIs Swany, Beck and Sheldon.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact</strong> &ndash; The DLT transforms global data-intensive collaboration by providing a generic interface to an essential logistical resource &ndash; storage &ndash; and by giving campuses with DLT-enabled nodes the network awareness and adaptivity needed to maximize the productivity of their wide area links to national and international data and computing resources.</p> <p>The Earth Observation Depot Network (EODN) is a collaboration among the United States Geological Survey (USGS), AmericaView and the DLT development team.&nbsp; EODN is designed to expand use of large remote sensing datasets by timely distribution and removing access barriers inherent in current distribution schemes.&nbsp; EODN is focused on three prevailing issues plaguing the remote sensing community:&nbsp; availability latency &ndash; the delay between acquisition and availability of data, download speed &ndash; exacerbated in some cases by rate-limiting policies of large satellite data providers, and connectivity, particularly in areas of sub-standard or damaged infrastructure.</p> <p>The DLT and EODN have facilitated the juxtaposition of land remote sensing data (Landsat 8) with coincident (in space and time) atmospheric remote sensing data (GOES series) by cutting the latency ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The escalation of data intensive research, and the proliferation of highly distributed collaboration in nearly every field of science have combined to make data management and movement increasingly problematic.  The goal of this project was the production of an easy-to-install, easy-to-use software system for data logistics, called the Data Logistics Toolkit (DLT).  Logistics is defined as "the time sensitive positioning of goods and services" or the "detailed coordination of a complex operation involving many people, facilities, or supplies".  The basis of our data logistics approach is to consider network-centric cyberinfrastructure in which the "goods" are data.  As such, we have developed models and software infrastructure for the coordination, positioning and distribution of data for various applications, packaged in a set of building blocks that comprise the DLT.  Various data logistics software components were integrated to become the DLT and the system was packaged for distribution in "shrink-wrapped" form. The Toolkit has guided installers and can configure itself to be usable as a platform for high-performance data sharing over high-speed research and education networks, as well as providing components that can be leveraged by other science applications and frameworks.  Instances of the Toolkit will boot, automatically configure themselves, register themselves with a global discovery service, and become immediately useable as logistical data resources.  Intellectual Merit The DLT integrates a set of storage and networking technologies to create network-aware storage nodes that dramatically improve the ability of data intensive research communities to collaborate in the wide area.  The components of the DLT, and the research embodied in those components, decomposes storage software systems into fundamental elements and enables those components to be synthesized into many different types of storage services.  DLT-enabled services, like a global "drop box" for research that supports automatic data positioning, enable automation and optimization of rapid movement and timely placement of data, across a wide range of scenarios, through policy-controlled sharing, replication, caching, control loop optimization and overlay multicast. The impact of the DLT on data-intensive campus bridging infrastructure builds on the fact that its components have been created and tested over several years of largely NSF funded research and infrastructure building by PIs Swany, Beck and Sheldon.  Broader Impact &ndash; The DLT transforms global data-intensive collaboration by providing a generic interface to an essential logistical resource &ndash; storage &ndash; and by giving campuses with DLT-enabled nodes the network awareness and adaptivity needed to maximize the productivity of their wide area links to national and international data and computing resources.  The Earth Observation Depot Network (EODN) is a collaboration among the United States Geological Survey (USGS), AmericaView and the DLT development team.  EODN is designed to expand use of large remote sensing datasets by timely distribution and removing access barriers inherent in current distribution schemes.  EODN is focused on three prevailing issues plaguing the remote sensing community:  availability latency &ndash; the delay between acquisition and availability of data, download speed &ndash; exacerbated in some cases by rate-limiting policies of large satellite data providers, and connectivity, particularly in areas of sub-standard or damaged infrastructure.  The DLT and EODN have facilitated the juxtaposition of land remote sensing data (Landsat 8) with coincident (in space and time) atmospheric remote sensing data (GOES series) by cutting the latency of Landsat 8 imagery access from 24 hours to as little as six hours.  The spatial resolution and spectral qualities of Landsat 8 imagery are useful to atmospheric scientists, but only if they can receive the imagery quickly ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
