<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>INSPIRE:   Executive Function and Conceptual Change</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>799862.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>799862</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chalandra Bryant</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This INSPIRE award is partially funded by the Developmental and Learning Sciences Program in the Division of Behavioral and Cognitive Sciences in the Directorate for Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences, and by the Research and Evaluation on Education in Science and Engineering Program in the Division of Research on Learning in Formal and Informal Settings in the Directorate for Education and Human Resources. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project explores the effects of Executive Function on the child's developing understanding of biology and mathematics.  Executive Function refers to a suite of mechanisms that underlie flexible thinking and higher-order cognition. Among these functions are Working Memory, the ability to hold information in memory and actively manipulate it (for example, to listen to a string of words and then say them out loud in backwards order);  Inhibition, the ability to suppress a strong and well-learned response in favor of a weaker or novel response (for example, in a game where you must say "moon" when presented with a drawing of the sun, and "sun" when presented with a drawing of the moon); and Set shifting, the ability to switch from one task goal to another (for example, to sort a deck of pictures one way (say, by shape), and then another (say, by color).  Recent findings suggest that Executive Function tests strongly predict children's success in school in every year from kindergarten through high school, but researchers still don't know why.  Using newly developed methods of manipulating the individual child's available Executive Function resources over brief durations (either increasing or decreasing the available capacity), the investigators will measure the effects of these manipulations on performance in biological and mathematical reasoning. The researchers will examine EF's effect on two independent abilities: first, the ability to express knowledge one already has; and second, the very ability to learn a theory to begin with; that is, the ability to undergo conceptual change. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research in education, developmental psychology, and neuroscience have all converged on the importance of Executive Function in learning and reasoning.  Specifying just how these mechanisms influence conceptual change, how they allow learning to take place, could prove transformative to both cognitive development and math/science education. Moreover, this research could have far-reaching importance to populations with particularly weak EF: children with ADHD (a population included in the present project), poor children, the elderly, patients with Alzheimer's disease, and many others. The relationship between EF and conceptual change appears to be powerful. The goal of this investigation is to begin to discover why.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1247396</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Carey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Carey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scarey@wjh.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174953896</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000290428</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
<LastName>Zaitchik</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deborah Zaitchik</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dzaitchiksamet@partners.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6177265571</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508028</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University Psychology Department]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021382044</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[33 Kirkland Street, Rm. 1170]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1698</Code>
<Text>DS -Developmental Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7625</Code>
<Text>REAL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8078</Code>
<Text>INSPIRE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1698</Code>
<Text>DS-Developmental Sciences</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8653</Code>
<Text>INSPIRE Track-1 Creative</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~799862</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;This project identifies several learning mechanisms that underlie the astonishing human ability to construct and use theories. Our findings provide clear evidence of a critical role played by a particular suite of cognitive mechanisms together known as Executive Function. We have demonstrated the importance of Executive Function in the construction and use of several different childhood theories, including intuitive theories of biology, physics, and psychology. We have also demonstrated the same relationship between Executive Function and theoretical knowledge in several different populations &ndash; preschoolers, 6 year olds, young adults, elderly adults. At every age investigated, individuals&rsquo; Executive Function scores predict their performance on tasks that measure theoretical knowledge.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This research is clearly critical to developmental psychological science. Moreover, its impact on society lies in its potential application to education.&nbsp; Executive Function scores in very young children have been shown to highly predict success decades later in every aspect of life from academic achievement to marital satisfaction to salary to rates of incarceration, and on and on. &nbsp;We have discovered <em>one</em> way it does that:&nbsp;it underlies the ability to construct and use the intuitive theories with which we understand the world. It underlies our ability to come up with causal-explanatory knowledge with which to explain the myriad phenomena we come across in our daily lives.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This view of Executive Function processes as enabling learning mechanisms provides a new way to understand individual differences in children's abilities to learn, both inside and outside the classroom. Moreover, it may be key to designing more successful curricula, particularly for children with social and economic disadvantages.&nbsp; Such children arrive at kindergarten with weak Executive Function, putting them at a great risk for early failure at school.&nbsp;Since there is some evidence that Executive Function may be malleable, it may well be feasible to increase the strength of their learning mechanisms, putting them on a more equal footing with their more advantaged classmates.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/06/2017<br>      Modified by: Deborah&nbsp;Zaitchik</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[             This project identifies several learning mechanisms that underlie the astonishing human ability to construct and use theories. Our findings provide clear evidence of a critical role played by a particular suite of cognitive mechanisms together known as Executive Function. We have demonstrated the importance of Executive Function in the construction and use of several different childhood theories, including intuitive theories of biology, physics, and psychology. We have also demonstrated the same relationship between Executive Function and theoretical knowledge in several different populations &ndash; preschoolers, 6 year olds, young adults, elderly adults. At every age investigated, individuals? Executive Function scores predict their performance on tasks that measure theoretical knowledge.              This research is clearly critical to developmental psychological science. Moreover, its impact on society lies in its potential application to education.  Executive Function scores in very young children have been shown to highly predict success decades later in every aspect of life from academic achievement to marital satisfaction to salary to rates of incarceration, and on and on.  We have discovered one way it does that: it underlies the ability to construct and use the intuitive theories with which we understand the world. It underlies our ability to come up with causal-explanatory knowledge with which to explain the myriad phenomena we come across in our daily lives.              This view of Executive Function processes as enabling learning mechanisms provides a new way to understand individual differences in children's abilities to learn, both inside and outside the classroom. Moreover, it may be key to designing more successful curricula, particularly for children with social and economic disadvantages.  Such children arrive at kindergarten with weak Executive Function, putting them at a great risk for early failure at school. Since there is some evidence that Executive Function may be malleable, it may well be feasible to increase the strength of their learning mechanisms, putting them on a more equal footing with their more advantaged classmates.                Last Modified: 12/06/2017       Submitted by: Deborah Zaitchik]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
