<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Creating an Online Interactive Earth Science Environmental Simulator</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>144538.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>144538</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Glenn H. Larsen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovative Research Program Phase I project will develop a unique interactive online earth science educational tool that will meet current shortfalls in teaching earth sciences and related engineering technologies. This innovation will allow a learner to conduct realistic simulated experiments concerning hydrological and atmospheric processes and their interactions with underlying surface characteristics of the earth. The system will be called the Earth Science Environmental Simulator (ESES) and will provide a substantial benefit for teaching a broad range of science, technology, engineering and math (STEM) skills and concepts in an interdisciplinary approach. Applications will include renewable energy, agricultural management, building/sensor design, climate change impact and emergency management. This technology overcomes the significant problem related to a lack of realistic applications for teaching the processes important to the earth sciences. These processes are extremely intricate, complex and powerful affect every person on our planet. The research objectives are to 1) create a cost effective online educational prototype tool, 2) investigate and create intuitive interface and visualization tools and 3) do a limited educational evaluation in order to determine the ESES educational and commercial potential. The software innovation at the core of this system is a series of physics based earth science and application models. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is brought on by the fact that the educational process in the earth sciences has been hampered because the earth-atmospheric system cannot be brought into the classroom to study and manipulate. The proposed project has the capability to greatly improve this situation by bringing true earth-scientific experimentation to learners. The anticipated far-reaching benefits of this research are that all learners will further develop: (1) problem-solving and decision making capabilities essential to every citizen in a modern society that are fundamentally governed by processes that obey the laws of physics to include the knowledge of the earth science and their application such as meteorology, hydrology, oceanography, geology, energy production and management, regional and global climate change, forensic meteorology (insurance and legal claims), agriculture, and even other planets just to name a few; (2) cognizance of strengths and limitations of science capabilities, especially related to earth science; and (3) awareness of relevance of short term environmental forecasts, e.g. severe weather, flooding, forest fires movement, toxic material dispersion, to personal safety.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/01/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/01/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1248765</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Glenn</FirstName>
<LastName>Van Knowe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Glenn E Van Knowe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gevanknowe@meso.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5182835169</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000092015</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/01/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>MESOSCALE ENVIRONMENTAL SIMULATIONS AND OPERATIONS, INC</Name>
<CityName>TROY</CityName>
<ZipCode>121800761</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182835169</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>185 JORDAN RD STE 8</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>151881349</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MESOSCALE ENVIRONMENTAL SIMULATIONS AND OPERATIONS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[MESOSCALE ENVIRONMENTAL SIMULATIONS AND OPERATIONS, INC]]></Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121808343</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[185 Jordan Rd suite 8]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>Education Products</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8039</Code>
<Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~144538</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This final report summarizes the work performed for the National Science Foundation Phase I Small Business Innovation Research grant entitled &ldquo;Creating an Online Interactive Earth Science Environmental Simulator&rdquo; (ESES).&nbsp; In the US, there is a shortfall in teaching science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) related subjects. The objectives for this project were to address this shortfall by studying the 1) technical feasibility and 2) commercial potential of developing an innovative online earth science educational tool.&nbsp; The objectives were met by creating a proof-of-concept prototype and then performing a limited in-class educational evaluation to assess the educational and commercial potential.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp; This innovation will help prepare students for living and working in the 21st century by allowing students from grades 6 to the undergraduate college level to conduct realistic simulated experiments and role-playing exercises concerning earth system processes. It is important to keep in mind that the earth system processes are intricate, complex and powerful---and affect every person on our planet. In addition to addressing the intricate earth science concepts, ESES uses basic elements of games and social interaction to help keep the learning fun and engaging.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; ESES consists of two main branches, the Virtual Earth Lab (VEL) branch and the Interactive Case Study (ICS) branch. The software innovation at the core of this system is using physics-based earth science models combined with data visualization and analysis tools.&nbsp; For many years research scientists and graduate students have used physics-based earth science models to do realistic virtual experimentation of the earth ocean-atmosphere system. Now these intricate models will be accessible to a wider group. The key to making both the virtual laboratories and case studies usable for 21st century education is building the proper online interfaces and analysis tools. Along with the VEL and the ICS branches there are modules to allow teachers to modify the experiments and exercises. For both students and teachers there are interactive instructions.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;This multipurpose tool allows students to conduct inquiry-based interactive experiments and realistic role-playing exercises. The VEL allows students to perform realistic virtual experimentation of the earth ocean-atmosphere system.&nbsp; The teaching strategies used in the VEL are based on the investigation of questions, scenarios or problems. The ICS presents various engineering disciplines as they relate to atmospheric, hydrological, and geological processes. The ICS puts students in realistic occupational simulations to learn concepts and decision-making skills in environmentally sensitive occupations such as energy management, emergency management, agriculture and forensic meteorology.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;This teaching technology overcomes the significant problem in teaching earth science of not being able to bring the earth science systems into a standard lab. This project has the capability to greatly improve this situation by bringing true earth system experimentation to students. The new tools provide a substantial benefit for teaching a broad range of STEM skills and concepts that integrate concepts across different disciplines. Applications of ESES include renewable energy management, agricultural management, climate change impact, forensic meteorology (for insurance and legal claims), and emergency management.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;The anticipated far-reaching benefits of this research are that students will further develop (1) problem-solving and decision-making capabilities in the earth sciences that are essenti...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[        This final report summarizes the work performed for the National Science Foundation Phase I Small Business Innovation Research grant entitled "Creating an Online Interactive Earth Science Environmental Simulator" (ESES).  In the US, there is a shortfall in teaching science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) related subjects. The objectives for this project were to address this shortfall by studying the 1) technical feasibility and 2) commercial potential of developing an innovative online earth science educational tool.  The objectives were met by creating a proof-of-concept prototype and then performing a limited in-class educational evaluation to assess the educational and commercial potential.        This innovation will help prepare students for living and working in the 21st century by allowing students from grades 6 to the undergraduate college level to conduct realistic simulated experiments and role-playing exercises concerning earth system processes. It is important to keep in mind that the earth system processes are intricate, complex and powerful---and affect every person on our planet. In addition to addressing the intricate earth science concepts, ESES uses basic elements of games and social interaction to help keep the learning fun and engaging.        ESES consists of two main branches, the Virtual Earth Lab (VEL) branch and the Interactive Case Study (ICS) branch. The software innovation at the core of this system is using physics-based earth science models combined with data visualization and analysis tools.  For many years research scientists and graduate students have used physics-based earth science models to do realistic virtual experimentation of the earth ocean-atmosphere system. Now these intricate models will be accessible to a wider group. The key to making both the virtual laboratories and case studies usable for 21st century education is building the proper online interfaces and analysis tools. Along with the VEL and the ICS branches there are modules to allow teachers to modify the experiments and exercises. For both students and teachers there are interactive instructions.         This multipurpose tool allows students to conduct inquiry-based interactive experiments and realistic role-playing exercises. The VEL allows students to perform realistic virtual experimentation of the earth ocean-atmosphere system.  The teaching strategies used in the VEL are based on the investigation of questions, scenarios or problems. The ICS presents various engineering disciplines as they relate to atmospheric, hydrological, and geological processes. The ICS puts students in realistic occupational simulations to learn concepts and decision-making skills in environmentally sensitive occupations such as energy management, emergency management, agriculture and forensic meteorology.         This teaching technology overcomes the significant problem in teaching earth science of not being able to bring the earth science systems into a standard lab. This project has the capability to greatly improve this situation by bringing true earth system experimentation to students. The new tools provide a substantial benefit for teaching a broad range of STEM skills and concepts that integrate concepts across different disciplines. Applications of ESES include renewable energy management, agricultural management, climate change impact, forensic meteorology (for insurance and legal claims), and emergency management.         The anticipated far-reaching benefits of this research are that students will further develop (1) problem-solving and decision-making capabilities in the earth sciences that are essential in our modern society, (2) an increased understanding of the strengths and limitations of science capabilities, particularly computer modeling, and (3) an awareness of the importance of short term environmental forecasts to personal safety, e.g. severe weather, flooding, and forest fires.        Last Modified: 08...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
