<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Subduction Zone Flight Recorders: Integrating P-T-t-f Histories of Subduction and Exhumation of Eclogite through Microanalysis of Garnet and its Inclusions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>174794.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>174794</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030107</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonia Esperanca</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The recycling of oceanic crust into the mantle through subduction is ultimately responsible for the formation of the Earth's continental crust through arc magmatism. The origin of these magmatic processes is thought to be the melting of mantle rocks under volcanic arcs triggered by the release of fluids from the subducting oceanic slab. The composition of the fluids ultimately responsible for this magmatism is the subject of much research, including the study of the metamorphic byproducts of subduction that are occasionally returned to the surface. These garnet-bearing metamorphic rocks (eclogite) are the only samples of material that have been subducted to great depth, but are available for study. Although eclogite can preserve a record of fluids from subduction zones, it is difficult to determine whether the fluid record preserved in these rocks comes from deep in the subduction zone, or is a result of their exhumation. The research funded by this grant will tie the record of fluids preserved in the oxygen isotope composition of garnets that grew during subduction with the pressure and temperature conditions recorded by the chemical composition of the garnets, generating an integrated tectonic and fluid record for these rocks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Chemically zoned garnets and mineral inclusions entrapped during their growth have been shown to preserve pressure and temperature information from both the subduction of ocean crust and exhumation of eclogite. Slow intragranular diffusion of oxygen in garnet suggests that these garnets will preserve the &amp;#948;18O of fluids in equilibrium with the garnet along these paths as well. New advances in ion microprobe technique now allow the &amp;#948;18O of garnet to be measured in situ with high precision. By integrating in situ &amp;#948;18O analysis of garnet with existing and new quantitative prograde and retrograde P-T-fO2 information and texturally guided geochronology, this study will generate the first detailed P-T-t-f paths for eclogite and related rocks formed in subduction zones.  These histories will allow samples of eclogite to serve as probes into the tectonic and fluid conditions of the fore-arc and subduction channel environment of fossil subduction zones. The integrated nature of these data will tie information on fluids directly to the tectonic evolution of these rocks, and allow them to be used to test a number of hypotheses regarding the nature and timing of the fluid record preserved by exhumed subduction-zone metamorphic rocks. Comparison of data sets between rocks with sedimentary and igneous protoliths found in mélange zones and in coherent fault bounded blocks will offer insight into the timing of their juxtaposition, and will allow existing geochemical studies to be tied to a common tectonic and thermal framework.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1249778</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>F. Zeb</FirstName>
<LastName>Page</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>F. Zeb Page</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zeb.page@oberlin.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4407756701</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000497432</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oberlin College</Name>
<CityName>Oberlin</CityName>
<ZipCode>440741090</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4407758461</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 N. Professor Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Room 100]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068911908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OBERLIN COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068911908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oberlin College]]></Name>
<CityName>Oberlin</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>440741090</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[52 W. Lorain St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~122542</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~52252</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The rocks that make up the continents on our planet are initially formed by arcs of volcanoes, such as the Cascades. These volcanoes are found above subduction zones - places where the dense rocks that form the ocean floor sink back down into the Earth&rsquo;s mantle. It is impossible to directly observe the processes by which subduction triggers the melting that forms these volcanoes. However, the geochemistry of the volcanic products of arcs has long implicated fluids liberated from the metamorphism of the sinking oceanic slab as the cause of this volcanism, and the growth of the planet&rsquo;s continents. Occasionally, pieces of the subducting ocean floor (volcanic rocks and overlying sediments) break off of the downgoing slab and are returned to the surface near where they were first buried. During their subduction, these rocks were metamorphosed, growing new minerals, such as garnet, because of the increased pressure and temperature during their burial. In order to get a better understanding of the deep fluids responsible for subduction metamorphism, a number of scientists have been studying the geochemistry of these metamorphic rocks, looking for traces of these important fluids better understand the processes responsible for continental growth. One potential problem with this approach is that the metamorphic rocks likely encounter different fluids as they are returned to the surface&hellip;how do we ensure that the fluids we are studying are those deep fluids responsible for volcanism and continental growth?The research funded by this grant attempts to solve this problem by integrating the fluid record preserved in these rocks with their metamorphic history preserved in the mineral garnet. We analyzed samples from the Franciscan Complex of Northern California, and from Santa Catalina Island near Los Angeles, both locales where&nbsp; rocks formed in subduction zones are well-known to contain evidence of subduction fluids. As the ocean floor rocks are buried and metamorphosed, garnet grows, preserving a geochemical history of the rock in the form of concentric rings of subtly changing mineral chemistry, analogous to the record of climate preserved in tree rings. Garnet is a particularly resilient mineral that retains its original chemistry even if the rest of the rock is altered by later fluids.&nbsp; The chemical history in the garnets is recorded in major elements (measured by electron-beam microprobes), trace elements (measured by laser-beam mass-spectrometer microprobes), and stable oxygen isotopes (a powerful tracer of the origins of fluids, measured by ion-beam microprobes). All of these measurements were made on tiny, &lt;30&micro;m pits across the garnets, often in the same locations. These geochemical records of fluids are put into a chronology of garnet growth based on their position relative to the centers of the crystals, and in the context of the pressure-temperature evolution of the rock by using thermodynamic models to predict the conditions of the rock&rsquo;s formation based on its chemistry.&nbsp; We found several interesting and provocative results in our work:Metamorphosed sediments from Catalina record dramatic evidence of fluid flow from their burial, near the peak of their metamorphism, whereas metamorphosed volcanic rocks from the island preserve no evidence of deep fluid interaction in their garnets. However, the volcanic rocks have garnet-bearing rinds of material that formed during their return to the surface, and those rinds contain garnets that record a complicated series of fluid and mechanical mixing events that took place during uplift. Metamorphosed volcanic rocks from Northern California also show no evidence of external fluid interaction during their burial, but have complicated records of fluid interaction late in their history.&nbsp;The data collection in this project was almost entirely completed by 15 undergraduate students, who gained important skills in scientific planning, observation, analysis, and presentation. Oberlin College has longstanding traditions of excellence in both scientific training and inclusivity, and it is significant that 3/4 of the students involved are women, who remain underrepresented in geochemistry. To date, the research has been shared with the scientific community in 16 presentations at national and international conferences, 14 of those with undergraduate student presenters and lead authors.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2018<br>      Modified by: F. Zeb&nbsp;Page</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The rocks that make up the continents on our planet are initially formed by arcs of volcanoes, such as the Cascades. These volcanoes are found above subduction zones - places where the dense rocks that form the ocean floor sink back down into the Earth?s mantle. It is impossible to directly observe the processes by which subduction triggers the melting that forms these volcanoes. However, the geochemistry of the volcanic products of arcs has long implicated fluids liberated from the metamorphism of the sinking oceanic slab as the cause of this volcanism, and the growth of the planet?s continents. Occasionally, pieces of the subducting ocean floor (volcanic rocks and overlying sediments) break off of the downgoing slab and are returned to the surface near where they were first buried. During their subduction, these rocks were metamorphosed, growing new minerals, such as garnet, because of the increased pressure and temperature during their burial. In order to get a better understanding of the deep fluids responsible for subduction metamorphism, a number of scientists have been studying the geochemistry of these metamorphic rocks, looking for traces of these important fluids better understand the processes responsible for continental growth. One potential problem with this approach is that the metamorphic rocks likely encounter different fluids as they are returned to the surface&hellip;how do we ensure that the fluids we are studying are those deep fluids responsible for volcanism and continental growth?The research funded by this grant attempts to solve this problem by integrating the fluid record preserved in these rocks with their metamorphic history preserved in the mineral garnet. We analyzed samples from the Franciscan Complex of Northern California, and from Santa Catalina Island near Los Angeles, both locales where  rocks formed in subduction zones are well-known to contain evidence of subduction fluids. As the ocean floor rocks are buried and metamorphosed, garnet grows, preserving a geochemical history of the rock in the form of concentric rings of subtly changing mineral chemistry, analogous to the record of climate preserved in tree rings. Garnet is a particularly resilient mineral that retains its original chemistry even if the rest of the rock is altered by later fluids.  The chemical history in the garnets is recorded in major elements (measured by electron-beam microprobes), trace elements (measured by laser-beam mass-spectrometer microprobes), and stable oxygen isotopes (a powerful tracer of the origins of fluids, measured by ion-beam microprobes). All of these measurements were made on tiny, &lt;30&micro;m pits across the garnets, often in the same locations. These geochemical records of fluids are put into a chronology of garnet growth based on their position relative to the centers of the crystals, and in the context of the pressure-temperature evolution of the rock by using thermodynamic models to predict the conditions of the rock?s formation based on its chemistry.  We found several interesting and provocative results in our work:Metamorphosed sediments from Catalina record dramatic evidence of fluid flow from their burial, near the peak of their metamorphism, whereas metamorphosed volcanic rocks from the island preserve no evidence of deep fluid interaction in their garnets. However, the volcanic rocks have garnet-bearing rinds of material that formed during their return to the surface, and those rinds contain garnets that record a complicated series of fluid and mechanical mixing events that took place during uplift. Metamorphosed volcanic rocks from Northern California also show no evidence of external fluid interaction during their burial, but have complicated records of fluid interaction late in their history. The data collection in this project was almost entirely completed by 15 undergraduate students, who gained important skills in scientific planning, observation, analysis, and presentation. Oberlin College has longstanding traditions of excellence in both scientific training and inclusivity, and it is significant that 3/4 of the students involved are women, who remain underrepresented in geochemistry. To date, the research has been shared with the scientific community in 16 presentations at national and international conferences, 14 of those with undergraduate student presenters and lead authors.       Last Modified: 05/29/2018       Submitted by: F. Zeb Page]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
