<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Physical Links between Coronal Mass Ejection (CME) Velocity and Source Region Parameters</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>390444.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>390444</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020203</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Meriwether</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmeriwet@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927212</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Principal Investigator (PI) and his team will investigate the physical relationship between the height profile (or decay index) of the magnetic flux in the corona above a given solar source region and the known 'torus instability' of magnetic flux ropes. They intend to establish that this interaction provides a key link between the magnetic structure of the source region of a coronal mass ejection (CME) and that CME's ultimate eruption velocity. The team expects to determine that this physical influence affects the coronal field's polarity structure at great heights, as well as the association of CME velocity with solar source region size and complexity, the occurrence of precursor CMEs, and the Sun's large-scale coronal density structure. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI's parametric numerical investigation will quantify how the height profile and the coronal density structure control the peak rise velocity of unstable magnetic flux ropes, which represent the erupting magnetic flux in CMEs. The steepness of the height profile will be investigated in relation to the structure of the photospheric field while considering bipolar, quadrupolar, and more complex flux distributions, in order to establish quantitative dependencies of the CME velocity on the directly observable source region parameters. These results will be verified by several means, including numerical modeling of selected CME events under realistic thermal and magnetic conditions with events covering a range of moderate to extremely high velocities, and statistical studies of CME velocities that will include, for the first time, the height profiles of the coronal magnetic field (obtained by extrapolations) and newly identified source region parameters. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The peak CME velocity in the solar corona is a key parameter for effective space weather forecasting, since the arrival time and potential impact of CMEs may threaten the nation's astronauts, satellites, and ground-based technologies. This project will build research infrastructure in solar physics by creating a new partnership between Predictive Science, Inc. (PSI) and George Mason University (GMU). These research results will be broadly disseminated in the refereed literature as well as at science workshops and conferences. A catalog of studied CME events, including source region parameters, field extrapolations, and height profiles, will be provided on PSI and GMU web pages for community access, and the PI's simulation output will also be made available upon request. This project will train a graduate student at GMU and support the professional development of a postdoctoral solar physicist at PSI.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1249270</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jie</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jie Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jzhang7@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7039931998</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000229995</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bernhard</FirstName>
<LastName>Kliem</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bernhard Kliem</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bkliem@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7039932295</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000557706</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tibor</FirstName>
<LastName>Torok</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tibor Torok</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tibor@predsci.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8584509504</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000599265</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cooper</FirstName>
<LastName>Downs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cooper Downs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cdowns@predsci.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3039993800</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000622936</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Predictive Science Incorporated</Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<ZipCode>921213933</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3039993801</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9990 Mesa Rim Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 170]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>52</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA52</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>824866045</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PREDICTIVE SCIENCE INCORPORATED</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Predictive Science Incorporated]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921213933</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9990 Mesa Rim Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>52</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA52</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1523</Code>
<Text>SOLAR-TERRESTRIAL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~126763</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~130116</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~133565</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Coronal mass ejections (CMEs) are large "bubbles" of plasma and magnetic field that are ejected from the Sun's outer atmosphere, the corona. CMEs are one of the largest energy-release events in the solar system. These huge eruptions liberate energies in excess of ten thousand times the world's annual total energy consumption. CMEs travel at millions of miles per hour, the fastest ones reaching Earth in less than a day. When they impact Earth's magnetosphere they can trigger large geomagnetic storms, which damage satellites in space and even power grids on the ground. Figure 1 illustrates the arrival of a CME at Earth. The top panel shows a numerical simulation of a CME performed by our group at Predictive Science Inc.; the bottom panel shows the speed of the real event as it passes Earth.</p> <p>The propagation speed is one of the main parameters that determine a CME's impact upon arrival at Earth (others are the plasma density and the magnetic-field strength and orientation). CME speeds, however, vary within a wide range (about 100 - 3500 km/s in the corona), and at present it is not understood which conditions determine the CME speed. This lack of knowledge impedes our abilities to forecast the strength of space-weather disturbances caused by CMEs.</p> <p>The overarching goal of this project has been to improve our understanding of the physical mechanisms and conditions that determine CME speeds. Our combined numerical and data analysis techniques build on the conception that the torus instability of a magnetic flux rope (Kliem &amp; T&ouml;r&ouml;k 2006) is the main CME initiation and acceleration mechanism (supported by magnetic reconnection below the erupting rope), and that the height profile of the ambient coronal magnetic field is key in determining the strength and duration of the acceleration, i.e., the final CME speed.</p> <p>For our data analysis, we considered a sample of 15 very fast CMEs (&gt; 1500 km/s) and 22 events with speeds below this limit. For each source region, we produced a model of the local coronal magnetic field (which cannot be measured directly), using a potential-field extrapolation technique. We then quantified the height profile of the field at several locations in the center of the source region (Figure 2), using the so-called decay index n(h). Finally, we correlated its slope, dn/dh, averaged over a certain height range above the onset height of the torus instability, with the observed CME speed (Figure 3).</p> <p>We first found a strong correlation (70&ndash;80 %) for fast CMEs (&gt; 1500 km/s), but practically no correlation for the whole sample. However, close inspection of the n(h) profiles revealed a strong dip at larger heights in the corona for some cases (Figure 4, right), meaning that the magnetic field decays much slower above a certain height. This happens if a strong field is present above the source region of the eruption. We thus conjectured that such an overlying field acts as a "net" that significantly reduces the acceleration, leading to a final CME speed smaller than suggested by the dn/dh analysis. After excluding cases with a strong n(h) dip, we indeed found a much better correlation (50&ndash;65 %) for the whole sample (Figure 3).&nbsp;</p> <p>To confirm this conjecture, we numerically studied the velocity of erupting magnetic flux ropes in a quadrupolar ambient field (Figure 5). Producing a range of n(h) profiles by varying the distance and magnetic flux of the outer bipole pair relative to the inner one, we simulated a CME for each case and measured its velocity. As for the observations, we found a clear correlation between the velocity and the steepness of n(h). Additionally, we found that increasing the outer flux (leading to larger dips in n(h)) progressively slows down and eventually confines the eruption. The same result was revealed when we added a varying external magnetic field that runs parallel to the flux rope axis (a so-called shear field, B_t), as shown in Figure 6.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>In summary, we could convincingly demonstrate that the slope of the coronal magnetic field is a main factor in determining the propagation velocity of CMEs. The faster the field drops with height, the larger is the acceleration of the CME. However, we also showed that if a strong overlying magnetic field is present at larger heights in the corona, the final propagation speed of the CME can be much smaller than expected from the slope at low heights. These results provide an important step in understanding the conditions that determine the speed of CMEs. As a next step, a quantitative analysis method that includes the effect of overlying fields on CME acceleration has to be developed. &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2017<br>      Modified by: Tibor&nbsp;Torok</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219606048_f1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219606048_f1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219606048_f1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Top: Simulation of the "Bastille Day" CME, visualized by magnetic field lines (colored by speed) and plasma density in the ecliptic plane (transparent blue-white). The green sphere symbolizes Earth. Bottom: Satellite measurements of the plasma speed at Earth during the passage of the CME.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tibor Torok and Predictive Science Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tibor&nbsp;Torok</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219697262_f2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219697262_f2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219697262_f2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An example from our data set, showing an active region that produced a fast CME. The right panel shows  plasma emission hat depicts the associated flare, which was used to determine the locations at which the decay index n(h) was obtained (red symbols in the magnetogram on the left).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Images: ESA/NASA - SOHO/MDI; NASA - TRACE</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tibor&nbsp;Torok</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219776816_f3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219776816_f3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219776816_f3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">ME speed vs. slope of decay index, dn/dh, for fast events (left) and the whole sample (right). Events 2, 19, 20, 33, and 36 have strong dips in n(h) and are therefore excluded in the fits shown in red. Event 11 was excluded as it was preceded by a fast CME that took place only 16.5 hours earlier.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tibor Torok and Predictive Science Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tibor&nbsp;Torok</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219854080_f4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219854080_f4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219854080_f4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Decay­ index n(h) for two CMEs from our sample. Despite of having a similar slope of n(h) low in the corona, the CME on the right is much slower. That is because it is decelerated by a strong overlying magnetic field that manifests as a pronounced dip of n(h) at larger heights in the corona.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tibor Torok and Predictive Science Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tibor&nbsp;Torok</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219936700_f5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219936700_f5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 5"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490219936700_f5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 5"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Magnetic flux rope (yellow) in a quadrupolar background magnetic field, based on the model by Titov and Démoulin 1999 (A&A 351, 707). This model was used in our parametric numerical study of the relation between CME speed and decay index. The figure is adapted from Kliem et al. 2014 (ApJ 789, 46).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tibor Torok, Bernhard Kliem, Predictive Science Inc., The Astrophysical Journal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tibor&nbsp;Torok</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 5</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490220435938_f6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490220435938_f6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 6"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1249270/1249270_10229998_1490220435938_f6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 6"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Height h, velocity v_z, and decay index n for a series of simulated flux-­rope eruptions in which the strength of the exterior field, B_et, was varied. Larger B_et leads to a larger slow-down of the eruption (left), and to a shift of the dip of the decay index to successively lower heights (right)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Bernhard Kliem, Tibor Torok, and Predictive Science Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tibor&nbsp;Torok</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 6</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Coronal mass ejections (CMEs) are large "bubbles" of plasma and magnetic field that are ejected from the Sun's outer atmosphere, the corona. CMEs are one of the largest energy-release events in the solar system. These huge eruptions liberate energies in excess of ten thousand times the world's annual total energy consumption. CMEs travel at millions of miles per hour, the fastest ones reaching Earth in less than a day. When they impact Earth's magnetosphere they can trigger large geomagnetic storms, which damage satellites in space and even power grids on the ground. Figure 1 illustrates the arrival of a CME at Earth. The top panel shows a numerical simulation of a CME performed by our group at Predictive Science Inc.; the bottom panel shows the speed of the real event as it passes Earth.  The propagation speed is one of the main parameters that determine a CME's impact upon arrival at Earth (others are the plasma density and the magnetic-field strength and orientation). CME speeds, however, vary within a wide range (about 100 - 3500 km/s in the corona), and at present it is not understood which conditions determine the CME speed. This lack of knowledge impedes our abilities to forecast the strength of space-weather disturbances caused by CMEs.  The overarching goal of this project has been to improve our understanding of the physical mechanisms and conditions that determine CME speeds. Our combined numerical and data analysis techniques build on the conception that the torus instability of a magnetic flux rope (Kliem &amp; T&ouml;r&ouml;k 2006) is the main CME initiation and acceleration mechanism (supported by magnetic reconnection below the erupting rope), and that the height profile of the ambient coronal magnetic field is key in determining the strength and duration of the acceleration, i.e., the final CME speed.  For our data analysis, we considered a sample of 15 very fast CMEs (&gt; 1500 km/s) and 22 events with speeds below this limit. For each source region, we produced a model of the local coronal magnetic field (which cannot be measured directly), using a potential-field extrapolation technique. We then quantified the height profile of the field at several locations in the center of the source region (Figure 2), using the so-called decay index n(h). Finally, we correlated its slope, dn/dh, averaged over a certain height range above the onset height of the torus instability, with the observed CME speed (Figure 3).  We first found a strong correlation (70&ndash;80 %) for fast CMEs (&gt; 1500 km/s), but practically no correlation for the whole sample. However, close inspection of the n(h) profiles revealed a strong dip at larger heights in the corona for some cases (Figure 4, right), meaning that the magnetic field decays much slower above a certain height. This happens if a strong field is present above the source region of the eruption. We thus conjectured that such an overlying field acts as a "net" that significantly reduces the acceleration, leading to a final CME speed smaller than suggested by the dn/dh analysis. After excluding cases with a strong n(h) dip, we indeed found a much better correlation (50&ndash;65 %) for the whole sample (Figure 3).   To confirm this conjecture, we numerically studied the velocity of erupting magnetic flux ropes in a quadrupolar ambient field (Figure 5). Producing a range of n(h) profiles by varying the distance and magnetic flux of the outer bipole pair relative to the inner one, we simulated a CME for each case and measured its velocity. As for the observations, we found a clear correlation between the velocity and the steepness of n(h). Additionally, we found that increasing the outer flux (leading to larger dips in n(h)) progressively slows down and eventually confines the eruption. The same result was revealed when we added a varying external magnetic field that runs parallel to the flux rope axis (a so-called shear field, B_t), as shown in Figure 6.       In summary, we could convincingly demonstrate that the slope of the coronal magnetic field is a main factor in determining the propagation velocity of CMEs. The faster the field drops with height, the larger is the acceleration of the CME. However, we also showed that if a strong overlying magnetic field is present at larger heights in the corona, the final propagation speed of the CME can be much smaller than expected from the slope at low heights. These results provide an important step in understanding the conditions that determine the speed of CMEs. As a next step, a quantitative analysis method that includes the effect of overlying fields on CME acceleration has to be developed.                  Last Modified: 03/31/2017       Submitted by: Tibor Torok]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
