<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant: Las Minas Archaeometallurgical Project</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With NSF support, Mr. Colin Thomas will excavate the smelting site of Las Minas.  Las Minas is a terraced natural hill site located along the Zaña river in the Department of Lambayeque, Peru.  The primary purpose of the site appears to have been the extraction of metal from ore material, and surface survey indicates that Las Minas was inhabited from the Early Horizon (800-200 B.C.) to the Chimu period (A.D. 1000-1470).  Las Minas has the potential of being the earliest smelting site yet excavated on the Peruvian coast as well as one of very few Chimu metallurgical sites known to date.  Thomas' research will focus on the physical and chemical analysis of recovered smelting byproducts and furnace remains to determine the exact physical processes that were used at Las Minas through time. This project will also involve the excavation of the residences of the metalworkers and the analysis of resulting ceramic and subsistence remains in order to determine the social standing and affiliation of the smelters at Las Minas.  The laboratory component of this project will require the use of optical metallography as well as elemental analysis techniques, and Mr. Thomas will oversee the creation of a new optical metallography laboratory at a local museum in Lambayeque, Peru to facilitate this analysis.&lt;br/&gt;The Andean region, and the North Coast of Peru in particular, was the site of large scale and long- term metallurgical activity.  However, nearly all available information about the nature of Andean metallurgy currently comes from the study of finished artifacts.  This stands in contrast to the understanding of metallurgical developments in other regions, such as Africa, Anatolia and Europe, where the development of smelting has played a central role.  In order to advance the understanding of metallurgy in Peruvian prehistory it is necessary to combine the analysis of finished artifacts with the full range of steps necessary to create them, including the preceding steps necessary to acquire ore and smelt it to metal.&lt;br/&gt;Acquiring this detailed information about the physical processes used at Las Minas is a first step towards understanding the broader social context of smelting in the Andes.  It is known that Andean smiths were concerned with the use of certain colors to indicate social status and ritual information as well as other guiding ideological principles.  It is very likely that the smelting processes were directed by a similarly intricate web of non-technical meaning.  Understanding this web requires a detailed study of the remnants of smelting, so that one can identify the traces of technological choice encoded within the physical data. &lt;br/&gt;Excavations at Las Minas will also result in the creation of a new optical metallography lab in Lambayeque as well as the training of several Peruvian graduate students in both field and laboratory techniques.  The research will be disseminated in peer-reviewed journals both in the United States and Peru, and the raw data will be made available to the public online.  Mr. Thomas will also present the findings of his research at the SAA meetings as well as other archaeological conferences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/07/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1249579</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Burger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard L Burger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>richard.burger@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034323700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000150431</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colin</FirstName>
<LastName>Thomas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Colin Thomas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>colin.thomas@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034323700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000604449</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 208327]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Projects]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>Archaeology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~25200</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project began with the goal of investigating the technological, ritual, and economic aspects of smelting on the North Coast of Peru.&nbsp; While Peruvian metallurgy in general is well-studied, smelting in particular remains poorly understood.&nbsp; To this end, excavations were conducted from February to June of 2013 at the site of Dos Cruces, a Chim&uacute; era smelting site near the town of Oyot&uacute;n, on the Northern Coast of Peru.</p> <p>Dos Cruces contained significant evidence of smelting activity, including an entire artificial terrace and its associated architecture purpose built to serve as a smelting area.&nbsp; This smelting area contained the first direct evidence of Chim&uacute; smelting technology.&nbsp; Smelting at Dos Cruces was organized around wind power, with adobe walls and the entire terrace itself arranged to channel incoming wind to the furnace structures.&nbsp; This differs significantly from smelting technologies previously excavated in the region, and may indicate either dramatic technological innovation or the adopting of similar technology from the Southern Highlands.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Dos Cruces also revealed the first evidence of ritual activity directly involving smelting in the Andean Region.&nbsp; The furnace structures were intentionally destroyed and buried at the end of their use life.&nbsp; Artifacts associated with the destroyed furnaces indicate that they were buried with offerings of juvenile camelids, imported ceramics, and beer.&nbsp; Further, each destruction event was followed by the rebuilding of the terrace floor, its architectural elements, and the furnaces themselves.&nbsp; The artifacts and behaviors recorded at Dos Cruces indicate that the furnaces were themselves ritually significant and that their destruction and burial was a key component in the continual renewal of the site, a common pattern in the Andes. This process appears to have repeated at least 3 times during the occupation of Dos Cruces.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Economically and politically Dos Cruces represents a contradiction.&nbsp; Classical ideas of empire indicate that the Chim&uacute; should have exercised direct control over the means of copper production.&nbsp; This type of control should be architecturally obvious at Dos Cruces by the presence of an audiencia-type structure.&nbsp; No such structure exists.&nbsp; Other indications of Chim&uacute; association, such as pottery and household architecture, indicate that the residents of Dos Cruces were Chim&uacute; in their material culture.&nbsp; This, along with radiocarbon dates, indicates that the Chim&uacute; were actively engaged in the exercise of indirect control over an important strategic resource long after they were assumed to have completely &lsquo;conquered&rsquo; the Lambayeque region.&nbsp; The existence of a well defended, Chim&uacute; affiliated but locally controlled smelting operation in the Lambayeque region during this time period makes a strong argument for a system of decentralized control during Chim&uacute; occupation.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/06/2016<br>      Modified by: Colin&nbsp;Thomas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project began with the goal of investigating the technological, ritual, and economic aspects of smelting on the North Coast of Peru.  While Peruvian metallurgy in general is well-studied, smelting in particular remains poorly understood.  To this end, excavations were conducted from February to June of 2013 at the site of Dos Cruces, a Chim&uacute; era smelting site near the town of Oyot&uacute;n, on the Northern Coast of Peru.  Dos Cruces contained significant evidence of smelting activity, including an entire artificial terrace and its associated architecture purpose built to serve as a smelting area.  This smelting area contained the first direct evidence of Chim&uacute; smelting technology.  Smelting at Dos Cruces was organized around wind power, with adobe walls and the entire terrace itself arranged to channel incoming wind to the furnace structures.  This differs significantly from smelting technologies previously excavated in the region, and may indicate either dramatic technological innovation or the adopting of similar technology from the Southern Highlands.                  Dos Cruces also revealed the first evidence of ritual activity directly involving smelting in the Andean Region.  The furnace structures were intentionally destroyed and buried at the end of their use life.  Artifacts associated with the destroyed furnaces indicate that they were buried with offerings of juvenile camelids, imported ceramics, and beer.  Further, each destruction event was followed by the rebuilding of the terrace floor, its architectural elements, and the furnaces themselves.  The artifacts and behaviors recorded at Dos Cruces indicate that the furnaces were themselves ritually significant and that their destruction and burial was a key component in the continual renewal of the site, a common pattern in the Andes. This process appears to have repeated at least 3 times during the occupation of Dos Cruces.                   Economically and politically Dos Cruces represents a contradiction.  Classical ideas of empire indicate that the Chim&uacute; should have exercised direct control over the means of copper production.  This type of control should be architecturally obvious at Dos Cruces by the presence of an audiencia-type structure.  No such structure exists.  Other indications of Chim&uacute; association, such as pottery and household architecture, indicate that the residents of Dos Cruces were Chim&uacute; in their material culture.  This, along with radiocarbon dates, indicates that the Chim&uacute; were actively engaged in the exercise of indirect control over an important strategic resource long after they were assumed to have completely æconqueredÆ the Lambayeque region.  The existence of a well defended, Chim&uacute; affiliated but locally controlled smelting operation in the Lambayeque region during this time period makes a strong argument for a system of decentralized control during Chim&uacute; occupation.            Last Modified: 02/06/2016       Submitted by: Colin Thomas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
