<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAR-PF:  Paleoecology of marine mammal herbivory: a multidisciplinary analysis of fossil sirenians, desmostylians and sloths from the Eastern Pacific Ocean</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>170000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>170000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030203</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Luciana Astiz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lastiz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924705</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Dr. Jorge Velez-Juarbe has been awarded an NSF Earth Science Postdoctoral Fellowship to study the ancient ecology of co-occurring extinct marine mammal herbivores from the Eastern Pacific region. Seacows (manatees and dugongs) are the only extant marine mammal herbivores. However, until about 11 million years ago, two other groups of marine mammals, desmostylians in the Northern Pacific region; and aquatic sloths in the Southeastern Pacific region once occurred alongside seacows. To understand how these three groups of marine herbivores interacted with each other, two approaches will be taken. First, description and measurements of the shape and size of the skulls, mandibles and teeth will help formulate hypotheses about the feeding modes of the species in each group. The second approach will use stable isotopes, more specifically, carbon and oxygen, obtained from small tooth or bone samples. The carbon isotopes will aid in the determination of the type of marine plants (either seagrasses, seaweed or a combination of the two) that the different species within each group were consuming. Oxygen isotopes will then provide information regarding their habitats, and will help determine whether the different species were spending more time in marine, brackish or freshwater environments. The goal of this project is to determine if these various groups were sharing the resources (more specifically, marine vegetation) and if so, how was it achieved; and secondly, to compare these multispecies assemblages with others where only seacows were present. The results of this project will be relevant to questions about ocean productivity patterns in the last 20 million years, and can also further our understanding of current changes in marine habitats.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will be carried out at the Department of Geological Sciences, California State University Fullerton (CSU F) and at the John D. Cooper Center. This will give Dr. Velez-JUarbe the opportunity to train students and volunteers in museum curation through (STEM)2 and Project BONES intern programs, as well as co-teach paleontology courses. CSUF is also one of the top institution awarding degrees to Hispanic and other minority students in the US. As a Hispanic, Dr. Velez-Juarbe will be able to contribute to broader efforts in encouraging minority groups pursuing STEM degrees.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1249920</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jorge</FirstName>
<LastName>Velez-Juarbe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jorge Velez-Juarbe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>7147971812</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000623206</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Velez-Juarbe            Jorge</Name>
<CityName>Chevy Chase</CityName>
<ZipCode>208153622</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Department of Geological Sciences, California State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fullerton</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>928346550</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>39</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA39</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6898</Code>
<Text>EAR-Earth Sciences Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~170000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 28.0px Helvetica; color: #3e382b} --> <p class="p1">Seacows (manatees and dugongs) are the only living marine mammals that have a strictly herbivorous diet. However, when we look at the fossil record it reveals that there are two other groups of marine mammal herbivores that co-existed with sirenians between 20-10 million years ago: desmostylians, in the north Pacific region; and aquatic sloths, in the southeastern Pacific region. Currently, there are no extant analog for these co-occurring species of marine herbivore assemblages in the northern Pacific (sirenians and desmostylians) and southeastern Pacific (sirenians and thalassocnines). So, how did these multiple, cooccurring marine herbivores partition their resources?</p> <p class="p1">To answer this question, I used a multidisciplinary approach to evaluate the paleoecology of these herbivorous marine mammals. Morphological data from the skull, teeth and jaws were studied to ecologically link functional traits with feeding preferences. While body size estimates were used as another aspect of niche partitioning. The aim of this multidisciplinary approach was to determine: 1) What kind of marine vegetation did each group consume; 2) ecological interactions between the groups; 3) differences between these multigroup marine mammal assemblages, compared to sirenian-only multispecies assemblages.</p> <p class="p1">The sirenian taxa were represented by two different clades, large-tusked dugongines, and hydrodamalines. Dugongines, represented mainly by <em>Dioplotherium allisoni</em>, were seagrass specialist, preferrably consuming larger seagrass species that were uprooted using their enlarged tusks. On the other hand, hydrodamalines had no tusks, and seemed to have consumed kelp. This particular lineage survived until historical times, when it was represented by Steller's sea cow (<em>Hydrodamalis gigas</em>) a species that specialized in kelp. Similarly, desmostylians are represented by two clades, desmostylids and paleoparadoxiids. Desmostylids are characterized by their high-crowned, thick enameled teeth, seemingly an adaptation for an abrasive diet, likely seagrasses. In contrast, paleoparadoxiids have proportionately smaller, low-crowned teeth not suitable for an abrassive diet.</p> <p class="p1">These sirenian-desmostylian assemblages were present between 20 and 10 million years ago, and niche partitioning in these assemblages can most likely be explained by different food preferences (seagrasses vs kelp). However, the demise of these multispecies assemblages cannot be fully explained at the moment. However, it is notable that desmostylians became extinct around 10 million years ago and only kelp-consuming sirenians survived as the only herbivorous marine mammals in the region. This time period also marks the beginning of other marked changes in the marine fauna, including birds and pinnipeds, and seem to correlate with changes in marine productivity.&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">The sirenian/desmostylian assemblages in the North Pacific and sirenian/thalassocnine assemblages in the South Pacific are in stark contrast to coeaval assemblages in the Caribbean and Western Atlantic region. The later assemblages were composed of distinct species of sirenians, and preferences for feeding on different species of seagrasses and/or different water depths seemd to have driven diversity and niche partitioning. In contrast, Pacific assemblages seems to have been driven by differences in food source (seagrasses vs kelp) and foraging area. Finally, the presence of kelp in the North Pacific provided an alternative food source that could be exploited by large marine herbivores, and allowed for coevolution and survival of hydrodamalines, culminating in the historically extinct Steller's sea cow.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/15/2017<br>      Modified by: Jorge&nbsp;Velez-Juarbe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Seacows (manatees and dugongs) are the only living marine mammals that have a strictly herbivorous diet. However, when we look at the fossil record it reveals that there are two other groups of marine mammal herbivores that co-existed with sirenians between 20-10 million years ago: desmostylians, in the north Pacific region; and aquatic sloths, in the southeastern Pacific region. Currently, there are no extant analog for these co-occurring species of marine herbivore assemblages in the northern Pacific (sirenians and desmostylians) and southeastern Pacific (sirenians and thalassocnines). So, how did these multiple, cooccurring marine herbivores partition their resources? To answer this question, I used a multidisciplinary approach to evaluate the paleoecology of these herbivorous marine mammals. Morphological data from the skull, teeth and jaws were studied to ecologically link functional traits with feeding preferences. While body size estimates were used as another aspect of niche partitioning. The aim of this multidisciplinary approach was to determine: 1) What kind of marine vegetation did each group consume; 2) ecological interactions between the groups; 3) differences between these multigroup marine mammal assemblages, compared to sirenian-only multispecies assemblages. The sirenian taxa were represented by two different clades, large-tusked dugongines, and hydrodamalines. Dugongines, represented mainly by Dioplotherium allisoni, were seagrass specialist, preferrably consuming larger seagrass species that were uprooted using their enlarged tusks. On the other hand, hydrodamalines had no tusks, and seemed to have consumed kelp. This particular lineage survived until historical times, when it was represented by Steller's sea cow (Hydrodamalis gigas) a species that specialized in kelp. Similarly, desmostylians are represented by two clades, desmostylids and paleoparadoxiids. Desmostylids are characterized by their high-crowned, thick enameled teeth, seemingly an adaptation for an abrasive diet, likely seagrasses. In contrast, paleoparadoxiids have proportionately smaller, low-crowned teeth not suitable for an abrassive diet. These sirenian-desmostylian assemblages were present between 20 and 10 million years ago, and niche partitioning in these assemblages can most likely be explained by different food preferences (seagrasses vs kelp). However, the demise of these multispecies assemblages cannot be fully explained at the moment. However, it is notable that desmostylians became extinct around 10 million years ago and only kelp-consuming sirenians survived as the only herbivorous marine mammals in the region. This time period also marks the beginning of other marked changes in the marine fauna, including birds and pinnipeds, and seem to correlate with changes in marine productivity.  The sirenian/desmostylian assemblages in the North Pacific and sirenian/thalassocnine assemblages in the South Pacific are in stark contrast to coeaval assemblages in the Caribbean and Western Atlantic region. The later assemblages were composed of distinct species of sirenians, and preferences for feeding on different species of seagrasses and/or different water depths seemd to have driven diversity and niche partitioning. In contrast, Pacific assemblages seems to have been driven by differences in food source (seagrasses vs kelp) and foraging area. Finally, the presence of kelp in the North Pacific provided an alternative food source that could be exploited by large marine herbivores, and allowed for coevolution and survival of hydrodamalines, culminating in the historically extinct Steller's sea cow.       Last Modified: 05/15/2017       Submitted by: Jorge Velez-Juarbe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
