<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Paleoclimate Analysis of a Miocene Arctic Forest from the Kolyma River Basin, Northeastern Russia</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>170000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Judith Skog</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Paleoclimate Analysis of a Miocene Arctic Forest from the Kolyma River Basin, Northeastern Russia&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A. Hope Jahren&lt;br/&gt;University of Hawaii&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Throughout most of the Tertiary (~65 Ma to ~3 Ma), forests have thrived north of the Arctic Circle. These unique ecosystems were subject to prolonged periods of continuous darkness and light each year, yet managed to persist through the major climate transitions of the Eocene, Oligocene, and Miocene. Much is known about the fossil forests of Arctic North America from studies of Paleocene (e.g., Chickaloon, Alaska), early Eocene(e.g., Ellesmere Island), middle Eocene (e.g., Axel Heiberg Island), and Miocene (e.g., Banks Island) terrestrial sediments. Previous NSF-funded work has supported our reconstructions of seasonal precipitation (Schubert et al., 2012), relative humidity (Jahren and Sternberg, 2003, 2008), the isotopic composition of environmental water (Jahren et al., 2009), soil-methane production (Jahren et al., 2004), and possible water transport mechanisms (Jahren and Sternberg, 2002) using stable isotope analyses of plant fossil materials from the Eocene sediments of Arctic Canada. Russian literature from the 1970s and 80s described the Miocene sediments of Siberia as temporally extensive and spectacularly rich in fossil forests, however, they have not yet been examined using stable isotope techniques. In this proposal, we describe our plan to collect, archive, and analyze Pinaceae and Taxodiaceae fossils from the Baekovo and Nekkeiveem floras, located in the Kolyma River Basin of northeastern Siberia. The sediments we will sample are part of the Khapchan Formation which is late Miocene in age (11.6 to 5.3 Ma; Nikitin, 2007); we will perform one season of fieldwork as part of the Polaris Project II, a recently funded NSF research and education initiative under the direction of Dr. R.M. Holmes (WHRC; see letter of support within Supplementary Documents) to study transport and transformation of carbon in rivers flowing into the Arctic Ocean. As part of Polaris II, we will receive assistance with visas, export permission, and housing at the Northeast Science Station near Cherskiy, as well as the use of an existing boat charter scheduled to navigate the Kolyma River Basin (contact: Dr. Sergei Zimov). We will employ our recent innovations in microanalysis of intra-ring ä13C profiles (Schubert and Jahren, 2011) for determination of the seasonal timing of precipitation (Schubert et al., 2012) for the Miocene Arctic forests of northeastern Siberia. This proposal represents a significant revision of the proposal approved for funding, as necessitated by the &gt;50% reduction in the level of funding, and the restriction of time to two years of total funding. The main alteration of the scientific goals within the original proposal is the exclusion of oxygen isotope analyses of recovered fossil material that were proposed in the original version. In the event that further funding becomes available, collected fossil may be analyzed for oxygen isotope composition, and our hypotheses about paleorelative humidity can be tested under separate support at a later date. The budget has also been altered in that PI Brian Schubert is now an Assistant Professor at University of Louisiana at Lafayette; what would have been postdoc salary to him has been redirected into two months of his summer salary within a subcontract to ULL.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of this study is its potential to open up new intellectual territory on Tertiary Arctic forests via the Miocene sediments of Northeastern Siberia. Fundamentally, we are interested to learn whether the climate scenarios we have constructed for the Canadian Arctic Eocene were global and long-standing, or limited to the Western Hemisphere and/or to the Paleogene. We hypothesize that a general attribute of Tertiary Arctic forests is a summer-dominated hydrologic regime where maximum light levels and maximum water availability coincide, similar to what we observed for the Eocene forests of Arctic North America. We propose a first test of this hypothesis as the determination of the seasonal precipitation regime within Miocene Arctic forests using stable isotope analyses of fossils from the Kolyma River Basin. The Broader Impacts As part of the Polaris II field seasons, we will provide two educational modules introducing students to the Tertiary Arctic forests including hands-on exercises to define simple stratigraphy and collection/identification of plant fossils. Our module will form a separate blog on the website documenting the evolution of the Polaris Project since its inception in 2008 (http://www.thepolarisproject.org/journals/blog/). Finally, we note that our research at the University of Hawaii serves the State of Hawaii, an EPSCoR state. The EPSCoR program is designed to broadly impact science capabilities in EPSCoR jurisdictions, and coinvests with NSF Directorates and Offices in support of proposals submitted to the Foundation's research and education programs, and crosscutting initiatives.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1250063</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hope</FirstName>
<LastName>Jahren</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hope Jahren</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hopejahren@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089560874</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000380710</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965088057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII SYSTEMS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009438664</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968222327</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1680 East-West Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7570</Code>
<Text>SURFACE EARTH PROCESS SECTION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5939</Code>
<Text>US/USSR ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;We proposed to collect, archive, and analyze Pinaceae and Taxodiaceae fossils from the Baekovo and Nekkeiveem floras, located in the Kolyma River Basin that are late Miocene in age [11.6 to 5.3 Ma]. In addition to prospecting for fossil wood during the two field seasons, we obtained sample cores from four separate living Larch (<em>Larix cajanderi</em>) trees to be used for comparing modern environmental conditions to that of fossil wood proxy interpretations.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; While stationed at the Northeast Science Station in Cherskiy, Russia, we visited five field sites to prospect for, and collect mummified fossil wood of Miocene/Pliocene age or Pleistocene age. Described below are our activities at each site:</p> <p>Site 1: Finish Creek (N 68&deg;43.432&rsquo;, E 161&deg;35.225&rsquo;). We excavated along the creek bank to expose a Miocene/Pliocene age layer. Within the layer were exceptionally well-preserved mummified wood fragments with distinct ring structures. We collected a total of thirty wood fragments from this site, with eight of them holding potential for intra-ring stable isotope analyses (ring widths &gt; 0.4 mm).</p> <p>Site 2: We traveled by boat to the well documented Duvanny Yar site (N 68&deg;37.832&rsquo;, E 159&deg;9.039&rsquo;). We collected 5 specimens of well-preserved Pleistocene age mummified wood.</p> <p>Site 3: We hiked to an abandoned gold mine (N 68&deg;46.135&rsquo;, E 161&deg;37.860&rsquo;) where potential Miocene/Pliocene wood had been described 7 years earlier after fresh mining excavations. Due to the time that has passed since excavation, and the overlying Yedoma sediments slumping over the outcrops, it was not possible to gain access to the layers suspected of containing Miocene/Pliocene fossils.</p> <p>Site 4: We prospected along the Kolyma River bank (running along the border of the town of Cherskiy; N 68&deg;45.525&rsquo;, E 161&deg;19.767&rsquo;) for Pleistocene age wood within Yedoma layers. We collected 5 mummified wood specimens.</p> <p>Site 5: We prospected for mummified wood at the &ldquo;Ovrag&rdquo; site, just outside the Cheriskiy airport (N 68&deg;44.301&rsquo;, E 161&deg;21.942&rsquo;). The layers have been described previously as Olyorian Mammal Age (Early to early Middle Pleistocene). We collected 5 mummified wood specimens.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Upon returning to the laboratory, we processed the samples by gently cleaned residual sediment off of the fossil wood specimens using deionized water and a soft bristle brush. For the Finish Creek site specimens (Miocene/Pliocene age), we assessed and documented the preservation state such as describing the cellular structure, ring widths, and whether any deformation was present. We identified annual ring boundaries based on early to late wood transitions (i.e. changes in cell size). For eight of the Finish Creek specimens, we extracted bulk cellulose. These extractions provided us with % cellulose information needed to formulate a sampling scheme for intra-ring oxygen analyses. Based on these extractions, we determined that specimens with a minimum ring width of 0.6 mm would be necessary for intra-ring oxygen isotope analysis. We stored the extracted bulk cellulose in a desiccator until oxygen isotope analysis. &nbsp;The results of these analyses were used to inform two published papers, four conference proceedings and one M.S. thesis (full details within final report).</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The interpretation of seasonal isotope records&nbsp;across diverse environments has been problematic because a unifying model for the quantitative interpretation of seasonal climate parameters from oxygen isotopes in wood is lacking. <strong>The most impactful result of...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[             We proposed to collect, archive, and analyze Pinaceae and Taxodiaceae fossils from the Baekovo and Nekkeiveem floras, located in the Kolyma River Basin that are late Miocene in age [11.6 to 5.3 Ma]. In addition to prospecting for fossil wood during the two field seasons, we obtained sample cores from four separate living Larch (Larix cajanderi) trees to be used for comparing modern environmental conditions to that of fossil wood proxy interpretations.               While stationed at the Northeast Science Station in Cherskiy, Russia, we visited five field sites to prospect for, and collect mummified fossil wood of Miocene/Pliocene age or Pleistocene age. Described below are our activities at each site:  Site 1: Finish Creek (N 68&deg;43.432Æ, E 161&deg;35.225Æ). We excavated along the creek bank to expose a Miocene/Pliocene age layer. Within the layer were exceptionally well-preserved mummified wood fragments with distinct ring structures. We collected a total of thirty wood fragments from this site, with eight of them holding potential for intra-ring stable isotope analyses (ring widths &gt; 0.4 mm).  Site 2: We traveled by boat to the well documented Duvanny Yar site (N 68&deg;37.832Æ, E 159&deg;9.039Æ). We collected 5 specimens of well-preserved Pleistocene age mummified wood.  Site 3: We hiked to an abandoned gold mine (N 68&deg;46.135Æ, E 161&deg;37.860Æ) where potential Miocene/Pliocene wood had been described 7 years earlier after fresh mining excavations. Due to the time that has passed since excavation, and the overlying Yedoma sediments slumping over the outcrops, it was not possible to gain access to the layers suspected of containing Miocene/Pliocene fossils.  Site 4: We prospected along the Kolyma River bank (running along the border of the town of Cherskiy; N 68&deg;45.525Æ, E 161&deg;19.767Æ) for Pleistocene age wood within Yedoma layers. We collected 5 mummified wood specimens.  Site 5: We prospected for mummified wood at the "Ovrag" site, just outside the Cheriskiy airport (N 68&deg;44.301Æ, E 161&deg;21.942Æ). The layers have been described previously as Olyorian Mammal Age (Early to early Middle Pleistocene). We collected 5 mummified wood specimens.              Upon returning to the laboratory, we processed the samples by gently cleaned residual sediment off of the fossil wood specimens using deionized water and a soft bristle brush. For the Finish Creek site specimens (Miocene/Pliocene age), we assessed and documented the preservation state such as describing the cellular structure, ring widths, and whether any deformation was present. We identified annual ring boundaries based on early to late wood transitions (i.e. changes in cell size). For eight of the Finish Creek specimens, we extracted bulk cellulose. These extractions provided us with % cellulose information needed to formulate a sampling scheme for intra-ring oxygen analyses. Based on these extractions, we determined that specimens with a minimum ring width of 0.6 mm would be necessary for intra-ring oxygen isotope analysis. We stored the extracted bulk cellulose in a desiccator until oxygen isotope analysis.  The results of these analyses were used to inform two published papers, four conference proceedings and one M.S. thesis (full details within final report).              The interpretation of seasonal isotope records across diverse environments has been problematic because a unifying model for the quantitative interpretation of seasonal climate parameters from oxygen isotopes in wood is lacking. The most impactful result of this research has been our compilation of a dataset of intra-ring oxygen isotope measurements on modern wood cellulose (d18Ocell) from 33 globally distributed sites and the successful construction of a model that achieves the above. We defined the intra-annual change in oxygen isotope value of wood cellulose [D(d18Ocell)] as the difference between the maximum and minimum d18Ocell values determined within the r...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
