<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Constraining Heat Flux from the Shallow Geothermal System, Yellowstone Caldera, Wyoming</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>295134.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>295134</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030107</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonia Esperanca</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Estimating the heat flux from the Yellowstone volcanic system has been pursued in different ways over the past 50 years.  Understanding the geothermal flux from Yellowstone is important for many reasons: heat and mass flux are an important part of determining the volcano's eruptive potential, and it has been suggested that changes in heat flux or hot brine migration may be correlated with inflation/deflation of the caldera floor or large seismic events.  More fundamentally, the heat flux at the land surface is controlled by the quantity of heat entering the bottom of the system.  The overall active heat budget of the Yellowstone caldera has been estimated in the past using chloride mass balance in spring discharges.  This method is subject to assumptions and uncertainties.  This project will explore the feasibility of a new method to infer mass and energy fluxes for Yellowstone hot springs.  The team will use cross-correlation of spring and atmospheric temperatures that allow estimates for spring discharge (mass flux) and the inflow spring temperature (and hence enthalpy flux).   Estimates of the advective mass and energy flux (using a time-series method) combined with the diffusive energy flux between springs will allow them to derive a comprehensive description of mass and energy fluxes between the shallow subsurface and the atmosphere.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The data to be obtained in this project will be used to improve estimates of heat and mass flux for the shallow hydrothermal system in the Yellowstone caldera.  The methods that to be developed will define a template for future heat and mass balance studies of hydrothermal systems.  It is expected that the methods to be employed in this study and the data to be gathered in the course of this project will be important to volcanic hazard assessment, as well as contributing to public education and enjoyment of Yellowstone and other national resources.  It is also possible that the time-series method of evaluating heat and mass flux of hydrothermal springs as developed here could be approached via satellite-based telemetry.  Graduate and undergraduate students will be involved in the research and their training in this project will provide them with career-building opportunities.  They will be well prepared to face societies future challenges with thoughtful solutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1250435</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Larson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter B Larson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>plarson@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5093353095</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000328913</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington State University</Name>
<CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>991641060</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5093359661</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>280 Lighty</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO BOX 641060]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041485301</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041485301</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>991642812</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~184165</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~110969</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project &ldquo;Constraining Heat Flux from the Shallow Geothermal System, Yellowstone Caldera, Wyoming&rdquo; was a collaborative undertaking between Washington State University and the University of Idaho that sought to identify modes of heat transfer from the land surface to the atmosphere in the vicinity of thermal areas of the Yellowstone Caldera.&nbsp; Almost all studies of heat loss from the land surface at Yellowstone have concentrated on chloride balance in surface waters draining the park as a means of estimating heat flux; however, these estimation methods are restricted to advective heat flux (heat associated with flowing water), and generally neglect the contribution of conductive heat transfer (heat diffusing through the earth in the areas immediately adjacent to hot springs or flowing fluids).&nbsp; We investigated the partitioning of heat between advective and conductive modes in the vicinity of three hot spring groups in the Yellowstone Caldera: the Morning Mist Springs, River Group Springs, and Pocket Basin.&nbsp; Our results show that a significant fraction of the total heat budget of a group of springs may be transferred by conduction; in some cases, the conductive heat losses may account for as much as 50% of the total heat flux (although in many cases advective heat transfer probably dominates).&nbsp; We developed and tested the heavy water doping method for measuring advective recharge/discharge for individual hot springs in the Alvord, OR, and Yellowstone study areas. &nbsp;We also compared the distribution of ground temperatures in the vicinity of hot spring groups, and were able to show that different settings of spring groups give rise to diagnostic temperature distributions in the near-surface.&nbsp; In particular, we can distinguish between diffusive heat flux from a shallow, liquid-water dominated system (exemplified by the Morning Mist Springs area), heat loss through an altered clay cap by steam-heating (River Group Springs I), and heat loss in a fracture controlled, liquid-dominated discharge area (River Group Springs II).&nbsp; On the basis of our observations, data collected at these three areas, and supplemental data and observations from hydrothermal discharge areas in southeast Oregon (Borax Lake and Mickey Hot Springs, Alvord Basin, OR) and central Idaho (Burgdorf Hot Springs), we developed a quantitative theory for interpreting ground surface thermal anomalies arising from shallow, laterally-flowing hydrothermal fluids.&nbsp; In the final year of this study, we sought to expand our work to a new, unstudied area of the Yellowstone Caldera on the northeast flank of Sour Creek Dome.&nbsp; This new area is located in close proximity to what is believed to be the shallowest magma in the caldera, and is likely positioned above or near to ring-faulting associated with caldera collapse following the Lava Creek eruption (~640,000 years ago), which places it in a critical position for understanding the current dynamics of the Yellowstone volcanic system.&nbsp; Future studies will aim at expanding our heat flux studies to this new site, and other under-studied thermal areas in the Yellowstone Caldera.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Beyond the intellectual merit of the study, described above, the project offered broader impacts to society in terms of research experiences for eight undergraduate students, four of whom were recruited from non-PhD granting institutions of higher education, graduate education opportunities (including thesis/dissertation topics) for five graduate students, and avenues for professional development and collaboration for both student and faculty researchers.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/18/2017<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;B&nbsp;Larson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project "Constraining Heat Flux from the Shallow Geothermal System, Yellowstone Caldera, Wyoming" was a collaborative undertaking between Washington State University and the University of Idaho that sought to identify modes of heat transfer from the land surface to the atmosphere in the vicinity of thermal areas of the Yellowstone Caldera.  Almost all studies of heat loss from the land surface at Yellowstone have concentrated on chloride balance in surface waters draining the park as a means of estimating heat flux; however, these estimation methods are restricted to advective heat flux (heat associated with flowing water), and generally neglect the contribution of conductive heat transfer (heat diffusing through the earth in the areas immediately adjacent to hot springs or flowing fluids).  We investigated the partitioning of heat between advective and conductive modes in the vicinity of three hot spring groups in the Yellowstone Caldera: the Morning Mist Springs, River Group Springs, and Pocket Basin.  Our results show that a significant fraction of the total heat budget of a group of springs may be transferred by conduction; in some cases, the conductive heat losses may account for as much as 50% of the total heat flux (although in many cases advective heat transfer probably dominates).  We developed and tested the heavy water doping method for measuring advective recharge/discharge for individual hot springs in the Alvord, OR, and Yellowstone study areas.  We also compared the distribution of ground temperatures in the vicinity of hot spring groups, and were able to show that different settings of spring groups give rise to diagnostic temperature distributions in the near-surface.  In particular, we can distinguish between diffusive heat flux from a shallow, liquid-water dominated system (exemplified by the Morning Mist Springs area), heat loss through an altered clay cap by steam-heating (River Group Springs I), and heat loss in a fracture controlled, liquid-dominated discharge area (River Group Springs II).  On the basis of our observations, data collected at these three areas, and supplemental data and observations from hydrothermal discharge areas in southeast Oregon (Borax Lake and Mickey Hot Springs, Alvord Basin, OR) and central Idaho (Burgdorf Hot Springs), we developed a quantitative theory for interpreting ground surface thermal anomalies arising from shallow, laterally-flowing hydrothermal fluids.  In the final year of this study, we sought to expand our work to a new, unstudied area of the Yellowstone Caldera on the northeast flank of Sour Creek Dome.  This new area is located in close proximity to what is believed to be the shallowest magma in the caldera, and is likely positioned above or near to ring-faulting associated with caldera collapse following the Lava Creek eruption (~640,000 years ago), which places it in a critical position for understanding the current dynamics of the Yellowstone volcanic system.  Future studies will aim at expanding our heat flux studies to this new site, and other under-studied thermal areas in the Yellowstone Caldera.      Beyond the intellectual merit of the study, described above, the project offered broader impacts to society in terms of research experiences for eight undergraduate students, four of whom were recruited from non-PhD granting institutions of higher education, graduate education opportunities (including thesis/dissertation topics) for five graduate students, and avenues for professional development and collaboration for both student and faculty researchers.        Last Modified: 04/18/2017       Submitted by: Peter B Larson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
