<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Experimental Investigation of the Effects of Lithology and Melt Composition on Permeability and 3-D Melt Distribution in Partially Molten Rocks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>184958.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>184958</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030107</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Wade</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwade@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924739</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Beneath ocean ridges, the divergence of lithospheric plates causes hot mantle peridotite to ascend and induces partial melting. The buoyant melt formed by this process rises through the mantle, is focused towards the ridge axis, and forms new oceanic crust. Because the chemical and physical properties of the upper mantle and lower crust are strongly influenced by the amount of melt present, better understanding of permeability of partially molten rocks is crucial. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to place better constraints on rates of melt migration and melt extraction within the partially molten regions at depth. An approach that integrates state-of-the-art micro-tomography, FIB/SEM CrossBeam imaging techniques, high temperature and pressure laboratory experiments, and numerical models will be used to quantify three-dimensional (3-D) melt distribution in partially molten mantle peridotite. With the experimentally determined 3-D melt distributions as input data, permeability of partially molten rocks with different compositions and melt fractions will be determined. Empirical relations between permeability, melt fraction, and pyroxene content will be derived. Permeability anisotropy for sheared samples with stress-driven melt bands will also be calculated. This study will produce the most reliable results to date on melt distribution and permeability of partially molten rocks. These results will lead to a better understanding of the geochemical and geophysical processes at mid-ocean ridges.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/25/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/25/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1250460</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Glenn</FirstName>
<LastName>Gaetani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Glenn A Gaetani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ggaetani@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5082893724</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000097535</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/25/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<ZipCode>025431535</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082892623</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>266 Wood Hole Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Fenno House, MS#39]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001766682</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WOODS HOLE OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTITUTION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001766682</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution]]></Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>025431541</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[266 Woods Hole Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~184958</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Beneath ocean ridges, the divergence of lithospheric plates causes hot mantle peridotite to ascend and induces partial melting. The buoyant melt formed by this process rises through the mantle, is focused towards the ridge axis, and forms new oceanic crust. The chemical and physical properties of the upper mantle and lower crust are strongly influenced by the amount of melt present. Better understanding of transport properties of partially molten rocks is crucial in order to correctly interpret seismic and electromagnetic measurements.<strong> </strong>Using the state-of-the-art X-ray synchrotron microtomography imaging tools, we obtained the first 3-dimensional (3-D) images of melt distribution for olivine-basalt aggregates [Zhu et al., Science 2011]. Equipped with the high resolution 3-D microstructure, we developed numerical models to accurately evaluate permeability and electrical conductivity of partially molten mantle rocks to melt fractions relevant to mantle conditions [Miller et al., 2014]. By linking permeability and electrical conductivity to melt content, we are able to better guide interpretations of geophysical data and constrain melt connectivity and transport at mid-ocean ridges [Miller et al., 2015]. Our data indicate that spatial variations in mineralogy can lead to preferential localization of melt on the grain-scale. This lithologic melting partitioning may enhance the formation of high-melt fraction conduits beneath mid-ocean ridges [Miller et al., 2016].&nbsp; These results provide new insights on the geochemical and geophysical processes at mid-ocean ridges.</p> <p>This research project provided a good opportunity for training researchers of the future. Several graduate and undergraduate students participated in this study. Two of the students graduated with a PhD and a Master&rsquo;s degree, respectively. The experimental results are made available through publications, web sites, and presentations.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/14/2017<br>      Modified by: Glenn&nbsp;A&nbsp;Gaetani</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Beneath ocean ridges, the divergence of lithospheric plates causes hot mantle peridotite to ascend and induces partial melting. The buoyant melt formed by this process rises through the mantle, is focused towards the ridge axis, and forms new oceanic crust. The chemical and physical properties of the upper mantle and lower crust are strongly influenced by the amount of melt present. Better understanding of transport properties of partially molten rocks is crucial in order to correctly interpret seismic and electromagnetic measurements. Using the state-of-the-art X-ray synchrotron microtomography imaging tools, we obtained the first 3-dimensional (3-D) images of melt distribution for olivine-basalt aggregates [Zhu et al., Science 2011]. Equipped with the high resolution 3-D microstructure, we developed numerical models to accurately evaluate permeability and electrical conductivity of partially molten mantle rocks to melt fractions relevant to mantle conditions [Miller et al., 2014]. By linking permeability and electrical conductivity to melt content, we are able to better guide interpretations of geophysical data and constrain melt connectivity and transport at mid-ocean ridges [Miller et al., 2015]. Our data indicate that spatial variations in mineralogy can lead to preferential localization of melt on the grain-scale. This lithologic melting partitioning may enhance the formation of high-melt fraction conduits beneath mid-ocean ridges [Miller et al., 2016].  These results provide new insights on the geochemical and geophysical processes at mid-ocean ridges.  This research project provided a good opportunity for training researchers of the future. Several graduate and undergraduate students participated in this study. Two of the students graduated with a PhD and a Master?s degree, respectively. The experimental results are made available through publications, web sites, and presentations.       Last Modified: 07/14/2017       Submitted by: Glenn A Gaetani]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
