<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Summer Institutes in Social and Personality Psychology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>382896.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>382896</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tamera Schneider</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal supports the continuation and extension of the highly successful program of Summer Institutes in Social and Personality Psychology. Scheduled every two years, the SISPP brings together approximately 80 graduate students in social and personality psychology from graduate programs throughout North America and abroad for an advanced two-week intensive training program, led by the best scholars in the field. Supported by NSF, the first five SISPPs (2003 through 2011) have been highly successful in its goals of providing advanced training in theory and methodology. Evaluations of the first five SISPPs indicate that they were exceptionally strong in both intellectual merit and broader impacts. Participating in SISPP has significantly facilitated the scholarly careers of several cohorts of new social and personality psychologists, offering unique training and collaborative experiences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SISPP is designed to provide promising young scholars with intensive experience and instruction into cutting-edge theories, research, and methods. Preference is given to students who do not have access to this expertise at their home institutions. In order to make valued contributions, young scholars must have access to the increasingly specialized knowledge and technical complexity that marks the best research programs. The SISPP program is carefully designed to provide instruction in research domains and methodological innovations that represent the field's most promising areas. It offers an intensive and intimate intellectual experience. Thus participation in SISPP significantly enhances the training of young scholars and stimulates significant and innovative research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1251506</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Gosling</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel D Gosling</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gosling@psy.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124716424</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488894</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Dovidio</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John F Dovidio</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>john.dovidio@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8607426870</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000623325</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Iris</FirstName>
<LastName>Mauss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Iris Mauss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>imauss@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106428109</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000739619</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Society for Personality and Social Psychology</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200360000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2025246541</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1120 Connecticut Ave NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[#280]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>623575482</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOCIETY FOR PERSONALITY AND SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Society for Personality and Social Psychology]]></Name>
<CityName>Coventry</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>062381936</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[265 High Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>Social Psychology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~182706</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~193608</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~6582</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the past two decades, social and personality psychological research has become more complex in theory, methodology, statistics, and scope, with great growth within the field and in interdisciplinary work. The Society for Personality and Social Psychology in 2003 launched a bi-annual, two-week intensive graduate summer training program, SISPP (Summer Institute in Social and Personality Psychology) to help graduate students receive the training they need to meet these new demands. The current grant supported part or all of the planning and execution of the 2013, 2015 summer institutes, as well as planning for the 2017 summer institute.</p> <p>Each institute consisted of a cohort of 80 students from the US and around the world. Students attended topical and methodological classes taught by top scholars in each field. This allowed them exposure and experience in areas not covered in their home institutions with the goal to spark new interests and ideas. Additionally, the institutes provide opportunity for relationships to be formed and a professional network to be created.&nbsp;</p> <p>Students are selected based on a variety of criteria including academic achievement, area of research interest, and consideration of home institution as well as underrepresented group status.</p> <p>Feedback is solicited from participants at the end of each institute. Also, a follow up of all former participants was completed in 2015. Responses indicate that participants highly rate their experience in terms of quality, content, and networking. Alumni show great productivity in their careers as shown through collaborations, peer-reviewed publications, and securing academic positions.</p> <p>The world is changing at a rapid pace. Social and personality psychologists are uniquely equipped to help examine and address many of the issues facing society today. SISPP has played an important part in readying scholars to contribute in meaningful ways for years to come.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2017<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;F&nbsp;Dovidio</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the past two decades, social and personality psychological research has become more complex in theory, methodology, statistics, and scope, with great growth within the field and in interdisciplinary work. The Society for Personality and Social Psychology in 2003 launched a bi-annual, two-week intensive graduate summer training program, SISPP (Summer Institute in Social and Personality Psychology) to help graduate students receive the training they need to meet these new demands. The current grant supported part or all of the planning and execution of the 2013, 2015 summer institutes, as well as planning for the 2017 summer institute.  Each institute consisted of a cohort of 80 students from the US and around the world. Students attended topical and methodological classes taught by top scholars in each field. This allowed them exposure and experience in areas not covered in their home institutions with the goal to spark new interests and ideas. Additionally, the institutes provide opportunity for relationships to be formed and a professional network to be created.   Students are selected based on a variety of criteria including academic achievement, area of research interest, and consideration of home institution as well as underrepresented group status.  Feedback is solicited from participants at the end of each institute. Also, a follow up of all former participants was completed in 2015. Responses indicate that participants highly rate their experience in terms of quality, content, and networking. Alumni show great productivity in their careers as shown through collaborations, peer-reviewed publications, and securing academic positions.  The world is changing at a rapid pace. Social and personality psychologists are uniquely equipped to help examine and address many of the issues facing society today. SISPP has played an important part in readying scholars to contribute in meaningful ways for years to come.          Last Modified: 06/29/2017       Submitted by: John F Dovidio]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
