<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Pinpointing the Initiation of Modern Caribbean Reefs: Closing the Million Year Gap</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>288077</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Judith Skog</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Pinpointing the Initiation of Modern Caribbean Reefs: Closing the Million Year Gap&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;James Klaus&lt;br/&gt;University of Miami&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; This project will fill a key temporal gap (1.8-0.4 Ma) in the evolutionary/ecological transition to modern Caribbean reefs.  Reefs in the Pliocene are well documented, as are those from the later Pleistocene (0.4 Ma) to Recent.  What is missing, is a record that bridges this critical gap: the final stage of a regional faunal extinction event.  With this terminal evolutionary event came a change in the way reefs build their framework, the way corals are zoned, the rate of coral growth, and thus the way they respond to high-frequency sea level fluctuations and other climatic changes.  To address this data gap we have identified a coral-rich section along the southern coast of the Dominican Republic that records the missing transition from Sylophora dominated reefs to Acropora dominated reefs in a series of step-like coastal terraces.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;An integrated model of fringing reef development will be generated for the early/middle Pleistocene that includes the controlling factors of climate change, sea level, tectonics, antecedent topography, and the maximum growth rate of dominant reef builders.  A sequence stratigraphic model will be developed for a seven core transect of the Pleistocene reef deposits on the southern coast of the Dominican Republic. Age determinations will be based on strontium isotopes, magnetostratigraphy, and radiometric dating.  Once dated, these cores will be used to calculate accretion and progradation, and reconstruct fringing reef zonation and facies geometries both vertically and perpendicular to the coast.  These data will allow us to pinpoint the terminal stage of faunal turnover, evaluate the ecological and environmental factors that gave rise to this transition, and determine the impact on fringing reef development, including changes in reef initiation, vertical accretion, progradation, and development of backreef lagoons and foreslope reefs.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Results from this project will provide the missing stratigraphic and environmental framework to evaluate the final stage of Plio-Pleistocene faunal turnover, and the rise of modern Caribbean reefs. It addresses questions including: (1) how did reef communities change during an episode of turnover and biodiversity loss which shaped the development of modern Caribbean reef ecosystems, (2) how did climate change and global high-amplitude sea level changes influence this ecological transition, and (3) what impact did ecological and environmental changes have on the fundamental shift in morphology to fringing reef terraces. Results will contribute to conservation measures and predictive models to determine how threatened coral reef ecosystems around the world might respond to ecologic collapse, climate change and global sea level rise. To promote international outreach, and broaden participation in the project, a collaboration will be established with the Universidad Autónoma de Santo Domingo (UASD), and the Dirección General de Minería. To facilitate future access and use to the geoscience community, all taxonomic and chronostratigraphic information will be added to the Neogene Marine Biota of Tropical America webpage (NMITA).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1252003</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>McNeill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald F McNeill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmcneill@rsmas.miami.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3054214790</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000169614</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Klaus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James S Klaus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>j.klaus@miami.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3057817756</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000536087</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ali</FirstName>
<LastName>Pourmand</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ali Pourmand</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>apourmand@rsmas.miami.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3054214384</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000539270</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Miami</Name>
<CityName>CORAL GABLES</CityName>
<ZipCode>331462926</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3052843924</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1320 S. Dixie Highway Suite 650</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 100-A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>625174149</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004146619</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Miami]]></Name>
<CityName>Coral Gables</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331462403</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1301 Memorial Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7570</Code>
<Text>SURFACE EARTH PROCESS SECTION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~163828</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~124249</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A critical gap (&gt;1 Myr) exists in the evolutionary history of modern Caribbean reefs.&nbsp; This gap contains the transition from well-documented late Pliocene <em>Stylophora</em>-dominated reefs to the <em>Acropora</em>-dominated reefs of the middle/late Pleistocene to recent. Associated with this faunal transition is a marked change in reef depositional profiles. Late Pliocene reefs typically consist of patch reefs and low-relief thickets (producing planar bedded deposits) while later Pleistocene reefs form well-developed reef crests with steep forereef slopes and backreef lagoons. We have discovered a key section on the southern coast of Hispaniola that spans this early/middle Pleistocene reef gap. Through integrated stratigraphic and paleoecologic investigations of the section we provide the first record of how Caribbean reef ecosystems responded to over a million years of Pleistocene climatic change including the onset of high-amplitude 100 kyr sea level cycles (Mid-Pleistocene Climate Transition).&nbsp; This record provides new insights into the ecological and environmental factors that gave rise to the modern Caribbean reef coral fauna and the resilience of modern reef systems to environmental changes beyond what we have seen for the past 400 kyr.</p> <p class="Default">Specifically, this award developed an integrated model of fringing reef development for the early to late Pleistocene that includes the controlling factors of climate change, sea level, tectonics, antecedent topography, and reef paleoecology.&nbsp; A sequence stratigraphic model was developed for a seven core transect of the Pleistocene reef deposits on the southern coast of the Dominican Republic. Age determinations were based on biostratigraphic markers, strontium isotopes, magnetostratigraphy, and radiometric dating.&nbsp; Once dated, these cores were used to assess accretion and progradation, and reconstruct fringing reef zonation and facies geometries both vertically and perpendicular to the coast.&nbsp; These data allow us to pinpoint the terminal stage of faunal turnover, evaluate the ecological and environmental factors that gave rise to this transition, and determine the impact on fringing reef development.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;<strong>Key Findings</strong>:</p> <p>&nbsp;<strong>Coral Collections and Transect Surveys:</strong></p> <p class="Default">A total of 1641 coral specimens were collected from quarry exposures and terrace escarpments. These collections range from the earliest Pleistocene (2.5-2.0 Ma) to the last interglacial. The oldest localities contain 14 extinct coral taxa comprising 42% of the coral fauna. The middle and late Pleistocene localities contain only one extinct taxa, comprising less than 3% of the coral fauna. In addition to the coral collections, a total of 98 20-meter coral transects were collected from surface outcrops. These transect surveys further document the transition from early to middle Pleistocene reef communities, and the transition from reefs dominated by the extinct coral genus <em>Stylophora</em>, to the modern coral genus <em>Acropora</em>.</p> <p>&nbsp;<strong>&delta;<sup>18</sup>O, and Sr/Ca Temperature Records from a Low-Stand (MIS-16) Coral</strong><strong>:</strong></p> <p>High-resolution &delta;<sup>18</sup>O and Sr/Ca<strong> </strong>time-series was sampled from the coral <em>Orbicella annularis</em> collected from 114.6 m in core 5b. Based on current age information we estimate the coral was growing during the MIS-16 glacial period and sea-level lowstand. Preliminary temperature estimates based on Sr/Ca data range from 14-26 &deg;C.&nbsp; These values are in stark contrast to values observed in the region today which range from 26-30 &deg;C. Our data indicate significantly colder sea-surface temperatures and a much larger annual range of sea-surface temperature. The oxygen isotope data is confounded by changes in seawater isotopic composition, but initial corrections suggest a similar temperature range to the Sr/Ca data.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>In situ Injection Tests to Evaluate Hydrologic Conductivity:</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong>The documented reefal limestones also provide a unique environment for assessing potential fluid flow properties in a complex pore system. Vertical profiles of permeability were calculated from short-interval packer well tests in a three borehole transect across the Pleistocene reefal limestones of the southern Dominican Republic. Combined with whole core porosity estimates, as well as small diameter (2.54 cm) plug estimates of matrix porosity and permeability, these data provide a means of assessing the variability within, and primary factors controlling flow within a complex carbonate pore system.&nbsp; Permeability values based on insitu injection tests ranged between 5-25 D, up to three orders of magnitude higher than associated plug permeability values (0.0001-19 Darcy). While plug permeability was correlated to the primary depositional environment (backreef, reef crest, forereef), well tests showed no correlation to environment.&nbsp; Well permeability showed no correlation to plug-based porosity or permeability values, however it was strongly correlated to larger-scale vuggy porosity, quantified by subtracting the plug-based matrix porosity from the whole core &ldquo;total&rdquo; porosity. The underestimation in permeability that results from plug versus well injection tests for these vuggy carbonates becomes enhanced over time as diagenetic progression occludes matrix porosity and opens up larger vugs through the dissolution of corals and other large aragonitic grains.&nbsp; The in situ permeability values measured in the DR reefal carbonates provide realistic values useful in assessing flow potential in aquifers and reservoirs of other complex matrix-vug dual pore systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/15/2016<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;S&nbsp;Klaus</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1252003/1252003_10238422_1471296705534_DSC_0808_1024--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1252003/1252003_10238422_1471296705534_DSC_0808_1024--rgov-800width.jpg" title="DR Core"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1252003/1252003_10238422_1471296705534_DSC_0808_1024--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="DR Core"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Graduate student Viviana Diaz examining coral material collected from the DRDP cores.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Klaus</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;S&nbsp;Klaus</div> <div class="imageTitle">DR Core</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1252003/1252003_10238422_1471296527048_DSC_0004_1024--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1252003/1252003_10238422_1471296527048_DSC_0004_1024--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Drill Rig and Students"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1252003/1252003_10238422_1471296527048_DSC_0004_1024--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Drill Rig and Students"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students preparing to examine core</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Klaus</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;S&nbsp;Klaus</div> <div class="imageTitle">Drill Rig and Students</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A critical gap (&gt;1 Myr) exists in the evolutionary history of modern Caribbean reefs.  This gap contains the transition from well-documented late Pliocene Stylophora-dominated reefs to the Acropora-dominated reefs of the middle/late Pleistocene to recent. Associated with this faunal transition is a marked change in reef depositional profiles. Late Pliocene reefs typically consist of patch reefs and low-relief thickets (producing planar bedded deposits) while later Pleistocene reefs form well-developed reef crests with steep forereef slopes and backreef lagoons. We have discovered a key section on the southern coast of Hispaniola that spans this early/middle Pleistocene reef gap. Through integrated stratigraphic and paleoecologic investigations of the section we provide the first record of how Caribbean reef ecosystems responded to over a million years of Pleistocene climatic change including the onset of high-amplitude 100 kyr sea level cycles (Mid-Pleistocene Climate Transition).  This record provides new insights into the ecological and environmental factors that gave rise to the modern Caribbean reef coral fauna and the resilience of modern reef systems to environmental changes beyond what we have seen for the past 400 kyr. Specifically, this award developed an integrated model of fringing reef development for the early to late Pleistocene that includes the controlling factors of climate change, sea level, tectonics, antecedent topography, and reef paleoecology.  A sequence stratigraphic model was developed for a seven core transect of the Pleistocene reef deposits on the southern coast of the Dominican Republic. Age determinations were based on biostratigraphic markers, strontium isotopes, magnetostratigraphy, and radiometric dating.  Once dated, these cores were used to assess accretion and progradation, and reconstruct fringing reef zonation and facies geometries both vertically and perpendicular to the coast.  These data allow us to pinpoint the terminal stage of faunal turnover, evaluate the ecological and environmental factors that gave rise to this transition, and determine the impact on fringing reef development.  Key Findings:   Coral Collections and Transect Surveys: A total of 1641 coral specimens were collected from quarry exposures and terrace escarpments. These collections range from the earliest Pleistocene (2.5-2.0 Ma) to the last interglacial. The oldest localities contain 14 extinct coral taxa comprising 42% of the coral fauna. The middle and late Pleistocene localities contain only one extinct taxa, comprising less than 3% of the coral fauna. In addition to the coral collections, a total of 98 20-meter coral transects were collected from surface outcrops. These transect surveys further document the transition from early to middle Pleistocene reef communities, and the transition from reefs dominated by the extinct coral genus Stylophora, to the modern coral genus Acropora.   &delta;18O, and Sr/Ca Temperature Records from a Low-Stand (MIS-16) Coral:  High-resolution &delta;18O and Sr/Ca time-series was sampled from the coral Orbicella annularis collected from 114.6 m in core 5b. Based on current age information we estimate the coral was growing during the MIS-16 glacial period and sea-level lowstand. Preliminary temperature estimates based on Sr/Ca data range from 14-26 &deg;C.  These values are in stark contrast to values observed in the region today which range from 26-30 &deg;C. Our data indicate significantly colder sea-surface temperatures and a much larger annual range of sea-surface temperature. The oxygen isotope data is confounded by changes in seawater isotopic composition, but initial corrections suggest a similar temperature range to the Sr/Ca data.     In situ Injection Tests to Evaluate Hydrologic Conductivity:              The documented reefal limestones also provide a unique environment for assessing potential fluid flow properties in a complex pore system. Vertical profiles of permeability were calculated from short-interval packer well tests in a three borehole transect across the Pleistocene reefal limestones of the southern Dominican Republic. Combined with whole core porosity estimates, as well as small diameter (2.54 cm) plug estimates of matrix porosity and permeability, these data provide a means of assessing the variability within, and primary factors controlling flow within a complex carbonate pore system.  Permeability values based on insitu injection tests ranged between 5-25 D, up to three orders of magnitude higher than associated plug permeability values (0.0001-19 Darcy). While plug permeability was correlated to the primary depositional environment (backreef, reef crest, forereef), well tests showed no correlation to environment.  Well permeability showed no correlation to plug-based porosity or permeability values, however it was strongly correlated to larger-scale vuggy porosity, quantified by subtracting the plug-based matrix porosity from the whole core "total" porosity. The underestimation in permeability that results from plug versus well injection tests for these vuggy carbonates becomes enhanced over time as diagenetic progression occludes matrix porosity and opens up larger vugs through the dissolution of corals and other large aragonitic grains.  The in situ permeability values measured in the DR reefal carbonates provide realistic values useful in assessing flow potential in aquifers and reservoirs of other complex matrix-vug dual pore systems.          Last Modified: 08/15/2016       Submitted by: James S Klaus]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
