<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: EarthScope Chronicles: Scientists' Stories and Media-Rich Earth Science Investigations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>142318.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>142318</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregory Anderson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>greander@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924693</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TERC, in collaboration with McLean Media, is developing multimedia-rich teaching modules that highlight the work and personal stories of EarthScope scientists and engage students in grades 7-12 in data-based investigations connected to the scientists? research. The EarthScope Chronicles modules include compelling videos that feature interviews with scientists and footage of them conducting EarthScope research. The investigations incorporate EarthScope visualizations, data, data products, and geospatial technology to connect STEM classroom content to current real-world scientific research. To increase EarthScope?s visibility within the educational community and the public at large, individual media resources from the modules, such as video clips, image sets, and e-books are distributed through online digital libraries and social media sites such as TeacherTube, YouTube, Vimeo, and STEM Stories. EarthScope Chronicles modules raise awareness of EarthScope research initiatives and resulting scientific discoveries, support the use of EarthScope visualizations, data, and data products in middle- and high-school classrooms, and provide engaging multimedia resources and a replicable model for connecting STEM classroom curriculum to current real-world research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1252031</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lois</FirstName>
<LastName>McLean</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lois M McLean</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>info@storyline.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5302715630</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000452796</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Tessman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard E Tessman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rt@storyline.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7079962464</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000449915</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>McLean Media</Name>
<CityName>Grass Valley</CityName>
<ZipCode>959458520</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5302727594</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>12489 Rough and Ready Highway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>615362068</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MCLEAN MEDIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[McLean Media]]></Name>
<CityName>Grass Valley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>959458520</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[12489 Rough and Ready Hwy]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>017F</Code>
<Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>017F</Code>
<Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~78879</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~42847</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~20592</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF), <em>EarthScope </em>is a network of observatories acting as an Earth "telescope" focused on both the exterior and interior structure and dynamics of our planet. It uses global positioning system (GPS) stations, strainmeters, and hundreds of both stationary and transportable seismometers located across the continental United States.</p> <p>The NSF-funded <em>EarthScope Chronicles </em>project is a collaborative effort between TERC and McLean Media to develop multimedia-rich teaching modules that highlight the work and personal stories of <em>EarthScope</em> scientists and engage students in grades 7-12 in data-based investigations connected to the scientists&rsquo; research.<em> </em>This project<em> </em>was designed to meet the following goals:<em></em></p> <ul> <li>Raise awareness of <em>EarthScope</em> research initiatives and resulting scientific discoveries</li> <li>Support the use of <em>EarthScope</em> visualizations, data, and data products in middle- and high-school classrooms</li> <li>Develop engaging multimedia resources and a replicable model for connecting STEM classroom curriculum to current real-world research</li> </ul> <p>The<em> EarthScope Chronicles</em> model<strong><em> </em></strong>uses<strong><em> </em></strong>video vignettes and data-based investigations to increase (1) access to quality materials; (2) personal connections among students and scientists; (3) visibility of women and minorities as role models; and (4) interactive experiences that underrepresented students might not otherwise have.</p> <p>&nbsp;McLean Media&rsquo;s main contribution to the project has been to produce 25 short videos featuring interviews with scientists and footage of them conducting EarthScope research. Video production took place at multiple locations, including Idaho, Wisconsin, Oregon, Vermont, California, and Texas.</p> <p>These videos are being incorporated into online data-based investigations produced by TERC that include <em>EarthScope</em> visualizations, data, data products, and geospatial technology to connect STEM classroom content to current, real-world scientific research. A range of evaluation and dissemination activities will also be employed when the TERC modules are complete. The modules will align with Next Generation Science Standards and be disseminated widely online through education portals.</p> <p>One <em>EarthScope</em> project that features heavily in the video series is the<em> Idaho-Oregon</em> project (IDOR). IDOR combined data from multiple sources, including research on gravity, seismology, structural geology, and geochronology, to study a boundary that occurred on the edge of North America between Idaho and Oregon and understand how it has evolved through geologic time. The <em>Chronicles</em> crew accompanied several IDOR teams in Idaho as they collected gravity readings, took rock samples, and removed a seismometer. Additional <em>EarthScope</em> projects highlighted include the <em>Superior Province Rifting EarthScope Experiment</em> (SPREE), the <em>Plate Boundary Observatory,</em> the <em>San Andreas Fault Observatory at Depth</em> (SAFOD), and the <em>Rio Grande Rift</em> project. In addition, several individuals who use EarthScope data were introduced in the series, including Harmony Colella, who investigates slow-slip earthquakes, Emily Hooft, whose research focuses on studying volcanoes, and Jenny Nakai, who is building an earthquake catalog for the Rio Grande region.</p> <p>To increase <em>EarthScope</em>&rsquo;s visibility within the educational community and the public at large, individual videos are already being distributed through several online sites. For example, the videos are available through an <em>EarthScope Chronicles</em> playlist (<em><a href="http://bit.ly/ChroniclesOnYouTube">http://bit.ly/ChroniclesOnYouTube</a></em>) on the <em>EarthScope </em>program&...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF), EarthScope is a network of observatories acting as an Earth "telescope" focused on both the exterior and interior structure and dynamics of our planet. It uses global positioning system (GPS) stations, strainmeters, and hundreds of both stationary and transportable seismometers located across the continental United States.  The NSF-funded EarthScope Chronicles project is a collaborative effort between TERC and McLean Media to develop multimedia-rich teaching modules that highlight the work and personal stories of EarthScope scientists and engage students in grades 7-12 in data-based investigations connected to the scientistsÆ research. This project was designed to meet the following goals:  Raise awareness of EarthScope research initiatives and resulting scientific discoveries Support the use of EarthScope visualizations, data, and data products in middle- and high-school classrooms Develop engaging multimedia resources and a replicable model for connecting STEM classroom curriculum to current real-world research   The EarthScope Chronicles model uses video vignettes and data-based investigations to increase (1) access to quality materials; (2) personal connections among students and scientists; (3) visibility of women and minorities as role models; and (4) interactive experiences that underrepresented students might not otherwise have.   McLean MediaÆs main contribution to the project has been to produce 25 short videos featuring interviews with scientists and footage of them conducting EarthScope research. Video production took place at multiple locations, including Idaho, Wisconsin, Oregon, Vermont, California, and Texas.  These videos are being incorporated into online data-based investigations produced by TERC that include EarthScope visualizations, data, data products, and geospatial technology to connect STEM classroom content to current, real-world scientific research. A range of evaluation and dissemination activities will also be employed when the TERC modules are complete. The modules will align with Next Generation Science Standards and be disseminated widely online through education portals.  One EarthScope project that features heavily in the video series is the Idaho-Oregon project (IDOR). IDOR combined data from multiple sources, including research on gravity, seismology, structural geology, and geochronology, to study a boundary that occurred on the edge of North America between Idaho and Oregon and understand how it has evolved through geologic time. The Chronicles crew accompanied several IDOR teams in Idaho as they collected gravity readings, took rock samples, and removed a seismometer. Additional EarthScope projects highlighted include the Superior Province Rifting EarthScope Experiment (SPREE), the Plate Boundary Observatory, the San Andreas Fault Observatory at Depth (SAFOD), and the Rio Grande Rift project. In addition, several individuals who use EarthScope data were introduced in the series, including Harmony Colella, who investigates slow-slip earthquakes, Emily Hooft, whose research focuses on studying volcanoes, and Jenny Nakai, who is building an earthquake catalog for the Rio Grande region.  To increase EarthScopeÆs visibility within the educational community and the public at large, individual videos are already being distributed through several online sites. For example, the videos are available through an EarthScope Chronicles playlist (http://bit.ly/ChroniclesOnYouTube) on the EarthScope programÆs YouTube channel. They are also being added to the EarthScope website and Facebook pages and are posted on the EarthScope Chronicles website in development at http://serc.carleton.edu/earthscope_chronicles/earthscope.html.  Individual animations produced originally for inclusion in the videos are also provided on the project website and have been shared with staff from EarthsScopeÆs Plate Boundary Observatory project for use in their outreach activit...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
