<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER-Nanoparticle-binding peptide tags for multiplexed immunosensing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49986.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49986</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Franklin Carrero-Martínez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This is an EAGER proposal submitted to OISE for research collaboration between Prof. Blake of Tulane University and Prof. Merkoçi?s of Nanobioelectronics and Biosensors Group in the Catalan Institute of Nanotechnology at the Autonomous University of Barcelona, Spain.&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this one-year project is to develop new peptide tags for quantum dots of specific metal ion compositions. These peptide tags, when incorporated into engineered antibodies, will permit the development of integrated, miniaturized electrochemical sensors that can be multiplexed with minimal sample pretreatment. Such electrochemical sensors, which will ultimately be miniaturized for rapid, on-site analysis, would have the capacity for rapid, simultaneous detection of multiple environmental contaminants, serum biomarkers, or analytes of concern for homeland security.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/25/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/25/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1253272</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diane</FirstName>
<LastName>Blake</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diane A Blake</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>blake@tulane.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5045842478</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000273765</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/25/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tulane University</Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<ZipCode>701185698</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5048654000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6823 ST CHARLES AVENUE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADMINISTRATORS OF THE TULANE EDUCATIONAL FUND, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tulane University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>701122699</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1430 Tulane Avenue, SL-43]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7909</Code>
<Text>BIOSENS-Biosensing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>019E</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>142E</Code>
<Text>Multi-sens probes &amp; platforms</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5952</Code>
<Text>SPAIN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~49986</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The United States Agency for Toxic Substance and Disease Registry (ATSDR) publishes a priority list of toxic substances every two years. Chemicals of concern are ranked according to their toxicity, their prevalence in the environment and their potential for human exposure. Heavy metals appear prominently in this ATSDR List. In fact, four metals rank in the top 10 of the ATSDR pollutants: arsenic; lead; mercury; and cadmium.&nbsp; Most of the other priority pollutants on this list (pesticides, herbicides, petroleum products, etc.) can eventually be metabolized to carbon dioxide and water. Metals, however, do not undergo such biological transformations and therefore remain at the site of contamination unless they are physically removed. Sites that are contaminated with heavy metals must therefore be monitored on a regular basis to insure that the metals are not released into groundwater, surface water or drinking water.</p> <p>Conventional methods of testing for heavy metal contamination are laborious and require highly skilled personnel in a centralized facility. The purpose of this project was to develop new tools for the rapid measurement of metals and other contaminants at the site of the contamination. The tools we developed in this project were protein molecules (antibodies) that were genetically engineered to bind more tightly to nanoparticles. Antibodies with bound gold nanoparticles were then used to develop small disposable devices, much like pregnancy test strips, to measure cadmium and uranium in environmental water samples.</p> <p>This project, which involved collaboration between a biochemistry laboratory in the United States and an instrumental/analytical chemistry laboratory in Spain, also provided the cross-training of graduate student from different countries and diverse scientific disciplines. Students from Spain learned how to handle and manipulate antibodies in order to increase the sensitivity and specificity of their test strips; the US-based student supported by the NSF learned how to engineer antibodies for more efficient performance in this sensor format.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/02/2015<br>      Modified by: Diane&nbsp;A&nbsp;Blake</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The United States Agency for Toxic Substance and Disease Registry (ATSDR) publishes a priority list of toxic substances every two years. Chemicals of concern are ranked according to their toxicity, their prevalence in the environment and their potential for human exposure. Heavy metals appear prominently in this ATSDR List. In fact, four metals rank in the top 10 of the ATSDR pollutants: arsenic; lead; mercury; and cadmium.  Most of the other priority pollutants on this list (pesticides, herbicides, petroleum products, etc.) can eventually be metabolized to carbon dioxide and water. Metals, however, do not undergo such biological transformations and therefore remain at the site of contamination unless they are physically removed. Sites that are contaminated with heavy metals must therefore be monitored on a regular basis to insure that the metals are not released into groundwater, surface water or drinking water.  Conventional methods of testing for heavy metal contamination are laborious and require highly skilled personnel in a centralized facility. The purpose of this project was to develop new tools for the rapid measurement of metals and other contaminants at the site of the contamination. The tools we developed in this project were protein molecules (antibodies) that were genetically engineered to bind more tightly to nanoparticles. Antibodies with bound gold nanoparticles were then used to develop small disposable devices, much like pregnancy test strips, to measure cadmium and uranium in environmental water samples.  This project, which involved collaboration between a biochemistry laboratory in the United States and an instrumental/analytical chemistry laboratory in Spain, also provided the cross-training of graduate student from different countries and diverse scientific disciplines. Students from Spain learned how to handle and manipulate antibodies in order to increase the sensitivity and specificity of their test strips; the US-based student supported by the NSF learned how to engineer antibodies for more efficient performance in this sensor format.          Last Modified: 12/02/2015       Submitted by: Diane A Blake]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
