<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: DNA-templated Assembly of Nanoscale Circuit Interconnects</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>435050</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>khcooper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927017</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) Program grant is to develop a novel, robust method of assembling interconnects between nanoscale device terminals. Nanoscale circuits could allow for faster computers, devices to manipulate light at the nanoscale and exquisitely sensitive molecular detection systems.  However, a major current obstacle to the further development of these devices is the difficulty of manufacturing them. In particular, while it is possible to build an increasing number of individual nanoscale devices, assembling and properly placing interconnects (wires) that provide inputs to and channel outputs from these devices remains a major challenge.  The project's process, point-to-point interconnect assembly, uses chemical markers attached to device terminals to direct the assembly of an interconnecting filament. The chemical markers and filaments will be constructed from synthetic DNA, which can be used as a template for the assembly of a variety of functional interconnects.  The DNA-based interconnect process will be characterized dynamically and yield will be optimized for assembly of interconnects between actual nanoscale device terminals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will be integrated with a program for education and outreach focused on biologically inspired methods for nanoscale fabrication. Undergraduate and graduate level courses will be developed in which students will learn fundamental programming and statistical analysis skills that can be applied across fields.  A graduate courses will help engineering students understand biological information processing with the goal of developing biologically inspired fabrication methods.  Finally, high school students will participate in research projects in the laboratory and lectures on self-assembly and biologically inspired fabrication will be presented to middle and high school students from Baltimore who participate in robotics competitions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1253876</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Schulman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebecca Schulman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schulman.rk@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4105168457</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000599828</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212182686</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439971898</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1101 E 33rd St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite B001]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001910777</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001910777</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Johns Hopkins University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3400 N. Charles Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1788</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>081E</Code>
<Text>NANO SCALE ASSEMBLY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>084E</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>093E</Code>
<Text>System fab/packaging &amp; assembly</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~4800</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~9500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~4750</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><br /><br />Nanoscale circuits could allow for faster computers, devices to manipulate light at the nanoscale and exquisitely sensitive molecular detection systems. However, a major current obstacle to the further development of these devices is the difficulty of manufacturing them. In particular, while some such circuits have been produced, assembling and properly placing interconnects that provide inputs to and channel outputs from nanoscale devices remains a major challenge. The difficulty in this process is that to be functional, such interconnects must have the precise size and be in the precise position, as determined by nanometer accuracy, yet many nanoscale devices themselves have variations at the same scale in both size and position.<br />During the period funded by this research grant, our group developed a novel, robust method of assembling interconnects between nanoscale device terminals that are precisely oriented even when the location of the terminals on a circuit substrate is not known.&nbsp; &nbsp;We developed a process called point-to-point interconnect assembly that uses chemical markers attached to device terminals to direct interconnect assembly. These chemical markers nucleate filaments which then polymerize at the filament ends. The two filament ends diffuse simultaneously,and when the filaments are long enough to contact one another, they&nbsp; can join, producing a stable interconnect.&nbsp; &nbsp;To make it possible to control this process precisely, we constructed the filaments and markers from synthetic DNA, which is both amenable to the implementation of complex self-assembly processes and can be used as a template for the assembly of a variety of functionalinterconnects.&nbsp; We showed that this process could be used to reliably (i.e. at least 80% of the time) connect pairs of markers separated anywhere from 1-10 microns and published these results in a high-impact peer-reviewed journal.&nbsp;&nbsp;<br />We have also worked to develop (but have not yet published) developments that addressed the other two aims of the proposal: (a) demonstrate that this process can be used to produce interconnects between nanoscale device terminals and (b) develop a method to grow multiple overlapping interconnects on the same substrate simultaneously, permitting this technique to be used to form complex circuits with many interconnects.&nbsp; This research now allows the development of a new classes of nanoscale circuits that can "wire themselves."&nbsp; We are currently pursuing work to make these connections conductive, and thus practical for a particular kind of circuit, as part of a new project.<br /><br />The development of novel techniques such as point-to-point assembly requires a multi-faceted approach, drawing on many traditional disciplines. These broader conceptual themes were integrated into an educational and outreach program focused on preparing students for research in nanomanufacturing by improving interdisciplinary training. We developed two new courses at the undergraduate and graduate level where students a) learned&nbsp; programming and statistical analysis in such a way that can be applied across traditional fields&nbsp; b) gained an understanding of biological information processing with the goal of developing biologically inspired fabrication methods.&nbsp; &nbsp;Three female high school students from Baltimore City public high schools, two of whom are from underrepresented minorities participated in this project as part of a paid mentorship and training program, and numerous undergraduate students participated in this research, at least four of whom are now co-authors on peer-reviewed publications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/19/2018<br>      Modified by: Rebecca&nbsp;Schulman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1253876/1253876_10226042_1521469482192_nanotube-interconnect-figure-career-final-report--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1253876/1253876_10226042_1521469482192_nanotube-interconnect-figure-career-final-report--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Point to point assembly of circuit interconnects."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1253876/1253876_10226042_1521469482192_nanotube-interconnect-figure-career-final-report--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Point to point assembly of circuit interconnects."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">DNA nanotubes grow between and connect DNA landmarks (red and blue).  Landmarks are about 6 micrometers apart.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Schulman research group, Johns Hopkins University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rebecca&nbsp;Schulman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Point to point assembly of circuit interconnects.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Nanoscale circuits could allow for faster computers, devices to manipulate light at the nanoscale and exquisitely sensitive molecular detection systems. However, a major current obstacle to the further development of these devices is the difficulty of manufacturing them. In particular, while some such circuits have been produced, assembling and properly placing interconnects that provide inputs to and channel outputs from nanoscale devices remains a major challenge. The difficulty in this process is that to be functional, such interconnects must have the precise size and be in the precise position, as determined by nanometer accuracy, yet many nanoscale devices themselves have variations at the same scale in both size and position. During the period funded by this research grant, our group developed a novel, robust method of assembling interconnects between nanoscale device terminals that are precisely oriented even when the location of the terminals on a circuit substrate is not known.   We developed a process called point-to-point interconnect assembly that uses chemical markers attached to device terminals to direct interconnect assembly. These chemical markers nucleate filaments which then polymerize at the filament ends. The two filament ends diffuse simultaneously,and when the filaments are long enough to contact one another, they  can join, producing a stable interconnect.   To make it possible to control this process precisely, we constructed the filaments and markers from synthetic DNA, which is both amenable to the implementation of complex self-assembly processes and can be used as a template for the assembly of a variety of functionalinterconnects.  We showed that this process could be used to reliably (i.e. at least 80% of the time) connect pairs of markers separated anywhere from 1-10 microns and published these results in a high-impact peer-reviewed journal.   We have also worked to develop (but have not yet published) developments that addressed the other two aims of the proposal: (a) demonstrate that this process can be used to produce interconnects between nanoscale device terminals and (b) develop a method to grow multiple overlapping interconnects on the same substrate simultaneously, permitting this technique to be used to form complex circuits with many interconnects.  This research now allows the development of a new classes of nanoscale circuits that can "wire themselves."  We are currently pursuing work to make these connections conductive, and thus practical for a particular kind of circuit, as part of a new project.  The development of novel techniques such as point-to-point assembly requires a multi-faceted approach, drawing on many traditional disciplines. These broader conceptual themes were integrated into an educational and outreach program focused on preparing students for research in nanomanufacturing by improving interdisciplinary training. We developed two new courses at the undergraduate and graduate level where students a) learned  programming and statistical analysis in such a way that can be applied across traditional fields  b) gained an understanding of biological information processing with the goal of developing biologically inspired fabrication methods.   Three female high school students from Baltimore City public high schools, two of whom are from underrepresented minorities participated in this project as part of a paid mentorship and training program, and numerous undergraduate students participated in this research, at least four of whom are now co-authors on peer-reviewed publications.             Last Modified: 03/19/2018       Submitted by: Rebecca Schulman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
