<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Understanding the Interfacial Rheology of Carbon Nanotubes at the Fluid-Fluid Interfaces for Creating Ultra-stable Emulsions and Microcapsules</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ron Joslin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rjoslin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927030</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1253613&lt;br/&gt;Ma&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It has been known for more than a century that particles can stabilize emulsions by adsorbing at the fluid-fluid interface and lowering the interfacial energy. Thermodynamics and earlier experimental studies indicate that controlling the particle size and wetability are two key factors to stabilize emulsions. However, the effect of particle shape has remained largely unexplored and unexploited. The hypothesis of this proposal is that particle shape matters and that rod-like and high-aspect-ratio particles will increase the number of particle-particle contacts, leading to the formation of a stronger layer at the interface and consequently more stable emulsions relative to spheres. To examine this hypothesis, carbon nanotubes (CNTs) with high aspect ratio (&gt;1000) will be investigated as a model system. The objective is to establish a fundamental understanding of the physics of an interface decorated with CNTs. The microstructure and the interfacial rheology will be carefully examined and further linked to the mechanical integrity and stability of a CNT-laden interface. The intellectual merit of this proposal involves: (1) exploring the complex physics of CNTs at the fluid-fluid interface, and (2) connecting the rheology with interfacial phenomena. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: Exploiting the particle shape could be the missing key to unlocking the full potential of nanoparticle-stabilized emulsions. The proposed research may offer a general and yet relatively simple strategy to improve the stability of emulsions and prolong the shelf life of widely used pharmaceutical, agricultural, and personal care products. Secondly, the findings may revolutionize the use of nanoparticles for enhanced oil recovery, essential to ensuring national energy independence and addressing the world's energy challenge. Thirdly, understanding the interfacial behavior of nanoparticles will help comprehend the fate of both naturally occurring and engineered nanoparticles in the environment and wastewater treatment processes, such as flotation, which could have an impact on the sustainable use of nanoparticles. Finally, the proposed research may also impact the creation of technologically important materials such as: (1) novel microcapsules with controllable permeability for drug encapsulation and delivery, (2) scrims and polymer blends for composite and membrane applications, and (3) metamaterials that can be further used in cloaking devices and light-based circuits that may ultimately outperform electron-based computers in terms of speed, power consumption, and costs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Education and Outreach: The proposed research will be integrated with educational and outreach activities at all levels to maximize its impact. The graduate and undergraduate students involved in this project will receive cross-discipline training across the fields of rheology, interfacial phenomena, and carbon nanotubes. To engage the younger generation and the local community, culinary foams and emulsions will be used as the theme for the outreach plan. With the support of the CAREER award, the PI and his team will continue their outreach efforts through several programs (e.g., UConn's Mentor Connection Program and da Vinci project) and will attempt a new initiative on introducing basic scientific concepts through debunking cooking myths at high schools in inner-city Hartford and Willimantic with high minority populations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/18/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/18/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1253613</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anson</FirstName>
<LastName>Ma</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anson Ma</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>anson.ma@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8604864630</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000596643</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Unit 1133]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>614209054</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004534830</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Connecticut]]></Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>062693136</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[97 N. Eagleville Rd, Unit 3136]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FD-Fluid Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>059E</Code>
<Text>Complex fluids</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Emulsions and foams, involving a liquid-liquid or a gas-liquid interface, are ubiquitous in pharmaceutical, agricultural, and personal care products. Understanding the mechanical stability of these interfaces has far reaching implications on engineering more stable interfaces for prolonging the shelf-life and enhancing the performance of emulsions and foams during applications. Using carbon nanotubes (CNTs) as a model system, we explored nano-sized particles as an interface stabilizing agent. The <strong>intellectual merits</strong> of this proposal are about: (1) exploring the complex physics at an interface stabilized by CNTs and (2) connecting the flow behavior (rheology) with interfacial phenomena.</p> <p>Several key accomplishments with both scientific merits and technological relevance have been achieved throughout this project. First, we discovered that a more robust interface can be engineered by chemically modifying the surface of the particles, which in turn mediates the interactions between the particles and their collective behavior at an interface. Second, a new experimental method has been developed to visualize and quantify how a particle-decorated interface is deformed during compression. The results clearly showed, for the first time, the non-uniform deformation of an interface during a compression experiment, challenging an assumption that has been widely used by researchers for more than a century. More importantly, the method also offers a way to correct the deficiency associated with this type of experiments. Third, a new instrument accessory has been envisioned and constructed to study the mechanical integrity of an interface. This tool may be further leveraged for high throughput screening of chemical formulations, which will translate into faster innovation for emulsion- and foam-based products and cost saving for manufacturers. These findings have resulted in two high-impact, peer-reviewed journal publications, with a third one under preparation, more than 18 presentations, and a patentable invention.</p> <p>In terms of <strong>broader impact</strong>, the general test method has been successfully used to predict the stability of new personal care product prototypes despite the complexity of the chemical formulations. Intellectual property protection is sought and a leading instrument manufacturer has expressed interest in commercializing the accessory invented during this project. One postdoctoral fellow, four graduate students, three undergraduates, and three high school students have participated in the research supported by this grant and have become well versed in the fields of chemical engineering, rheology, and surface science. Three of the graduate students have remained in the US and joined the technical workforce, while the fourth graduate student is aspired to become a faculty in the US and is currently pursuing further postdoctoral training.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Anson&nbsp;Ma</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1253613/1253613_10228968_1551649407684_ScreenShot2019-03-03at4.37.24PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1253613/1253613_10228968_1551649407684_ScreenShot2019-03-03at4.37.24PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Complex deformation field induced by compressing a particle-decorated interface"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1253613/1253613_10228968_1551649407684_ScreenShot2019-03-03at4.37.24PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Complex deformation field induced by compressing a particle-decorated interface"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The non-uniform deformation field of a particle-decorated interface has been successfully captured using digital image correlation. This experimental finding challenges a long-held assumption in widely used Langmuir-Pockels trough experiments.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sahil Vora</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anson&nbsp;Ma</div> <div class="imageTitle">Complex deformation field induced by compressing a particle-decorated interface</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Emulsions and foams, involving a liquid-liquid or a gas-liquid interface, are ubiquitous in pharmaceutical, agricultural, and personal care products. Understanding the mechanical stability of these interfaces has far reaching implications on engineering more stable interfaces for prolonging the shelf-life and enhancing the performance of emulsions and foams during applications. Using carbon nanotubes (CNTs) as a model system, we explored nano-sized particles as an interface stabilizing agent. The intellectual merits of this proposal are about: (1) exploring the complex physics at an interface stabilized by CNTs and (2) connecting the flow behavior (rheology) with interfacial phenomena.  Several key accomplishments with both scientific merits and technological relevance have been achieved throughout this project. First, we discovered that a more robust interface can be engineered by chemically modifying the surface of the particles, which in turn mediates the interactions between the particles and their collective behavior at an interface. Second, a new experimental method has been developed to visualize and quantify how a particle-decorated interface is deformed during compression. The results clearly showed, for the first time, the non-uniform deformation of an interface during a compression experiment, challenging an assumption that has been widely used by researchers for more than a century. More importantly, the method also offers a way to correct the deficiency associated with this type of experiments. Third, a new instrument accessory has been envisioned and constructed to study the mechanical integrity of an interface. This tool may be further leveraged for high throughput screening of chemical formulations, which will translate into faster innovation for emulsion- and foam-based products and cost saving for manufacturers. These findings have resulted in two high-impact, peer-reviewed journal publications, with a third one under preparation, more than 18 presentations, and a patentable invention.  In terms of broader impact, the general test method has been successfully used to predict the stability of new personal care product prototypes despite the complexity of the chemical formulations. Intellectual property protection is sought and a leading instrument manufacturer has expressed interest in commercializing the accessory invented during this project. One postdoctoral fellow, four graduate students, three undergraduates, and three high school students have participated in the research supported by this grant and have become well versed in the fields of chemical engineering, rheology, and surface science. Three of the graduate students have remained in the US and joined the technical workforce, while the fourth graduate student is aspired to become a faculty in the US and is currently pursuing further postdoctoral training.       Last Modified: 03/03/2019       Submitted by: Anson Ma]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
