<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: A GENERALIZED APPROACH TO THE CHARACTERIZATION OF NATIVE RNA WITHIN THE CELLULAR MILIEU-AN INTEGRATED EDUCATION AND RESEARCH STUDY</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>236646.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aleksandr Simonian</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimonia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1253691 - Santangelo&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overall focus of the research and education components of this work is on the integration of cell biology and molecular engineering.  Within the research component, integration of these disciplines will be utilized in the development of a generalized approach for the sensing and characterization of RNA molecules in the cellular milieu, based on previously published single RNA sensitive imaging probes.  This approach will then be applied to the study of megakaryocytes, which recently were discovered to sort RNAs to sites of platelet formation. In the education portion of this proposal, the goal is to create education modules, utilizing active learning experiences, at both the undergraduate and secondary school level, that facilitate the ability of students to integrate engineering principles and biology, and new assessment strategies will be employed in order to gauge their utility. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is targeted to have broad impact at both the scientific level and within society.  From a scientific perspective, given the role of RNA in almost every biological problem, new tools that allow for its thorough characterization will impact the science of many researchers. On a societal level, by improving the ability of students to integrate engineering approaches with cellular biology, we?ll be able to improve their general ability to think critically and solve problems using all the tools they have been exposed to during their education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/18/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1253691</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Santangelo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philip Santangelo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>philip.santangelo@bme.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048944819</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000522874</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Tech Research Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[313 Ferst Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7909</Code>
<Text>BIOSENS-Biosensing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>142E</Code>
<Text>Multi-sens probes &amp; platforms</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~76726</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~158614</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~81582</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~83078</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><em>Project Outcomes</em></strong>: From this project there were a number of technological outcomes achieved, which were in line with our proposed outcomes, but like any research project they differed in the specifics as the project progressed.&nbsp; The work primarily focused on our proposed second technological outcome, developing a general method for detecting RNA-protein interactions, with single molecule sensitivity,&nbsp;<em>in situ.&nbsp; </em>This outcome was achieved, and given the importance of cancer at that time, we focused on demonstrating the approach to interrogate actual tumor tissue from patients.&nbsp; This work was published in the presitgious journal, <em>Cancer Research (Blanchard et al., Cancer Research, 2019). </em>In that paper, we demonstrated the optimization of a method that is based on fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH) and proximity ligation (PLA) techniques to quantify mRNA interactions with RNA-binding proteins relevant for tumorigenesis and cancer progression in archival patient-derived tumor tissue. This method was validated for multiple mRNA-protein pairs in several cellular models and in multiple types of archival human tumor samples. Furthermore, this approach allowed high-throughput analysis of mRNA&ndash;protein interactions across a wide range of tumor types and stages through tumor microarrays. This method is quantitative, specific, and sensitive for detecting interactions and their localization at both the individual cell and whole-tissue scales with single interaction sensitivity.&nbsp;We demonstrated that abnormal mRNA&ndash;proteins interactions can be spatially resolved and quantified in various types of tumors in patient-derived samples. We believe PMTRIP FISH-PLA (the approach we developed) will be a valuable tool in investigating cancer biology on a high-throughput scale, with great potential for translatability into any disease where abnormal RNA&ndash;protein interactions occur. We did discover new relevant RNA-protein interactions in both colon and lung cancer. The increase of interactions between TIAR and polyadenylated or COX-2 mRNA in both colon and lung cancer was unexpected. TIAR represses translation and is thought to be a tumor suppressor, so we anticipated to measure fewer interactions with mRNA in tumors. However, the observed interactions correlated with the increased expression of TIAR and COX-2 mRNA observed in colon cancer samples. Strong TIAR signal has previously been observed in infiltrating inflammatory cells in tumors, which may explain the significant interactions detected by our assay, which relies on the ability to observe interactions on a whole tumor level. These interactions require further investigation, including the characterization by cell type and their heterogeneous spatial distribution across the tumor via immunofluorescence staining post-FISH-PLA.&nbsp; In addition, we also validated our findings in cancer cell lines using immunoprecipitation (IP) and analysis of RNP complexes of a given RNA species within cells.&nbsp; This was in accordance with our first proposed technological outcome, the development of an IP process for confirming RNA-protein interactions. This approach was also demonstrated in this manuscript, and used to validate our in situ findings. Overall, we were able to achieve success with two of our three technological outcomes.&nbsp; With regard to educational outcomes, we were able to achieve success with our first proposed technological outcome,&nbsp;the design of cell biology course for undergraduates, that combines diagnostic question clusters, to improve and focus the didactic portions of the course, facilitating fact and concept acquisition, and problem-based learning (PBL) projects, to facilitate their ability to create new probes/interventions and understand how to target them to specific cellular components.&nbsp; Sets of DQC questions and PBL projects were created and have been shared across institutions.&nbsp; Overall, the use of PBL and DQC questions, was successful and implemented with over 300 students during the grant period.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/25/2021<br>      Modified by: Philip&nbsp;Santangelo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes: From this project there were a number of technological outcomes achieved, which were in line with our proposed outcomes, but like any research project they differed in the specifics as the project progressed.  The work primarily focused on our proposed second technological outcome, developing a general method for detecting RNA-protein interactions, with single molecule sensitivity, in situ.  This outcome was achieved, and given the importance of cancer at that time, we focused on demonstrating the approach to interrogate actual tumor tissue from patients.  This work was published in the presitgious journal, Cancer Research (Blanchard et al., Cancer Research, 2019). In that paper, we demonstrated the optimization of a method that is based on fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH) and proximity ligation (PLA) techniques to quantify mRNA interactions with RNA-binding proteins relevant for tumorigenesis and cancer progression in archival patient-derived tumor tissue. This method was validated for multiple mRNA-protein pairs in several cellular models and in multiple types of archival human tumor samples. Furthermore, this approach allowed high-throughput analysis of mRNA&ndash;protein interactions across a wide range of tumor types and stages through tumor microarrays. This method is quantitative, specific, and sensitive for detecting interactions and their localization at both the individual cell and whole-tissue scales with single interaction sensitivity. We demonstrated that abnormal mRNA&ndash;proteins interactions can be spatially resolved and quantified in various types of tumors in patient-derived samples. We believe PMTRIP FISH-PLA (the approach we developed) will be a valuable tool in investigating cancer biology on a high-throughput scale, with great potential for translatability into any disease where abnormal RNA&ndash;protein interactions occur. We did discover new relevant RNA-protein interactions in both colon and lung cancer. The increase of interactions between TIAR and polyadenylated or COX-2 mRNA in both colon and lung cancer was unexpected. TIAR represses translation and is thought to be a tumor suppressor, so we anticipated to measure fewer interactions with mRNA in tumors. However, the observed interactions correlated with the increased expression of TIAR and COX-2 mRNA observed in colon cancer samples. Strong TIAR signal has previously been observed in infiltrating inflammatory cells in tumors, which may explain the significant interactions detected by our assay, which relies on the ability to observe interactions on a whole tumor level. These interactions require further investigation, including the characterization by cell type and their heterogeneous spatial distribution across the tumor via immunofluorescence staining post-FISH-PLA.  In addition, we also validated our findings in cancer cell lines using immunoprecipitation (IP) and analysis of RNP complexes of a given RNA species within cells.  This was in accordance with our first proposed technological outcome, the development of an IP process for confirming RNA-protein interactions. This approach was also demonstrated in this manuscript, and used to validate our in situ findings. Overall, we were able to achieve success with two of our three technological outcomes.  With regard to educational outcomes, we were able to achieve success with our first proposed technological outcome, the design of cell biology course for undergraduates, that combines diagnostic question clusters, to improve and focus the didactic portions of the course, facilitating fact and concept acquisition, and problem-based learning (PBL) projects, to facilitate their ability to create new probes/interventions and understand how to target them to specific cellular components.  Sets of DQC questions and PBL projects were created and have been shared across institutions.  Overall, the use of PBL and DQC questions, was successful and implemented with over 300 students during the grant period.                  Last Modified: 02/25/2021       Submitted by: Philip Santangelo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
