<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Bulk and boundary properties of topological matter</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>465000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>465000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daryl Hess</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dhess@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER award supports theoretical research aimed at improving our understanding of topological phases of matter. Topological phases, such as fractional quantum Hall states and topological insulators, pose a fundamental conceptual challenge because they cannot be characterized using order parameters or symmetry breaking. Consequently, new concepts and tools need to be developed to understand these systems. The research supported by this award will focus on two aspects of these novel phases. First, the PI will investigate the general relationship between bulk and boundary properties of topological phases of matter. This 'bulk-boundary correspondence' is important both for theory and experiment since one of the easiest ways to probe these systems is via transport measurements at the boundary. Second, the PI will investigate concrete microscopic models for these phases, with the dual aims of (a) identifying experimental realizations and (b) understanding the deeper structure of these states and the limitations of numerical approaches. Some of the main topics that will be explored include:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1) Conditions for protected edge modes for 2D topological phases,&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2) Exactly soluble lattice models for 2D topological phases and their limitations,&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;3) Quasi-realistic models for bosonic integer quantum Hall states,&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;4) Bulk and surface properties of 3D bosonic symmetry-protected topological phases. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;In addition to research, this award supports education in two ways. First, the PI will create a new graduate class on 'Topology and Physics.' Importantly, this class will cover topological phenomena in both condensed matter and high energy physics with the goal of attracting a mixture of students from both groups and thereby facilitating interactions between the two subfields. Second, the PI will supervise summer research projects for undergraduates. Other benefits of this award will come from outreach activities, including several talks on quantum computing and superconductivity that will be given to the undergraduate students participating in the summer REU program at the University of Chicago.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NONTECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER award supports theoretical research aimed at improving our understanding of exotic phases of matter known as 'topological phases.' Just as a collection of water molecules can behave like a solid, a liquid, or a gas depending on the temperature and pressure, the electrons in a material can organize into metals, insulators, superconductors and other phases depending on various parameters. One of the basic goals of condensed matter physics is to characterize and analyze the different phases that can form in these many-electron or many-particle systems. More than 70 years ago, Lev Landau developed a powerful framework for answering these types of questions. His theory, based on the concept of symmetry, was able to explain a vast array of phases -- everything from superconductors to magnets. Despite these successes it is now clear that, in some materials, quantum effects can lead to new phases of matter that are fundamentally beyond the Landau paradigm. The most dramatic examples are known as 'topological phases.' These phases have a rich internal structure, but unlike conventional phases like magnets or superconductors, this structure has nothing to do with symmetry. Instead, the defining features of these phases have a topological character. As a result, entirely new concepts and tools need to be developed to understand these systems. The research supported by this award aims to develop this machinery with the ultimate goal of building a general theoretical framework, analogous to Landau theory, for analyzing these novel phases of matter.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to research, this award supports education in two ways. First, the PI will create a new graduate class on 'Topology and Physics.' Importantly, this class will cover topological phenomena in both condensed matter and high energy physics with the goal of attracting a mixture of students from both groups and thereby facilitating interactions between the two subfields. Second, the PI will supervise summer research projects for undergraduates. Other benefits of this proposal will come from outreach activities, including several talks on quantum computing and superconductivity that will be given to the undergraduate students participating in the summer REU program at the University of Chicago.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1254741</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Levin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Levin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>malevin@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056269</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000601171</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6054 South Drexel Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~186000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~93000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~93000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~93000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This CAREER award has supported the research group of a new faculty member in the Department of Physics at the University of Chicago over a five year period. The research that was funded by this grant focused on the theory of `topological phases of matter&rsquo; --- exotic phases of matter that can occur in certain materials at very low temperatures. As a result of this award, the PI and his research group made progress on three problems that are important for understanding these novel phases of matter. First, the PI and his group developed new theoretical tools for determining which topological phases have `protected edge modes&rsquo; and which do not. Second, the PI and his group constructed exactly solvable models for large classes of topological phases. These models have a number of potential applications, including serving as a starting point for numerical simulations of these systems. Finally, the PI and his group discovered a way to generalize the idea of `braiding statistics&rsquo; to three dimensional systems. The concept of braiding statistics is one of the most powerful tools for studying two dimensional topological phases and the generalization that was discovered as a result of this award may provide a similar tool in the three dimensional case.</p> <p>In addition to the scientific results described above, the award has supported in part four graduate students and a postdoctoral researcher. These junior participants were co-authors on almost all of the publications associated with the award, and were also given an opportunity to present their work each year at the March Meeting of the American Physical Society. In this way, junior members of the research group received training in science writing and communication in addition to technical training. More generally, the results of this project were presented in over 30 seminars and conference talks over the period of the award.</p> <p>As part of the educational component of the project, the PI created a new graduate course on topological phases of matter at the University of Chicago, with the course number Physics 412. When it was taught for the first time, the course had 12 students and 5 auditors, coming from a wide variety of backgrounds including at least one undergraduate, and several graduate students specializing in molecular engineering, atomic physics, and high energy physics. The course will be offered again in the coming year, giving more students an opportunity to learn about these novel phases of matter.</p> <p>An additional educational benefit was that the PI gave eight lectures on topological phases of matter at two summer schools at the University of Colorado and the University of Illinois. As further outreach, the PI also gave annual lectures on his research to undergraduate research students at the University of Chicago as well as to the Society of Physics Students.</p> <!-- p { margin-bottom: 0.1in; line-height: 115%; } --><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/10/2018<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;Levin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This CAREER award has supported the research group of a new faculty member in the Department of Physics at the University of Chicago over a five year period. The research that was funded by this grant focused on the theory of `topological phases of matter? --- exotic phases of matter that can occur in certain materials at very low temperatures. As a result of this award, the PI and his research group made progress on three problems that are important for understanding these novel phases of matter. First, the PI and his group developed new theoretical tools for determining which topological phases have `protected edge modes? and which do not. Second, the PI and his group constructed exactly solvable models for large classes of topological phases. These models have a number of potential applications, including serving as a starting point for numerical simulations of these systems. Finally, the PI and his group discovered a way to generalize the idea of `braiding statistics? to three dimensional systems. The concept of braiding statistics is one of the most powerful tools for studying two dimensional topological phases and the generalization that was discovered as a result of this award may provide a similar tool in the three dimensional case.  In addition to the scientific results described above, the award has supported in part four graduate students and a postdoctoral researcher. These junior participants were co-authors on almost all of the publications associated with the award, and were also given an opportunity to present their work each year at the March Meeting of the American Physical Society. In this way, junior members of the research group received training in science writing and communication in addition to technical training. More generally, the results of this project were presented in over 30 seminars and conference talks over the period of the award.  As part of the educational component of the project, the PI created a new graduate course on topological phases of matter at the University of Chicago, with the course number Physics 412. When it was taught for the first time, the course had 12 students and 5 auditors, coming from a wide variety of backgrounds including at least one undergraduate, and several graduate students specializing in molecular engineering, atomic physics, and high energy physics. The course will be offered again in the coming year, giving more students an opportunity to learn about these novel phases of matter.  An additional educational benefit was that the PI gave eight lectures on topological phases of matter at two summer schools at the University of Colorado and the University of Illinois. As further outreach, the PI also gave annual lectures on his research to undergraduate research students at the University of Chicago as well as to the Society of Physics Students.        Last Modified: 10/10/2018       Submitted by: Michael Levin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
