<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: IDBR: Instrumented Diamond Window for Synchrotron Beamlines</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>244764.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>244764</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Sanford</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the structure and dynamics of biological molecules and their interactions has proven to be critical in understanding, and even influencing, their functions. National synchrotron facilities provide a powerful array of tools for such structural biology studies, including a variety of x-ray techniques such as macromolecular x-ray crystallography, small-angle x-ray solution scattering, x-ray microscopy, x-ray absorption spectroscopy, x-ray fluorescence and x-ray footprinting. Many of these technologies, as they are developed to take advantage of next-generation synchrotron sources, are trending toward use of high flux beams and/or beams which require enhanced stability and precise understanding of beam position and intensity. An award is made to an integrated collaborative team from Case Western Reserve University, Stony Brook University and Brookhaven National Laboratory to develop instrumented diamond-based vacuum windows capable of simultaneously measuring the volumetric flux, position and morphology of a high flux x-ray beam to address the needs of these upcoming facilities. Because the instrument is integrated into a vacuum window, these devices are expected to offer a robust replacement option for the fragile, toxic beryllium windows nearly ubiquitous in current x-ray beamlines, while also providing beam monitoring capabilities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will directly enhance the research infrastructure at current and next-generation bioscience beamlines, with capabilities applicable across many scientific disciplines. Our national synchrotron user facilities are critical resources both for research and education, serving many thousands of users from nearly every scientific discipline every year, thus the potential user community for these devices is quite profound. These facilities also serve as training grounds at all levels of education, with programs for community outreach, K-12 programs, undergraduate internships, graduate dissertation research, postdoctoral training, and workshops to introduce established scientists to new research tools. In addition to active participation in these programs, this project directly supports the training of a graduate student who will learn a broad range of experimental techniques, taking advantage of the diverse expertise of the collaborative group. Recruitment of undergraduate students from the REU program is also expected to enhance the program. The multi-institution collaboration established to develop the instrument is comprised of researchers from the fields of biophysics, accelerator physics, and materials science, and the project includes academic, government and industrial participation. This diverse set of backgrounds will provide a breadth of experience for student training through the project. The instrument design and software developed during the project will be disseminated through publication, participation in conferences and workshops as well as seminars specifically directed toward educating the synchrotron community. Upon successful completion of this project, it is expected that funding will be pursued to move these devices into a broadly applicable format appropriate for commercial production.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1254804</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
<LastName>Muller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erik M Muller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>erik.muller@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6313448112</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000540053</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804878247</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brookhaven National Laboratory]]></Name>
<CityName>Upton</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>119735000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Building 535B]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1108</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~112889</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~131875</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>High intensity x-rays produced by modern synchrotrons have many useful applications in areas such as condensed matter physics, materials science, biology and medicine. The National Synchrotron Light Source II (NSLS-II), a brand new facility at Brookhaven National Laboratory (BNL), provides world leading capabilities for x-ray imaging and high resolution energy analysis, and brings together researchers from diverse scientific disciplines. The intensity of the powerful x-ray beams produced at NSLS-II requires the design of new detectors constructed from materials that are capable of operating in these extreme radiation conditions. One such material is synthetic diamond, which is resistant to radiation damage, is transparent to x-rays, and has high thermal conductivity (necessary for carrying away the heat produced in these powerful beams), thus making it an ideal material for the measurement of x-ray beams. In comparison to natural diamond, synthetic diamond has a much higher purity, which gives it far superior electrical properties. Dr. Erik Muller&rsquo;s group in the Materials Science and Engineering Department, in collaboration with researchers at BNL and Case Western Reserve University (CWRU), have developed a new x-ray monitor using synthetic diamond to measure flux and position at NSLS-II as well as synchrotrons worldwide. They recently published this work in the <em>Journal of Synchrotron Radiation</em>, describing one of these unique devices that not only measures beam position and flux but also beam shape, essentially the equivalent of a transparent x-ray camera with more than 1000 pixels. One critical feature of this detector is that it has no interconnects occluding the back of the detector (like the camera in your smartphone) allowing the beam to be directly transmitted through the detector to the experiment.</p> <p>The successful development of this x-ray imaging detector resulted from 2 years of close collaboration between Dr. Muller and Dr. John Smedley, a physicist from BNL, and Dr. Jen Bohon, a structural biologist at CWRU. Dr. Muller, working with students from the Materials Science and Engineering Department (Tianyi Zhou, Mengnan Zou, and recently graduated Mengjia Gaowei), led the sensor development, fabrication (at the Center for Functional Nanomaterials) and testing. A graduate student in the Electrical and Computer Engineering Department (Wenxiang Ding) developed the readout electronics under the guidance of Dr. Gianluigi De Geronimo, Adjunct Professor in Electrical and Computer Engineering. The team is continually improving the detector performance by pursuing larger area, thinner detectors with faster readout. These detectors have much potential beyond synchrotron science -- including high energy particle beam detectors, medical x-ray imaging and radiotherapy.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/26/2016<br>      Modified by: Erik&nbsp;M&nbsp;Muller</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ High intensity x-rays produced by modern synchrotrons have many useful applications in areas such as condensed matter physics, materials science, biology and medicine. The National Synchrotron Light Source II (NSLS-II), a brand new facility at Brookhaven National Laboratory (BNL), provides world leading capabilities for x-ray imaging and high resolution energy analysis, and brings together researchers from diverse scientific disciplines. The intensity of the powerful x-ray beams produced at NSLS-II requires the design of new detectors constructed from materials that are capable of operating in these extreme radiation conditions. One such material is synthetic diamond, which is resistant to radiation damage, is transparent to x-rays, and has high thermal conductivity (necessary for carrying away the heat produced in these powerful beams), thus making it an ideal material for the measurement of x-ray beams. In comparison to natural diamond, synthetic diamond has a much higher purity, which gives it far superior electrical properties. Dr. Erik MullerÆs group in the Materials Science and Engineering Department, in collaboration with researchers at BNL and Case Western Reserve University (CWRU), have developed a new x-ray monitor using synthetic diamond to measure flux and position at NSLS-II as well as synchrotrons worldwide. They recently published this work in the Journal of Synchrotron Radiation, describing one of these unique devices that not only measures beam position and flux but also beam shape, essentially the equivalent of a transparent x-ray camera with more than 1000 pixels. One critical feature of this detector is that it has no interconnects occluding the back of the detector (like the camera in your smartphone) allowing the beam to be directly transmitted through the detector to the experiment.  The successful development of this x-ray imaging detector resulted from 2 years of close collaboration between Dr. Muller and Dr. John Smedley, a physicist from BNL, and Dr. Jen Bohon, a structural biologist at CWRU. Dr. Muller, working with students from the Materials Science and Engineering Department (Tianyi Zhou, Mengnan Zou, and recently graduated Mengjia Gaowei), led the sensor development, fabrication (at the Center for Functional Nanomaterials) and testing. A graduate student in the Electrical and Computer Engineering Department (Wenxiang Ding) developed the readout electronics under the guidance of Dr. Gianluigi De Geronimo, Adjunct Professor in Electrical and Computer Engineering. The team is continually improving the detector performance by pursuing larger area, thinner detectors with faster readout. These detectors have much potential beyond synchrotron science -- including high energy particle beam detectors, medical x-ray imaging and radiotherapy.           Last Modified: 01/26/2016       Submitted by: Erik M Muller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
