<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CIF21 DIBBs: Designing the Roadmap for Social Network Data Management</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>109738.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>109738</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Chadduck</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rchadduc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922247</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CIF21 DIBBs: Designing the Roadmap for Social Network Data Management &lt;br/&gt;Scholarly interest in network analysis has increased dramatically in the social sciences and beyond. The explosion of social media tools such as Facebook, Flickr, and Twitter, along with new developments in machine learning and data mining have produced new types of behavioral data for scholars to analyze (Mislove et al., 2007). Significant advances in mathematics, statistics, and computer science have also produced unprecedented opportunities to analyze ?Big? social network data. Social network analysis sits at the cutting edge of social science and also links the social, natural, and computational sciences. Understanding the multi-faceted nature of social networks and their effects on human behavior is one of the grand challenges faced as this project seeks to maximize our investments in scientific research (NSF-ACCI, 2011). However, the community has not seen comparable advances in the management, archiving, and sharing of social network data. This presents a fundamental obstacle to advancing network science across the social, natural, and computational sciences. This proposal seeks to begin to remedy this problem. The data management needs social network scholars are complex. Network data often come from unstructured environments that require researchers to define and describe a set of units or actors (called nodes) and the connections (called edges) between them. Networks might be static or dynamic, include one type of node or multiple node types, and include edges that are uni-directional or bi-directional and weighted or unweighted. In addition, as relationships spread within the network and/or a network grows, the associated data management, data storage, and analytical memory requirements can grow exponentially.  This proposal brings together the social network analysis, information science, computer science, and data archive communities to develop a data infrastructure to support advanced analysis and research on social networks as well as to facilitate data sharing and archiving within this community. The group will address key questions concerning data storage architecture and lifecycle requirements, develop design specifications for creating a sustainable data infrastructure that will be discoverable, searchable, accessible, and usable to the entire research and education community, and initialize a prototype solution based on that plan.  Intellectual Merit: The proposed project will bring together the social network analysis community to work with information technology professionals to design a robust data management infrastructure to promote the sharing and interoperability of social network data. Effective data management for social network data amplifies the impact of research by revealing data quality issues early in the data collection process, ensuring that required data is retained and usable throughout the life of a research project. It also facilitates data sharing and reuse. A key to responsible data stewardship is the application and auditing of quality data management policies ? something included in this proposal. Providing a robust infrastructure to store, analyze, curate, share, and manage important social network data will increase researchers? production and provide an unprecedented view of the social world only visible through social network data.  Broader Impacts: The project will facilitate data sharing and increase social network data availability while assuring researchers that data management policies are followed. It will help formalize a community of network data experts that will begin developing best practices for the community. Availability of data particularly benefits early-stage researchers, and researchers at diverse institutions. Widespread availability of data facilitates citizen science and the integration of science and teaching at all levels of education. Managed data sharing is critical to the multi disciplinary research to answer the critical challenges facing society today. It would be difficult to overstate the importance of social network analysis to better understand human networks and social behavior.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1255826</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Carsey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas M Carsey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>carsey@unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9199663411</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000498404</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>608195277</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[H.W. Odum Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Chapel Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275993355</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Room 25 Manning Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7726</Code>
<Text>Data Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8048</Code>
<Text>Data Infrstr Bldg Blocks-DIBBs</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~109738</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The focus of this project was to identify key challenges in the collection, storage, and sharing of social network data with the goal of beginning to develop some common standards and best practices for researchers working in this field.&nbsp; Social network analysis has a long history in the social and behavioral sciences, but has recently remerged with the advent of new sophisticated statistical methods.&nbsp; Scholars study social networks because so much of how individuals behave is shaped by those with whom those individuals interact.&nbsp; Traditional regression-based methods of analysis are simply not able to fully capture this type of interdependency.&nbsp; However, social network data is often more complex than traditional social/behavioral data because of the need to capture relational interactions.&nbsp; It is also frequently quite large.&nbsp; The result is that there are no common standards for how to collect, organize, and store network data.&nbsp; This creates barriers to sharing such data between researchers, collaborating with other researchers, and setting standards for research transparency and data access for research using social network data.&nbsp; Thus, this project had as its objective a survey of current practices with the hope of beginning to develop some standards for best practices.</p> <p>The project itself included participation in several conferences and workshops, a graduate seminar in computational social science, and a small survey of social network analysis experts. The information gathered from both the surveys and through presentations at conferences to groups of experts produced several tentative conclusions.</p> <p>First, there is tremendous variation in the researchers conducting social network analysis, the tools they use, and the problems they encounter. &nbsp;It is clear that the first barrier to developing common standards and best practices is that the community has not evolved anything close to similar practices on its own. &nbsp;For example, scholars are using everything from advanced specialized commercial software for network analysis (e.g. UCINET), packages within established commercial software (e.g. SAS), a broad range of tools in open source platforms (e.g. R and Python), and even many tools not really well designed for any analysis of even moderate sophistication (e.g. Access, Excel). &nbsp;There are also significant divides between those who analyze complete networks and those who study incomplete or ego-centric networks. &nbsp;Furthermore, some scholars mention needing to work with Terabytes of data while others have networks that involve just a few dozen individuals. &nbsp;There is nothing close to a "one-size-fits-all" solution emerging in this field -- there seems not to even been a clear "few-sizes-fit-many" clustering of solutions emerging yet.</p> <p>Second, there were more concerns raised about the challenges associated with collecting social network data than any other facet of the research process. &nbsp;Researchers struggle to obtain the resources for collecting network data -- a process that is often more complex, and thus more costly, than other forms of data collection. &nbsp;There are also privacy concerns with network data in many cases that do not emerge from more traditional forms of data that create problems for researchers with their Institutional Review Boards. &nbsp;For example, in many network data collection efforts, Respondent A might be asked to report on Respondent B regarding particularly private or sensitive information and Respondent B may have no ability to give consent to such reporting.</p> <p>Third, there were substantial concerns raised about issues in manipulating and analyzing social network data. &nbsp; This was closer to the focus on this particular project, so in a way it was encouraging to learn that researchers see these concerns as significant. &nbsp;It appears that pa...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The focus of this project was to identify key challenges in the collection, storage, and sharing of social network data with the goal of beginning to develop some common standards and best practices for researchers working in this field.  Social network analysis has a long history in the social and behavioral sciences, but has recently remerged with the advent of new sophisticated statistical methods.  Scholars study social networks because so much of how individuals behave is shaped by those with whom those individuals interact.  Traditional regression-based methods of analysis are simply not able to fully capture this type of interdependency.  However, social network data is often more complex than traditional social/behavioral data because of the need to capture relational interactions.  It is also frequently quite large.  The result is that there are no common standards for how to collect, organize, and store network data.  This creates barriers to sharing such data between researchers, collaborating with other researchers, and setting standards for research transparency and data access for research using social network data.  Thus, this project had as its objective a survey of current practices with the hope of beginning to develop some standards for best practices.  The project itself included participation in several conferences and workshops, a graduate seminar in computational social science, and a small survey of social network analysis experts. The information gathered from both the surveys and through presentations at conferences to groups of experts produced several tentative conclusions.  First, there is tremendous variation in the researchers conducting social network analysis, the tools they use, and the problems they encounter.  It is clear that the first barrier to developing common standards and best practices is that the community has not evolved anything close to similar practices on its own.  For example, scholars are using everything from advanced specialized commercial software for network analysis (e.g. UCINET), packages within established commercial software (e.g. SAS), a broad range of tools in open source platforms (e.g. R and Python), and even many tools not really well designed for any analysis of even moderate sophistication (e.g. Access, Excel).  There are also significant divides between those who analyze complete networks and those who study incomplete or ego-centric networks.  Furthermore, some scholars mention needing to work with Terabytes of data while others have networks that involve just a few dozen individuals.  There is nothing close to a "one-size-fits-all" solution emerging in this field -- there seems not to even been a clear "few-sizes-fit-many" clustering of solutions emerging yet.  Second, there were more concerns raised about the challenges associated with collecting social network data than any other facet of the research process.  Researchers struggle to obtain the resources for collecting network data -- a process that is often more complex, and thus more costly, than other forms of data collection.  There are also privacy concerns with network data in many cases that do not emerge from more traditional forms of data that create problems for researchers with their Institutional Review Boards.  For example, in many network data collection efforts, Respondent A might be asked to report on Respondent B regarding particularly private or sensitive information and Respondent B may have no ability to give consent to such reporting.  Third, there were substantial concerns raised about issues in manipulating and analyzing social network data.   This was closer to the focus on this particular project, so in a way it was encouraging to learn that researchers see these concerns as significant.  It appears that part of the concerns raised about collecting network data is linked to the challenges of organizing that data, so these two concerns are linked.  Fourth, most researchers contact...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
