<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IDBR:   Portable monitoring device for off-gassed volatile plant metabolites</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600039.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>600039</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rfleisch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An award is made to the University of California, Davis to develop a small, mobile chemical detection platform for the plant science research community.  Plant sciences in the 21st century broadly makes use of many instruments to assess plant health status and stress changes, and these instruments can be very useful to study important agriculture and horticulture systems.  One key plant science research need has not been addressed by existing portable instrumentation platforms.  All plants and trees produce (off-gas) volatile organic compounds (VOCs) as a normal byproduct of baseline physiological processes.  These VOCs are chemicals that represent a unique non-invasive route to assess plant health, infection, nutrient stresses, and many other important biological questions. However, prior instrumentation to assess and monitor these plant VOCs has been rudimentary at best, has many manual steps, and relies heavily on laboratory-based analytical chemistry equipment.  This project will create a miniature portable easy-to-use detection system for these VOCs.  It will be highly sensitive and be capable of quantifying the amount of specific VOCs that are released from plants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Agriculture remains a critical portion of many national economies, and is regionally important to many communities.  New scientific breakthroughs that can enhance food production and safety will ultimately have large societal and economic benefits.  This project will engage in extensive outreach efforts across all education levels, bringing together trainees from multiple disciplines. Each year an undergraduate engineering student team will contribute to a technical task of the instrument development plan.  Mentoring and career development for both graduate students and post-PhD researchers are a key aim of this proposal as well.  Finally, this project allows for broad dissemination of the research tool to the plant science community as a new commercial product.  The new VOC detection system can be broadly used by many researchers in the plant science community to investigate topics ranging from host pathogen responses to fruit quality assessment and even to assessing the effect of pest eradication efforts in field settings.  The platform can ultimately be tailored for many different plant science research questions, which are likely to lead to increased agriculture performance across the world.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1255915</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cristina</FirstName>
<LastName>Davis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cristina E Davis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cedavis@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307479004</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000242622</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Aksenov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander Aksenov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aaaksenov@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307547000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000596249</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956186153</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1108</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~380792</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~219247</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our laboratory has made major advances to develop small scale, mobile chemical sensors. We focus on sensors that detect volatile organic compounds (VOCs), or gaseous chemicals. All living systems emit chemicals into the air. Plant VOCs can be used by plant systems to attract pollinators, or other insects. However, plants are even sophisticated enough to communicate to each other via scents. For example, if an herbivore begins feeding on a plant, the plant can release an odor that will attract the herbivore&rsquo;s predator, defending the plant.&nbsp; Intercepting these plant-plant, plant-insect or even plant-pathogen communications can be extremely useful in real world settings. Thus, a portable VOC detector could &ldquo;smell&rdquo; these signals can be used for many type of agriculture management and can be widely used by researchers to study these complex problems.</p> <p>Our laboratory was able to develop two novel, microscale trace chemical detection sensors. Current detector technologies are relatively large and are often difficult to take out of laboratories. Our laboratory developed novel, microscale chemical detectors that could be easily placed into a mobile platform. One sensor, called a micro differential mobility spectrometer, took a preexisting detector and reduced its size into a device only a couple inches long. A second sensor, uses a completely new way to detect volatile compounds. Like the first sensor, it is extremely small and was developed with portability in mind. Both have drastically reduced power consumption needs, greatly increasing their portability.</p> <p>Many of our sensors are so small that they require specialized fabrication techniques. This can be prohibitive, as institutions such as universities may not always have the required tools for these processes. In this grant, we developed a new fabrication technique, which can be used to easily etch flow channels in our sensors without the need for expensive equipment.</p> <p>We also worked to develop accessories to improve chemical detection in a complete, portable detector platform. Our team developed a new micro gas preconcentrator, which increases the sensitivity of our chemical detectors, allowing them to detect chemicals in extremely small concentrations. We also published an open-access software that interprets the data. It applies advanced statistics and performs model building, which determines if a plant sample came from a healthy or infected plant.</p> <div id="_mcePaste" class="mcePaste" style="position: absolute; left: -10000px; top: 889px; width: 1px; height: 1px; overflow: hidden;"><span style="color: #1f497d; font-family: Calibri, sans-serif; font-size: 14.6667px;">Due to the tremendous scientific success of this program, Prof. Cristina Davis has worked with her UC Davis technology transfer office to aggressively patent and prepare commercialization plans for the pieces of technology developed or invented under this effort.&nbsp; The technologies from this award were aggregated together with other chemical sensor technologies that were developed in her lab under separate funding.&nbsp; Together this package of IP was licensed to a start-up company SensIT Ventures, Inc.&nbsp; Prof. Davis is a Co-Founder of the company, and equity holder, and she acts as a Scientific Advisor to the start-up.&nbsp; She has received Conflict-of-Interest training from UC Davis, and is actively helping to push forward the commercialization of the technologies. &nbsp;There are several key technology sectors that the trace chemical detection IP from Prof. Davis&rsquo; group enables: (1) plant and agriculture applications; (2) homeland security and defense; (3) industrial process control; and (4) healthcare applications.&nbsp; The company is formulating strategic plans and partnering with stakeholders in multiple areas, at this time.&nbsp;</span></div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Cristina&nbsp;E&nbsp;Davis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1255915/1255915_10235339_1506448696727_2_polyimidemask--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1255915/1255915_10235339_1506448696727_2_polyimidemask--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Chromium Polyimide Technique"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1255915/1255915_10235339_1506448696727_2_polyimidemask--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Chromium Polyimide Technique"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Examples of microchannels etched with our newly developed fabrication process. These flow channels can be used for chemical detection in miniaturized devices. We reduced the fabrication time from days to hours with our new technique.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Regents of the University of California</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cristina&nbsp;E&nbsp;Davis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Chromium Polyimide Technique</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1255915/1255915_10235339_1506448745468_3_upc--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1255915/1255915_10235339_1506448745468_3_upc--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Micro gas preconcentrator"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1255915/1255915_10235339_1506448745468_3_upc--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Micro gas preconcentrator"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Our newly developed micro gas preconcentrator helps increase the limits of detection of our chemical sensors. This means we can detect extremely small concentrations in the air. In our experiments, we reached the low part per billion levels.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Regents of the University of California</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cristina&nbsp;E&nbsp;Davis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Micro gas preconcentrator</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1255915/1255915_10235339_1506448975691_5_gc-dms--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1255915/1255915_10235339_1506448975691_5_gc-dms--rgov-800width.jpg" title="GC-DMS Portable Chemical Sensor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1255915/1255915_10235339_1506448975691_5_gc-dms--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="GC-DMS Portable Chemical Sensor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">We built a new GC-DMS mobile chemical detection platform. This system can be used completely out of the laboratory for real-time chemical analysis.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Regents of the University of California</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cristina&nbsp;E&nbsp;Davis</div> <div class="imageTitle">GC-DMS Portable Chemical Sensor</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our laboratory has made major advances to develop small scale, mobile chemical sensors. We focus on sensors that detect volatile organic compounds (VOCs), or gaseous chemicals. All living systems emit chemicals into the air. Plant VOCs can be used by plant systems to attract pollinators, or other insects. However, plants are even sophisticated enough to communicate to each other via scents. For example, if an herbivore begins feeding on a plant, the plant can release an odor that will attract the herbivore?s predator, defending the plant.  Intercepting these plant-plant, plant-insect or even plant-pathogen communications can be extremely useful in real world settings. Thus, a portable VOC detector could "smell" these signals can be used for many type of agriculture management and can be widely used by researchers to study these complex problems.  Our laboratory was able to develop two novel, microscale trace chemical detection sensors. Current detector technologies are relatively large and are often difficult to take out of laboratories. Our laboratory developed novel, microscale chemical detectors that could be easily placed into a mobile platform. One sensor, called a micro differential mobility spectrometer, took a preexisting detector and reduced its size into a device only a couple inches long. A second sensor, uses a completely new way to detect volatile compounds. Like the first sensor, it is extremely small and was developed with portability in mind. Both have drastically reduced power consumption needs, greatly increasing their portability.  Many of our sensors are so small that they require specialized fabrication techniques. This can be prohibitive, as institutions such as universities may not always have the required tools for these processes. In this grant, we developed a new fabrication technique, which can be used to easily etch flow channels in our sensors without the need for expensive equipment.  We also worked to develop accessories to improve chemical detection in a complete, portable detector platform. Our team developed a new micro gas preconcentrator, which increases the sensitivity of our chemical detectors, allowing them to detect chemicals in extremely small concentrations. We also published an open-access software that interprets the data. It applies advanced statistics and performs model building, which determines if a plant sample came from a healthy or infected plant. Due to the tremendous scientific success of this program, Prof. Cristina Davis has worked with her UC Davis technology transfer office to aggressively patent and prepare commercialization plans for the pieces of technology developed or invented under this effort.  The technologies from this award were aggregated together with other chemical sensor technologies that were developed in her lab under separate funding.  Together this package of IP was licensed to a start-up company SensIT Ventures, Inc.  Prof. Davis is a Co-Founder of the company, and equity holder, and she acts as a Scientific Advisor to the start-up.  She has received Conflict-of-Interest training from UC Davis, and is actively helping to push forward the commercialization of the technologies.  There are several key technology sectors that the trace chemical detection IP from Prof. Davis? group enables: (1) plant and agriculture applications; (2) homeland security and defense; (3) industrial process control; and (4) healthcare applications.  The company is formulating strategic plans and partnering with stakeholders in multiple areas, at this time.        Last Modified: 09/30/2017       Submitted by: Cristina E Davis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
