<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Cross-Layer Intelligent System-Based Adaptive Power Conditioning for Robust and Reliable Mixed-Signal Multi-Core SoCs</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>192000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>192000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sabasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927843</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project seeks to investigate the effectiveness of adaptive power conditioning in averting failures and enhancing reliability of mixed-signal multi-core Systems-on-Chips (SoCs), while retaining power efficiency. The investigation aims to leverage the increasing integration of non-intrusive sensors for monitoring various operational parameters and cost-effective tuning knobs for calibrating circuit performance through online power condition adjustment. The project aims to develop a cross-layer intelligent system, which will continuously adjust the flow of the entire power distribution network based on the feedback provided by the sensors. Ultimately, the aspiration of this project is to demonstrate that a holistic approach to adaptive power conditioning can (i) ensure operational robustness while minimizing power consumption, and (ii) enhance reliability and prolong life expectancy of integrated circuits. The intellectual contribution of this work will be in the development of a practical, yet theoretically rooted and analytically supported intelligent system for capturing correlations between circuit performance, sensor readings, and calibration knob positions, and utilizing them to improve robustness and reliability. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research is complemented by educational and outreach activities demonstrating the principle investigators' (PIs') commitment to an integrated role as researchers, educators, and active community members. A new graduate-level course will be developed and offered by the PIs, who have proven track records of involving the students of various levels in their research activities, including women and other under-represented groups. Several opportunities for participation in interdisciplinary research spanning Electrical Engineering, Computer Science, and Applied Mathematics as well as internships with industrial partners are expected.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/01/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1255754</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yiorgos</FirstName>
<LastName>Makris</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yiorgos Makris</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yiorgos.makris@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728834360</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488515</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>D Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Ma</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>D Brian Ma</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>d.ma@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728835558</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000493989</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800188161</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT DALLAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Dallas]]></Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 W. Campbell Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8081</Code>
<Text>Failure Resistant Systems(FRS)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~128000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~32000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~32000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main objective for this project was to design an intelligent cross layer system which reduces aging of the circuit components based on the workload profile that it can predict. To implement this task, the project was divided in 2 parts.</p> <ol> <li>Setting up an infrastructure to smoothly transition between system level and circuit level. The infrastructure consists of Multi-Core and Multi-thread processor.</li> <li>Develop and characterize sensors and power tuning knobs which are to be implemented on the circuit and would act as a feedback to the system and change the performance of the system with the aging reduction goal in mind.</li> </ol> <p>The key outcomes of the project are listed below:</p> <ol> <li>We have achieved the ability to perform workload execution on real OS and system, collect Performance traces by utilizing the available Performance Monitoring registers. Then we used the traces to develop and train the Prediction model based of Support Vector Regression method. Also we used the same traces to generate the equivalent power consumption per core using McPAT power simulator. Later on, we showed that our SVR prediction model is able to predict the traces into the future without any dynamic retraining. The same prediction model was able to predict the Performance monitoring register values for different benchmarks without further retraining. The max error observer with our predictor was 12% which was on par with the ARMA model (ARMA model requires retraining whenever a threshold has been reached in the traces). </li> <li>We developed the capability to ran workload on the RTL design of the OpenSPARC T1 processor and generate the activity on the core and some particular modules (ALU). This activity trace was then annotated into the synthesized module and generated more accurate power number from the synthesized netlist activity.&nbsp; The goal was to use this number as a feedback to the upper layer (Architectural level) to have a more accurate power estimation using cross layer feature. </li> <li>To provide a power supply efficiently and reliably, a high-frequency, monolithic, and breakdown-resilient power converter was designed. The two-stage cascaded structure overcomes the high risk of breakdown, and the implementation of each stage enables the area-efficient fully monolithic integration. The 2/5 SC power stage realizes reliable and efficient voltage conversion, while the fully on-chip LDO regulator regulates the output with a wide bandwidth and a high PSRR. A monolithic switched-capacitor power converter is designed in the nanoscale CMOS technology, employing a two-stage system architecture to mitigate overvoltage breakdown risk. The efficiency impact of various parasitic components is analyzed for design optimization on both the topology level and the device level. An external capacitor-less low-dropout regulator with a wide bandwidth and a high power supply rejection ratio is introduced, removing high-frequency ripples and enabling a fast load transient response. The proposed design was implemented with the 180-nm CMOS process. At a switching frequency of 100 MHz, it regulates output voltage at 0.8 V, with a maximum power efficiency of 60%. When the load current changes between 1.5 and 15 mA, the respond time is within 45 ns, with a voltage droop below 45 mV.</li> <li>A course module on Robust, Reliable and Power-Efficient System Design was developed, 4 Ph.D. students were educated and industry was made aware of these contributions through presentations at SRC review meetings. </li> </ol><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Yiorgos&nbsp;Makris</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1255754/1255754_10231053_1490756072306_Overall_System--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1255754/1255754_10231053_1490756072306_Overall_System--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Overall System"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1255754/1255754_10231053_1490756072306_Overall_System--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Overall System"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">High-Level View of Project Objective</div> <div class="imageCredit">Y. Makris & D. Ma</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yiorgos&nbsp;Makris</div> <div class="imageTitle">Overall System</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main objective for this project was to design an intelligent cross layer system which reduces aging of the circuit components based on the workload profile that it can predict. To implement this task, the project was divided in 2 parts.  Setting up an infrastructure to smoothly transition between system level and circuit level. The infrastructure consists of Multi-Core and Multi-thread processor. Develop and characterize sensors and power tuning knobs which are to be implemented on the circuit and would act as a feedback to the system and change the performance of the system with the aging reduction goal in mind.   The key outcomes of the project are listed below:  We have achieved the ability to perform workload execution on real OS and system, collect Performance traces by utilizing the available Performance Monitoring registers. Then we used the traces to develop and train the Prediction model based of Support Vector Regression method. Also we used the same traces to generate the equivalent power consumption per core using McPAT power simulator. Later on, we showed that our SVR prediction model is able to predict the traces into the future without any dynamic retraining. The same prediction model was able to predict the Performance monitoring register values for different benchmarks without further retraining. The max error observer with our predictor was 12% which was on par with the ARMA model (ARMA model requires retraining whenever a threshold has been reached in the traces).  We developed the capability to ran workload on the RTL design of the OpenSPARC T1 processor and generate the activity on the core and some particular modules (ALU). This activity trace was then annotated into the synthesized module and generated more accurate power number from the synthesized netlist activity.  The goal was to use this number as a feedback to the upper layer (Architectural level) to have a more accurate power estimation using cross layer feature.  To provide a power supply efficiently and reliably, a high-frequency, monolithic, and breakdown-resilient power converter was designed. The two-stage cascaded structure overcomes the high risk of breakdown, and the implementation of each stage enables the area-efficient fully monolithic integration. The 2/5 SC power stage realizes reliable and efficient voltage conversion, while the fully on-chip LDO regulator regulates the output with a wide bandwidth and a high PSRR. A monolithic switched-capacitor power converter is designed in the nanoscale CMOS technology, employing a two-stage system architecture to mitigate overvoltage breakdown risk. The efficiency impact of various parasitic components is analyzed for design optimization on both the topology level and the device level. An external capacitor-less low-dropout regulator with a wide bandwidth and a high power supply rejection ratio is introduced, removing high-frequency ripples and enabling a fast load transient response. The proposed design was implemented with the 180-nm CMOS process. At a switching frequency of 100 MHz, it regulates output voltage at 0.8 V, with a maximum power efficiency of 60%. When the load current changes between 1.5 and 15 mA, the respond time is within 45 ns, with a voltage droop below 45 mV. A course module on Robust, Reliable and Power-Efficient System Design was developed, 4 Ph.D. students were educated and industry was made aware of these contributions through presentations at SRC review meetings.         Last Modified: 03/28/2017       Submitted by: Yiorgos Makris]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
