<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Determination of enzyme mechanisms using new kinetic isotope effect approaches</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>550000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>550000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robin McCarley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccarle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927514</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this CAREER award, the Chemistry of Life Processes Program is supporting Dr. Andrew Murkin of the University at Buffalo, The State University of New York, in the development of new methods for studying the mechanisms of enzymatic reactions.  The objective of this research is to determine the transition state structures of two enzymes that catalyze reactions with unresolved mechanisms. To reach this goal, Dr. Murkin developed a method for measuring kinetic isotope effects based on two-dimentional NMR spectroscopy that delivers better sensitivity and precision than previous methods. Transition state models will be constructed by matching the theoretical kinetic isotope effects obtained computationally to those measured experimentally.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When a molecule undergoes a reaction and reaches the transition state, the atoms that react or experience geometric or electrostatic changes exert differences in rates when substituted with heavier isotopes. Such kinetic isotope effects provide an experimentally accessible picture of the substrate during the rate-limiting step in a mechanism.  The techniques developed from this award should be of interest to a wide audience of scientists who depend on kinetic isotope effects to study a variety of processes, including the design of new therapies. This program is also designed to encourage youth to pursue training in biochemistry and related sciences. To stimulate educational interest among youth, an introduction to enzymes will be provided to K-12 students in greater-Buffalo schools, including underrepresented youths, through informative hands-on, inquiry-based experiments conducted in middle schools and in a university laboratory. At the university level, the design of transition state inhibitors and measurement of kinetic isotope effects will be integrated into undergraduate and graduate chemistry courses.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1255136</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Murkin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew S Murkin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amurkin@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7166454249</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000581490</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038633251</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142603000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~330000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~220000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A catalyst serves to increase the rate of a reaction by providing a pathway for the reactant to transform into the product using less energy than in its absence. The overall rate is largely dictated by the highest-energy species along the path known as the transition state (TS). The structure of the TS is of great interest to chemists attempting to design new and improved catalysts as well as to researchers who would like to prevent catalysis, such as in the case of enzyme inhibition, which is the goal of many therapeutic drugs. Owing to its extremely short existence, on the order of 10<sup>&ndash;14</sup> seconds, the TS eludes most experimental techniques used to determine chemical structure. Despite this challenge, TS structure can be indirectly obtained by measurement of kinetic isotope effects (KIEs), which reflect changes in bonding as the TS is traversed in a reaction.</p> <p>The ultimate objective of the research funded by this award was to determine the TS structures of two enzymes that are targets for the treatment of tuberculosis. While unanticipated complications did not allow realization of this outcome, several successful steps towards this goal were completed. The most significant advance was the establishment of an improved method for measuring KIEs using nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy that could be of benefit in cases where substrate availability is limited. This technique was used to measure three KIEs for 1-deoxy-D-xylulose-5-phosphate reductoisomerase (DXR), one of the two enzymes under investigation, solidifying its chemical mechanism. Additional exploration on DXR revealed an intimate connection between a flexible catalytic loop on the enzyme and the phosphoryl group of the substrate, a finding that has implications on inhibitor design. Investigations into the mechanism of the other enzyme, isocitrate lyase (ICL), revealed fundamental roles for an active-site cysteine residue in catalysis and inhibition. The mechanism of ICL was exploited by two distinct inhibitors that each formed a covalent link to this residue. The first of these was designed and confirmed to function like the substrate, producing a reactive species that was intercepted by the cysteine. The second, 3-nitropropionate, was unexpectedly found to react covalently with the same cysteine residue, presumably through a more reactive intermediate form. This observation established the first known example of covalent inhibition of an enzyme by a nitro compound. Thus, these investigations may inspire future inhibitor development for targeting other proteins with binding pocket architecture similar to ICL.</p> <p>The broader impacts of this CAREER award aimed to inspire students of all ages to explore science, with a focus on biochemistry and enzymology. In collaboration with local science teachers, a K&ndash;12 outreach program was established in which youths, including those from underrepresented groups, performed an enzyme kinetics assay using catalase extracted from a potato. Some of these students additionally visited the PI&rsquo;s laboratory at the University at Buffalo (UB) to be introduced to advanced instrumentation and to perform additional experiments with assistance from graduate students. At the university level, undergraduate and graduate chemistry and medicinal chemistry courses included descriptive explanations on the topics of KIEs and the design of TS inhibitors. Six graduate students were supported by this award, and of these, four are women, all currently employed as postdoctoral researchers or as industrial scientists. Five UB undergraduate students and two international interns also contributed to the research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/22/2019<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;S&nbsp;Murkin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A catalyst serves to increase the rate of a reaction by providing a pathway for the reactant to transform into the product using less energy than in its absence. The overall rate is largely dictated by the highest-energy species along the path known as the transition state (TS). The structure of the TS is of great interest to chemists attempting to design new and improved catalysts as well as to researchers who would like to prevent catalysis, such as in the case of enzyme inhibition, which is the goal of many therapeutic drugs. Owing to its extremely short existence, on the order of 10&ndash;14 seconds, the TS eludes most experimental techniques used to determine chemical structure. Despite this challenge, TS structure can be indirectly obtained by measurement of kinetic isotope effects (KIEs), which reflect changes in bonding as the TS is traversed in a reaction.  The ultimate objective of the research funded by this award was to determine the TS structures of two enzymes that are targets for the treatment of tuberculosis. While unanticipated complications did not allow realization of this outcome, several successful steps towards this goal were completed. The most significant advance was the establishment of an improved method for measuring KIEs using nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy that could be of benefit in cases where substrate availability is limited. This technique was used to measure three KIEs for 1-deoxy-D-xylulose-5-phosphate reductoisomerase (DXR), one of the two enzymes under investigation, solidifying its chemical mechanism. Additional exploration on DXR revealed an intimate connection between a flexible catalytic loop on the enzyme and the phosphoryl group of the substrate, a finding that has implications on inhibitor design. Investigations into the mechanism of the other enzyme, isocitrate lyase (ICL), revealed fundamental roles for an active-site cysteine residue in catalysis and inhibition. The mechanism of ICL was exploited by two distinct inhibitors that each formed a covalent link to this residue. The first of these was designed and confirmed to function like the substrate, producing a reactive species that was intercepted by the cysteine. The second, 3-nitropropionate, was unexpectedly found to react covalently with the same cysteine residue, presumably through a more reactive intermediate form. This observation established the first known example of covalent inhibition of an enzyme by a nitro compound. Thus, these investigations may inspire future inhibitor development for targeting other proteins with binding pocket architecture similar to ICL.  The broader impacts of this CAREER award aimed to inspire students of all ages to explore science, with a focus on biochemistry and enzymology. In collaboration with local science teachers, a K&ndash;12 outreach program was established in which youths, including those from underrepresented groups, performed an enzyme kinetics assay using catalase extracted from a potato. Some of these students additionally visited the PI?s laboratory at the University at Buffalo (UB) to be introduced to advanced instrumentation and to perform additional experiments with assistance from graduate students. At the university level, undergraduate and graduate chemistry and medicinal chemistry courses included descriptive explanations on the topics of KIEs and the design of TS inhibitors. Six graduate students were supported by this award, and of these, four are women, all currently employed as postdoctoral researchers or as industrial scientists. Five UB undergraduate students and two international interns also contributed to the research.          Last Modified: 08/22/2019       Submitted by: Andrew S Murkin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
