<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Brain Evolution, Communication, and the Diversification of Behavior</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>632000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>638000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jodie Jawor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjawor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927887</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project, researchers from Washington University in St. Louis will collaborate with researchers at several institutions around the world to determine how natural selection shapes behavioral variation among species, and how species differences in sensory perception and communication relate to underlying changes in the nervous system. Closely related species can differ dramatically in their behavior, but little is known about why these differences arise and how they result from changes in brain anatomy and physiology. The goals of this project are to determine how behavioral differences allow organisms to adapt to diverse environments, and to identify a neurobiological basis for this adaptation. There are over 200 species of African electric fishes, and the unique characteristics of their electric communication signals make it possible to establish direct links between brain and behavior. Using a combination of electrophysiology, neuronal imaging, molecular genetic analysis, and behavioral studies, the researchers will characterize species diversity in sensory perception and communication, and determine how perceptual variation relates to differences in neural circuitry and social behavior. This research will prove broadly applicable by providing an integrated, mechanistic understanding of how behavioral variation arises among individuals and species. Electric fish are ideally suited for public outreach in neuroscience and behavior. As exotic animals, they attract a wide audience. In addition, they provide a unique opportunity to easily perform neurophysiology experiments in an intact, freely behaving animal. The researchers will expand ongoing outreach activities to produce and make freely available a formal lab module that uses weakly electric fish to expose middle and high school students to hypothesis-driven science and teach them about the role of electricity in the nervous system. Providing teachers with the tools needed to perform hypothesis-driven experiments in the classroom will ensure that these activities have an extended and enduring impact.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1255396</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Carlson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce A Carlson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>carlson.bruce@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3148895100</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000309282</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7659</Code>
<Text>Animal Behavior</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~217000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~220000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~201000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Animals communication signals can lead to the evolution of new species, as well as maintain reproductive barriers between existing species. Despite the critical role of the nervous system in both generating and processing communication signals, we know relatively little about the relationship between brain evolution and the diversification of communication signals across species. The goal of this project was to better understand species differences in communication behavior and how they relate to evolutionary change in the sensory pathways that process communication signals.</p> <p>African fishes called mormyrids, or elephant fishes, use an electric organ to generate weak pulses of electricity. They also have electroreceptors for detecting these pulses, and they are therefore able to communicate with each other using electricity. The waveform of these electric pulses is constant, and provides information about the identity of the signaling fish, including its species, sex, relative dominance, and individual identity. Evolutionary change in the electrosensory systems of these fishes led to the novel ability to detect variation in electric signal waveform. In this project, we sought to understand both how this difference in sensory perception has been shaped by natural selection, as well as how this perceptual difference relates to evolutionary change in the brain pathway that processes these signals.</p> <p>Previous work in species that can detect variation in electric signal waveform demonstrated that signal waveform is encoded into small differences in the timing of electrical spikes between different sensory receptors. By studying species that cannot detect variation in signal waveform, we discovered a new mechanism for encoding sensory stimuli. Rather than generating spikes, these receptors oscillate continuously. In response to an electric signal, these oscillations reset, leading to temporary synchrony of the oscillations across receptors. We went on to show that these brief moments of synchrony are detected by neurons in the brain, thus conclusively documenting a newly discovered mechanism for sensory coding. Further, we found that these oscillatory responses are unaffected by changes in signal waveform. Thus, species that cannot perceive variation in signal waveform have sensory receptors that do not encode that variation in the first place.</p> <p>In species that can detect variation in signal waveform, the detection of small spike timing differences between receptors relies on two key features: (i) inhibitory input from one receptor combined with excitatory input from another receptor; and (ii) a delay in the excitatory input, which varies for different target neurons. When there is a timing difference between the responses of the two receptors that closely matches the excitatory delay, the two inputs will arrive close in time, and the inhibition will block the neuron from responding to the excitation. However, the inhibition will not block excitation for other timing differences. Because each neuron in the population receives excitation with a different delay, each neuron responds to a distinct range of timing differences. We discovered that species lacking the ability to detect variation in electric signal waveform have the same essential circuit in place, but with one key difference: they are lacking delays in the excitatory pathway. Thus, evolution of the ability to detect signal waveform variation was associated with the addition of excitatory delay lines that allow the neural circuit to detect the small timing differences between sensory receptors.</p> <p>In addition to discovering mechanisms underlying evolutionary change in perception, we also discovered some key behavioral and ecological differences between the two types of fish that may explain why this difference evolved. Fish that evolved the ability to perceive signal variation tend to live close to the bottoms of rivers and streams, where they are solitary, territorial, and aggressive. By contrast, fish that lack this ability tend to be gregarious and live in the open water. Indeed, their oscillatory sensory receptors are maximally sensitive to the electric signals emanating from groups of fish rather than individuals. Thus, it may be that the ability to precisely locate and identify signaling individuals in dark, cluttered habitats drove these evolutionary changes in the electrosensory system.</p> <p>Besides our research activities, we also regularly engaged in interactive public outreach involving weakly electric fish to teach basic concepts in electricity, neuroscience, and animal communication. This included: yearly hands-on demonstrations and lectures targeted to K-12 students held at the St. Louis Science Center in conjunction with Brain Awareness Week; a yearly Neuroscience Day targeted towards middle school students held at the St. Louis Science Center; and yearly participation in the St. Louis Area Brain Bee, a regional competition associated with the Society for Neuroscience&rsquo;s National Brain Bee. These activities included a hypothesis-testing component to expose students and the public to question-oriented, hypothesis-driven science. This helped to demystify the scientific process and make science more accessible as both a career choice and as a way of understanding. Our outreach efforts reached hundreds of children in the St. Louis region.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/05/2018<br>      Modified by: Bruce&nbsp;A&nbsp;Carlson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Animals communication signals can lead to the evolution of new species, as well as maintain reproductive barriers between existing species. Despite the critical role of the nervous system in both generating and processing communication signals, we know relatively little about the relationship between brain evolution and the diversification of communication signals across species. The goal of this project was to better understand species differences in communication behavior and how they relate to evolutionary change in the sensory pathways that process communication signals.  African fishes called mormyrids, or elephant fishes, use an electric organ to generate weak pulses of electricity. They also have electroreceptors for detecting these pulses, and they are therefore able to communicate with each other using electricity. The waveform of these electric pulses is constant, and provides information about the identity of the signaling fish, including its species, sex, relative dominance, and individual identity. Evolutionary change in the electrosensory systems of these fishes led to the novel ability to detect variation in electric signal waveform. In this project, we sought to understand both how this difference in sensory perception has been shaped by natural selection, as well as how this perceptual difference relates to evolutionary change in the brain pathway that processes these signals.  Previous work in species that can detect variation in electric signal waveform demonstrated that signal waveform is encoded into small differences in the timing of electrical spikes between different sensory receptors. By studying species that cannot detect variation in signal waveform, we discovered a new mechanism for encoding sensory stimuli. Rather than generating spikes, these receptors oscillate continuously. In response to an electric signal, these oscillations reset, leading to temporary synchrony of the oscillations across receptors. We went on to show that these brief moments of synchrony are detected by neurons in the brain, thus conclusively documenting a newly discovered mechanism for sensory coding. Further, we found that these oscillatory responses are unaffected by changes in signal waveform. Thus, species that cannot perceive variation in signal waveform have sensory receptors that do not encode that variation in the first place.  In species that can detect variation in signal waveform, the detection of small spike timing differences between receptors relies on two key features: (i) inhibitory input from one receptor combined with excitatory input from another receptor; and (ii) a delay in the excitatory input, which varies for different target neurons. When there is a timing difference between the responses of the two receptors that closely matches the excitatory delay, the two inputs will arrive close in time, and the inhibition will block the neuron from responding to the excitation. However, the inhibition will not block excitation for other timing differences. Because each neuron in the population receives excitation with a different delay, each neuron responds to a distinct range of timing differences. We discovered that species lacking the ability to detect variation in electric signal waveform have the same essential circuit in place, but with one key difference: they are lacking delays in the excitatory pathway. Thus, evolution of the ability to detect signal waveform variation was associated with the addition of excitatory delay lines that allow the neural circuit to detect the small timing differences between sensory receptors.  In addition to discovering mechanisms underlying evolutionary change in perception, we also discovered some key behavioral and ecological differences between the two types of fish that may explain why this difference evolved. Fish that evolved the ability to perceive signal variation tend to live close to the bottoms of rivers and streams, where they are solitary, territorial, and aggressive. By contrast, fish that lack this ability tend to be gregarious and live in the open water. Indeed, their oscillatory sensory receptors are maximally sensitive to the electric signals emanating from groups of fish rather than individuals. Thus, it may be that the ability to precisely locate and identify signaling individuals in dark, cluttered habitats drove these evolutionary changes in the electrosensory system.  Besides our research activities, we also regularly engaged in interactive public outreach involving weakly electric fish to teach basic concepts in electricity, neuroscience, and animal communication. This included: yearly hands-on demonstrations and lectures targeted to K-12 students held at the St. Louis Science Center in conjunction with Brain Awareness Week; a yearly Neuroscience Day targeted towards middle school students held at the St. Louis Science Center; and yearly participation in the St. Louis Area Brain Bee, a regional competition associated with the Society for Neuroscience?s National Brain Bee. These activities included a hypothesis-testing component to expose students and the public to question-oriented, hypothesis-driven science. This helped to demystify the scientific process and make science more accessible as both a career choice and as a way of understanding. Our outreach efforts reached hundreds of children in the St. Louis region.          Last Modified: 09/05/2018       Submitted by: Bruce A Carlson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
