<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Role of Software and Software Institutes in Computational Science Over Time</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>74430.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74430</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel Katz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The workshop will bring together Principle Investigators of the leading software cyberinfrastructure projects and discuss issues relevant to the community as we move into the future.  In 2011 and 2012 the OCI Software Infrastructure for Sustained Innovation (SI2) program funded software efforts in small development efforts that can provide software pieces that can be integrated into the larger cyberinfrastructure, and larger collaborations that were delivering significant community software. In addition, new SI2 awards aimed at conceptualizing large-scale software institutes, aimed at providing a fabric for the software needed by domain scientists to achieve breakthroughs in their intra and inter-disciplinary efforts, will be awarded. New NSF initiatives such as EarthCube are defining roadmaps for cyberinfrastructure development in Earth sciences. This workshop will bring together the Principle Investigators of the recent SI2 awards to discuss potential synergies and collaborations, define challenges ahead, discuss the relationship of the SI2 efforts to the planned Software Institutes, and explore the relationship of the OCI-funded software in the context of the broad NSF initiatives such as EarthCube, DataWay, and other planned community-focused efforts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To achieve its goals, the workshop will focus on these main themes: (i) Discussing SI2 projects within the context of SI2 Institutes and NSF-wide initiative such as EarthCube, DataWay, and others; (ii) sharing experiences in building quality software and services; (iii) fostering collaboration and providing incentives for collaboration and cyberinfrastructure development as a career; and (iv) sustaining the software capabilities in the long term, defining software value.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will solicit participation from major science and engineering projects that rely on the national cyberinfrastructure for their computations and data management needs. Their participation will help ensure that the cyberinfrastructure software developed as part of SI2 projects will be relevant and broadly applicable to a number of science and engineering domains. The results of this workshop will then potentially guide cyberinfrastructure development and testing in the future.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1256100</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Miron</FirstName>
<LastName>Livny</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Miron Livny</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>miron@cs.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6083164336</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000340383</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ewa</FirstName>
<LastName>Deelman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ewa Deelman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>deelman@isi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3104488408</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000119337</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Marina del Rey</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>902927008</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7477</Code>
<Text>CI-TEAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8004</Code>
<Text>Software Institutes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7477</Code>
<Text>CI-TEAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8005</Code>
<Text>Scientific Software Elements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8009</Code>
<Text>Scientifc Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~74430</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This workshop brought together Principle Investigators of the leading software cyberinfrastructure projects and to discuss issues relevant to the community as it moves into the future. &nbsp;It is critical that the funds used by NSF for software development result in software being used effectively by scientists and engineers so that researchers in a number of domains can make advances in their respective fields without being burdened by the interactions with the cyberinfrastructure.</p> <p>The workshop was organized to include guest presentations, panel discussions, and a poster session. &nbsp;In total 62 Software Infrastructure for Sustained Innovation&nbsp;(SI2) projects were represented in total. These included: 12 Institute Conceptualization, 20 Scientific Software Integration&nbsp;(SSI), and 30 Scientific Software Elements (SSE) awards. Sixty principle investigators represented the projects. SSE focused primarily on small development efforts that can provide software pieces that can be integrated into the larger cyberinfrastructure.&nbsp; SSI targeted larger collaborations that were delivering significant community software</p> <p>Additionally, nine participants from the community were invited to share their experiences and ideas. &nbsp;</p> <p>Some of the workshop findings included: 1) outreach is a critical part of software adoption, 2) it is important to be open with the community and contributors, 3) workforce development is important to the success of scientific software but it is hard to do, because it often requires multi-disciplinary training, 4) it is sometimes hard and yet important to have your software credited by others, and 5) software institutes can play an important role in the scientific software ecosystem.</p> <p>All workshop materials can be found at:&nbsp;https://sites.google.com/site/si2pimeeting/&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/12/2014<br>      Modified by: Ewa&nbsp;Deelman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This workshop brought together Principle Investigators of the leading software cyberinfrastructure projects and to discuss issues relevant to the community as it moves into the future.  It is critical that the funds used by NSF for software development result in software being used effectively by scientists and engineers so that researchers in a number of domains can make advances in their respective fields without being burdened by the interactions with the cyberinfrastructure.  The workshop was organized to include guest presentations, panel discussions, and a poster session.  In total 62 Software Infrastructure for Sustained Innovation (SI2) projects were represented in total. These included: 12 Institute Conceptualization, 20 Scientific Software Integration (SSI), and 30 Scientific Software Elements (SSE) awards. Sixty principle investigators represented the projects. SSE focused primarily on small development efforts that can provide software pieces that can be integrated into the larger cyberinfrastructure.  SSI targeted larger collaborations that were delivering significant community software  Additionally, nine participants from the community were invited to share their experiences and ideas.    Some of the workshop findings included: 1) outreach is a critical part of software adoption, 2) it is important to be open with the community and contributors, 3) workforce development is important to the success of scientific software but it is hard to do, because it often requires multi-disciplinary training, 4) it is sometimes hard and yet important to have your software credited by others, and 5) software institutes can play an important role in the scientific software ecosystem.  All workshop materials can be found at: https://sites.google.com/site/si2pimeeting/           Last Modified: 11/12/2014       Submitted by: Ewa Deelman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
