<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  High-speed Low-cost Spectral Domain Optical Coherence Tomography System for Intravascular Imaging Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>498325.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>597985</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project proposes to develop an 840 nm spectral domain optical coherence tomography (OCT) system for intravascular imaging applications.  The system will be designed to provide images equal to or better than what is currently clinically available, and will have higher imaging speeds with lower cost.  Intravascular OCT is poised for clinical acceptance and commercial growth, but is still limited by availability and cost.  Increasing system speed and reducing cost will accelerate clinical use of intravascular-OCT.  The Phase II research will move the system toward commercial readiness by including in vivo imaging in a porcine animal model.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project, if successful, will be the availability of a new imaging tool for the identification and treatment of coronary artery disease (CAD).  CAD affects an estimated 16 million Americans and is the primary cause of heart attacks and strokes, which killed over 631,000 and 137,000 people, respectively, in the United States in 2006.   Intravascular OCT provides detailed imaging information on plaque assessment, stent implantation, and stent monitoring over time.  Identification and treatment of unstable plaques and other intravascular conditions will reduce the morbidity and mortality rate from CAD.  Billions of dollars are spent on imaging and treatment of CAD.  An OCT system with increased imaging capability and competitive cost will provide a significant improvement over the current state-of-the-art.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1256374</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wbrown@wasatchphotonics.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4357524301</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000582917</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/27/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roman</FirstName>
<LastName>Kuranov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roman Kuranov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rkuranov@opticenthealth.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4093702575</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000646985</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wasatch Photonics, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<ZipCode>843216832</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4357524301</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1301 N. 1000 W. Suite 150</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>034399936</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASATCH PHOTONICS, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>034399936</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wasatch Photonics, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277038998</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~498325</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~99660</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Outcomes for Phase II NSF SBIR project IIP-1256374:&ldquo;High-speed low-cost spectral domain optical coherence tomography system for intravascular imaging applications&rdquo;</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>This project supports the development of 840&nbsp;nm Spectral Domain Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT) system for high speed intravascular imaging. Current commercial systems utilize 1300&nbsp;nm light and use Swept Source (SS) OCT approach. We envision several benefits of switching to non-obvious 840&nbsp;nm light and using Spectral Domain (SD) OCT approach.</p> <p>The project innovation helped us to increase imaging contrast and resolution while reducing system cost and complexity. In addition using supplemental funding - Technology Enhancement for Commercial Partnerships (TECP) &ndash; we provided proof-of-principle data for potential 20x increase of the OCT speed.</p> <p>Intravascular OCT (IV-OCT) provides detailed imaging information for plaque assessment, stent implantation, and stent monitoring over time. Identification and treatment of unstable plaques and other intravascular conditions can reduce the morbidity and mortality rate from coronary artery disease (CAD). CAD is the primary cause of heart attacks and strokes which killed over 631,000 and 137,000 people respectively in the U.S in 2006.</p> <p>Intravascular OCT is poised for commercial growth, but is still limited by availability, limited imaging quality and cost. Increasing imaging quality and reducing cost will accelerate clinical use of IV-OCT.</p> <p>Societal benefits of this project include the commercialization of a new product with clinical impact for the imaging and treatment of CAD. Improved imaging and treatment can reduce the morbidity and mortality from CAD and improve patient outcome and quality of life.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During the Phase II we completed the following work:</p> <p>- We have designed and built Spectral Domain IV-OCT engine operating at 840 nm with similar imaging depth and two times better axial resolution than commercial 1300&nbsp;nm Swept Source IV-OCT systems.</p> <p>- We confirmed parameters of our IV-OCT system in phantom studies.</p> <p>- We developed original catheters for ex vivo imaging of the coronary arteries.</p> <p>- We proved in ex vivo studies in pig&rsquo;s coronary arteries, significantly better performance of our 840&nbsp;nm over commercial 1300&nbsp;nm.</p> <p>- We adapted commercial 1300&nbsp;nm catheters for 840&nbsp;nm IV-OCT imaging</p> <p>- We showed in normal pigs in vivo better delineation of the coronary arteries structure while similar penetration depth of our 840&nbsp;nm as compared with commercial 1300&nbsp;nm.</p> <p>- We showed in genetically modified pigs in vivo significantly better delineation of the thin fibrous cap atheroma by our 840&nbsp;nm IV-OCT as compared with commercial 1300&nbsp;nm IV-OCT (please refer to the figure 1).</p> <p>- We added motorized pull back option to our IV-OCT and showed better volumetric imaging of the metal stent as compared with 1300&nbsp;nm IV-OCT (please refer to the figure 2).</p> <p>- We guided stent deployment in vivo in normal pig</p> <p>- We showed proof-of-principle data that MHz-range OCT with parameters suitable for IV-OCT application is feasible</p> <p>- We received 1 and submitted 4 patents to protect our approach.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/21/2015<br>      Modified by: Roman&nbsp;Kuranov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigat...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Outcomes for Phase II NSF SBIR project IIP-1256374:"High-speed low-cost spectral domain optical coherence tomography system for intravascular imaging applications"     This project supports the development of 840 nm Spectral Domain Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT) system for high speed intravascular imaging. Current commercial systems utilize 1300 nm light and use Swept Source (SS) OCT approach. We envision several benefits of switching to non-obvious 840 nm light and using Spectral Domain (SD) OCT approach.  The project innovation helped us to increase imaging contrast and resolution while reducing system cost and complexity. In addition using supplemental funding - Technology Enhancement for Commercial Partnerships (TECP) &ndash; we provided proof-of-principle data for potential 20x increase of the OCT speed.  Intravascular OCT (IV-OCT) provides detailed imaging information for plaque assessment, stent implantation, and stent monitoring over time. Identification and treatment of unstable plaques and other intravascular conditions can reduce the morbidity and mortality rate from coronary artery disease (CAD). CAD is the primary cause of heart attacks and strokes which killed over 631,000 and 137,000 people respectively in the U.S in 2006.  Intravascular OCT is poised for commercial growth, but is still limited by availability, limited imaging quality and cost. Increasing imaging quality and reducing cost will accelerate clinical use of IV-OCT.  Societal benefits of this project include the commercialization of a new product with clinical impact for the imaging and treatment of CAD. Improved imaging and treatment can reduce the morbidity and mortality from CAD and improve patient outcome and quality of life.     During the Phase II we completed the following work:  - We have designed and built Spectral Domain IV-OCT engine operating at 840 nm with similar imaging depth and two times better axial resolution than commercial 1300 nm Swept Source IV-OCT systems.  - We confirmed parameters of our IV-OCT system in phantom studies.  - We developed original catheters for ex vivo imaging of the coronary arteries.  - We proved in ex vivo studies in pigÆs coronary arteries, significantly better performance of our 840 nm over commercial 1300 nm.  - We adapted commercial 1300 nm catheters for 840 nm IV-OCT imaging  - We showed in normal pigs in vivo better delineation of the coronary arteries structure while similar penetration depth of our 840 nm as compared with commercial 1300 nm.  - We showed in genetically modified pigs in vivo significantly better delineation of the thin fibrous cap atheroma by our 840 nm IV-OCT as compared with commercial 1300 nm IV-OCT (please refer to the figure 1).  - We added motorized pull back option to our IV-OCT and showed better volumetric imaging of the metal stent as compared with 1300 nm IV-OCT (please refer to the figure 2).  - We guided stent deployment in vivo in normal pig  - We showed proof-of-principle data that MHz-range OCT with parameters suitable for IV-OCT application is feasible  - We received 1 and submitted 4 patents to protect our approach.           Last Modified: 05/21/2015       Submitted by: Roman Kuranov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
