<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Signaling Network for Brassinosteroid-Regulated Gene Expression in Arabidopsis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>863615.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>863615</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gerald Schoenknecht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gschoenk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925076</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The increasing demand for food, feed and biofuel makes it very important to increase crop production, especially under adverse climate conditions. Plant steroid hormones, Brassinosteroids (BRs), have the potential to promote crop yield and improve plant performance against bacterial and fungal diseases and stresses such as drought and high temperature. Understanding BR functions in plants is essential to fully harvest its beneficial effects. Although BR signaling pathway has been well established, how BR regulates thousands of genes for various hormonal responses is not well understood. In this project, the investigators will use genetic, genomic, and computational approaches to establish gene regulatory networks through which BRs control the expression of the large number of genes for plant growth and stress tolerance. While the genetic and genomic studies will define the gene functions, the computational approach is required to build models for how hundreds to thousands of genes coordinate to carry out specific functions. The combination of functional genomic studies and computational modeling in establishing and validating transcriptional networks in hormone signaling is novel and is anticipated to provide unprecedented new insights into BR signaling network. The knowledge can be applied to agriculture to increase crop production. Moreover, the computational and bioinformatic tools developed and validated in the context of this project will be applicable to other systems biology studies. The research will also provide outstanding training opportunities at the interface of functional genomics and computational modeling for graduate and undergraduate students. High school science teachers will be recruited to participate in the research and to integrate such research into high school science education. The BR mutants will be introduced to an undergraduate laboratory course, in which a large number of undergraduate students each year will design and perform experiments to learn how plant steroid hormones control plant growth.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1257631</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Srinivas</FirstName>
<LastName>Aluru</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Srinivas Aluru</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aluru@cc.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043851486</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000388133</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yanhai</FirstName>
<LastName>Yin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yanhai Yin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yin@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152945225</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000490762</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maneesha</FirstName>
<LastName>Aluru</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maneesha R Aluru</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maluru@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152945015</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000390449</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1138 Pearson]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1165</Code>
<Text>ADVANCES IN BIO INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7658</Code>
<Text>Physiolgcl Mechnsms&amp;Biomechnsm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~313615</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The increasing demand for food, feed and biofuel makes it very important to increase crop production, especially under adverse climate conditions. Plant steroid hormones, Brassinosteroids (BRs), have the potential to promote crop yield and improve plant performance under drought conditions. Understanding BR functions in plants is essential to fully harvest its beneficial effects. Although BR signaling pathway has been well established, how BR regulates thousands of genes for various hormonal responses was not well understood. In this project, the investigators used genetic, genomic, and computational approaches to establish gene regulatory networks through which BRs control the expression of the more than 5,000 genes for plant growth and drought stress tolerance. First, the researchers developed and compared different computational methods to analyze more than 10,000 gene expression datasets and inferred gene regulatory networks (GRNs) that include about 2/3 of genes in the Arabidopsis genome. The GRNs were further used in conjunction with existing bioinfomatics tools to refine the networks and identify key genes in the regulation of BR-regulated gene expression. Second, it was discovered that that BR&shy; regulated transcription factor BES1 and drought induced transcription factors RD26 and its close homologs function antagonistically to coordinate plant growth and drought stress responses. RD26 and BES1 bind to same promoter elements to regulate genes for plant growth or drought responses in opposite ways and thus coordinate growth under drought conditions. Third, BES1 interacts with WRKY family transcription factor to promote plant growth and repress drought response. It was found that WRKY46, WRKY54 and WRKY70 are required for BR-&shy;regulated plant growth and inhibit drought responses by cooperating with BES1 in the regulation of BR target gene expression. Fourth, BES1 interacts with other transcription factors (HAT1) and histone-modifying enzymes (SDG8) to regulate the expression of a large number of genes. Finally, it was discovered that under drought and other stress conditions, BES1 is targeted to selective autophagy pathway, allowing plants to slow down growth under stresses. The studies revealed molecular mechanisms and transcriptional networks through which plants balance growth and drought responses. The gene expression studies from the generated mutants were also used to validate the GRNs, which can be used to identify additional key genes controlling plant growth under drought conditions. Twenty scientific papers have been published based on research supported by the grant. The results generated from the grant have also been presented more than twenty times in national and international conferences and other Universities or research Institutes.&nbsp; The knowledge can be applied to agriculture to increase crop production under drought conditions. Moreover, the computational and bioinformatic tools developed and validated in the context of this project will be applicable to other systems biology studies. The research also provided outstanding training opportunities at the interface of functional genomics and computational modeling for seven graduate students, one associate scientist, one postdoctoral fellow and six undergraduate students. Three high school teachers were recruited to participate in the research and to integrate such research into high school science education. The BR mutants were also introduced to an undergraduate laboratory course, which involved more than 3,000 undergraduate students who design and perform experiments to learn how plant steroid hormones control plant growth.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Yanhai&nbsp;Yin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The increasing demand for food, feed and biofuel makes it very important to increase crop production, especially under adverse climate conditions. Plant steroid hormones, Brassinosteroids (BRs), have the potential to promote crop yield and improve plant performance under drought conditions. Understanding BR functions in plants is essential to fully harvest its beneficial effects. Although BR signaling pathway has been well established, how BR regulates thousands of genes for various hormonal responses was not well understood. In this project, the investigators used genetic, genomic, and computational approaches to establish gene regulatory networks through which BRs control the expression of the more than 5,000 genes for plant growth and drought stress tolerance. First, the researchers developed and compared different computational methods to analyze more than 10,000 gene expression datasets and inferred gene regulatory networks (GRNs) that include about 2/3 of genes in the Arabidopsis genome. The GRNs were further used in conjunction with existing bioinfomatics tools to refine the networks and identify key genes in the regulation of BR-regulated gene expression. Second, it was discovered that that BR&shy; regulated transcription factor BES1 and drought induced transcription factors RD26 and its close homologs function antagonistically to coordinate plant growth and drought stress responses. RD26 and BES1 bind to same promoter elements to regulate genes for plant growth or drought responses in opposite ways and thus coordinate growth under drought conditions. Third, BES1 interacts with WRKY family transcription factor to promote plant growth and repress drought response. It was found that WRKY46, WRKY54 and WRKY70 are required for BR-&shy;regulated plant growth and inhibit drought responses by cooperating with BES1 in the regulation of BR target gene expression. Fourth, BES1 interacts with other transcription factors (HAT1) and histone-modifying enzymes (SDG8) to regulate the expression of a large number of genes. Finally, it was discovered that under drought and other stress conditions, BES1 is targeted to selective autophagy pathway, allowing plants to slow down growth under stresses. The studies revealed molecular mechanisms and transcriptional networks through which plants balance growth and drought responses. The gene expression studies from the generated mutants were also used to validate the GRNs, which can be used to identify additional key genes controlling plant growth under drought conditions. Twenty scientific papers have been published based on research supported by the grant. The results generated from the grant have also been presented more than twenty times in national and international conferences and other Universities or research Institutes.  The knowledge can be applied to agriculture to increase crop production under drought conditions. Moreover, the computational and bioinformatic tools developed and validated in the context of this project will be applicable to other systems biology studies. The research also provided outstanding training opportunities at the interface of functional genomics and computational modeling for seven graduate students, one associate scientist, one postdoctoral fellow and six undergraduate students. Three high school teachers were recruited to participate in the research and to integrate such research into high school science education. The BR mutants were also introduced to an undergraduate laboratory course, which involved more than 3,000 undergraduate students who design and perform experiments to learn how plant steroid hormones control plant growth.          Last Modified: 04/30/2018       Submitted by: Yanhai Yin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
