<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Stress hormone effects on disease resistance, tolerance and transmission</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>604123.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>610123</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Irwin Forseth</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>iforseth@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927862</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Superspreaders are disproportionately responsible for the infections of other hosts.  Perhaps the best-known human superspreader was Typhoid Mary, who caused 53 deaths due to Salmonella bacteria transmission.  Although the frequency of "Typhoid Marys" is unclear, they are probably not rare.  Superspreading is implicated in the rapid expansion of SARS (Sudden Acute Respiratory Syndrome) and HIV across the globe.  For most infectious diseases, 20% of hosts cause 80% of infections.  The goal of this research is to determine whether glucocorticoids, major vertebrate stress hormones that have been implicated in disease transmission, are involved in superspreading.  Stress hormones could impact superspreading by affecting how parasites (or vectors, such as mosquitos and biting flies) choose hosts on which to feed, how hosts resist or tolerate parasites, or how hosts transmit parasites to other hosts or vectors.  Surprisingly, there has never been a systematic study of the effects of stress hormones on all aspects of one complex host-vector-parasite system.  This knowledge gap is significant and deserves attention because many anthropogenic and natural factors alter stress hormone regulation, and these factors are increasingly important in the context of global change. By knowing how and when stress hormones affect host-parasite interactions, we may become better able to predict and control zoonotic disease outbreaks.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: To investigate the role of stress hormones in superspreading, interactions among zebra finches (ZEFI), Culex pipiens mosquitos, and West Nile virus (WNV) will be studied. WNV was chosen because it has decimated some songbird populations and is thought responsible for more than 33,000 human infections and 1150 deaths. ZEFI and Culex were chosen because their genomes have been sequenced, providing opportunities for strong experimental approaches. Stress hormones are predicted to impact i) ZEFI behavior to Culex exposure, ii) Culex blood-feeding preference on ZEFI, iii) ZEFI resistance to WNV infection, iv) ZEFI tolerance of WNV infection, and/or v) ZEFI competency to transmit WNV to Culex. Ultimately, data will be used to determine directly when stress hormones have the largest impacts, information valuable for human and wildlife populations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts:  In animals, superspreading appears important for the transmission of several zoonotic diseases (infections that spill from animal into human populations) such as West Nile virus and some hantaviruses. In the context of global change, basic research on understanding superspreading has significant societal value because zoonotic diseases are predicted to become more prevalent. Collaboration with the Tampa Museum of Science and Industry, which attracts more than one million guests annually, will include the development of a Science Works Theater that helps the public understand disease ecology.  Training workshops for Hillsborough County high school teachers will also be held, providing teachers tools to train incipient scientists in modern disease biology.  For USF students, about 40% of whom come from under-represented backgrounds, robust learning experiences will be provided.  Individuals on the project will learn animal husbandry, minor surgeries, how to work in a high-security infectious disease research facility, modern lab assays, data analysis, and scientific writing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1257773</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lynn</FirstName>
<LastName>Martin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lynn Martin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lbmartin@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8139740157</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000239061</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Unnasch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas R Unnasch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tunnasch@health.usf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8139745465</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000520242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Florida</Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<ZipCode>336172008</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4019 E. Fowler Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 100]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069687242</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069687242</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>336129446</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7657</Code>
<Text>Integrtv Ecological Physiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~443426</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~101205</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~65492</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of our project was to determine how physiological stress in birds affects their propensity to transmit West Nile virus to other birds as well as humans, as West Nile is a zoonotic infection.&nbsp;&nbsp;Through a series of experiments, we revealed that experimental alterations of stress in birds, via hormone manipulation, affected WNV risk ecologically.&nbsp;&nbsp;Birds with elevated hormones were 2x more attractive to biting mosquito vectors, infectious to mosquitoes for several days longer than controls, and minimally more sensitive to mortality caused by the virus.&nbsp;&nbsp;Stress hormones in birds did not affect the rate at which mosquitoes became infectious with WNV, but there was an indication that stress to the hosts on which mosquitoes feed could have reduced vector reproductive output.&nbsp;&nbsp;Work in other systems had revealed that short-term stressors could protect against infections, but we found no such evidence in this system.&nbsp;&nbsp;We also found compelling and consistent effects of stress hormones on the way birds tolerate infection, in other words how they cope with the virus once they&rsquo;ve become infected.&nbsp;&nbsp;In an effort to link our lab focus to consequences in the wild, we also found that a pervasive anthropogenic stressor, artificial light at night, increased the duration birds were infectious of mosquitoes with WNV, but mortality rate was not enhanced.&nbsp;&nbsp;Although these effects were seemingly more driven by alterations in the regulation of melatonin than the focal hormone for the majority of our studies (corticosterone), it was clear that light pollution, too, can act as a stressor to affect WNV risk.&nbsp;&nbsp;Indeed, our ongoing study of chickens held in outdoor pens in Florida to survey for arboviruses is revealing that light pollution level predicts local WNV risk.&nbsp;&nbsp;Intermediately light-polluted sites have the greatest WNV exposure risk compared to naturally dark and highly light-polluted sites.&nbsp;&nbsp;Fortunately, one preliminary study indicates that alterations of lighting practices (e.g., the use of warm-wavelength bulbs) might ameliorate some of these effects of ALAN.</p> <p>In terms of Intellectual Merit, our work revealed extensive yet complex effects of host stress on infection risk for other wildlife and humans, important findings given that this infection is zoonotic.&nbsp;&nbsp;It also provided some of the first insight about how stress affect songbird immune responses to a now-common but introduced virus, and it laid a foundation for future work on the potentially strong effects of light pollution on WNV risk and other infections transmitted by biting insects.&nbsp;</p> <p>In terms of Broader Impacts, our research program provided extensive training opportunities in modern molecular immunology and endocrinology in Biosafety-Level 3 conditions for trainees at diverse career stages, most of whom are female.&nbsp;&nbsp;Through collaboration with high school teachers, we also produced a website that is a repository of lessons and materials for students interested in disease ecology.&nbsp;&nbsp;Practically our work provided some insight about the value of ameliorating stress to wildlife; we often think about direct effects of stressors on animals, but our research emphasizes the subtler, less intuitive pathways by which wildlife health can affect human health.&nbsp;&nbsp;Several outreach efforts, namely a series of events at the Tamps Museum for Science and Industry, educated the public about our work and its implications.&nbsp;&nbsp;A new podcast, Big Biology, also conveyed to a broad audience important insight into the origins of zoonotic infections and impacts of anthropogenic stressors.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/21/2019<br>      Modified by: Lynn&nbsp;Martin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of our project was to determine how physiological stress in birds affects their propensity to transmit West Nile virus to other birds as well as humans, as West Nile is a zoonotic infection.  Through a series of experiments, we revealed that experimental alterations of stress in birds, via hormone manipulation, affected WNV risk ecologically.  Birds with elevated hormones were 2x more attractive to biting mosquito vectors, infectious to mosquitoes for several days longer than controls, and minimally more sensitive to mortality caused by the virus.  Stress hormones in birds did not affect the rate at which mosquitoes became infectious with WNV, but there was an indication that stress to the hosts on which mosquitoes feed could have reduced vector reproductive output.  Work in other systems had revealed that short-term stressors could protect against infections, but we found no such evidence in this system.  We also found compelling and consistent effects of stress hormones on the way birds tolerate infection, in other words how they cope with the virus once they’ve become infected.  In an effort to link our lab focus to consequences in the wild, we also found that a pervasive anthropogenic stressor, artificial light at night, increased the duration birds were infectious of mosquitoes with WNV, but mortality rate was not enhanced.  Although these effects were seemingly more driven by alterations in the regulation of melatonin than the focal hormone for the majority of our studies (corticosterone), it was clear that light pollution, too, can act as a stressor to affect WNV risk.  Indeed, our ongoing study of chickens held in outdoor pens in Florida to survey for arboviruses is revealing that light pollution level predicts local WNV risk.  Intermediately light-polluted sites have the greatest WNV exposure risk compared to naturally dark and highly light-polluted sites.  Fortunately, one preliminary study indicates that alterations of lighting practices (e.g., the use of warm-wavelength bulbs) might ameliorate some of these effects of ALAN.  In terms of Intellectual Merit, our work revealed extensive yet complex effects of host stress on infection risk for other wildlife and humans, important findings given that this infection is zoonotic.  It also provided some of the first insight about how stress affect songbird immune responses to a now-common but introduced virus, and it laid a foundation for future work on the potentially strong effects of light pollution on WNV risk and other infections transmitted by biting insects.   In terms of Broader Impacts, our research program provided extensive training opportunities in modern molecular immunology and endocrinology in Biosafety-Level 3 conditions for trainees at diverse career stages, most of whom are female.  Through collaboration with high school teachers, we also produced a website that is a repository of lessons and materials for students interested in disease ecology.  Practically our work provided some insight about the value of ameliorating stress to wildlife; we often think about direct effects of stressors on animals, but our research emphasizes the subtler, less intuitive pathways by which wildlife health can affect human health.  Several outreach efforts, namely a series of events at the Tamps Museum for Science and Industry, educated the public about our work and its implications.  A new podcast, Big Biology, also conveyed to a broad audience important insight into the origins of zoonotic infections and impacts of anthropogenic stressors.          Last Modified: 11/21/2019       Submitted by: Lynn Martin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
