<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Hemolymph Circulation in Mosquitoes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>359880.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>364880</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathryn Dickson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdickson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927380</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Insects employ an open circulatory system for the transport of nutrients, wastes, and signaling molecules throughout the body.  The insect circulatory system also functions in thermoregulation, promoting respiration, and the circulation of immune factors that survey tissues for foreign invaders.  The insect circulatory system consists of hemolymph (blood), an open body cavity called the hemocoel, and a series of pumps, with the primary pump being a muscular dorsal vessel that is divided into a thoracic aorta and an abdominal heart.  While some recent work has focused on the physiology of the insect heart, little is known about hemolymph flow.  Thus, the goal of this research is to characterize the mechanics of hemolymph circulation throughout the mosquito hemocoel.  Objective 1 will employ novel fluorescence-based intravital imaging methods to qualitatively and quantitatively map hemolymph circulation in all regions of this insect.  Objective 2 will assess the role accessory pulsatile organs play in hemolymph propulsion.  Objective 3 will determine how heart rhythms and hemolymph currents change under various physiological conditions.  Finally, objective 4 will test how mosquito infection affects circulatory physiology.  The research will make critical contributions to the field of insect circulatory physiology and will create the first quantitative map of hemolymph circulation in any insect.  Furthermore, this research will be carried out in mosquitoes, a socially and ecologically important insect group because of their role as pests and pathogen transmitters.  Because hemolymph circulation affects the dissemination of insecticides throughout the mosquito body, as well as the obligate migration of pathogens prior to their transmission, a better understanding of hemolymph circulation could contribute to the development of novel pest and disease control strategies.  In addition to its scientific merit, this project will result in the training of graduate and undergraduate students in biological research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1257936</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julian</FirstName>
<LastName>Hillyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julian F Hillyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>julian.hillyer@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153432065</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000484936</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PMB 407749 2301 Vanderbilt Place]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965717143</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004413456</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372401104</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[465 21st Ave S]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7658</Code>
<Text>Physiolgcl Mechnsms&amp;Biomechnsm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~265534</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~99346</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The survival of an insect depends in part on the efficient circulation of hemolymph (insect blood) throughout the hemocoel (body cavity). Hemolymph circulation transports nutrients, wastes and signaling molecules to their target sites, and also facilitates effective immune responses against pathogens.&nbsp; The major organ that propels hemolymph is the dorsal vessel, which is a muscular tube that spans the length of the body and is composed of two regions: a heart in the abdomen and an aorta in the thorax.&nbsp; In addition to the action of the dorsal vessel, insects possess accessory pulsating organs, or auxiliary hearts, that propel hemolymph into specific appendages. This project built on our previous work characterizing the circulatory system of the mosquito, an insect that is of great social importance because of its role as a pest and a disease vector. Here, we discuss some of the major findings of the project, most notably, the characterization of the functional mechanics of hemolymph propulsion throughout the mosquito hemocoel.</p> <p>Experiments conducted in adult mosquitoes demonstrated that the activity of the valves of the heart, called the ostia, is asymmetrical, and that most hemolymph enters the heart via the ostia that are located in the middle abdominal segments.&nbsp; This correlates with the locations of the body where the mosquito&rsquo;s immune cells aggregate, indicating that the circulatory and immune systems of mosquitoes are functionally integrated.&nbsp; Further experiments conducted on both larvae and adults showed that circulatory physiology in two life stages of the same insect can be drastically different.&nbsp; Specifically, although the dorsal vessel is the main circulatory organ in both larvae and adults, the larval dorsal vessel contracts in only one direction (toward the head) whereas the adult heart contracts in two different directions (alternating between contracting toward the head and the posterior of the abdomen).&nbsp; Additionally, the location at which hemolymph enters the heart is different between these two life stages: hemolymph enters the larval heart through openings in the posterior of the body whereas hemolymph enters the adult heart via ostia located along the abdominal segments.</p> <p>We also comprehensively characterized the auxiliary hearts that propel hemolymph into the antennae and the wings.&nbsp; We found that the activity of two antennal hearts propels hemolymph into the antenna via specialized vessels.&nbsp; Once hemolymph reaches the end of an antenna, it exits the vessel and returns to the main body cavity via an antennal hemocoel.&nbsp; This efficient circulatory network supplies hemolymph to antennal cells that function in processes such as smell and hearing, which are important for host-seeking and mating.&nbsp; Next, we described the functional mechanics of hemolymph flow through the wings.&nbsp; We discovered that hemolymph circulates through both wings via the action of a single wing heart, which aspirates hemolymph out of the wings rather than pushing hemolymph into the wings.&nbsp; In both the antennae and the wings, we determined the velocity and acceleration of hemolymph flow, creating spatial maps of flow across these appendages.</p> <p>To understand and characterize factors that affect circulatory physiology, we tested the effect of three neurohormones (CCAP, FMRFamide and SALDKNFMRFamide) on circulatory physiology.&nbsp; We found that the contractions of the antennal hearts and the dorsal vessel are not linked; however, both are regulated by some of the same neurohormones.&nbsp; To determine whether neurotransmitters also modulate heart physiology, we treated mosquitoes with serotonin and glutamate and found that both neurotransmitters significantly increase the heart rate.&nbsp; Finally, we tested the effects of starvation, the combination of starvation and dehydration, and aging on the heart in order to explore conditions that may alter circulatory physiology.&nbsp; We found that the combination of starvation and dehydration reduces the heart rate, and that aging results in an initial increase and then a decrease in the heart rate of a mosquito.</p> <p>The data collected in this project are important in several respects.&nbsp; From the perspective of the field of insect physiology, the experiments illustrate the functional mechanics of an essential organ system.&nbsp; From a social perspective, this research has implications for combating mosquitoes as pests or vectors of disease.&nbsp; All mosquito-transmitted pathogens are acquired during blood feeding, and these pathogens migrate from the gut to the salivary glands and mouthparts with the aid of hemolymph flow, where they are then transmitted to the next host. &nbsp;Thus, gaining a better understanding of mosquito circulatory physiology could aid in the development of disease control strategies at the vector-host interface.&nbsp; A comprehensive understanding of circulatory physiology could also aid in the development of pest control strategies, as many pesticides used to control mosquito populations are subject to hemolymph currents.&nbsp; In addition to the experimental findings, this project provided invaluable mentorship to developing scientists, as graduate and undergraduate students carried out a large proportion of the work.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/08/2017<br>      Modified by: Julian&nbsp;F&nbsp;Hillyer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The survival of an insect depends in part on the efficient circulation of hemolymph (insect blood) throughout the hemocoel (body cavity). Hemolymph circulation transports nutrients, wastes and signaling molecules to their target sites, and also facilitates effective immune responses against pathogens.  The major organ that propels hemolymph is the dorsal vessel, which is a muscular tube that spans the length of the body and is composed of two regions: a heart in the abdomen and an aorta in the thorax.  In addition to the action of the dorsal vessel, insects possess accessory pulsating organs, or auxiliary hearts, that propel hemolymph into specific appendages. This project built on our previous work characterizing the circulatory system of the mosquito, an insect that is of great social importance because of its role as a pest and a disease vector. Here, we discuss some of the major findings of the project, most notably, the characterization of the functional mechanics of hemolymph propulsion throughout the mosquito hemocoel.  Experiments conducted in adult mosquitoes demonstrated that the activity of the valves of the heart, called the ostia, is asymmetrical, and that most hemolymph enters the heart via the ostia that are located in the middle abdominal segments.  This correlates with the locations of the body where the mosquito?s immune cells aggregate, indicating that the circulatory and immune systems of mosquitoes are functionally integrated.  Further experiments conducted on both larvae and adults showed that circulatory physiology in two life stages of the same insect can be drastically different.  Specifically, although the dorsal vessel is the main circulatory organ in both larvae and adults, the larval dorsal vessel contracts in only one direction (toward the head) whereas the adult heart contracts in two different directions (alternating between contracting toward the head and the posterior of the abdomen).  Additionally, the location at which hemolymph enters the heart is different between these two life stages: hemolymph enters the larval heart through openings in the posterior of the body whereas hemolymph enters the adult heart via ostia located along the abdominal segments.  We also comprehensively characterized the auxiliary hearts that propel hemolymph into the antennae and the wings.  We found that the activity of two antennal hearts propels hemolymph into the antenna via specialized vessels.  Once hemolymph reaches the end of an antenna, it exits the vessel and returns to the main body cavity via an antennal hemocoel.  This efficient circulatory network supplies hemolymph to antennal cells that function in processes such as smell and hearing, which are important for host-seeking and mating.  Next, we described the functional mechanics of hemolymph flow through the wings.  We discovered that hemolymph circulates through both wings via the action of a single wing heart, which aspirates hemolymph out of the wings rather than pushing hemolymph into the wings.  In both the antennae and the wings, we determined the velocity and acceleration of hemolymph flow, creating spatial maps of flow across these appendages.  To understand and characterize factors that affect circulatory physiology, we tested the effect of three neurohormones (CCAP, FMRFamide and SALDKNFMRFamide) on circulatory physiology.  We found that the contractions of the antennal hearts and the dorsal vessel are not linked; however, both are regulated by some of the same neurohormones.  To determine whether neurotransmitters also modulate heart physiology, we treated mosquitoes with serotonin and glutamate and found that both neurotransmitters significantly increase the heart rate.  Finally, we tested the effects of starvation, the combination of starvation and dehydration, and aging on the heart in order to explore conditions that may alter circulatory physiology.  We found that the combination of starvation and dehydration reduces the heart rate, and that aging results in an initial increase and then a decrease in the heart rate of a mosquito.  The data collected in this project are important in several respects.  From the perspective of the field of insect physiology, the experiments illustrate the functional mechanics of an essential organ system.  From a social perspective, this research has implications for combating mosquitoes as pests or vectors of disease.  All mosquito-transmitted pathogens are acquired during blood feeding, and these pathogens migrate from the gut to the salivary glands and mouthparts with the aid of hemolymph flow, where they are then transmitted to the next host.  Thus, gaining a better understanding of mosquito circulatory physiology could aid in the development of disease control strategies at the vector-host interface.  A comprehensive understanding of circulatory physiology could also aid in the development of pest control strategies, as many pesticides used to control mosquito populations are subject to hemolymph currents.  In addition to the experimental findings, this project provided invaluable mentorship to developing scientists, as graduate and undergraduate students carried out a large proportion of the work.       Last Modified: 05/08/2017       Submitted by: Julian F Hillyer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
