<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The 36th Conference on Stochastic Processes and their Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>47500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project provides participant support for the 36th Conference on  &lt;br/&gt;Stochastic Processes and their Applications (SPA) to be held July 29- &lt;br/&gt;August 2, 2013 at the University Colorado Boulder. Organized under the  &lt;br/&gt;auspices of the Bernoulli Society and the Institute of Mathematical  &lt;br/&gt;Statistics, SPA has emerged as the premier international forum for the  &lt;br/&gt;dissemination of new results in probability and random processes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As with past SPAs, the Boulder meeting will feature a wide range of  &lt;br/&gt;topics, bringing together both theoretical and applied researchers.   &lt;br/&gt;In addition to plenary talks which include the most prestigious named  &lt;br/&gt;lectures of the probability calendar, the Boulder meeting will be  &lt;br/&gt;organized around a large number of shorter contributed talks. This  &lt;br/&gt;provides a platform for young probabilists and affiliated researchers  &lt;br/&gt;to present their work alongside the key figures of the field.  To  &lt;br/&gt;facilitate these important exchanges, travel support for Ph.D.  &lt;br/&gt;students, postdocs, and new faculty, particularly for women and  &lt;br/&gt;underrepresented minorities, represents a large portion of the project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to the scientific program the Boulder meeting will feature  &lt;br/&gt;a series of round table discussions aimed at supporting new  &lt;br/&gt;researchers to the field.  Full program details are available at the  &lt;br/&gt;conference website: math.colorado.edu/spa2013/.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/31/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/31/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1257845</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sergei</FirstName>
<LastName>Kuznetsov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sergei E Kuznetsov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Sergei.Kuznetsov@Colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034924579</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000158274</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/31/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janos</FirstName>
<LastName>Englander</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janos Englander</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>janos.englander@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034924846</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000490718</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/31/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vanja</FirstName>
<LastName>Dukic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vanja Dukic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Vanja.Dukic@Colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037350919</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000109120</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/31/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Rider</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian C Rider</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brian.rider@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2152047841</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000180782</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/31/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Manuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Lladser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Manuel E Lladser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lladser@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034920694</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000333295</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/31/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street, Room 481]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~47500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 36th Conference on Stochastic Processes and Their Applications was held on the beautiful campus of the University of Colorado, Boulder, from July 29 to August 2, 2013. There were 250 participants. The international scientific committee was chaired by Steve Lalley (Chicago), and the local organizers were Anne Dougherty, Vanja Dukic, J&aacute;nos Engl&auml;nder, Sergei Kuznetsov, Manuel Lladser and Brian Rider (chair).</p> <p>At the beginning of the conference David Aldous announced that the 2013 Line and Michel Lo&egrave;ve International Prize in Probability was awarded to Sourav Chatterjee of the Courant Institute, New York (see &ldquo;Members&rsquo; News&rdquo; on page 2 of the September issue or this link).</p> <p>Named lectures were given by G&eacute;rard Ben Arous (Courant, New York University), who gave the L&eacute;vy Lecture; Itai Benjamini (Weizmann Institute of Science), who was the Inaugural Schramm Lecturer; Ken Golden (University of Utah), the Bernoulli Society Open Lecture; Neil O&rsquo;Connell (University of Warwick) the Doob Lecture; Hirofumi Osada (Kyushu University) the It&ocirc; Prize Lecture; and B&aacute;lint Vir&aacute;g (University of Toronto), who was an IMS Medallion Lecturer. The other plenary speakers were: Zhen-Qing Chen (University of Washington); Ron Doney (University of Manchester); Hugo Duminil-Copin (Universit&eacute; de Gen&egrave;ve); Tadahisa Funaki (University of Tokyo); Niels Jacob (Swansea University); Vadim Kaimanovich (University of Ottawa); Jeremy Quastel (University of Toronto); Kavita Ramanan (Brown University); Qi-Man Shao (Chinese University of Hong Kong); Amandine V&eacute;ber (&Eacute;cole Polytechnique); and Ofer Zeitouni (University of Minnesota &amp; Weizmann Institute of Science). Pablo Ferrari unfortunately had to cancel his plenary address.</p> <p>The inaugural Schramm lecture, by I. Benjamini, was in memory of the outstanding Israeli-American mathematician, Oded Schramm, known for the invention of the Schramm&ndash;Loewner evolution, who lost his life in a hiking accident in his forties. The It&ocirc; Prize Lecture was delivered by the recent winner of the prize, H. Osada. The Bernoulli Society Open Lecture, by K. Golden, was a &ldquo;public&rdquo; lecture, aimed at a broader audience; it addressed environmental as well as mathematical problems.</p> <p>A large number of invited and contributed sessions complemented the plenary talks, and a successful &ldquo;Early Researcher Panel Discussion&rdquo; took place on the Tuesday.<br />According to feedback from the participants, the scientific program was very well received, and those who participated either in the organized Wednesday hike in the Rockies or in one of the &ldquo;more privately organized&rdquo; ones, were fascinated by the natural beauties of the conference venue. The conference dinner took place at Hotel Boulderado, a landmark hotel in Boulder.</p> <p>The meeting was sponsored by IMS, the Bernoulli Society, International Society for Bayesian Analysis, Elsevier, Illinois Journal of Mathematics, National Science Foundation, National Security Agency, US Army Research Office, Department of the US Navy, Microsoft Research, and furthermore by the University of Colorado as well as its Departments of Mathematics and Applied Mathematics. All support received from the above agencies is gratefully acknowledged by the organizers.</p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">The leftover amount from the conference grant has been used (during the granted extension period, up to May 2015) to fund seminar speakers and visitors at the University of Colorado &nbsp;Boulder. The PI's are grateful to the National Science Fund for providing this extension.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/09/2015<br>      Modified by: Janos&nbsp;Englander</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 36th Conference on Stochastic Processes and Their Applications was held on the beautiful campus of the University of Colorado, Boulder, from July 29 to August 2, 2013. There were 250 participants. The international scientific committee was chaired by Steve Lalley (Chicago), and the local organizers were Anne Dougherty, Vanja Dukic, J&aacute;nos Engl&auml;nder, Sergei Kuznetsov, Manuel Lladser and Brian Rider (chair).  At the beginning of the conference David Aldous announced that the 2013 Line and Michel Lo&egrave;ve International Prize in Probability was awarded to Sourav Chatterjee of the Courant Institute, New York (see "MembersÆ News" on page 2 of the September issue or this link).  Named lectures were given by G&eacute;rard Ben Arous (Courant, New York University), who gave the L&eacute;vy Lecture; Itai Benjamini (Weizmann Institute of Science), who was the Inaugural Schramm Lecturer; Ken Golden (University of Utah), the Bernoulli Society Open Lecture; Neil OÆConnell (University of Warwick) the Doob Lecture; Hirofumi Osada (Kyushu University) the It&ocirc; Prize Lecture; and B&aacute;lint Vir&aacute;g (University of Toronto), who was an IMS Medallion Lecturer. The other plenary speakers were: Zhen-Qing Chen (University of Washington); Ron Doney (University of Manchester); Hugo Duminil-Copin (Universit&eacute; de Gen&egrave;ve); Tadahisa Funaki (University of Tokyo); Niels Jacob (Swansea University); Vadim Kaimanovich (University of Ottawa); Jeremy Quastel (University of Toronto); Kavita Ramanan (Brown University); Qi-Man Shao (Chinese University of Hong Kong); Amandine V&eacute;ber (&Eacute;cole Polytechnique); and Ofer Zeitouni (University of Minnesota &amp; Weizmann Institute of Science). Pablo Ferrari unfortunately had to cancel his plenary address.  The inaugural Schramm lecture, by I. Benjamini, was in memory of the outstanding Israeli-American mathematician, Oded Schramm, known for the invention of the Schramm&ndash;Loewner evolution, who lost his life in a hiking accident in his forties. The It&ocirc; Prize Lecture was delivered by the recent winner of the prize, H. Osada. The Bernoulli Society Open Lecture, by K. Golden, was a "public" lecture, aimed at a broader audience; it addressed environmental as well as mathematical problems.  A large number of invited and contributed sessions complemented the plenary talks, and a successful "Early Researcher Panel Discussion" took place on the Tuesday. According to feedback from the participants, the scientific program was very well received, and those who participated either in the organized Wednesday hike in the Rockies or in one of the "more privately organized" ones, were fascinated by the natural beauties of the conference venue. The conference dinner took place at Hotel Boulderado, a landmark hotel in Boulder.  The meeting was sponsored by IMS, the Bernoulli Society, International Society for Bayesian Analysis, Elsevier, Illinois Journal of Mathematics, National Science Foundation, National Security Agency, US Army Research Office, Department of the US Navy, Microsoft Research, and furthermore by the University of Colorado as well as its Departments of Mathematics and Applied Mathematics. All support received from the above agencies is gratefully acknowledged by the organizers. The leftover amount from the conference grant has been used (during the granted extension period, up to May 2015) to fund seminar speakers and visitors at the University of Colorado  Boulder. The PI's are grateful to the National Science Fund for providing this extension.          Last Modified: 06/09/2015       Submitted by: Janos Englander]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
