<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Metabolic multitasking: How Ralstonia solanacearum uses nitrate for plant pathogenesis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>508000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>508000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Mishkind</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmishkin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928413</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The pathogenic bacterium Ralstonia solanacearum is very successful in the vascular tissue of its plant hosts even though this habitat contains few nutrients and little oxygen.  This project's central hypothesis is that R. solanacearum uses inorganic nitrogen, one of the few abundant nutrients in plant sap, not just for food but also to generate energy and to sense and manipulate plant defenses. The investigators will use genetic and biochemical experiments to identify the specific adaptations that allow this pathogen to use inorganic nitrogen in multiple ways as it causes plant disease. Expected results include a better understanding of how R. solanacearum grows at low oxygen levels and a definition of the role(s) in virulence of nitric oxide, a common biological signal molecule that also has antimicrobial properties. R. solanacearum is a widely distributed pathogen with many hosts, so these results are likely to be relevant to diverse plant-associated microbes. Plant vascular systems are home to many microbes, ranging from destructive pathogens like R. solanacearum to valuable mutualists that can increase plant stress tolerance or growth.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will generate basic biological knowledge about the biochemical mechanisms used by plant-inhabiting microbes. In addition, this project will contribute to the nation's scientific workforce by training a postdoctoral researcher and a doctoral student in laboratory research, teaching and mentoring, which are all key skills for future faculty. Three undergraduate students will also receive independent research experiences in microbiology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1258082</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Caitilyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Allen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Caitilyn Allen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cza@plantpath.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082629578</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000177863</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 North Park St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7656</Code>
<Text>Symbiosis Infection &amp; Immunity</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~166000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~176000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~166000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Bacterial wilt is a lethal plant disease that limits production of many subsistence and cash crops such as potato, tomato, banana, peanut, and ginger. The disease, which is caused by the soilborne bacterium <em>Ralstonia solanacearum</em>, is difficult to control and has major socioeconomic impacts on a global scale. <em>R. solanacearum</em> colonizes the water-transporting xylem vessels of host plants. Although xylem sap is considered nutrient-poor, the pathogen multiplies rapidly in this environment, ultimately reaching population sizes of over 1 billion bacteria per gram of stem. The bacteria and their products block water transport, causing plants to wilt and die (Figure 1). To understand how <em>R. solanacearum</em> succeeds in this unpromising environment, we identified the metabolic processes used by the bacterium during tomato pathogenesis.&nbsp; Several biochemical pathways involving nitrogen were very highly expressed when <em>R. solanacearum </em>grew in tomato plants. We found that tomato xylem sap contains a significant amount of nitrogen in the form of nitrate (NO<sub>3</sub>).</p> <p>The goal of this project was to determine how this active nitrogen metabolism helps <em>R. solanacearum</em> kill plants. &nbsp;We identified three distinct types of nitrogen metabolism that play important roles in bacterial wilt disease. First, <em>R. solanacearum</em> extracts the essential nutrient nitrogen from nitrate and uses it to make proteins, DNA, RNA, and other cellular components. Mutant bacteria lacking the ability to assimilate nitrogen were significantly reduced in virulence on tomato, indicating that this trait helps <em>R. solanacearum</em> infect plants.</p> <p>Second, <em>R. solanacearum</em> uses nitrate to make energy in a process known as denitrifying respiration. The bacterium prefers to use oxygen to respire, as humans do, but when oxygen is limiting, <em>R. solanacearum</em> can respire by substituting nitrogen for oxygen. Direct measurements with a micro-probe detected very little oxygen inside xylem vessels of wilting plants. We constructed a set of <em>R. solanacearum</em> mutants lacking each of the five steps by which nitrate is converted to inert nitrogen gas (Fig 2A). The more of the pathway that was missing from a mutant, the less able it was to colonize tomato stems or cause disease, demonstrating that denitrifying respiration contributes to <em>R. solanacearum&rsquo;s</em> success as a pathogen (Fig 2B).</p> <p>Third, bacterial denitrifying respiration releases a highly reactive molecule, nitric oxide (NO), which is both a toxin and a common signaling molecule. We noticed that <em>R. solanacearum</em> mutants that overproduce NO also trigger an abnormally strong plant defense. Mutants that cannot make NO are less able to trigger this defense. We hypothesize that <em>R. solanacearum</em> uses NO to activate the molecular syringe it uses to inject virulence proteins into plant cells thereby increasing disease and also triggering plant defenses. This sort of NO-mediated activation is rare in bacteria. Experiments are not complete, but preliminary results support this hypothesis.</p> <p>Together, these experiments revealed that <em>R. solanacearum</em> makes maximum use of nitrate, one of the only resources available in its low-oxygen, nutrient-poor niche inside plants. The pathogen has adapted its metabolism to use nitrate to eat (assimilation), breathe (denitrifying respiration), and attack (NO-mediated activation of virulence).</p> <p>The broader impacts of the project include: 1) improved understanding of the fundamental biology of plant-microbe interactions, disseminated by publications in peer-reviewed scientific journals; 2) potential tools for reducing crop losses to bacterial wilt disease by managing nitrate fertilizer or breeding plants that make nitrate less available to the pathogen by sequestering or transforming it; 3) trained members of the scientific workforce, including one Ph.D., two postdoctoral researchers, and two Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) students who are currently Ph.D. students.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/13/2017<br>      Modified by: Caitilyn&nbsp;Allen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1258082/1258082_10237942_1497382026903_Fig1.TomatoBWDinPainter,VA--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1258082/1258082_10237942_1497382026903_Fig1.TomatoBWDinPainter,VA--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Bacterial wilt disease in the field"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1258082/1258082_10237942_1497382026903_Fig1.TomatoBWDinPainter,VA--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Bacterial wilt disease in the field"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Tomato plants near Painter, Virginia dying of bacterial wilt disease caused by Ralstonia solanacearum.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alejandra Huerta</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Caitilyn&nbsp;Allen</div> <div class="imageTitle">Bacterial wilt disease in the field</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1258082/1258082_10237942_1497382518243_Fig2Nmutantvirulence--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1258082/1258082_10237942_1497382518243_Fig2Nmutantvirulence--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Rs needs to respire on nitrate"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1258082/1258082_10237942_1497382518243_Fig2Nmutantvirulence--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Rs needs to respire on nitrate"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A. Ralstonia solanacearum mutants lacking steps in the denitrifying respiration pathway; B. The more of the pathway they have, the better they colonize tomato plants. Each symbol, color-coded by mutation, represents the bacteria in a tomato stem. Black symbols represent the non-mutated wildtype (WT)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Caitilyn Allen</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Caitilyn&nbsp;Allen</div> <div class="imageTitle">Rs needs to respire on nitrate</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Bacterial wilt is a lethal plant disease that limits production of many subsistence and cash crops such as potato, tomato, banana, peanut, and ginger. The disease, which is caused by the soilborne bacterium Ralstonia solanacearum, is difficult to control and has major socioeconomic impacts on a global scale. R. solanacearum colonizes the water-transporting xylem vessels of host plants. Although xylem sap is considered nutrient-poor, the pathogen multiplies rapidly in this environment, ultimately reaching population sizes of over 1 billion bacteria per gram of stem. The bacteria and their products block water transport, causing plants to wilt and die (Figure 1). To understand how R. solanacearum succeeds in this unpromising environment, we identified the metabolic processes used by the bacterium during tomato pathogenesis.  Several biochemical pathways involving nitrogen were very highly expressed when R. solanacearum grew in tomato plants. We found that tomato xylem sap contains a significant amount of nitrogen in the form of nitrate (NO3).  The goal of this project was to determine how this active nitrogen metabolism helps R. solanacearum kill plants.  We identified three distinct types of nitrogen metabolism that play important roles in bacterial wilt disease. First, R. solanacearum extracts the essential nutrient nitrogen from nitrate and uses it to make proteins, DNA, RNA, and other cellular components. Mutant bacteria lacking the ability to assimilate nitrogen were significantly reduced in virulence on tomato, indicating that this trait helps R. solanacearum infect plants.  Second, R. solanacearum uses nitrate to make energy in a process known as denitrifying respiration. The bacterium prefers to use oxygen to respire, as humans do, but when oxygen is limiting, R. solanacearum can respire by substituting nitrogen for oxygen. Direct measurements with a micro-probe detected very little oxygen inside xylem vessels of wilting plants. We constructed a set of R. solanacearum mutants lacking each of the five steps by which nitrate is converted to inert nitrogen gas (Fig 2A). The more of the pathway that was missing from a mutant, the less able it was to colonize tomato stems or cause disease, demonstrating that denitrifying respiration contributes to R. solanacearum?s success as a pathogen (Fig 2B).  Third, bacterial denitrifying respiration releases a highly reactive molecule, nitric oxide (NO), which is both a toxin and a common signaling molecule. We noticed that R. solanacearum mutants that overproduce NO also trigger an abnormally strong plant defense. Mutants that cannot make NO are less able to trigger this defense. We hypothesize that R. solanacearum uses NO to activate the molecular syringe it uses to inject virulence proteins into plant cells thereby increasing disease and also triggering plant defenses. This sort of NO-mediated activation is rare in bacteria. Experiments are not complete, but preliminary results support this hypothesis.  Together, these experiments revealed that R. solanacearum makes maximum use of nitrate, one of the only resources available in its low-oxygen, nutrient-poor niche inside plants. The pathogen has adapted its metabolism to use nitrate to eat (assimilation), breathe (denitrifying respiration), and attack (NO-mediated activation of virulence).  The broader impacts of the project include: 1) improved understanding of the fundamental biology of plant-microbe interactions, disseminated by publications in peer-reviewed scientific journals; 2) potential tools for reducing crop losses to bacterial wilt disease by managing nitrate fertilizer or breeding plants that make nitrate less available to the pathogen by sequestering or transforming it; 3) trained members of the scientific workforce, including one Ph.D., two postdoctoral researchers, and two Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) students who are currently Ph.D. students.          Last Modified: 06/13/2017       Submitted by: Caitilyn Allen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
