<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Proposal: A New Model For Chemical Ecology: Integrating Chemistry, Genetics and Behavior to Understand the Role of Individual Scent  in a Colonial Nesting Seabird.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>334000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>580860</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jodie Jawor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjawor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927887</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Personal odors can play an essential role in communication and individual recognition.  Scents make be influenced by genes that are critical for immune function, including genes of the major histocompatibility complex (MHC). This study will marry chemical ecology with modern forensic science techniques establishing the Leach's storm-petrel (Oceanodroma leucorhoa), as a model system studying what appears to be a critical but little studied aspect of social interactions in birds.This long-lived, burrow-nesting species has an excellent sense of smell, making them an ideal model for this investigation. Extensive field study sites have already been established on Bon Portage Island, Nova Scotia, Canada, where over 300 breeding pairs have been genotyped for the MHC class 2B gene. The aim is to characterize the individual odor profiles of these genotyped birds using state-of-the-art chemical techniques developed for human scent discrimination. Specific research objectives are a) to test whether individual birds produce odor signatures related to their MHC-genotype, b) to determine if birds use MHC-related scent marks to label their home burrows,  and  c) to determine whether the scent of an individual bird is an indicator of individual quality, health and fitness, or plays a role in mate choice decisions. Showing that any species of bird uses MHC-related odors in mate choice decisions would represent a paradigm shift in how biologists think about mate choice decisions in birds, and will provide insights relevant to avian immunology and health in a wide-ranging species. Just as importantly, many species of petrels and albatrosses are facing extinction, and understanding the factors driving mate choice and colony demographics will make a valuable contribution to comprehensive management plans for endangered species. Published phenotypic/chemical or genetic data will be deposited in the Dryad Repository (http://datadryad.org/) or submitted to Genbank (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/), and deposited in Merritt Data Repository (http://www.dataone.org/software-tools/merritt-repository-service).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1258784</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Edwards</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott V Edwards</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sedwards@fas.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174952471</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000170352</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Davis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles C Davis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cdavis@oeb.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174952365</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000328557</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/10/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021383846</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1350 Masschusetts Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7659</Code>
<Text>Animal Behavior</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~334000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~246860</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This study attempted to understand the mechanisms by which wild birds choose mates for breeding, and the evolutionary consequences of those mate choices. Scott Edwards, an evolutionary biologists and geneticist at Harvard and Gabrielle Nevitt, a behavioral ecologist and seabird physiologist at the University of California, Davis, joined forces to study this question in wild populations of seabirds.&nbsp; Understanding mate choice in wild animals is important for a thorough understanding of their breeding biology and the constraints and adaptations that allow them to survive and reproduce in an environment heavily dominated by the sea. Our work could have implications for human biology as well.</p> <p>We chose to study a North American seabird called Leach's Storm Petrel (Oceanodroma leucorhoa) a small, burrow-nesting seabird nesting throughout the North Pacific and Atlantic coasts of North America. We chose this bird because it was already known from previous studies that it had an excellent olfactory sense (its sense of smell), since it had been shown to be able to distinguish the burrow in which it was born from a foreign burrow by smell. We monitored hundreds of seabird couples in the field at our field site on Bon Portage Island, Nova Scotia. We took blood samples and kept track of who was mating with whom over a period of 5 years. We analyzed specific genes known to influence mate choice in mice, genes of the major histocompatibility complex (MHC). We also used next-generation sequencing techniques to understand how mating preferences may be influenced by genes outside the MHC. Ongoing work at Davis includes analysis of chemical profiles of birds so as to understand how the MHC and other genes influence the individual odor of birds and how these odors affect mate choice.<br /><br />We found that MHC genes do play a role in influencing the mate choices of males, whereas in females MHC genes seem to have no effect. We found that male storm petrels prefer to avoid females that are homozygous at specific MHC genes. The fact that males are more choosy in finding a mate than females is unusual in birds, since in most species females are the choosier gender. This insight came ony after studying hundreds of mated pairs and their offspring, and was recently published in the journal Molecular Ecology (Hoover, et al. 2018. Ecology Can Inform Genetics: Disassortative Mating Contributes to MHC Polymorphism in Leach&rsquo;s Storm-Petrels (<em>Oceanodroma leucorhoa</em>). <em>Molecular Ecology</em> 27: 3371&ndash;85.)</p> <p>We also used next-generation sequencing techniques to understand how genes outside the MHC might influence mate choice and chemical pofiles in Leach's Storm Petrel. We found that 2.4% of chicks were being fed and cared for by a male bird that was not the chick's father. Evidence of such "extra-pair mating" is growing in birds yet the ecological forces driving it remain an enigma. One possibility is that ecological pressures constrain the choice of mates during initial breeding attempts, resulting in birds that solicit matings with individuals other than those with whom they have settled and maintained a burrow. Our genome-wide analysis also indicated that female birds that were more inbred (had more homozygous positions in the genome) tended to raise chicks that were smaller and grew more slowly than females with more genetic variation. This finding may help explain why males are so choosy - they prefer to avoid inbred females. The MHC may be an indicator of such genome-wide inbreeding.</p> <p>Our study had several broader impacts for society. We trained one postdoctoral fellow and one undergraduate in the techniques of biotechnology. These individuals are now trained to assume multiple types of careers employing biotechnology and an understanding of biological principles, ecology and evolution. We also gave several public lectures in various venues to expose a broader audience to our findings. Our work may have implications for human biology in so far as several studies have found that MHC genes, which are also present in humans, may influence mate choice in our own species. Thus the study of seabirds may have relevance to the understanding the biology of our own species.&nbsp; Our large collection of blood and tissue samples has also improved scientific infrastructure. Their availability to researchers around the world will improve the foundation on which future studies of the genome of this and other species can build.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Scott&nbsp;V&nbsp;Edwards</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This study attempted to understand the mechanisms by which wild birds choose mates for breeding, and the evolutionary consequences of those mate choices. Scott Edwards, an evolutionary biologists and geneticist at Harvard and Gabrielle Nevitt, a behavioral ecologist and seabird physiologist at the University of California, Davis, joined forces to study this question in wild populations of seabirds.  Understanding mate choice in wild animals is important for a thorough understanding of their breeding biology and the constraints and adaptations that allow them to survive and reproduce in an environment heavily dominated by the sea. Our work could have implications for human biology as well.  We chose to study a North American seabird called Leach's Storm Petrel (Oceanodroma leucorhoa) a small, burrow-nesting seabird nesting throughout the North Pacific and Atlantic coasts of North America. We chose this bird because it was already known from previous studies that it had an excellent olfactory sense (its sense of smell), since it had been shown to be able to distinguish the burrow in which it was born from a foreign burrow by smell. We monitored hundreds of seabird couples in the field at our field site on Bon Portage Island, Nova Scotia. We took blood samples and kept track of who was mating with whom over a period of 5 years. We analyzed specific genes known to influence mate choice in mice, genes of the major histocompatibility complex (MHC). We also used next-generation sequencing techniques to understand how mating preferences may be influenced by genes outside the MHC. Ongoing work at Davis includes analysis of chemical profiles of birds so as to understand how the MHC and other genes influence the individual odor of birds and how these odors affect mate choice.  We found that MHC genes do play a role in influencing the mate choices of males, whereas in females MHC genes seem to have no effect. We found that male storm petrels prefer to avoid females that are homozygous at specific MHC genes. The fact that males are more choosy in finding a mate than females is unusual in birds, since in most species females are the choosier gender. This insight came ony after studying hundreds of mated pairs and their offspring, and was recently published in the journal Molecular Ecology (Hoover, et al. 2018. Ecology Can Inform Genetics: Disassortative Mating Contributes to MHC Polymorphism in Leach?s Storm-Petrels (Oceanodroma leucorhoa). Molecular Ecology 27: 3371&ndash;85.)  We also used next-generation sequencing techniques to understand how genes outside the MHC might influence mate choice and chemical pofiles in Leach's Storm Petrel. We found that 2.4% of chicks were being fed and cared for by a male bird that was not the chick's father. Evidence of such "extra-pair mating" is growing in birds yet the ecological forces driving it remain an enigma. One possibility is that ecological pressures constrain the choice of mates during initial breeding attempts, resulting in birds that solicit matings with individuals other than those with whom they have settled and maintained a burrow. Our genome-wide analysis also indicated that female birds that were more inbred (had more homozygous positions in the genome) tended to raise chicks that were smaller and grew more slowly than females with more genetic variation. This finding may help explain why males are so choosy - they prefer to avoid inbred females. The MHC may be an indicator of such genome-wide inbreeding.  Our study had several broader impacts for society. We trained one postdoctoral fellow and one undergraduate in the techniques of biotechnology. These individuals are now trained to assume multiple types of careers employing biotechnology and an understanding of biological principles, ecology and evolution. We also gave several public lectures in various venues to expose a broader audience to our findings. Our work may have implications for human biology in so far as several studies have found that MHC genes, which are also present in humans, may influence mate choice in our own species. Thus the study of seabirds may have relevance to the understanding the biology of our own species.  Our large collection of blood and tissue samples has also improved scientific infrastructure. Their availability to researchers around the world will improve the foundation on which future studies of the genome of this and other species can build.       Last Modified: 09/01/2018       Submitted by: Scott V Edwards]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
