<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Indigenous activism and epidemiological knowledge: An international comparison</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224315.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224315</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick Kronz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fkronz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Since the 1990s a rising number of indigenous-controlled epidemiology centers have been founded in multiple nation-states.  By collecting, interpreting, and disseminating statistical information about indigenous health, these centers aim to link the political &amp; cultural authority of "science" with indigenous claims for greater social justice in health, and for greater indigenous control of health research and services.  This study offers an international comparison of these efforts, examining the different resources, strategies and political-economic contexts for indigenous-controlled health research in two settings: Aotearoa/New Zealand and the United States.  These two nation-states share significant cultural and political similarities, but different historical legacies have shaped the institutionalization of indigenous-controlled research in each.  As such, indigenous researchers face distinctive challenges as they continually articulate and assert their goals and findings to multiple audiences in each setting.  Using ethnographic methods of participant observation and interviewing, complemented by methods of discourse analysis, this study will compare how epidemiological research is conducted at selected indigenous-controlled health research centers in both New Zealand and the U.S.; and how the resulting knowledge claims circulate in public life (e.g., through publication and presentation, media coverage, and/or public policy debates and decisions) in each setting.  This international comparison enables a nuanced analysis of how cultural and political contexts are shaping indigenous epidemiological research, and engages ongoing efforts to better understand the dynamics of articulating indigeneity worldwide.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Study findings will enhance understanding of the complex boundaries between science and politics, and promote appreciation of the complexity and diversity of contemporary indigenous peoples, in ways that encourage further communication and collaboration across the fields of medical anthropology, science &amp; technology studies, indigenous studies, and public health.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1259051</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erica</FirstName>
<LastName>Prussing</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erica Prussing</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>erica-prussing@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3193352123</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000082221</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Iowa</Name>
<CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2 GILMORE HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>062761671</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF IOWA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>062761671</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName>Iowa City</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>522421322</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[114 MacBride Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>STS-Sci, Tech &amp; Society</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, TECH &amp; SOCIETY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~224315</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This social scientific study aimed to better understand the rise and workings of epidemiological research &ldquo;by, with and for&rdquo; indigenous peoples.&nbsp;&nbsp; Epidemiologists use statistical analysis to study patterns of health and disease in populations, and focus on identifying causes for these patterns that will support effective public health interventions.&nbsp; Health research &ldquo;by, with and for&rdquo; indigenous peoples focuses on alleviating the disparities in lifespan and well-being that are commonly encountered by indigenous communities.&nbsp; Epidemiological research by, with and for indigenous peoples includes both indigenous and non-indigenous researcher/practitioners, and has developed since the 1970s in concert with broader global and regional activism for indigenous rights.&nbsp;</p> <p>Indigenous peoples frequently experience higher rates of sickness and premature death compared to non-indigenous populations.&nbsp; Inaccuracies and omissions in official health statistics often limit recognition of these disparities, however, and/or provide little or no explanation for why they exist.&nbsp; Such portraits can therefore reinforce common tendencies to assume that unequal health reflects biological factors or individual behaviors, rather than considering sociopolitical causes.&nbsp; In response, a growing body of research by, with and for indigenous peoples is using epidemiological methods to help better document indigenous population health patterns, and to assess how colonialism and its legacies have produced these patterns.&nbsp; This field has developed especially visibly across the Americas, the Caribbean, Australia, New Zealand, and the Pacific.&nbsp;</p> <p>As a social scientific study of this emerging body of research and its practitioners, this project featured ethnographic fieldwork (including interviews with researchers/practitioners, participant observation at events and in workplaces) at multiple sites in three major settings across the Pacific and North America: New Zealand, Hawai&rsquo;i, and the continental U.S.&nbsp; A total of 47 researchers/practitioners were interviewed across these three settings.&nbsp; A systematic review of published research in this field has also produced three study databases (one for each setting) that include over 500 studies total.&nbsp; Key themes within these interviews, ethnographic fieldnotes, and published studies and now being identified and assessed through content analysis.</p> <p>Findings from this study successfully fulfill its initial aim to better connect two bodies of existing scholarship: (1) anthropological and other social scientific studies of epidemiology, which examine how cultural assumptions shape epidemiological research questions, measures, analyses, and resulting knowledge claims; and (2) studies of indigenous activism, which offer tools for better understanding how health data figures in the politically complex fields of health policy and practice. Specifically, study findings highlight how researchers/practitioners involved in indigenous-centered epidemiological research make strategic use of the credibility of quantitative data, as they advocate for changes in health policies and practices that lessen disparities in indigenous health.&nbsp; Key features of such work include:</p> <ul> <li>using well-recognized epidemiologic risk factors and health outcomes, as well as newer measures (for example, racial discrimination);</li> <li>broadening conventional ways of thinking about how risk factors and outcomes relate (for example, examining how stress may cause rather than only stem from chronic diseases, and considering how understandings of well-being are diverse and culturally shaped);</li> <li>conceptualizing and measuring new risk factors (for example, historical/colonial trauma) as well as new health outcomes (for example, local concepts of health and well-being that include capacities for collective self-determination);</li> <li>carefully evaluating health interventions before adopting them as &ldquo;best practices,&rdquo; assuming that they are &ldquo;promising practices&rdquo; needing further assessment in socially, culturally and politically diverse communities;</li> <li>recognizing transnationally-shared indigenous experiences while also responding to regionally-specific indigenous health profiles (for example, exceptionally high rates of cardiometabolic diseases among Native Hawaiians in Hawai&rsquo;i) and sociopolitical contexts (for example, variable state and national political support for indigenous rights, and regionally distinctive debates about health/health care);</li> <li>using community-driven research methods to help to insure that epidemiological knowledge is produced not only in the service of research alone, but in collaborative and respectful ways that help communities to address their current health priorities.</li> </ul> <p>By working within the profession of epidemiology itself, researchers/practitioners in this field are especially skilled at producing detailed technical and methodological critiques that call for improvements in statistical practices, in order to provide valid and useful statistics about health in indigenous and other smaller, non-standard populations.&nbsp; In these ways, concepts, measures and methods from this field are providing innovative technical contributions to epidemiology and public health, while working from an ethical framework which holds that all human communities should have equal rights to health.</p> <p>Dissemination of findings from this study of epidemiology by, with and for indigenous peoples offers concrete suggestions for how to improve cultural diversity within public health, by providing specific illustrations of what cultural diversity means--and practical examples of what it produces--in epidemiology and other scientific research fields.&nbsp; Such work emphasizes how human actions and interactions, unfolding within historical and cultural contexts, inevitably shape all scientific research&mdash;or as one M?ori researcher interviewed for this study aptly summarized, of how &ldquo;data doesn&rsquo;t speak for itself; we speak for it.&rdquo;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/04/2017<br>      Modified by: Erica&nbsp;Prussing</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This social scientific study aimed to better understand the rise and workings of epidemiological research "by, with and for" indigenous peoples.   Epidemiologists use statistical analysis to study patterns of health and disease in populations, and focus on identifying causes for these patterns that will support effective public health interventions.  Health research "by, with and for" indigenous peoples focuses on alleviating the disparities in lifespan and well-being that are commonly encountered by indigenous communities.  Epidemiological research by, with and for indigenous peoples includes both indigenous and non-indigenous researcher/practitioners, and has developed since the 1970s in concert with broader global and regional activism for indigenous rights.   Indigenous peoples frequently experience higher rates of sickness and premature death compared to non-indigenous populations.  Inaccuracies and omissions in official health statistics often limit recognition of these disparities, however, and/or provide little or no explanation for why they exist.  Such portraits can therefore reinforce common tendencies to assume that unequal health reflects biological factors or individual behaviors, rather than considering sociopolitical causes.  In response, a growing body of research by, with and for indigenous peoples is using epidemiological methods to help better document indigenous population health patterns, and to assess how colonialism and its legacies have produced these patterns.  This field has developed especially visibly across the Americas, the Caribbean, Australia, New Zealand, and the Pacific.   As a social scientific study of this emerging body of research and its practitioners, this project featured ethnographic fieldwork (including interviews with researchers/practitioners, participant observation at events and in workplaces) at multiple sites in three major settings across the Pacific and North America: New Zealand, Hawai?i, and the continental U.S.  A total of 47 researchers/practitioners were interviewed across these three settings.  A systematic review of published research in this field has also produced three study databases (one for each setting) that include over 500 studies total.  Key themes within these interviews, ethnographic fieldnotes, and published studies and now being identified and assessed through content analysis.  Findings from this study successfully fulfill its initial aim to better connect two bodies of existing scholarship: (1) anthropological and other social scientific studies of epidemiology, which examine how cultural assumptions shape epidemiological research questions, measures, analyses, and resulting knowledge claims; and (2) studies of indigenous activism, which offer tools for better understanding how health data figures in the politically complex fields of health policy and practice. Specifically, study findings highlight how researchers/practitioners involved in indigenous-centered epidemiological research make strategic use of the credibility of quantitative data, as they advocate for changes in health policies and practices that lessen disparities in indigenous health.  Key features of such work include:  using well-recognized epidemiologic risk factors and health outcomes, as well as newer measures (for example, racial discrimination); broadening conventional ways of thinking about how risk factors and outcomes relate (for example, examining how stress may cause rather than only stem from chronic diseases, and considering how understandings of well-being are diverse and culturally shaped); conceptualizing and measuring new risk factors (for example, historical/colonial trauma) as well as new health outcomes (for example, local concepts of health and well-being that include capacities for collective self-determination); carefully evaluating health interventions before adopting them as "best practices," assuming that they are "promising practices" needing further assessment in socially, culturally and politically diverse communities; recognizing transnationally-shared indigenous experiences while also responding to regionally-specific indigenous health profiles (for example, exceptionally high rates of cardiometabolic diseases among Native Hawaiians in Hawai?i) and sociopolitical contexts (for example, variable state and national political support for indigenous rights, and regionally distinctive debates about health/health care); using community-driven research methods to help to insure that epidemiological knowledge is produced not only in the service of research alone, but in collaborative and respectful ways that help communities to address their current health priorities.   By working within the profession of epidemiology itself, researchers/practitioners in this field are especially skilled at producing detailed technical and methodological critiques that call for improvements in statistical practices, in order to provide valid and useful statistics about health in indigenous and other smaller, non-standard populations.  In these ways, concepts, measures and methods from this field are providing innovative technical contributions to epidemiology and public health, while working from an ethical framework which holds that all human communities should have equal rights to health.  Dissemination of findings from this study of epidemiology by, with and for indigenous peoples offers concrete suggestions for how to improve cultural diversity within public health, by providing specific illustrations of what cultural diversity means--and practical examples of what it produces--in epidemiology and other scientific research fields.  Such work emphasizes how human actions and interactions, unfolding within historical and cultural contexts, inevitably shape all scientific research&mdash;or as one M?ori researcher interviewed for this study aptly summarized, of how "data doesn?t speak for itself; we speak for it."          Last Modified: 08/04/2017       Submitted by: Erica Prussing]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
