<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Geometry of Moduli Spaces, Geometric Invariant Theory, and Deformations of Singularities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>117999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>117999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>adpollin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal is concerned with the study of moduli spaces in algebraic geometry. By using methods of Geometric Invariant Theory, deformation theory, and enumerative geometry, the investigator will pursue several projects in order to elucidate the geometry of well-studied moduli spaces and to adopt new approaches to less studied ones. In the first project, the investigator will continue the study of finite Hilbert stability of embedded curves with the goal of advancing the log minimal model program for the Deligne-Mumford moduli space of stable curves. In the second project, the investigator will approach fundamental open questions about effective and ample divisors on this moduli space and its variants. The study of singularities is an important ingredient of these two projects. In the third project, the investigator will extend recent results in the theory of curves to certain classes of higher-dimensional varieties (e.g., K3 surfaces) and their moduli spaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An algebraic variety is a collection of solutions to a system of polynomial equations. Algebraic varieties are fundamental objects of study in mathematics and, in particular, in the field of algebraic geometry, to which this proposal belongs. Variation of the polynomials' coefficients gives rise to a moduli space for a given class of varieties. The study of moduli spaces is essential to understanding algebraic varieties themselves and, ultimately, to solving systems of polynomial equations. The investigator proposes to study moduli spaces of algebraic varieties depending on one or two free parameters using both classical and modern techniques. The broader impacts of the proposal include advancing an active research program and co-organizing workshops on moduli spaces and related problems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1259226</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maksym</FirstName>
<LastName>Fedorchuk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maksym Fedorchuk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maksym.fedorchuk@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175523757</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574412</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/05/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673806</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[140 Commonwealth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~117999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The investigator works in algebraic geometry. &nbsp;</span>The main objects of his study in this project were parameter spaces of algebraic curves. &nbsp;One can think of algebraic curves in two ways: algebraically as solutions to the systems of polynomial equations with one degree of freedom, or geometrically as shapes of dimension one (e.g., unions of lines or more curved trajectories) in space. &nbsp;In both viewpoints, a curve depends on parameters, which are the coefficients of the equations in the algebraic viewpoint, or curvature, the number of loops, and singularities (i.e., sharp changes in direction) in the geometric viewpoint. &nbsp;The allowable parameters for which a curve can physically exist can in turn be encoded in another geometric shape, called a moduli space. &nbsp;These moduli spaces can also be described by a system of equations, but with a much more complicated structure and with a large degree of freedom. &nbsp;</p> <p>Together with his collaborators, the investigator has developed a long-term program to prod at the structure and geometry of various moduli spaces of curves using both recent advances in algebraic geometry, such as algebraic stacks, and more classical techniques such as invariant theory. &nbsp;This program has already produced a number of new results (e.g., about invariant theory) and revealed new interesting problems (e.g., about curve singularities and how they fit into moduli spaces). &nbsp;</p> <p>While supported by this award, the investigator has organized a number of research workshops and conferences that furthered graduate student training and education. &nbsp;He also has offered research opportunities to undergraduate students at Boston College and has participated in outreach efforts directed at K12 math teachers. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/14/2016<br>      Modified by: Maksym&nbsp;Fedorchuk</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The investigator works in algebraic geometry.  The main objects of his study in this project were parameter spaces of algebraic curves.  One can think of algebraic curves in two ways: algebraically as solutions to the systems of polynomial equations with one degree of freedom, or geometrically as shapes of dimension one (e.g., unions of lines or more curved trajectories) in space.  In both viewpoints, a curve depends on parameters, which are the coefficients of the equations in the algebraic viewpoint, or curvature, the number of loops, and singularities (i.e., sharp changes in direction) in the geometric viewpoint.  The allowable parameters for which a curve can physically exist can in turn be encoded in another geometric shape, called a moduli space.  These moduli spaces can also be described by a system of equations, but with a much more complicated structure and with a large degree of freedom.    Together with his collaborators, the investigator has developed a long-term program to prod at the structure and geometry of various moduli spaces of curves using both recent advances in algebraic geometry, such as algebraic stacks, and more classical techniques such as invariant theory.  This program has already produced a number of new results (e.g., about invariant theory) and revealed new interesting problems (e.g., about curve singularities and how they fit into moduli spaces).    While supported by this award, the investigator has organized a number of research workshops and conferences that furthered graduate student training and education.  He also has offered research opportunities to undergraduate students at Boston College and has participated in outreach efforts directed at K12 math teachers.         Last Modified: 10/14/2016       Submitted by: Maksym Fedorchuk]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
