<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NBER Summer Institute, 2013-2015</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>375000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>773412</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Lutz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nlutz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927280</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant provides renewed funding for the participation of junior faculty in the National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER) Summer Institute. For more than thirty years, NBER's Summer Institute has offered an ideal environment for developing new ideas and forging collaborative work relationships. Summer Institute brings together economists and scholars in other fields from universities, government, and international organizations for a few days or a few weeks of seminars, workshops, conferences, and cooperative research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Summer Institute is four weeks long, and includes at least 50 sessions organized and co-organized by over 80 individuals. There are more than 1,750 attendees from over 300 universities and non-academic institutions, and in 2012 more than twothirds of the individuals who attended Summer Institute were not NBER affiliates. While there are many presentations of work nearing completion, emphasis is placed on the workshop aspects of the program where new ideas are raised, preliminary research ideas are developed, and plans for joint or coordinated research efforts are established. Efforts are made to include a wide variety of new participants, and to reach out to women and minorities. Calls for papers are circulated widely and are available on the NBER website. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The NBER Summer Institutes generate timely and influential research on important economic policy questions related to such topics as international financial stability, economic productivity and technology, enviornmental regulations, social security policy, and educational policies. The workshops are an invaluable part of the research infrastructure in ecobnomics and assist the research of a large number of economists.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/03/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1259969</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Poterba</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James M Poterba</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>poterba@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6178683900</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000213169</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Bureau of Economic Research Inc</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385398</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6178683900</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1050 Massachusetts Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>054552435</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL BUREAU OF ECONOMIC RESEARCH, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>054552435</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Bureau of Economic Research Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021385398</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1050 Massachusetts Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O502</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~375000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~398412</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award supported the annual meetings of the National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER) Summer Institute in 2013, 2014, and 2015.&nbsp; In addition, it supported a meeting in 2017 on the Economics of Energy Markets.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The NBER Summer Institute is one of the premier annual meetings of applied economists, attracting more than 2500 researchers to Cambridge, Massachusetts over a three-week period in July.&nbsp; The Summer Institute provides researchers with an opportunity to learn about the latest research by attending seminar presentations, while also fostering interaction and in particular collaborative work.&nbsp; Many Summer Institute meetings involve only a half-day of scheduled presentations, so that participants can work in small groups during the other part of the day.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The Summer Institute consists of more than 50 distinct meetings, each organized either by an NBER program director or one or more researchers of their choosing.&nbsp; The participants are from a diverse range of institutions.&nbsp; In 2014, for example, there were attendees from more than 400 colleges, universities, central banks, and other research institutes.&nbsp; Roughly two-thirds of those who attended were not NBER affiliates, and about 20 percent were first-time Summer Institute participants. More than 100 graduate students attended the 2013 meeting, and more than 150 participated in each of the 2014 and 2015 meetings.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Every Summer Institute includes a set of plenary sessions.&nbsp; These are typically very popular, and they attract researchers from many sub-fields of economics.&nbsp; In 2013, NBER hosted an all-day session on "The Federal Reserve at 100." This meeting attracted more than 500 participants and featured a keynote address by then-Federal Reserve Chairman Ben Bernanke.&nbsp; Another highlight of the 2013 Summer Institute was a lecture by Harvard University professor Lawrence Summers, who spoke about "Economic Possibilities for our Children&rdquo; and the challenges posed by slow economic growth. Every Summer Institute includes a lecture on econometric methods.&nbsp; For 2013, the lecture focused on &ldquo;Econometric Methods for Big Data.&rdquo;&nbsp; It described the computational challenges of working with very large data sets, as well as some of the statistical methods that could be particularly helpful in this context.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The 2014 Summer Institute drew more participants than the 2013, and 2015 was larger still.&nbsp; In 2014, Federal Reserve Board Vice-Chair Stanley Fischer delivered a plenary lecture on the challenges of designing financial regulations.&nbsp; The methodology lectures were presented by Daron Acemoglu of MIT and Matthew Jackson of Stanford.&nbsp; Their topic was &ldquo;Theory and Application of Network Models.&rdquo;&nbsp; They focused on applications in labor economics as well as some of the econometric modeling issues that arise when network effects are important.&nbsp;</p> <p>In 2015, Alan Krueger of Princeton University delivered a plenary lecture on U.S. labor market dynamics, with particular attention to the recent evolution of the employment-to-population ratio.&nbsp; A panel discussion examined lessons learned from the Greek Crisis, and Susan Athey and Guido Imbens of Stanford University delivered a very well attended set of econometrics lectures on &ldquo;Applications of Machine Learning (ML) in Economics.&rdquo;&nbsp; They focused on ways in which ML could be combined with various econometric tools to facilitate more informative data analysis.&nbsp; These lecture spanned a day, and like all of the previous econometrics lectures and most of the other plenary talks, they were recorded and have been posted on the NBER website.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>While it is difficult to point to specific research breakthroughs that occurred while participants were attending the Summer Institute, in after-the-fact surveys, those who attend the meeting are strongly complimentary to the opportunity that the meeting provides for collaboration, and they note that informal interactions were among the most valuable components of their Cambridge visit.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The award also supported research on several studies concerning the economics of energy markets.&nbsp; In the fall of 2015, the NBER invited proposals for research on a range of topics in energy economics, including energy infrastructure and policy; strategic energy policy; energy financing; and the interaction between energy markets and innovation.&nbsp; Research on these topics by eight teams has been coordinated by Meredith Fowlie of the University of California at Berkeley and Chris Knittel of MIT.&nbsp; The findings were presented at a capstone conference in Washington, D.C. in 2017.&nbsp; The research provides insight on basic economic issues that are important for energy policy design.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/26/2018<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;M&nbsp;Poterba</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award supported the annual meetings of the National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER) Summer Institute in 2013, 2014, and 2015.  In addition, it supported a meeting in 2017 on the Economics of Energy Markets.      The NBER Summer Institute is one of the premier annual meetings of applied economists, attracting more than 2500 researchers to Cambridge, Massachusetts over a three-week period in July.  The Summer Institute provides researchers with an opportunity to learn about the latest research by attending seminar presentations, while also fostering interaction and in particular collaborative work.  Many Summer Institute meetings involve only a half-day of scheduled presentations, so that participants can work in small groups during the other part of the day.      The Summer Institute consists of more than 50 distinct meetings, each organized either by an NBER program director or one or more researchers of their choosing.  The participants are from a diverse range of institutions.  In 2014, for example, there were attendees from more than 400 colleges, universities, central banks, and other research institutes.  Roughly two-thirds of those who attended were not NBER affiliates, and about 20 percent were first-time Summer Institute participants. More than 100 graduate students attended the 2013 meeting, and more than 150 participated in each of the 2014 and 2015 meetings.      Every Summer Institute includes a set of plenary sessions.  These are typically very popular, and they attract researchers from many sub-fields of economics.  In 2013, NBER hosted an all-day session on "The Federal Reserve at 100." This meeting attracted more than 500 participants and featured a keynote address by then-Federal Reserve Chairman Ben Bernanke.  Another highlight of the 2013 Summer Institute was a lecture by Harvard University professor Lawrence Summers, who spoke about "Economic Possibilities for our Children" and the challenges posed by slow economic growth. Every Summer Institute includes a lecture on econometric methods.  For 2013, the lecture focused on "Econometric Methods for Big Data."  It described the computational challenges of working with very large data sets, as well as some of the statistical methods that could be particularly helpful in this context.      The 2014 Summer Institute drew more participants than the 2013, and 2015 was larger still.  In 2014, Federal Reserve Board Vice-Chair Stanley Fischer delivered a plenary lecture on the challenges of designing financial regulations.  The methodology lectures were presented by Daron Acemoglu of MIT and Matthew Jackson of Stanford.  Their topic was "Theory and Application of Network Models."  They focused on applications in labor economics as well as some of the econometric modeling issues that arise when network effects are important.   In 2015, Alan Krueger of Princeton University delivered a plenary lecture on U.S. labor market dynamics, with particular attention to the recent evolution of the employment-to-population ratio.  A panel discussion examined lessons learned from the Greek Crisis, and Susan Athey and Guido Imbens of Stanford University delivered a very well attended set of econometrics lectures on "Applications of Machine Learning (ML) in Economics."  They focused on ways in which ML could be combined with various econometric tools to facilitate more informative data analysis.  These lecture spanned a day, and like all of the previous econometrics lectures and most of the other plenary talks, they were recorded and have been posted on the NBER website.      While it is difficult to point to specific research breakthroughs that occurred while participants were attending the Summer Institute, in after-the-fact surveys, those who attend the meeting are strongly complimentary to the opportunity that the meeting provides for collaboration, and they note that informal interactions were among the most valuable components of their Cambridge visit.      The award also supported research on several studies concerning the economics of energy markets.  In the fall of 2015, the NBER invited proposals for research on a range of topics in energy economics, including energy infrastructure and policy; strategic energy policy; energy financing; and the interaction between energy markets and innovation.  Research on these topics by eight teams has been coordinated by Meredith Fowlie of the University of California at Berkeley and Chris Knittel of MIT.  The findings were presented at a capstone conference in Washington, D.C. in 2017.  The research provides insight on basic economic issues that are important for energy policy design.       Last Modified: 11/26/2018       Submitted by: James M Poterba]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
