<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Methylmercury Interactions with Marine Plankton</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>316611.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>316611</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Milne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmilne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924714</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Methylmercury (MeHg) causes a variety of adverse health effects in exposed humans and wildlife but its formation and cycling in oceanic waters have not been fully characterized or quantified.  This research program seeks to better understand factors controlling the production, fate, phytoplankton uptake, and transfer of MeHg in the marine environment&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A combination of laboratory, field studies and modeling efforts will investigate the bioaccumulation, trophic transfer in aquatic food webs, and implications that this may have on the global transport of this potent neurotoxin. Laboratory and coastal field studies of MeHg interactions with different types of phytoplankton, interaction with specific organic compounds, effects of light and temperature are all expected to influence MeHg binding and or uptake into phytoplankton.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of the work include: &lt;br/&gt;1) provision of  policy relevant information in support of monitoring and evaluation efforts for control of anthropogenic mercury releases; &lt;br/&gt;2) informing education on marine conservation and sustainability by developing a case study on mercury in the marine environment; and &lt;br/&gt;3) training the next generation of interdisciplinary scientists</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1260416</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Mason</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert P Mason</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robert.mason@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8604059129</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000064296</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/19/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Unit 1133]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>614209054</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004534830</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Connecticut]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1670</Code>
<Text>Chemical Oceanography</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~104168</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~112249</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~100194</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Anthropogenic activities have substantially altered the cycling of mercury (Hg) at the Earth's surface and have significantly increased the Hg input into the ocean. Studies have shown how these elevated inputs have increased concentrations in the environment but it is not clear how these changes have been transferred through the food chain to fish consumers. Elevated levels of Hg, as methylmercury (MeHg), in fish and seafood is an important health concern for humans and other wildlife. The project examined the factors controlling the uptake of inorganic Hg and MeHg into phytoplankton and their trophic transfer to zooplankton. These accumualtions at the base of the ocean food chain are the largest bioconcentration steps between the water and fish. Understanding the differences in accumulation at these lower trophic levels will allow for better understanding and management of the elevated levels of MeHg found in seafood, thereby reducing human exposure to the toxic effects of MeHg.</p> <p>The study collected samples in the open waters of the tropical Pacific Ocean and in coastal waters, focusing on Long Island Sound (LIS). Sampels were collected seasonally in LIS and in the adjecent shelf waters. Samples were also collected in a fjord in Labrador, Canada. Plankton samples were separated into different size classes before analysis. The expectation was that larger organisms would have higher concentrations but this was not always found. In larger phytoplankton, there were differences between coastal and open ocean waters as in the open ocean, small phytoplankton had the highest concentration while the opposite was generally true for the coastal species. For the zooplankton, it was generally the case that the concentrations increased with size, as did the fraction of the total Hg as MeHg (%MeHg). Interestingly, the plankton in the open ocean waters had higher or comparable concentrations to the coastal species even though the water concentrations were much lower. This was evident in the much higher bioaccumualtion factors (BCF; the ratio of the concentration in the plankton to that in the water) for the Pacific Ocean plankton. Overall, this result was consistent across the different size classes of plankton.</p> <p>Laboratory exposure experiments tended to concur with the results from the collections in the field. One important result of the lab studies, which were done at much lower exposure concentrations than previous studies, was that the relative bioaccumualtion at lower exposure could be greater than at higher exposure concentrations (i.e. a higher BCF for lower exposure for the same species). These results need to be incorporated into computer models which currently use the lower BCF values found previously is estimating bioaccumulation and exposure. The information collected during this study will provide detailed information to managers and modelers interested in examining how various factors may change the amount of MeHg in fish and therefore human exposure.</p> <p>There are important results from this study which will allow a better assessment of the potential impacts of climate change and anthropogenic releases of Hg to the atmosphere on the concentrations of MeHg in seafood. The results from this study have been published in the peer-reviewed literature and shared with interested scientists and other parties and presented to the public, including to students at high schools in the area. The project formed the major part of the thesis of Kati Gosnell, who submitted her final thesis in March 2016.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;P&nbsp;Mason</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galContro...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Anthropogenic activities have substantially altered the cycling of mercury (Hg) at the Earth's surface and have significantly increased the Hg input into the ocean. Studies have shown how these elevated inputs have increased concentrations in the environment but it is not clear how these changes have been transferred through the food chain to fish consumers. Elevated levels of Hg, as methylmercury (MeHg), in fish and seafood is an important health concern for humans and other wildlife. The project examined the factors controlling the uptake of inorganic Hg and MeHg into phytoplankton and their trophic transfer to zooplankton. These accumualtions at the base of the ocean food chain are the largest bioconcentration steps between the water and fish. Understanding the differences in accumulation at these lower trophic levels will allow for better understanding and management of the elevated levels of MeHg found in seafood, thereby reducing human exposure to the toxic effects of MeHg.  The study collected samples in the open waters of the tropical Pacific Ocean and in coastal waters, focusing on Long Island Sound (LIS). Sampels were collected seasonally in LIS and in the adjecent shelf waters. Samples were also collected in a fjord in Labrador, Canada. Plankton samples were separated into different size classes before analysis. The expectation was that larger organisms would have higher concentrations but this was not always found. In larger phytoplankton, there were differences between coastal and open ocean waters as in the open ocean, small phytoplankton had the highest concentration while the opposite was generally true for the coastal species. For the zooplankton, it was generally the case that the concentrations increased with size, as did the fraction of the total Hg as MeHg (%MeHg). Interestingly, the plankton in the open ocean waters had higher or comparable concentrations to the coastal species even though the water concentrations were much lower. This was evident in the much higher bioaccumualtion factors (BCF; the ratio of the concentration in the plankton to that in the water) for the Pacific Ocean plankton. Overall, this result was consistent across the different size classes of plankton.  Laboratory exposure experiments tended to concur with the results from the collections in the field. One important result of the lab studies, which were done at much lower exposure concentrations than previous studies, was that the relative bioaccumualtion at lower exposure could be greater than at higher exposure concentrations (i.e. a higher BCF for lower exposure for the same species). These results need to be incorporated into computer models which currently use the lower BCF values found previously is estimating bioaccumulation and exposure. The information collected during this study will provide detailed information to managers and modelers interested in examining how various factors may change the amount of MeHg in fish and therefore human exposure.  There are important results from this study which will allow a better assessment of the potential impacts of climate change and anthropogenic releases of Hg to the atmosphere on the concentrations of MeHg in seafood. The results from this study have been published in the peer-reviewed literature and shared with interested scientists and other parties and presented to the public, including to students at high schools in the area. The project formed the major part of the thesis of Kati Gosnell, who submitted her final thesis in March 2016.       Last Modified: 03/30/2016       Submitted by: Robert P Mason]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
