<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Scholarships for Undergraduates to Reach Goals in Education (SURGE)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>623608.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>623608</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dawn Rickey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>drickey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924674</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Mathematics Department at the University of Texas Arlington is supporting 30 students in two distinct 15-student cohorts, during their sophomore through senior years as they pursue bachelor's degrees in mathematics.  Scholars are receiving financial support commensurate with their demonstrated financial need, not exceeding $10,000 per year, and averaging about $5,800 per year.  The majority of scholars began their undergraduate education at a nearby 2-year institution and come from a diverse set of backgrounds.  The S-STEM scholar program is a comprehensive student support component that builds on an existing mathematics learning community, anchored by the local student chapter of the Mathematical Association of America.  S-STEM scholars are engaged with degree planning, networking, mentoring, engagement with the student discipline society, internships/research, conferences, and career workshops in a structured program that is supportive for the students' current achievement level.  Extensive faculty mentoring is being enabled by weekly lunch-time meetings that includes students and faculty as part of a dynamic learning community that enables professional development and minimizes demand on participants' time.  The S-STEM project's success is leading to mathematics graduates entering the workforce or continuing on to additional higher education.  Findings and best practices are being shared with other units on campus, with the institutions in the University of Texas System LS-AMP program, with colleges and universities in the Math Alliance, and through conference proceedings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1260019</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tuncay</FirstName>
<LastName>Aktosun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tuncay Aktosun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aktosun@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8172721545</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000156483</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jianzhong</FirstName>
<LastName>Su</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jianzhong Su</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>su@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8172725684</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000381776</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ruth</FirstName>
<LastName>Gornet</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ruth Gornet</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rgornet@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8172723261</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000397835</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Shipman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara A Shipman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bshipman@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8172722606</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000421914</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hristo</FirstName>
<LastName>Kojouharov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hristo V Kojouharov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hristo@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8172725763</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000414107</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Arlington</Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>701 S Nedderman Dr, Box 19145</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064234610</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT ARLINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Arlington]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>760190114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~105248</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~518360</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The mentoring and scholarship program SURGE (Scholarships for Undergraduates to Reach Goals in Education) was conducted during the period of September 1, 2013-August 31, 2018 in the Mathematics Department at the University of Texas at Arlington. A total of 48 students were supported, and 42 of these students have already received their undergraduate degrees in mathematics and the remaining six are making timely progress toward their degrees.</p> <p>The objectives of the SURGE program were to support the students as cohorts to help them to receive their bachelor&rsquo;s degrees in mathematics through S-STEM scholarships, to utilize and enhance the existing comprehensive support programs to ensure academic success of participating students and to place them after graduation in STEM workforce or graduate school, and to expand the success of the SURGE program to benefit more mathematics majors and other students in STEM areas at the University of Texas at Arlington. Each student in the SURGE program received a scholarship up to $10,000/year for up to three years, depending on demonstrated financial need. About half of the students in the SURGE program were transfer students from two area community college systems (with a combined enrollment of over 100,000).</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: The unique feature of the SURGE program was a comprehensive student support component that built on an existing mathematics learning community, anchored by the local student chapter of the Mathematical Association of America. The centerpiece of the support component was the faculty/peer/external career mentoring that ensured weekly in-person interactions between mentors and SURGE students.&nbsp; There were in place various special programs for interested SURGE students to participate, depending on their interest and time availability, such as tutoring in the Math Clinic and performing community services. About half of the SURGE students participated in funded summer undergraduate research experiences. There were five SURGE program faculty members involved and they provided mentoring&nbsp; for the success of the SURGE scholars.</p> <p>Broader Impacts: The SURGE program improved educational opportunities for mathematically talented and financially needy students in the Dallas/Fort Worth area, including women and underrepresented minorities. The women in the SURGE program constituted 41 percent and the underrepresented minorities 30 percent. Efforts continue to encourage more women and more underrepresented minorities to receive bachelor's degrees in mathematics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Tuncay&nbsp;Aktosun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The mentoring and scholarship program SURGE (Scholarships for Undergraduates to Reach Goals in Education) was conducted during the period of September 1, 2013-August 31, 2018 in the Mathematics Department at the University of Texas at Arlington. A total of 48 students were supported, and 42 of these students have already received their undergraduate degrees in mathematics and the remaining six are making timely progress toward their degrees.  The objectives of the SURGE program were to support the students as cohorts to help them to receive their bachelor?s degrees in mathematics through S-STEM scholarships, to utilize and enhance the existing comprehensive support programs to ensure academic success of participating students and to place them after graduation in STEM workforce or graduate school, and to expand the success of the SURGE program to benefit more mathematics majors and other students in STEM areas at the University of Texas at Arlington. Each student in the SURGE program received a scholarship up to $10,000/year for up to three years, depending on demonstrated financial need. About half of the students in the SURGE program were transfer students from two area community college systems (with a combined enrollment of over 100,000).  Intellectual Merit: The unique feature of the SURGE program was a comprehensive student support component that built on an existing mathematics learning community, anchored by the local student chapter of the Mathematical Association of America. The centerpiece of the support component was the faculty/peer/external career mentoring that ensured weekly in-person interactions between mentors and SURGE students.  There were in place various special programs for interested SURGE students to participate, depending on their interest and time availability, such as tutoring in the Math Clinic and performing community services. About half of the SURGE students participated in funded summer undergraduate research experiences. There were five SURGE program faculty members involved and they provided mentoring  for the success of the SURGE scholars.  Broader Impacts: The SURGE program improved educational opportunities for mathematically talented and financially needy students in the Dallas/Fort Worth area, including women and underrepresented minorities. The women in the SURGE program constituted 41 percent and the underrepresented minorities 30 percent. Efforts continue to encourage more women and more underrepresented minorities to receive bachelor's degrees in mathematics.          Last Modified: 10/30/2018       Submitted by: Tuncay Aktosun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
