<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Pathways to Economic Opportunity and Intergenerational Mobility:  Evidence from United States Tax Records</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>424020.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>424020</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Seung-Hyun Hong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Many Americans embrace the ideal of "equality of opportunity", believing in the ideal that ones' economic opportunities should not depend on the parents to whom they happen to be born. While numerous researchers have been interested in the drivers of intergenerational mobility and economic opportunity, previous studies have often been hindered by a lack of available large datasets linking parents and their children. As a result, there is much currently unknown about equality of opportunity in the US: To what extent does the US offer equality of opportunity today? How does this vary geographically? What pathways do people use to move up the income ladder? And what types of policies can increase the use of these pathways and further increase income mobility?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will seek to answer these questions by conducting a comprehensive analysis of intergenerational income mobility by linking parents to children in a comprehensive dataset comprising the vast majority of US workers and their families.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs will approach these questions in three stages. First, they will provide a descriptive analysis of intergenerational mobility in the United States. This includes calculating rates of mobility by fine geographic areas and studying the factors correlated with mobility, such as attending public higher educational institutions, starting a business, or strong local labor markets. The aim of this descriptive work is to motivate not only the subsequent work, but also to make these statistics accessible to future researchers so that others can study their own hypothesis about drivers of intergenerational mobility. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Second, the PIs will study several potential pathways of mobility in detail with the aim of quantifying the causal impact of these factors on income mobility. These pathways will depend on the first stage of the research, but the researchers suspect, for example, that access to low-cost higher educational institutions may be one important channel for upward mobility. To this aim, they will evaluate whether the cost of higher education is a barrier to mobility for disadvantaged children. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Finally, this project aims to explore which government policies (e.g. education tax credits, business incentives, etc.) are most effective in stimulating upward mobility. The broader goal of this study is to help policymakers design policies that promote equality of opportunity; hence, the PIs intend to contribute to an analysis of economic policy that focuses not only on the current generation, but identifies the impact of policies on the well-being of future generations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1260964</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raj</FirstName>
<LastName>Chetty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raj Chetty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chetty@fas.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6177449492</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000326285</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathaniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Hendren</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathaniel Hendren</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nhendren@fas.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7733448990</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000619299</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Bureau of Economic Research Inc</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385398</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6178683900</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1050 Massachusetts Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>054552435</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL BUREAU OF ECONOMIC RESEARCH, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>054552435</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Bureau of Economic Research Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021385398</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1050 Massachusetts Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~424020</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">The United States is often hailed as the &ldquo;land of opportunity,&rdquo; a society in which a child's chances of success depend little on her background. Is this reputation warranted? To what extent are children&rsquo;s opportunities for upward economic mobility shaped by the neighborhoods in which they grow up?&nbsp; We study these questions using data from de-identified tax records. The study consists of three main parts.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p>First, we show that intergenerational mobility varies substantially across areas within the United States. We use anonymous earnings records on 10 million children born between 1980-1982 to calculate upward mobility for every commuting zone (metro and rural area) in the U.S. &nbsp;We find that upward mobility varies substantially both across and within commuting zones. For example, the probability that a child reaches the top quintile of the national income distribution starting from a family in the bottom quintile is 4.4% in Charlotte but 12.9% in San Jose. We also find substantial variation <em>within</em> commuting zones. For example, within the New York commuting zone, the probability that a child reaches the top quintile of the national income distribution starting from a family in the bottom quintile is 7.3 % in the Bronx but 16.8% in Queens.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Second, we show that the neighborhoods in which children grow up have a causal effect on their earnings, college attendance rates, and fertility and marriage patterns by studying more than seven million families who move across commuting zones and counties in the U.S. Broadly, variation across the U.S. in intergenerational mobility could reflect either the causal effect of places, or the sorting of families to different areas. Exploiting variation in the age of children when families move, we find that neighborhoods have significant <em>childhood exposure effects</em>: the outcomes of children whose families move to a better neighborhood &ndash; as measured by the outcomes of children already living there &ndash; improve linearly in proportion to the amount of time they spend growing up in that area, at a rate of approximately 4% per year of exposure. We distinguish the causal effects of neighborhoods from confounding factors by comparing the outcomes of siblings within families, studying moves triggered by displacement shocks, and conducting over-identification tests.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The finding that neighborhoods affect intergenerational mobility primarily through childhood exposure helps reconcile conflicting results in the prior literature. For example, we return to the Moving to Opportunity experiment that offered families vouchers to move to lower poverty neighborhoods. While earlier literature found minimal effects of on adults and teenagers, we find that children under 12 whose families were randomly given the opportunity to move to a better neighborhood have 30% higher earnings in adulthood, are more likely to attend college, less likely to have a teenage birth, and live in better neighborhoods today.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, in the third piece of our analysis we estimate the causal effect of exposure to each county in the U.S. on children's incomes in adulthood. We then use these estimates to (a) quantify how much places matter for intergenerational mobility, (b) construct forecasts of the causal effect of growing up in each county that can be used to guide families seeking to move to opportunity, and (c) characterize which types of areas produce better outcomes. For children growing up in low-income families, each year of childhood exposure to a one standard deviation better county increases income in adulthood by 0.5%. Hence, growing up in a one standard deviation better county from birth increases a child's income by approximately 10%. There is substantial local area variation in children's outcomes: for example, growing up in the western suburbs of Chicago (DuPage County) would increase a given child's income by approximately 30% relative to growing up in Cook County. Areas with less concentrated poverty, less income inequality, better schools, a larger share of two-parent families, and lower crime rates tend to produce better outcomes for children in poor families. Boys' outcomes vary more across areas than girls' outcomes, and boys have especially negative outcomes in highly segregated areas. One-fifth of the black-white income gap can be explained by differences in the counties in which black and white children grow up. Areas that generate better outcomes have higher house prices on average, but our approach uncovers many &ldquo;opportunity bargains" &ndash; places that generate good outcomes but are not very expensive.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Taken together, our results demonstrate that there exists large variation in economic opportunity within the United States, and our analysis provides a foundation for understanding the pathways and determinants of intergenerational mobility in the US.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Nathaniel&nbsp;Hendren</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The United States is often hailed as the "land of opportunity," a society in which a child's chances of success depend little on her background. Is this reputation warranted? To what extent are children?s opportunities for upward economic mobility shaped by the neighborhoods in which they grow up?  We study these questions using data from de-identified tax records. The study consists of three main parts.    First, we show that intergenerational mobility varies substantially across areas within the United States. We use anonymous earnings records on 10 million children born between 1980-1982 to calculate upward mobility for every commuting zone (metro and rural area) in the U.S.  We find that upward mobility varies substantially both across and within commuting zones. For example, the probability that a child reaches the top quintile of the national income distribution starting from a family in the bottom quintile is 4.4% in Charlotte but 12.9% in San Jose. We also find substantial variation within commuting zones. For example, within the New York commuting zone, the probability that a child reaches the top quintile of the national income distribution starting from a family in the bottom quintile is 7.3 % in the Bronx but 16.8% in Queens.     Second, we show that the neighborhoods in which children grow up have a causal effect on their earnings, college attendance rates, and fertility and marriage patterns by studying more than seven million families who move across commuting zones and counties in the U.S. Broadly, variation across the U.S. in intergenerational mobility could reflect either the causal effect of places, or the sorting of families to different areas. Exploiting variation in the age of children when families move, we find that neighborhoods have significant childhood exposure effects: the outcomes of children whose families move to a better neighborhood &ndash; as measured by the outcomes of children already living there &ndash; improve linearly in proportion to the amount of time they spend growing up in that area, at a rate of approximately 4% per year of exposure. We distinguish the causal effects of neighborhoods from confounding factors by comparing the outcomes of siblings within families, studying moves triggered by displacement shocks, and conducting over-identification tests.     The finding that neighborhoods affect intergenerational mobility primarily through childhood exposure helps reconcile conflicting results in the prior literature. For example, we return to the Moving to Opportunity experiment that offered families vouchers to move to lower poverty neighborhoods. While earlier literature found minimal effects of on adults and teenagers, we find that children under 12 whose families were randomly given the opportunity to move to a better neighborhood have 30% higher earnings in adulthood, are more likely to attend college, less likely to have a teenage birth, and live in better neighborhoods today.     Finally, in the third piece of our analysis we estimate the causal effect of exposure to each county in the U.S. on children's incomes in adulthood. We then use these estimates to (a) quantify how much places matter for intergenerational mobility, (b) construct forecasts of the causal effect of growing up in each county that can be used to guide families seeking to move to opportunity, and (c) characterize which types of areas produce better outcomes. For children growing up in low-income families, each year of childhood exposure to a one standard deviation better county increases income in adulthood by 0.5%. Hence, growing up in a one standard deviation better county from birth increases a child's income by approximately 10%. There is substantial local area variation in children's outcomes: for example, growing up in the western suburbs of Chicago (DuPage County) would increase a given child's income by approximately 30% relative to growing up in Cook County. Areas with less concentrated poverty, less income inequality, better schools, a larger share of two-parent families, and lower crime rates tend to produce better outcomes for children in poor families. Boys' outcomes vary more across areas than girls' outcomes, and boys have especially negative outcomes in highly segregated areas. One-fifth of the black-white income gap can be explained by differences in the counties in which black and white children grow up. Areas that generate better outcomes have higher house prices on average, but our approach uncovers many "opportunity bargains" &ndash; places that generate good outcomes but are not very expensive.     Taken together, our results demonstrate that there exists large variation in economic opportunity within the United States, and our analysis provides a foundation for understanding the pathways and determinants of intergenerational mobility in the US.           Last Modified: 05/29/2017       Submitted by: Nathaniel Hendren]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
