<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SCHOLARS AWARDS:   Climate, Population Density, and Remote Sensing: Identifying Social-Ecological Hotspots</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>54999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>University of North Carolina (UNC) ecological anthropologist Colin Thor West will conduct research on land use and land cover change (LULCC) on ecological hotspots. The research will be focused on the northern Central Plateau of Burkina Faso, a place long recorded by experts as a textbook example of anthropogenic desertification. This region is part of the larger Sahel where population pressure and droughts are causing widespread environmental harm. More recent analyses, however, have documented a reversal in this process. Satellite imagery has detected a process of "greening" in the Sahel and it is particularly pronounced on the northern Central Plateau. Thus, there are conflicting interpretations of human-environment dynamics that generally describe either a widespread and uniform trajectory of environmental degradation (desertification) or a similarly homogeneous trajectory of environmental rehabilitation (greening). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Previous ethnographic fieldwork by the PI suggests that both processes are occurring simultaneously but in different places at different points in time. Using remote sensing techniques, this proposed research will identify social-ecological hotspots where negative (degrading) and positive (rehabilitating) human-environment interactions are occurring. Thus, it will show that land degradation/rehabilitation are ultimately patchy and discontinuous processes that co-occur within the same landscape. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. West will develop basic skills in remote sensing analysis through training at UNC?s Landscape Ecology and Biogeography Lab. Dr. Aaron Moody, an associate professor in UNC's Department of Geography, will mentor him in data acquisition, processing and analysis. The research will produce a spatially and temporally explicit dataset of vegetation, rainfall, and population that identifies social-ecological hotspots, which will enable development organizations and government agencies to better target assistance.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1261800</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colin</FirstName>
<LastName>West</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Colin T West</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ctw@email.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9199663411</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000554810</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/15/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>608195277</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName>Chapel Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[104 Airport Drive Suite 2200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>Cultural Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ASSP-Arctic Social Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~49999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award successfully allowed the PI, a human ecologist, to develop skils in the acquisition, processing, and analysis of remotely sensed satellite imagery. With his mentor Dr. Aaron Moody in the Geography Department of UNC Chapel Hill, the PI assembled a time series of gridded NDVI and Rainfall Estimate (RFE) for Burkina Faso, West Africa. This raster dataset identified "hot spots" within the country where the vegetative biomass productivity exceeds what one would expect based on rainfall alone, which suggests enhanced "greening." It also detected areas where biomass productivity is lower than that predicted by rainfall, which indicates "browning," or land degradation.</p> <p>&nbsp; These maps of greening and browning have been shared with stakeholders in Burkina Faso through preliminary ground-truthing exercises. Some experts strongly agree with the results and suggested that these patterns of greening and browning reflect different land-use practices in distinct parts of the country. Some also explained that the patterns reflect historic processes of internal in- and out-migration. Some local experts from the Department of Kongoussi in northern Burkina Faso, however, felt that the maps were incorrect. Zones of land degradation indicated in the NDVI/RFE data actually correspond to areas that have been gradually rehabilitated through investments in soil and water conservation (SWC) measures since the early 1990s. They emphasized that the contemporary landscape has to be understood in terms of severe Sahelian droughts that occurred during the 1970s and 1980s.</p> <p>&nbsp; This feedback prompted the PI and his mentor to extend the NDVI/RFE time series backward to the 1980s when the latest droughts occurred. Doing so changed the results dramatically. The initial timeseries covered the period 1995 to 2009. The extended series covered the period from 1983 to 2009. Zones within Kongoussi that appeared "brown" in 1995-2009 switched to "green" over the longer period from 1983 to 2009. The difference in the two timeseries suggests that SWC investments have contributed to greening over the long term in response to droughts.</p> <p>&nbsp; A supplemental Research Experience for Graduate Students (REU) award allowed the PI and a PhD student in the Department of Anthropology at UNC Chapel Hill to conduct participatory rapid rural appraisal (PRRA) exercises in Kongoussi and the national capitol, Ougadougou. This fieldwork was designed to ground-truth the preliminary results. This student is a young woman and host-country national of Burkina Faso. Thus the project is contributing to reserarch capacity in ethnography and spatial analysis within a developing country.</p> <p>&nbsp; Overall, the data produced from this project is contributing to a better understanding of social-ecological system (SES) dynamics in Sahelian West Africa. It provides evidence that greening in this part of the Sahel is anthropogenic. Although more fieldwork and analysis of imagery is necessary to confirm this, the PI, his mentor, and a PhD student have compelling results that will guide further investigations. Moreover, collaborators in Burkina Faso are excited by the findings and would like to conduct a series of ground-truthing exercises in different parts of the country where greening and browning are particularly pronounced.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/02/2016<br>      Modified by: Colin&nbsp;T&nbsp;West</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs"...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award successfully allowed the PI, a human ecologist, to develop skils in the acquisition, processing, and analysis of remotely sensed satellite imagery. With his mentor Dr. Aaron Moody in the Geography Department of UNC Chapel Hill, the PI assembled a time series of gridded NDVI and Rainfall Estimate (RFE) for Burkina Faso, West Africa. This raster dataset identified "hot spots" within the country where the vegetative biomass productivity exceeds what one would expect based on rainfall alone, which suggests enhanced "greening." It also detected areas where biomass productivity is lower than that predicted by rainfall, which indicates "browning," or land degradation.    These maps of greening and browning have been shared with stakeholders in Burkina Faso through preliminary ground-truthing exercises. Some experts strongly agree with the results and suggested that these patterns of greening and browning reflect different land-use practices in distinct parts of the country. Some also explained that the patterns reflect historic processes of internal in- and out-migration. Some local experts from the Department of Kongoussi in northern Burkina Faso, however, felt that the maps were incorrect. Zones of land degradation indicated in the NDVI/RFE data actually correspond to areas that have been gradually rehabilitated through investments in soil and water conservation (SWC) measures since the early 1990s. They emphasized that the contemporary landscape has to be understood in terms of severe Sahelian droughts that occurred during the 1970s and 1980s.    This feedback prompted the PI and his mentor to extend the NDVI/RFE time series backward to the 1980s when the latest droughts occurred. Doing so changed the results dramatically. The initial timeseries covered the period 1995 to 2009. The extended series covered the period from 1983 to 2009. Zones within Kongoussi that appeared "brown" in 1995-2009 switched to "green" over the longer period from 1983 to 2009. The difference in the two timeseries suggests that SWC investments have contributed to greening over the long term in response to droughts.    A supplemental Research Experience for Graduate Students (REU) award allowed the PI and a PhD student in the Department of Anthropology at UNC Chapel Hill to conduct participatory rapid rural appraisal (PRRA) exercises in Kongoussi and the national capitol, Ougadougou. This fieldwork was designed to ground-truth the preliminary results. This student is a young woman and host-country national of Burkina Faso. Thus the project is contributing to reserarch capacity in ethnography and spatial analysis within a developing country.    Overall, the data produced from this project is contributing to a better understanding of social-ecological system (SES) dynamics in Sahelian West Africa. It provides evidence that greening in this part of the Sahel is anthropogenic. Although more fieldwork and analysis of imagery is necessary to confirm this, the PI, his mentor, and a PhD student have compelling results that will guide further investigations. Moreover, collaborators in Burkina Faso are excited by the findings and would like to conduct a series of ground-truthing exercises in different parts of the country where greening and browning are particularly pronounced.       Last Modified: 02/02/2016       Submitted by: Colin T West]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
