<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MEETING:   IUPS 2013 Travel Progam, Birmingham, UK, July 21-26, 2013</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Inna Sokolova</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The International Union of Physiological Sciences (IUPS) will hold the XXXVII International Congress of Physiological Sciences in Birmingham, UK, July 21-26, 2013. The American Physiological Society (APS) will administer a travel grant program offering a limited number of travel awards to qualified scientists interested in attending the IUPS Congress. The APS has conducted a travel grant program and assisted U.S. scientists engaged in physiological research and its applications to attend Congresses every four years since the IUPS Congress was held in Buenos Aires in 1959. Most recently, the APS managed a travel award program for US physiologists for the IUPS Congress in 2009 in Kyoto, Japan. Special emphasis will be given to investigators within 15 years of receiving their doctoral degree and to women and under-represented minority scientists. Travel awards resulting from this proposal will be directed to individuals working in the research areas supported by the Division of Integrative Organismal Systems. Travel awards will 1) promote widespread participation of young scientists with an emphasis on women and under-represented minorities; 2) interest new investigators and students in pursuing research designed to understand physiological processes and traits; and 3) provide opportunities for the development of collaborative interactions with scientists from the United States and those working in other countries. The scientific program for the XXXVII Congress was developed by an international program committee with representatives both from the host society, The Physiological Society, and the IUPS. The program is organized around a number of IUPS Commissions. Traditionally, the one most relevant to NSF is associated with the Commission for Comparative Physiology: Evolution, Adaptation &amp; Environment. While the sessions associated with this Commission are most relevant, there are many others that should be of interest to comparative physiologists, providing physiological insights related to their comparative studies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1261451</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Frank</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin Frank</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mfrank@the-aps.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3016347118</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000297670</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/23/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Physiological Society</Name>
<CityName>Rockville</CityName>
<ZipCode>208524911</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3016347168</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6120 Executive Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 600]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064856685</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN PHYSIOLOGICAL SOCIETY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Physiological Society]]></Name>
<CityName>Rockville</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>208524911</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6120 Executive Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7657</Code>
<Text>Integrtv Ecological Physiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>APS Provides 80 Travel Awards to the XXXVII IUPS<br />Congress </strong></p> <p>The American Physiological Society (APS), administered a travel award program for attendees to the XXXVII International Congress of Physiological Sciences, Birmingham, UK, July 21 to 26, 2013. The APS International Physiology Committee, served as the screening and selection committee, responsible for identifying recipients of the travel awards. As fiscal agent, the APS received funds for the program from government agencies and from an income account derived from individual contributions and profits associated with the 1968 IUPS Congress in Washington D.C. &nbsp;Government funds were provided by the National Science Foundation (IOS-1261451) and the following NIH institutes &ndash; National Institute of Diabetes, Digestive and Kidney Disease and the National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (R13 DK098941-01).</p> <p>The XXXVII Congress was attended by 3061 scientists representing 88 counties. The US delegation was comprised of 258 scientists.&nbsp; The APS<br />received applications for the travel award program from 155 scientists and<br />students.&nbsp; The Society selected 80 applicants for inclusion in the program (51.6%). Fifty-seven applications (42.2%) were received from female scientists and forty-one received awards (71.9%). Of the 53 applications received from APS members in the US, 33 applications were awarded. Of these applications, only two were from scientists who identified themselves as being from an underrepresented minority groups and one of those applications was awarded with a travel grant. The remaining 47 award recipients went to APS members residing outside of the US with the largest contingents being from Brazil (12 awards) and from Nigeria (11 awards).&nbsp; Seventy percent of the applicants identified themselves as early-career scientists (either a student or within 15 years of their terminal doctoral degree).&nbsp; The median year for receipt of the doctorate for awardees was 2009.</p> <p>The awardees were provided with an award ranging from $500 - $1000 to partially defray the cost of travel to the Congress.&nbsp; Many of the awardees<br />not only attended the Congress but also visited research laboratories in the UK. The awardees were asked to rank the Congress on a scale from 1 to 10 with 10 being the best. More than 85% (68 out of 35) gave the Congress a ranking of 7 or higher. Overall, the attendees were supportive of the Congress and its scientific aspects.&nbsp;</p> <p>The awardees completed a survey and were asked to respond to the following questions:</p> <p>Did you combine your attendance at the IUPS Congress with attendance at a<br />satellite meeting? &nbsp; <strong>40.6% of the awardees responded yes! </strong></p> <p>Did you combine your attendance at the IUPS Congress with a visit to a<br />research laboratory? &nbsp; <strong>46.4% of the awardees responded yes! </strong></p> <p>Did the Congress provide you with an opportunity to develop collaborative<br />research projects with colleagues?  &nbsp;<strong> 92.9% of the awardees responded yes!</strong></p> <p>Did the Congress provide you with an opportunity to identify<br />opportunities to work in another laboratory? <strong> 65.2% of the awardees responded yes!</strong></p> <p>Did the Congress provide you with an opportunity to recruit candidates to<br />work in your laboratory? <strong>31.8% of the awardees responded yes!</strong></p> <p>When asked what the most positive aspect of their participation in the Congress was, this is what some of the awardees had to say:</p> <p>&ldquo;I had a chance to really get a sense of what kind of work is going on internationally in my field.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Perhaps more importantly, I met and formed<br />relationships with professionals at institutions that I would like to join<br />following my postdoc.&rdquo;</p> <p>&l...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ APS Provides 80 Travel Awards to the XXXVII IUPS Congress   The American Physiological Society (APS), administered a travel award program for attendees to the XXXVII International Congress of Physiological Sciences, Birmingham, UK, July 21 to 26, 2013. The APS International Physiology Committee, served as the screening and selection committee, responsible for identifying recipients of the travel awards. As fiscal agent, the APS received funds for the program from government agencies and from an income account derived from individual contributions and profits associated with the 1968 IUPS Congress in Washington D.C.  Government funds were provided by the National Science Foundation (IOS-1261451) and the following NIH institutes &ndash; National Institute of Diabetes, Digestive and Kidney Disease and the National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (R13 DK098941-01).  The XXXVII Congress was attended by 3061 scientists representing 88 counties. The US delegation was comprised of 258 scientists.  The APS received applications for the travel award program from 155 scientists and students.  The Society selected 80 applicants for inclusion in the program (51.6%). Fifty-seven applications (42.2%) were received from female scientists and forty-one received awards (71.9%). Of the 53 applications received from APS members in the US, 33 applications were awarded. Of these applications, only two were from scientists who identified themselves as being from an underrepresented minority groups and one of those applications was awarded with a travel grant. The remaining 47 award recipients went to APS members residing outside of the US with the largest contingents being from Brazil (12 awards) and from Nigeria (11 awards).  Seventy percent of the applicants identified themselves as early-career scientists (either a student or within 15 years of their terminal doctoral degree).  The median year for receipt of the doctorate for awardees was 2009.  The awardees were provided with an award ranging from $500 - $1000 to partially defray the cost of travel to the Congress.  Many of the awardees not only attended the Congress but also visited research laboratories in the UK. The awardees were asked to rank the Congress on a scale from 1 to 10 with 10 being the best. More than 85% (68 out of 35) gave the Congress a ranking of 7 or higher. Overall, the attendees were supportive of the Congress and its scientific aspects.   The awardees completed a survey and were asked to respond to the following questions:  Did you combine your attendance at the IUPS Congress with attendance at a satellite meeting?   40.6% of the awardees responded yes!   Did you combine your attendance at the IUPS Congress with a visit to a research laboratory?   46.4% of the awardees responded yes!   Did the Congress provide you with an opportunity to develop collaborative research projects with colleagues?    92.9% of the awardees responded yes!  Did the Congress provide you with an opportunity to identify opportunities to work in another laboratory?  65.2% of the awardees responded yes!  Did the Congress provide you with an opportunity to recruit candidates to work in your laboratory? 31.8% of the awardees responded yes!  When asked what the most positive aspect of their participation in the Congress was, this is what some of the awardees had to say:  "I had a chance to really get a sense of what kind of work is going on internationally in my field.    Perhaps more importantly, I met and formed relationships with professionals at institutions that I would like to join following my postdoc."  "The big opportunity to develop collaborative research projects with colleagues as well as taking knowledge of many research lines from laboratories all around the world."  "For me the best aspect was the coming together of human, clinically-oriented researchers with those studying fundamental aspects of physiology in non-traditional animal models."  "The presentation...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
