<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Political Economy of Branding a New Site for a Specialty Industry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299632.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>368602</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Kevin Yelvington of the University of South Florida proposes to explore how different producers and other stakeholders in otherwise competitive emerging markets cooperate in "branding" their products. The research is set in the Temecula Valley of Southern California, which is an ideal area to explore these issues as it is being challenged with plans for land use that have potentially large impacts in terms of the economy, ecology, and social development of region. The project seeks to understand landscape transformation and the uses of natural resources, especially water, in this process, as well as the multiple labor processes upon which niche agricultural markets are built. This project employs a number of qualitative methods including participant observation fieldwork, key informant interviews, focus groups, the collection of oral histories, surveys, and archival data research. The research for this 3-year project will be conducted by the Principal Investigator and a team of advanced graduate students in applied anthropology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Building on economic anthropological explorations into the conditions under which cooperation occurs among market competitors, this project's research design explores how many different stakeholders combine into a single system using the concept of terroir, a term that is used to explain how the land imparts a particular quality to a product. The researcher extends this concept to include other aspects of the land, including the effects on the environment, the interests of the residents and government, and the primary consumers of the products from this region. The methods have the potential to fundamentally transform anthropological and other social scientific approaches to the study of work, by creating a model that could be applied to other landscapes with complex social systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project includes a student training component that will also contribute development of competitive science and technological education. The broader impacts of the proposed research also include providing information on environmental sustainability, tourism, conditions of agricultural employment, and the impacts of food chain processes. These contributions will be achieved by an extensive publication program in academic and popular venues, as well as presentations aimed at professional and popular audiences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1261812</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Yelvington</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin A Yelvington</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yelvingt@usf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8139740582</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000265575</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Florida</Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<ZipCode>336172008</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4019 E. Fowler Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 100]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069687242</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069687242</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temecula Valley, southern California]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925915056</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>42</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA42</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>Cultural Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5209</Code>
<Text>ENVIR SOCIAL &amp; BEHAVIOR SCIENC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~92256</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~80598</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~195748</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Wine, for many centuries of central symbolic and religious importance in human history, has become a commodity of great economic consequence in the globalized world. In 2010, the United States became the world&rsquo;s largest wine market. By far the largest producer was the State of California, where 85 percent of all US wine was produced. In 2016, California wine shipments to the United States reached an estimated retail value of $34.1 billion, up 4.6 percent from the previous year, and by 2015 the California wine industry had an economic impact of $114 on the country. Wine tourism came to prominence as consumers, encouraged as part of the &ldquo;foodie&rdquo; and &ldquo;farm-to-table&rdquo; movements, sought to experience wine where it was produced and this came to have a significant economic impact in itself. According to the Wine Institute, 23.6 million tourists visited California wine regions in 2015 and the wine industry generated $7.2 billion in tourist expenditures in the state. And yet, the California wine industry was at the same time facing challenges in the form of labor politics, environmental concerns, especially the availability of water in the context of California&rsquo;s historic drought, and regulatory changes.</p> <p>This National Science Foundation (NSF)-funded research project was conceived by Principal Investigator (PI) Kevin A. Yelvington, an anthropologist, as an historical and ethnographic investigation of wine production, consumption, and wine tourism in the Temecula Valley, a popular wine growing region and tourist destination in southern California. Located roughly between San Diego and Los Angeles, by 2017 around 23 million people lived in the area. The project aimed to investigate the ways in which winery owners, winemakers, marketing specialists, and consumers co-constructed a &ldquo;Temecula Valley <em>terroir</em>,&rdquo; a sense of distinction and aesthetic valor, a &ldquo;taste of place.&rdquo; It sought to raise questions as to the sustainability of the wine tourism industry in the Temecula Valley by understanding the historical political economy of landscape transformation and the development of vineyards and wineries along with the uses of natural resources, especially water, in this process. It examined the multiple labor processes upon which the production of wine was built. It asked how wine was commodified and consumed. It sought to account for the state&rsquo;s role in development and regulation. And it investigated how wine consumption occurred in the context of the &ldquo;branding&rdquo; of the Temecula Valley as a wine tourism destination &mdash; a geographical space that becomes a cultural &ldquo;place.&rdquo;</p> <p>The NSF merit criteria addressed with this project were Intellectual Merit, encompassing the potential to advance knowledge, and Broader Impacts, entailing the potential to benefit society and contribute to the achievement of specific, desired societal outcomes. The project was designed to address these criteria by posing the following main research questions:</p> <p>1. What is the political economy of landscape transformation &mdash; the historical and contemporary political economy of environment &mdash; in the development of vineyards and wineries?</p> <p>2. What are the multiple labor processes upon which the Temecula Valley wine industry is built?</p> <p>3. What are the linkages between wine production and consumption?</p> <p>4. What is the role of the state and non-governmental official organizations in regulating and promoting wine production and consumption in the Temecula Valley?</p> <p>5. How is wine consumed and wine tourism experienced by wine tourists?</p> <p>The major goals of this project were to contribute to theoretical development in the area of political economy &mdash; more specifically on human interaction with the environment, labor, the commodification process, public policy and the society-state interface, the workings of neoliberalism, and the economics of tourism and leisure &mdash; and to provide ethnographic, ethnohistorical, and historical documentation of social structures, behaviors, and ideas related to wine tourism in order to contribute to debates on environmental sustainability.</p> <p>The project, conducted from 2013-2017 (although the PI had begun preliminary research on the project in 2010 with intermitent fieldwork over three years), employed, in addition to the PI, five Graduate Student Research Assistants, three postdoctoral Non-Student Research Assistants, and a Consultant. An intended byproduct of this research design was to train and mentor graduate students and young early-career professionals. The ethnic and gender diversity of the research team was also an intended outcome. Over the project period these researchers engaged in sustained interdisciplinary research, conducting ethnographic, oral history, and archival research, producing thousands of pages of field notes from participant-observation ethnographic fieldwork, scores of audio recordings and transcripts of key informant interviews, audio recordings and transcripts from dozens of oral history interview subjects, survey results, thousands of photographs and video recordings, and thousands of pages of primary archival materials from relevant repositories. Products were to include multiple Ph.D. dissertations and M.A. theses in anthropology, an ambitious program of single-authored and joint-authored scientific publications, as well as technical reports to be shared with local stakeholders in the local wine tourism industry.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;A&nbsp;Yelvington</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Wine, for many centuries of central symbolic and religious importance in human history, has become a commodity of great economic consequence in the globalized world. In 2010, the United States became the world?s largest wine market. By far the largest producer was the State of California, where 85 percent of all US wine was produced. In 2016, California wine shipments to the United States reached an estimated retail value of $34.1 billion, up 4.6 percent from the previous year, and by 2015 the California wine industry had an economic impact of $114 on the country. Wine tourism came to prominence as consumers, encouraged as part of the "foodie" and "farm-to-table" movements, sought to experience wine where it was produced and this came to have a significant economic impact in itself. According to the Wine Institute, 23.6 million tourists visited California wine regions in 2015 and the wine industry generated $7.2 billion in tourist expenditures in the state. And yet, the California wine industry was at the same time facing challenges in the form of labor politics, environmental concerns, especially the availability of water in the context of California?s historic drought, and regulatory changes.  This National Science Foundation (NSF)-funded research project was conceived by Principal Investigator (PI) Kevin A. Yelvington, an anthropologist, as an historical and ethnographic investigation of wine production, consumption, and wine tourism in the Temecula Valley, a popular wine growing region and tourist destination in southern California. Located roughly between San Diego and Los Angeles, by 2017 around 23 million people lived in the area. The project aimed to investigate the ways in which winery owners, winemakers, marketing specialists, and consumers co-constructed a "Temecula Valley terroir," a sense of distinction and aesthetic valor, a "taste of place." It sought to raise questions as to the sustainability of the wine tourism industry in the Temecula Valley by understanding the historical political economy of landscape transformation and the development of vineyards and wineries along with the uses of natural resources, especially water, in this process. It examined the multiple labor processes upon which the production of wine was built. It asked how wine was commodified and consumed. It sought to account for the state?s role in development and regulation. And it investigated how wine consumption occurred in the context of the "branding" of the Temecula Valley as a wine tourism destination &mdash; a geographical space that becomes a cultural "place."  The NSF merit criteria addressed with this project were Intellectual Merit, encompassing the potential to advance knowledge, and Broader Impacts, entailing the potential to benefit society and contribute to the achievement of specific, desired societal outcomes. The project was designed to address these criteria by posing the following main research questions:  1. What is the political economy of landscape transformation &mdash; the historical and contemporary political economy of environment &mdash; in the development of vineyards and wineries?  2. What are the multiple labor processes upon which the Temecula Valley wine industry is built?  3. What are the linkages between wine production and consumption?  4. What is the role of the state and non-governmental official organizations in regulating and promoting wine production and consumption in the Temecula Valley?  5. How is wine consumed and wine tourism experienced by wine tourists?  The major goals of this project were to contribute to theoretical development in the area of political economy &mdash; more specifically on human interaction with the environment, labor, the commodification process, public policy and the society-state interface, the workings of neoliberalism, and the economics of tourism and leisure &mdash; and to provide ethnographic, ethnohistorical, and historical documentation of social structures, behaviors, and ideas related to wine tourism in order to contribute to debates on environmental sustainability.  The project, conducted from 2013-2017 (although the PI had begun preliminary research on the project in 2010 with intermitent fieldwork over three years), employed, in addition to the PI, five Graduate Student Research Assistants, three postdoctoral Non-Student Research Assistants, and a Consultant. An intended byproduct of this research design was to train and mentor graduate students and young early-career professionals. The ethnic and gender diversity of the research team was also an intended outcome. Over the project period these researchers engaged in sustained interdisciplinary research, conducting ethnographic, oral history, and archival research, producing thousands of pages of field notes from participant-observation ethnographic fieldwork, scores of audio recordings and transcripts of key informant interviews, audio recordings and transcripts from dozens of oral history interview subjects, survey results, thousands of photographs and video recordings, and thousands of pages of primary archival materials from relevant repositories. Products were to include multiple Ph.D. dissertations and M.A. theses in anthropology, an ambitious program of single-authored and joint-authored scientific publications, as well as technical reports to be shared with local stakeholders in the local wine tourism industry.        Last Modified: 07/30/2017       Submitted by: Kevin A Yelvington]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
