<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Synthesis of Complex Molecules from Simple Aromatic Precursors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>418000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>418000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Synthesis Program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Vanderwal of the Department of Chemistry at UC Irvine will continue to develop Zincke aldehydes - the products of the ring-opening aminolysis of pyridinium salts - as useful reagents for complex molecule synthesis. For example, Zincke aldehydes will be used as readily functionalizable surrogates to pyridines, enabling the controlled preparation of polysubstituted pyridines. Previously developed methods to access complex polycyclic amines from cascade pericyclic reactions of Zincke aldehydes will be applied to the synthesis of the alkaloids gelsemine and alsmaphorazines A and B. Finally, in a new venture, the Himbert arene/allene cycloaddition reaction will be exploited for the generation of complex architectures.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;This work generally aims to improve the efficiency of assembly of complex, value-added compounds from readily available starting materials. The results of these studies will positively impact any area of applied science that benefits from chemical synthesis, including pharmaceutical development, materials science, and more. This project will provide a research training ground for undergraduate and graduate students. The grant provided in support of this project will also support the UCI-LEAPS (Laboratory Experiments &amp; Activities in the Physical Sciences) program that brings in local middle school students for day-long experiences in university chemistry and physics laboratories.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1262040</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Vanderwal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher D Vanderwal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cdv@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498246702</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486656</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926972025</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[FRH 5004]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6878</Code>
<Text>Chemical Synthesis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~288000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF-funded research program seeks to develop new methods and strategies for the conversion of simple, inexpensive aromatic chemical feedstocks into complex molecular architectures, including natural products and drug-like molecules.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As an extension of our previous work in which we made the notorious toxin strychnine (<strong>3</strong>, Figure 1) starting from the commodity chemical pyridine, we made the simpler natural product akuammicine (<strong>4</strong>) in sufficient quantities to test a hypothesis about how the much more complex natural alkaloid, alsmaphorazine B (<strong>5</strong>) is made in the plant from which it derived. As a culmination of this research project, we were able to make multigram quantities of akuammicine using a reaction that we had previously developed for our strychnine synthesis&mdash;the formal cycloaddition of Zincke aldehydes. We then developed a chemical synthesis route that converts it to alsmaphorazine B via a pathway that generates other known, naturally occurring alkaloids. In this way, while we do not with certainty pin down the biosynthesis of the alsmaphorazine alkaloids, we provided a new hypothesis for their biogenesis and generated strong circumstantial support for this idea.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Using a different reaction of Zincke aldehydes that we had uncovered&mdash;the thermal rearrangement and intramolecular Diels&ndash;Alder cycloaddition of alkene-bearing Zincke aldehydes to generate bicyclic lactams (Figure 2)&mdash;we endeavored to synthesize the complex, naturally occurring alkaloid gelsemine (<strong>8</strong>). In this work, the key reaction worked beautifully to generate intermediate <strong>7</strong> from Zincke aldehyde <strong>6</strong>; the product of this reaction bears many of the elements of gelsemine, and chemical &ldquo;handles&rdquo; that should permit the introduction of the remaining architectural elements of the target molecule. Unfortunately, we struggled with the seemingly straightforward creation of the C5&ndash;C16 bond, and were therefore unable to complete this synthesis. Nonetheless, the key chemical transformation worked beautifully, thereby showcasing its potential utility in complex molecular settings.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In the third area of research, we studied the potential utility of the Diels&ndash;Alder cycloaddition of readily available benzene rings, which occurs under special circumstances as first reported by Himbert (Figure 3). These &ldquo;Himbert cycloadditions&rdquo; provide complex three-dimensional architectures reminiscent of alkaloid natural products and with potential utility for drug discovery. Moreover, the scaffold thus produced is strained, and thus poised to react in numerous ways, leading to rearrangements that produce other novel, valuable chemical architectures. In collaboration with the Houk group at UCLA, whose expertise lies in the computational evaluation of reaction mechanisms, Together, we studied the cycloaddition reaction and established thermodynamic and kinetic parameters that permit prediction of the feasibility of these unusual reactions. Using that knowledge, we extended the reactivity to related compounds to expand the scope of Himbert cycloadditions. Moreover, we looked at two methods for catalytic rearrangements of the cycloadducts: first by ring-rearrangement alkene metathesis, and second via a formal dyotropic rearrangement. In total, we expanded the scope and utility of the previously poorly appreciated Himbert cycloaddition reaction.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;D&nbsp;Vanderwal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1262040/1262040_10242940_1511989307577_Fig3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1262040/1262040_10242940_1511989307577_Fig3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1262040/1262040_10242940_1511989307577_Fig3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Himbert cycloadducts</div> <div class="imageCredit">C. D. Vanderwal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;D&nbsp;Vanderwal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1262040/1262040_10242940_1511989224063_Fig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1262040/1262040_10242940_1511989224063_Fig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1262040/1262040_10242940_1511989224063_Fig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Total synthesis of almaphorazine B patterned on a new proposal for itsbiogenesis from akuammicine</div> <div class="imageCredit">C. D. Vanderwal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;D&nbsp;Vanderwal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1262040/1262040_10242940_1511989268042_Fig2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1262040/1262040_10242940_1511989268042_Fig2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1262040/1262040_10242940_1511989268042_Fig2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A proposal and progress toward the synthesisof gelsemine via a Zincke aldehyde rearrangement</div> <div class="imageCredit">C. D. Vanderwal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;D&nbsp;Vanderwal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF-funded research program seeks to develop new methods and strategies for the conversion of simple, inexpensive aromatic chemical feedstocks into complex molecular architectures, including natural products and drug-like molecules.     As an extension of our previous work in which we made the notorious toxin strychnine (3, Figure 1) starting from the commodity chemical pyridine, we made the simpler natural product akuammicine (4) in sufficient quantities to test a hypothesis about how the much more complex natural alkaloid, alsmaphorazine B (5) is made in the plant from which it derived. As a culmination of this research project, we were able to make multigram quantities of akuammicine using a reaction that we had previously developed for our strychnine synthesis&mdash;the formal cycloaddition of Zincke aldehydes. We then developed a chemical synthesis route that converts it to alsmaphorazine B via a pathway that generates other known, naturally occurring alkaloids. In this way, while we do not with certainty pin down the biosynthesis of the alsmaphorazine alkaloids, we provided a new hypothesis for their biogenesis and generated strong circumstantial support for this idea.     Using a different reaction of Zincke aldehydes that we had uncovered&mdash;the thermal rearrangement and intramolecular Diels&ndash;Alder cycloaddition of alkene-bearing Zincke aldehydes to generate bicyclic lactams (Figure 2)&mdash;we endeavored to synthesize the complex, naturally occurring alkaloid gelsemine (8). In this work, the key reaction worked beautifully to generate intermediate 7 from Zincke aldehyde 6; the product of this reaction bears many of the elements of gelsemine, and chemical "handles" that should permit the introduction of the remaining architectural elements of the target molecule. Unfortunately, we struggled with the seemingly straightforward creation of the C5&ndash;C16 bond, and were therefore unable to complete this synthesis. Nonetheless, the key chemical transformation worked beautifully, thereby showcasing its potential utility in complex molecular settings.     In the third area of research, we studied the potential utility of the Diels&ndash;Alder cycloaddition of readily available benzene rings, which occurs under special circumstances as first reported by Himbert (Figure 3). These "Himbert cycloadditions" provide complex three-dimensional architectures reminiscent of alkaloid natural products and with potential utility for drug discovery. Moreover, the scaffold thus produced is strained, and thus poised to react in numerous ways, leading to rearrangements that produce other novel, valuable chemical architectures. In collaboration with the Houk group at UCLA, whose expertise lies in the computational evaluation of reaction mechanisms, Together, we studied the cycloaddition reaction and established thermodynamic and kinetic parameters that permit prediction of the feasibility of these unusual reactions. Using that knowledge, we extended the reactivity to related compounds to expand the scope of Himbert cycloadditions. Moreover, we looked at two methods for catalytic rearrangements of the cycloadducts: first by ring-rearrangement alkene metathesis, and second via a formal dyotropic rearrangement. In total, we expanded the scope and utility of the previously poorly appreciated Himbert cycloaddition reaction.       Last Modified: 11/29/2017       Submitted by: Christopher D Vanderwal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
