<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FRG: Collaborative Research: Analysis of the Einstein Constraint Equations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>251491.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>251491</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS 1265187, 1262982, 1263431, 1263544&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI:  Rafe R Mazzeo, Stanford University &lt;br/&gt;PI:  Michael Holst, University of California - San Diego &lt;br/&gt;PI:  Jim Isenberg, University of Oregon &lt;br/&gt;PI:  David Maxell, University of Alaska&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to understand the extent to which one can parametrize and construct initial data sets for the Einstein  evolution equations. We plan to capitalize on the recent progress using the conformal method to obtain new existence results in the  nonconstant mean curvature (non-CMC) setting, to understand the limits of these methods, and then to develop alternate techniques toward these same goals, including degree theory, a priori estiimates, and gluing methods. The Lichnerowicz equation, central  to the conformal method, is a semilinear elliptic equation. Due to  the mixed sign of its nonlinear exponents, it is of a type not yet fully understood. The full Lichnerowicz-Choquet-Bruhat-York set of equations is a more difficult coupled system which incorporates  features presenting new analytic subtleties. The ultimate aim is to  provide a complete parametrization of initial data sets, particularly  in the non-CMC setting, not only on compact backgrounds but also  for manifolds with asymptotically Euclidean, hyperbolic or cylindrical ends, all of which are highly relevant for physical applications.  In exploring new methods, we plan to use new and advanced analytical tools, as well as increasingly accurate and flexible numerical simulation techniques. Technical advances made in the course of  this project should have a substantial application to many other  equations of this general type which play important roles in other  parts of pure and applied mathematics and mathematical physics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Einstein's gravitational field theory is a remarkably accurate mathematical model of gravitational physics, which does an excellent job  of predicting and modeling gravitational phenomena at both the  astrophysical and cosmological scales. It is consistent with every  known gravitational observation and experiment. From the point of  view of underlying mathematics, Einstein's theory involves two very  distinct types of equations. The study of dynamics of gravitational  fields involves the analysis of the Einstein equations as a nonlinear  system of time-dependent evolution partial differential equations  (PDE), while the study of initial data sets representing gravitational states involves Riemannian geometry and the study of the Einstein  constraint equations as a nonlinear system of time-independent  PDE.The last decade has witnessed remarkable progress in under- standing both equations. This project focuses on developing a  more complete understanding of the constraint equations. The study of the Einstein equations presents a very important point of contact  between mathematics and physics, one which has motivated many  advances in differential geometry and PDE on the one side, and  which also has provided a compelling and accurate model of the  physical world, both on the astrophysical and on the cosmological  scales. This project has the potential for settling significant open  questions in this area.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1262982</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Holst</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael J Holst</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mholst@math.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585344899</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000418981</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930112</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1616</Code>
<Text>FOCUSED RESEARCH GROUPS IN MATH SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~251491</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1"><span class="s1">The primary aim of this FRG project was to use the rather disparate sets of expertise of the investigators to continue the analytic study of the Einstein constraint equations.<span>&nbsp; </span>To date the most useful approach to the parametrization and construction of<span>&nbsp; </span>solutions to the Einstein constraint equations has been a technique known as the conformal method; it is responsible for a large fraction of our understanding of the constraint equations on compact manifolds, on asymptotically Euclidean manifolds, on asymptotically hyperbolic manifolds, and on manifolds with asymptotically cylindrical or periodic ends.<span>&nbsp; </span>It has been used to construct solutions which are smooth as well as solutions with low regularity.<span>&nbsp; </span>Its pervasive applications include the construction of initial data for black holes, for binary black holes and binary stars, for gravitational radiation, and for cosmological spacetimes.<span>&nbsp; </span>It is the primary tool used in the numerical simulation of gravitational radiation generation, and it plays an important role in the simulations that support the LIGO Project.<span>&nbsp; </span>Despite its many successes, the conformal method was only fully understood mathematically in the restricted case involving the construction of initial data with constant mean curvature (CMC); i.e., data for which mean extrinsic curvature is constant.<span>&nbsp; </span>The applicability of the conformal method for the construction of far-from-CMC initial data sets was largely unexplored. <span>&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">After essentially no progress on the far-from-CMC case since the conformal method was completely formulated in the early 1970's, a major breakthrough was the appearance of the 2008 article by Project PI Holst, and collaborators G. Nagy, and G. Tsogtgerel, which demonstrated that for a Yamabe-positive metric admitting no conformal Killing fields, and for any desired mean curvature function, then under some smallness restrictions on problem data, there exists at least one solution of the conformal method equations.<span>&nbsp; </span>This result was extended shortly afterward to handle vacuum initial data by (FRG collaborator) D. Maxwell.<span>&nbsp; </span>The central aim of this FRG project was to join forces with D. Maxwell (Alaska), R. Mazzeo (Stanford), and J. Isenberg (Oregon) to build on this new momentum and substantially advance the theory of the conformal method for far-from-CMC initial data.</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">The project achieved several of the goals of the investigators, and helped inject new ideas and energy into this area of mathematical relativity at just the right time, following the appearance of the first non-CMC results in 2008 and 2009.<span>&nbsp; </span>The intellectual merit of the original project idea is now clear, with investigators helping answer several long-standing open problems in mathematical relativity.<span>&nbsp; </span>However, while significant progress was made on developing a more complete solution theory for the conformal method, perhaps the most impactful of the discoveries made by the investigators and their collaborators during the project is that the conformal equations have a much richer mathematical structure than anyone anticipated.<span>&nbsp; </span>As a result, rather than finding a complete solution theory for the conformal equations, the work of the investigators has helped the research community understand that an alternative to the conformal method should be developed, particularly for use in numerical relativity.</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">The study of the Einstein equations presents a very important point of contact between mathematics and physics, and the project had broader impacts that reach well-beyond the new understanding of the conformal method.<span>&nbsp; </span>The techniques which emerged for analyzing these equations on confined regions such as compact manifolds with boundary, will have significant further impact on numerical simulation in general relativity.<span>&nbsp; </span>It is also expected that the technical advances made in the course of this project will have substantial application to other equations of this type, which play important roles in other parts of pure and applied mathematics, and in mathematical physics.<span>&nbsp; </span>The Einstein equations have motivated many advances in differential geometry and partial differential equations, and as evidenced by the LIGO project, they continue to provide a compelling and accurate model of the physical world both on astrophysical and cosmological scales.<span>&nbsp; </span>This project helped settle significant open questions in this area, and has helped crystallize several new important questions.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;J&nbsp;Holst</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The primary aim of this FRG project was to use the rather disparate sets of expertise of the investigators to continue the analytic study of the Einstein constraint equations.  To date the most useful approach to the parametrization and construction of  solutions to the Einstein constraint equations has been a technique known as the conformal method; it is responsible for a large fraction of our understanding of the constraint equations on compact manifolds, on asymptotically Euclidean manifolds, on asymptotically hyperbolic manifolds, and on manifolds with asymptotically cylindrical or periodic ends.  It has been used to construct solutions which are smooth as well as solutions with low regularity.  Its pervasive applications include the construction of initial data for black holes, for binary black holes and binary stars, for gravitational radiation, and for cosmological spacetimes.  It is the primary tool used in the numerical simulation of gravitational radiation generation, and it plays an important role in the simulations that support the LIGO Project.  Despite its many successes, the conformal method was only fully understood mathematically in the restricted case involving the construction of initial data with constant mean curvature (CMC); i.e., data for which mean extrinsic curvature is constant.  The applicability of the conformal method for the construction of far-from-CMC initial data sets was largely unexplored.   After essentially no progress on the far-from-CMC case since the conformal method was completely formulated in the early 1970's, a major breakthrough was the appearance of the 2008 article by Project PI Holst, and collaborators G. Nagy, and G. Tsogtgerel, which demonstrated that for a Yamabe-positive metric admitting no conformal Killing fields, and for any desired mean curvature function, then under some smallness restrictions on problem data, there exists at least one solution of the conformal method equations.  This result was extended shortly afterward to handle vacuum initial data by (FRG collaborator) D. Maxwell.  The central aim of this FRG project was to join forces with D. Maxwell (Alaska), R. Mazzeo (Stanford), and J. Isenberg (Oregon) to build on this new momentum and substantially advance the theory of the conformal method for far-from-CMC initial data. The project achieved several of the goals of the investigators, and helped inject new ideas and energy into this area of mathematical relativity at just the right time, following the appearance of the first non-CMC results in 2008 and 2009.  The intellectual merit of the original project idea is now clear, with investigators helping answer several long-standing open problems in mathematical relativity.  However, while significant progress was made on developing a more complete solution theory for the conformal method, perhaps the most impactful of the discoveries made by the investigators and their collaborators during the project is that the conformal equations have a much richer mathematical structure than anyone anticipated.  As a result, rather than finding a complete solution theory for the conformal equations, the work of the investigators has helped the research community understand that an alternative to the conformal method should be developed, particularly for use in numerical relativity. The study of the Einstein equations presents a very important point of contact between mathematics and physics, and the project had broader impacts that reach well-beyond the new understanding of the conformal method.  The techniques which emerged for analyzing these equations on confined regions such as compact manifolds with boundary, will have significant further impact on numerical simulation in general relativity.  It is also expected that the technical advances made in the course of this project will have substantial application to other equations of this type, which play important roles in other parts of pure and applied mathematics, and in mathematical physics.  The Einstein equations have motivated many advances in differential geometry and partial differential equations, and as evidenced by the LIGO project, they continue to provide a compelling and accurate model of the physical world both on astrophysical and cosmological scales.  This project helped settle significant open questions in this area, and has helped crystallize several new important questions.       Last Modified: 05/29/2020       Submitted by: Michael J Holst]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
