<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ABI Development: The Arabidopsis Information Portal</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>4492936.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>4992581</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter McCartney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmccartn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928470</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The small plant Arabidopsis thaliana is a "model organism" that is studied in great depth as a model for other plants.  This project will develop the Arabidopsis Information Portal (AIP), a new resource to bring together the ever-increasing amounts of Arabidopsis data into a single, user-friendly location using the latest web technologies and web services. It will adopt a modular, federated model which ensures that responsibility for generation and maintenance of valuable data remains in the hands of the individual data providers and spreads the burden of supporting such resources across a potentially wider range of funding agencies and countries. The AIP will be developed by a team with deep experience in scientific infrastructure, data integration, and community engagement, and will take advantage of significant NSF investments in the plant biology research community. Key elements of the new AIP include the development of modular, community-extensible web-based interface that will include user work spaces that can be configured with data retrieval, analysis, and visualization applications,  implementation of an Arabidopsis-specific instance of InterMine, a data integration platform that is widely accepted in the animal model organism database community, and the design and construction of a web services layer that facilitates data access, integration with iPlant Collaborative resources, federation with other data providers, and development of analytical workflows. The project will implement a sustainability strategy that embraces adoption of existing scientific infrastructure, use of virtualization, federated provision of data, collaborative development of new resources, and pursuit of alternative funding sources. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana has been recognized as a model organism for plant research for many decades and was the first plant species to have a fully sequenced genome. For the past twelve years, The Arabidopsis Information Resource (TAIR) has served a large, worldwide community of research scientists, educators and students as a central resource collecting, curating and disseminating information about the organism's genome, genes, mutants and other information. The TAIR database receives over 36,000 unique visitors and 1.8 million page views per month.  With the retirement of TAIR, the AIP will take on a similar role but with a new spectrum of responsibilities. In addition to providing the community with facile access to broader and richer data sets, including genomic, epigenomic, transcriptomic, proteomic, metabolomic and phenomic data, the AIP will cooperate with the iPlant project to provide access to a sophisticated suite of tools that can be used to analyze, visualize, and interpret the data. The AIP will continue the TAIR model of educational engagement with the plant science community and with students and educators at the K-12, Community College and 4 year college level. It will provide reviews and demonstrations of the developing AIP functionalities at appropriate national meetings and host workshops for potential developers of new tools and resources. Not only will AIP modernize the bioinformatics capacity of the Arabidopsis community, it will provide a foundation for multi-agency, multi-national collaboration in building and funding biological informatics capabilities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1262414</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Town</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher D Town</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cdtown@jcvi.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3017957523</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000463958</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Vaughn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew W Vaughn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vaughn@tacc.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5122327124</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000300030</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Konstantinos</FirstName>
<LastName>Krampis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Konstantinos Krampis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kkrampis@jcvi.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3017957653</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000562995</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/15/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Agnes</FirstName>
<LastName>Chan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Agnes Chan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>achan@jcvi.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3017957862</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000499737</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmiller@jcvi.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3017957591</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000572085</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gos</FirstName>
<LastName>Micklem</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gos Micklem</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gos@gen.cam.ac.uk</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>1223333543</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000625799</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>J. Craig Venter Institute, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920373498</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8582001864</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4120 Capricorn Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>52</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA52</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076364392</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>J. CRAIG VENTER INSTITUTE, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>076364392</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[J. Craig Venter Institute, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Rockville</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>208503343</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9704 Medical Center Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1165</Code>
<Text>ADVANCES IN BIO INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7577</Code>
<Text>Plant Genome Research Resource</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~2434910</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~2058026</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~499645</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-baab79c4-7fff-5a55-2a0a-905fd6fbf2ed"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Genome sequencing and analysis has made tremendous contributions to our understanding and functioning of organisms across all levels of biological organization. In the plant kingdom, <em>Arabidopsis thaliana</em> (also known as Thale Cress) was the first to have its genome fully sequenced. It has a relatively small genome and many attributes such as small size, simple genetics and short life cycle that make it a favorable &ldquo;model organism&rdquo; for a wide variety of studies - molecular, genetic, physiological, ecological etc. Over the last two decades, the amount of detailed information on the structure and function of its approximately 30,000 genes has grown exponentially, fuelled by striking advances in both genome technology and bioinformatics analysis tools. The products of the research are published in scientific journals and hosted and distributed through a large number of web sites, each of which specializes in subsets of all available data.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The concept of the Arabidopsis Information Portal (Araport) arose from a series of workshops intended to address the needs of laboratory researchers in the face of the ever-increasing amount of data. Using the latest web technologies, Araport brings together into a single portal - a &ldquo;one-stop-shop&rdquo; - diverse data sets from all the separate major resources, as well as smaller specialized databases, thus providing an integrated view of the latest data and relieving the laboratory researcher of the need to visit multiple web sites to find and assimilate the data that he/she requires. The site also provides tools that enable individual researchers to share their data with the scientific community by developing web services that can be consumed by &ldquo;apps&rdquo; at Araport. A separate section of the site allows users to post information about upcoming conferences and job vacancies. In addition to serving both the research and education communities, the project has, during its development introduced many state-of-the-art web technologies into plant bioinformatics. </span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/10/2018<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;D&nbsp;Town</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1262414/1262414_10280226_1539198586412_AraportScreenShot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1262414/1262414_10280226_1539198586412_AraportScreenShot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The Araport Web Portal"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1262414/1262414_10280226_1539198586412_AraportScreenShot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The Araport Web Portal"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Screen shot of the Araport front page, highlighting the major functionalities.</div> <div class="imageCredit">The Araport Project</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;D&nbsp;Town</div> <div class="imageTitle">The Araport Web Portal</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Genome sequencing and analysis has made tremendous contributions to our understanding and functioning of organisms across all levels of biological organization. In the plant kingdom, Arabidopsis thaliana (also known as Thale Cress) was the first to have its genome fully sequenced. It has a relatively small genome and many attributes such as small size, simple genetics and short life cycle that make it a favorable "model organism" for a wide variety of studies - molecular, genetic, physiological, ecological etc. Over the last two decades, the amount of detailed information on the structure and function of its approximately 30,000 genes has grown exponentially, fuelled by striking advances in both genome technology and bioinformatics analysis tools. The products of the research are published in scientific journals and hosted and distributed through a large number of web sites, each of which specializes in subsets of all available data. The concept of the Arabidopsis Information Portal (Araport) arose from a series of workshops intended to address the needs of laboratory researchers in the face of the ever-increasing amount of data. Using the latest web technologies, Araport brings together into a single portal - a "one-stop-shop" - diverse data sets from all the separate major resources, as well as smaller specialized databases, thus providing an integrated view of the latest data and relieving the laboratory researcher of the need to visit multiple web sites to find and assimilate the data that he/she requires. The site also provides tools that enable individual researchers to share their data with the scientific community by developing web services that can be consumed by "apps" at Araport. A separate section of the site allows users to post information about upcoming conferences and job vacancies. In addition to serving both the research and education communities, the project has, during its development introduced many state-of-the-art web technologies into plant bioinformatics.                Last Modified: 10/10/2018       Submitted by: Christopher D Town]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
