<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Expanding Understanding of the Innovation Process: R&amp;D and Non-R&amp;D Innovation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>213109.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>213109</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maryann Feldman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>While R&amp;D is an important input to innovation, there is growing evidence that a significant share of innovation is not born from formal R&amp;D activity. Given the importance of innovation for economic growth and the central role of innovation in policy debates, the project will expand the study of innovation to include non-R&amp;D innovations and analyze the drivers and outcomes of non-R&amp;D compared to R&amp;D-based innovations. The project includes three key parts: a detailed review and analysis of new and traditional indicators of innovation, including estimates of the rates of non-R&amp;D innovation; modeling and empirically testing the relation between knowledge environments and innovation type (R&amp;D v. non-R&amp;D); and examining the impact of innovation type on willingness to participate in markets for technology, and how invention idiosyncrasy affects this relationship.  The research also addresses more fundamental questions in the science of science and innovation policy on the nature of knowledge in the innovation process and the likely outcomes of inventions embedding different characteristics.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The project's goal is to broaden the understanding of innovation and leverage this broader understanding in order to develop theories of innovation and improve the empirical foundation for innovation policy. Findings will contribute to ongoing efforts at NSF to develop more sophisticated innovation measures, as well as make important contributions to understandings of non-R&amp;D innovations and helping organizations build their strategies for innovation related to knowledge environments. In addition, the findings on willingness-to-license by invention type may help firms devise better strategies for commercializing their new technologies. One objective is to broaden understanding of the innovation process and build an empirical base to guide policymaking that would address this broader universe of innovative activity, including building new models of the R&amp;D decision, new metrics (non-R&amp;D innovation, idiosyncrasy) and new results on the innovation process.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1262418</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Walsh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John P Walsh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>john.walsh@pubpolicy.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043850866</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000499392</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Ave NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SciSIP-Sci of Sci Innov Policy</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~213109</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>Summary</em>:</p> <p>The rojects goals were: describe the rates and characteristics of non-R&amp;D innovation; examine predictors of non-R&amp;D versus R&amp;D invention, focusing on impact of knowledge environments; and examine impact of invention type (R&amp;D v. non-R&amp;D) on technology licensing. <em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p><em>Data and availability</em>: We published (Lee, 2015) detailed industry tables based on analyses of rates of non-R&amp;D innovation from two NSF-funded surveys (this project and also the Division of Innovative Labor project (NSF#0830349)). We have also posted the survey instrument on the project home page (http://www.prism.gatech.edu/~jwalsh6/inventors/invent.html). This website also includes detailed question-by-question results for the US and Japanese surveys, by industry and by firm size. <strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merits</strong>: This project overcomes limitations in innovation research that focuses on R&amp;D activities by characterizing the understudied area of non-R&amp;D-based innovation. We find approximately 10% of significant innovations are non-R&amp;D. We also find rates of non-R&amp;D innovation are higher when knowledge is more visible and lower when knowledge is more general. We also analyze impact of innovation type on participation in technology markets. These results address more fundamental questions of organization of innovation and affects of varying knowledge environments on the innovation process. As an extension of the project, on the theme of organization of innovative activity, we have also developed new indicators of novelty (Lee, et al., 2015) and of the bureaucratization of innovative work (Walsh &amp; Lee, 2015). Thus, the project is both broadening understanding of innovation and leveraging this broader understanding to inform the science of science and innovation policy. Initial findings from the project have been presented at national and international meetings and invited seminars. <strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Broader Impact and Publications</strong>: This project will contribute to ongoing efforts at NSF to develop more sophisticated measures of innovation. PI Walsh has been consulting with NSF on this topic. This project is also designed to help firms build their strategies for innovation-related knowledge management. In addition, the findings on licensing rates by invention type may help firms devise better strategies for commercializing their new technologies. In addition, our work on bureaucratization of science was featured in <em>ScienceCareers</em>. Finally, one objective of the study is to broaden understanding of the innovation process to guide policymaking that would address this broader universe of innovative activity.</p> <p><em>Human Resource Development</em>: The project trained one student for her PhD and post-doctoral training (Y.N. Lee, currently visiting assistant professor at GT). The project has produced the following publications: (Lee, 2015; Lee et al., 2015; Walsh &amp; Lee, 2015; Lee &amp; Walsh, 2016; Walsh et al. 2016; Walsh et al., forthcoming).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>OUTCOMES: The project produced 6 publications in refereed journals, one dissertation, and one trained post-doc.&nbsp; Key findings include an estimate of the rate of non-R&amp;D innovation of about 10% of important innovations, evidence that this rate is relatively higher in more visible knowledge environments, and evidence that more heterogeneous collaborations are more creative.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>&nbsp;References:</em></p> <p><em>Lee, Y.-N. (2015). "Evaluating and extending innovation indicators for innovation policy." Research Evaluation 24(4): 471-488.</em></p> <p><em><em>YN Lee, JP Walsh. 2016. &ldquo;Inventing while you work: Knowledge,  non-R&amp;D learning and innovation.&rdquo; Research Policy 45 (1), 345-359</em></em></p> <p><em><em>You-Na Lee, John P. Walsh, Ji...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Summary:  The rojects goals were: describe the rates and characteristics of non-R&amp;D innovation; examine predictors of non-R&amp;D versus R&amp;D invention, focusing on impact of knowledge environments; and examine impact of invention type (R&amp;D v. non-R&amp;D) on technology licensing.    Data and availability: We published (Lee, 2015) detailed industry tables based on analyses of rates of non-R&amp;D innovation from two NSF-funded surveys (this project and also the Division of Innovative Labor project (NSF#0830349)). We have also posted the survey instrument on the project home page (http://www.prism.gatech.edu/~jwalsh6/inventors/invent.html). This website also includes detailed question-by-question results for the US and Japanese surveys, by industry and by firm size.    Intellectual Merits: This project overcomes limitations in innovation research that focuses on R&amp;D activities by characterizing the understudied area of non-R&amp;D-based innovation. We find approximately 10% of significant innovations are non-R&amp;D. We also find rates of non-R&amp;D innovation are higher when knowledge is more visible and lower when knowledge is more general. We also analyze impact of innovation type on participation in technology markets. These results address more fundamental questions of organization of innovation and affects of varying knowledge environments on the innovation process. As an extension of the project, on the theme of organization of innovative activity, we have also developed new indicators of novelty (Lee, et al., 2015) and of the bureaucratization of innovative work (Walsh &amp; Lee, 2015). Thus, the project is both broadening understanding of innovation and leveraging this broader understanding to inform the science of science and innovation policy. Initial findings from the project have been presented at national and international meetings and invited seminars.    Broader Impact and Publications: This project will contribute to ongoing efforts at NSF to develop more sophisticated measures of innovation. PI Walsh has been consulting with NSF on this topic. This project is also designed to help firms build their strategies for innovation-related knowledge management. In addition, the findings on licensing rates by invention type may help firms devise better strategies for commercializing their new technologies. In addition, our work on bureaucratization of science was featured in ScienceCareers. Finally, one objective of the study is to broaden understanding of the innovation process to guide policymaking that would address this broader universe of innovative activity.  Human Resource Development: The project trained one student for her PhD and post-doctoral training (Y.N. Lee, currently visiting assistant professor at GT). The project has produced the following publications: (Lee, 2015; Lee et al., 2015; Walsh &amp; Lee, 2015; Lee &amp; Walsh, 2016; Walsh et al. 2016; Walsh et al., forthcoming).     OUTCOMES: The project produced 6 publications in refereed journals, one dissertation, and one trained post-doc.  Key findings include an estimate of the rate of non-R&amp;D innovation of about 10% of important innovations, evidence that this rate is relatively higher in more visible knowledge environments, and evidence that more heterogeneous collaborations are more creative.      References:  Lee, Y.-N. (2015). "Evaluating and extending innovation indicators for innovation policy." Research Evaluation 24(4): 471-488.  YN Lee, JP Walsh. 2016. "Inventing while you work: Knowledge,  non-R&amp;D learning and innovation." Research Policy 45 (1), 345-359  You-Na Lee, John P. Walsh, Jian Wang. 2015. "Creativity in  scientific teams: Unpacking novelty and impact." Research Policy  44(3):684-697.    Walsh, John P., You-Na Lee, and Sadao Nagaoka. Forthcoming. Openness and innovation in the US: Collaboration form, idea generation and implementation. Research Policy.  Walsh, J.P., Lee, Y.-N., Jung, T., 2016. Win, lose or ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
