<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Modeling and Control of Magnetic Chemotherapy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>40261.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>40261</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jordan Berg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jberg@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925365</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this collaborative research award is to improve the delivery of chemotherapy drugs to its target tumors. With existing chemotherapy, it is estimated that less than 0.1 percent of the administered drugs are taken up by the tumor, the remaining 99.9 percent go to healthy tissue and cause severe and life-threatening side-effects. In magnetic drug targeting, chemotherapy can be attached to biocompatible magnetic particles. This allows magnetic control of the drugs - magnets placed outside the patient can potentially be used to focus the therapy to tumors. Doing so is difficult. The human body is complex and it is not yet understood how to actuate the magnets (when to turn them on and off) to best direct the drugs to the tumors. The goal of this project is to develop sophisticated and experimentally-validated tools to better understand how magnetized chemotherapy moves through the body, and based on these to develop methods to optimally actuate the magnets to better direct the chemotherapy to tumors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the broader impact will be a suite of techniques to improve magnetic drug targeting - potentially moving it from a method that could only focus drugs to single shallow tumors, to one that could access deep tumors as well as small and poorly vascularized metastatic tumors spread throughout the body. This project is a collaborative effort between cancer clinicians, engineers, and mathematicians, and will also serve to bring these fields closer together in major part by training students to work effectively at the intersection of these three areas. High school, undergraduate, and graduate students will be involved in the research, and will interact with doctors, engineers, and mathematicians on a weekly basis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1262063</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arkadi</FirstName>
<LastName>Nemirovski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arkadi S Nemirovski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nemirovs@isye.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043850769</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486169</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1403</Code>
<Text>Proc Sys, Reac Eng &amp; Mol Therm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1632</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>031E</Code>
<Text>MECHATRONICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>049E</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL PROCESS CONTROL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~40261</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>T<span>he overall goal of this NSF-funded collaborative research is to develop methods to optimize magnetic drug delivery to hard-to-reach tumors. In magnetic drug targeting, external (outside the body) &nbsp;magnets are used to manipulate therapy attached to magnetic <span>nanoparticles</span> (inside the body) to direct that therapy to disease locations. In prior work, in collaboration with the University of Maryland, we helped to develop methods to optimize magnet construction and actuation to better direct therapy to deep targets. However, that prior work did not take into account significant parameter uncertainty that arises from dealing with the human body -- for any single patient, blood flow and tissue parameters are not fully known, and differ significantly from patient to patient. As a result, there is a necessity in building magnetic control which is robust with respect to data uncertainty, and our goal was to develop computational techniques capable to find magnet actuations which are ``immunized'' against anticipated parameter uncertainty and thus can be used to direct therapy to deep targets in realistic clinical environment.</span></p> <p>The main outcomes of our research are as follows:</p> <p>(I) We have built a specific mathematical model for design of robust magnetic drug delivery control, rich enough to capture the "physics" of the actual drug delivery process.</p> <p><span>(II)&nbsp; ``Physics'' of magnetic drug delivery makes the related control design problems (technically, they are problems of <span>nonconvex</span> quadratic quadratically constrained optimization) intrinsically difficult computationally; for problems of this type, no algorithms capable to approximate the globally optimal solution to high accuracy in realistic time are known, and there are strong reasons to believe than no algorithms of this type exist. As a result, the main challenge in our research was developing algorithms capable to find in realistic time reasonably good suboptimal solutions to the intrinsically difficult problems in question. The related results of our research can be summarized as follows:</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>-- Leveraging characteristic for magnetic drug delivery low dimensionality of the nominal (with&nbsp; no uncertainty in parameters)&nbsp; problem, we&nbsp; developed a fast algorithm <em>provably</em> capable to approximate to high accuracy <em>globally optimal </em>solution to the nominal problem (which, in high dimensions, still is difficult). The resulting solutions serve as benchmark when processing the problem with data uncertainty.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>-- The main outcome of our research is in developing two dedicated algorithms for solving the problem with data uncertainty. Extensive numerical experimentation demonstrates that these algorithms are well suited, both in terms of running time and the quality of resulting solutions, to processing the drug delivery problem with significant (tens of percents) parametric uncertainty. The results were used by our collaborators from the University of Maryland in their research on magnetic drug delivery.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>It should be added that the two developed by us algorithms for solving the <span>nonconvex</span> optimization problems arising in robust magnetic drug delivery have essential innovative elements and are applicable to rather general problems of <span>nonconvex</span> optimization (technically -- problems of optimizing smooth <span>nonconvex</span> objectives on well-structured convex domains). We believe that these algorithms make a meaningful by its own right addition to the computational toolbox of <span>nonconvex</span> optimization.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/16/2016<br>      Modified by: Arkadi&nbsp;S&nbsp;Nemirovski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall goal of this NSF-funded collaborative research is to develop methods to optimize magnetic drug delivery to hard-to-reach tumors. In magnetic drug targeting, external (outside the body)  magnets are used to manipulate therapy attached to magnetic nanoparticles (inside the body) to direct that therapy to disease locations. In prior work, in collaboration with the University of Maryland, we helped to develop methods to optimize magnet construction and actuation to better direct therapy to deep targets. However, that prior work did not take into account significant parameter uncertainty that arises from dealing with the human body -- for any single patient, blood flow and tissue parameters are not fully known, and differ significantly from patient to patient. As a result, there is a necessity in building magnetic control which is robust with respect to data uncertainty, and our goal was to develop computational techniques capable to find magnet actuations which are ``immunized'' against anticipated parameter uncertainty and thus can be used to direct therapy to deep targets in realistic clinical environment.  The main outcomes of our research are as follows:  (I) We have built a specific mathematical model for design of robust magnetic drug delivery control, rich enough to capture the "physics" of the actual drug delivery process.  (II)  ``Physics'' of magnetic drug delivery makes the related control design problems (technically, they are problems of nonconvex quadratic quadratically constrained optimization) intrinsically difficult computationally; for problems of this type, no algorithms capable to approximate the globally optimal solution to high accuracy in realistic time are known, and there are strong reasons to believe than no algorithms of this type exist. As a result, the main challenge in our research was developing algorithms capable to find in realistic time reasonably good suboptimal solutions to the intrinsically difficult problems in question. The related results of our research can be summarized as follows:     -- Leveraging characteristic for magnetic drug delivery low dimensionality of the nominal (with  no uncertainty in parameters)  problem, we  developed a fast algorithm provably capable to approximate to high accuracy globally optimal solution to the nominal problem (which, in high dimensions, still is difficult). The resulting solutions serve as benchmark when processing the problem with data uncertainty.     -- The main outcome of our research is in developing two dedicated algorithms for solving the problem with data uncertainty. Extensive numerical experimentation demonstrates that these algorithms are well suited, both in terms of running time and the quality of resulting solutions, to processing the drug delivery problem with significant (tens of percents) parametric uncertainty. The results were used by our collaborators from the University of Maryland in their research on magnetic drug delivery.     It should be added that the two developed by us algorithms for solving the nonconvex optimization problems arising in robust magnetic drug delivery have essential innovative elements and are applicable to rather general problems of nonconvex optimization (technically -- problems of optimizing smooth nonconvex objectives on well-structured convex domains). We believe that these algorithms make a meaningful by its own right addition to the computational toolbox of nonconvex optimization.          Last Modified: 06/16/2016       Submitted by: Arkadi S Nemirovski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
