<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Travel for Participants to the 26th International Cartographic Conference, Dresden, Germany, 2013</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>34628.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>34628</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Holly Hapke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In cartography as in many other scientific fields, advances in research and education increasingly rely on the development of international collaborations that bring together skilled scholars and educators from many different nations. International contacts and collaborations develop through many different means, but one of the most successful has been the biennial meetings of the International Cartographic Association (ICA). The ICA has been the primary international forum for cartographic research since 1959, and it currently involves over 80 countries. The ICA's next biennial meeting will occur in Dresden, Germany in August 2013. To facilitate the continued involvement of U.S. scientists in ICA activities and to facilitate the inclusion of more Americans in international networks at early stages of their careers, this award will provide group-travel support to enable at least 22 early-career cartographers from the U.S. as well as a limited number of mid-career professionals to attend this ICA meeting. Funds will be distributed to U.S. cartographers whose applications are evaluated using a number of criteria associated with active participation in the meeting. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will foster greater and a more diverse participation by U.S. cartographers in the global forum of the International Cartographic Association. As has been demonstrated in follow-up reports from Americans who have been supported with previous travel grants to other major international meetings, opportunities abound for meeting professional colleagues from many other nations, for hearing ideas and information from a broad range of different perspectives, and for participating in discussions that frequently result in successful research collaborations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1263568</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Leitner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Leitner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mleitne@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2255782963</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000122945</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University</Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075050765</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>940050792</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 Himes Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~34628</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>The NSF grant supported 17 young US scholars for $1,500 each and one young scholar for $1446.63 (based on the total amount of receipts submitted) for a total of $26,946.63 (for 18 young scholars) to present a paper and/or poster at the 26th International Cartographic Conference (ICC) in Dresden, Germany from August 25-30 2013.&nbsp; Young scholars are students and those, who completed their Ph.D. degree within the last 5 years.&nbsp; In addition to publishing in the conference proceedings and presenting a paper, young scholars met and exchanged ideas with a wide variety of foreign colleagues and reported a wide range of benefits to their careers. &nbsp;Their scholarly achievements in terms of publications of peer-reviewed articles and the writing of grant proposals influenced by their ICC participation have been impressive. &nbsp;All young scholars made important international collaborations and some included conference material into their teaching. &nbsp;ICC participation provided new ideas for some young scholars&rsquo; thesis and dissertation research and facilitated the progress towards tenure and promotion. &nbsp;For maturing and mature U.S. scholars, who also participated at the Dresden ICC, but were not funded by this NSF grant, ICC experience has been an important influence on their careers as leaders in the U.S. cartographic research community and has provided a mechanism for international leadership.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>The evidence of return from this NSF grant and its impact on research and scholarly development is compelling in research innovation and on long-term development of research leaders in cartography. &nbsp;Without listing the records of the young, maturing, and mature scholars that resulted from the ICC participation, one is convinced that with about 30-40 U.S. scholars attending the ICC every two years, the impact on the field is significant. &nbsp;Current ICA Commissions address cutting-edge research and participation in the ICC allows American scholars to be a part of this leading research. &nbsp;The United States National Committee (USNC) to the International Cartographic Association (ICA) has more than doubled the funding of young scholars participating at ICC&rsquo;s over the past decade from nine young scholars being funded for the Durban ICC in 2003 to a record number of 22 young scholars at the Paris ICC and General Assembly (GA) in 2011 and 18 young scholars actively participating at the 2013 ICC in Dresden, Germany. &nbsp;In the future USNC wants to continue this momentum of the success of the Paris, Dresden, and previous ICCs in drawing in new participation, especially among young scholars and under-represented groups (women, ethnic minorities, and persons with disabilities) and foster their development as the future leaders in research and international dissemination of cartographic information.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Summary of Outcomes</strong></p> <p>The importance of early ICC attendance on cartographic research and leadership among United States scholars is significant and compelling.&nbsp; Of the eighteen young scholars, who attended the Dresden ICC, twelve attended an ICC for the first time, five had previously attended one other ICC, and one had previously attended two other ICC&rsquo;s. &nbsp;The record of these 18 young scholars in terms of publications, grant proposals, collaborations, etc. that resulted (directly or indirectly) from the Dresden ICC participation is truly impressive. &nbsp;In total, this record includes: 18 papers and 3 posters published in the Dresden ICC proceedings, three papers published in peer-reviewed journals, two in a book as a peer-reviewed chapter, three in other conference proceedings, one single-authored book published, one single-authored book under contract, one refereed paper under review, and one...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  The NSF grant supported 17 young US scholars for $1,500 each and one young scholar for $1446.63 (based on the total amount of receipts submitted) for a total of $26,946.63 (for 18 young scholars) to present a paper and/or poster at the 26th International Cartographic Conference (ICC) in Dresden, Germany from August 25-30 2013.  Young scholars are students and those, who completed their Ph.D. degree within the last 5 years.  In addition to publishing in the conference proceedings and presenting a paper, young scholars met and exchanged ideas with a wide variety of foreign colleagues and reported a wide range of benefits to their careers.  Their scholarly achievements in terms of publications of peer-reviewed articles and the writing of grant proposals influenced by their ICC participation have been impressive.  All young scholars made important international collaborations and some included conference material into their teaching.  ICC participation provided new ideas for some young scholarsÆ thesis and dissertation research and facilitated the progress towards tenure and promotion.  For maturing and mature U.S. scholars, who also participated at the Dresden ICC, but were not funded by this NSF grant, ICC experience has been an important influence on their careers as leaders in the U.S. cartographic research community and has provided a mechanism for international leadership.     Broader Impacts  The evidence of return from this NSF grant and its impact on research and scholarly development is compelling in research innovation and on long-term development of research leaders in cartography.  Without listing the records of the young, maturing, and mature scholars that resulted from the ICC participation, one is convinced that with about 30-40 U.S. scholars attending the ICC every two years, the impact on the field is significant.  Current ICA Commissions address cutting-edge research and participation in the ICC allows American scholars to be a part of this leading research.  The United States National Committee (USNC) to the International Cartographic Association (ICA) has more than doubled the funding of young scholars participating at ICCÆs over the past decade from nine young scholars being funded for the Durban ICC in 2003 to a record number of 22 young scholars at the Paris ICC and General Assembly (GA) in 2011 and 18 young scholars actively participating at the 2013 ICC in Dresden, Germany.  In the future USNC wants to continue this momentum of the success of the Paris, Dresden, and previous ICCs in drawing in new participation, especially among young scholars and under-represented groups (women, ethnic minorities, and persons with disabilities) and foster their development as the future leaders in research and international dissemination of cartographic information.     Summary of Outcomes  The importance of early ICC attendance on cartographic research and leadership among United States scholars is significant and compelling.  Of the eighteen young scholars, who attended the Dresden ICC, twelve attended an ICC for the first time, five had previously attended one other ICC, and one had previously attended two other ICCÆs.  The record of these 18 young scholars in terms of publications, grant proposals, collaborations, etc. that resulted (directly or indirectly) from the Dresden ICC participation is truly impressive.  In total, this record includes: 18 papers and 3 posters published in the Dresden ICC proceedings, three papers published in peer-reviewed journals, two in a book as a peer-reviewed chapter, three in other conference proceedings, one single-authored book published, one single-authored book under contract, one refereed paper under review, and one National Science Foundation (NSF) grant recommended by the Geography and Spatial Sciences Program for funding beginning August 1, 2014.  One young scholarÆs ICC presentation was later discussed in a blog post on the Moravian Library website, which...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
