<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Antibody Purification via Affinity Chromatography that Utilizes the Unconventional Nucleotide Binding Site</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>314431.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>314431</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Angie Lueking</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1263713 Bilgicer&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this project is to engineer a novel affinity chromatography technique for purification of monoclonal and polyclonal antibodies from cell culture media and ascites fluids. This method targets the unconventional nucleotide binding site (NBS) that exists on antibodies to facilitate their capture on an affinity column. Antibodies have extraordinary specificity and affinity for antigens and are used in a vast array of applications including detection, diagnosis, catalysis, and therapy.  In the last fifteen years, therapeutic antibodies have revolutionized the treatment of many diseases including cancers and autoimmune diseases. Despite their benefits to patients, monoclonal antibody-based therapies are expensive, making them unaffordable to many patients. A major contributor to this cost is use of Protein A (or G) affinity columns during antibody production.  These columns are expensive and have a short cycle life. The results of this project may lead to a low-cost purification method.  In preliminary studies, the PI targeted the NBS with indole butyric acid (IBA).  Preliminary results showed that IBA column's capture efficiency for selected antibodies was &gt;95%, with purity of &gt;98%. The PI's research plan includes the following specific aims: i) screening for high affinity small molecules (nucleotide analog) for the NBS; ii) identification of the NBS resin for the best antibody purification performance; iii) determination of antibody yield and purity achieved by NBS column; iv) determination of column regeneration and reusability.  The potential advantages of the NBS column are: i) reduced production cost, ii) increased column capacity, iii) increased column lifetime (more durable material is stable under harsh column regeneration conditions), iv) no leaching of protein A/G into purified antibody, and v) capture and elution of only bivalently active, purified antibody.  Because the nucleotide binding site is present on all antibodies, the column can be used to purify both monoclonal and polyclonal antibodies of all isotypes from all species. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts.  Antibodies are of high significance in therapy, diagnosis and life-science research. An NBS-based purification method will potentially contribute to increasing quality as well as lowering the overall cost associated with antibody production and be of societal benefit in all these areas. In addition to the scientific impact of the proposed research, the PI is also committed to enhancing the educational climate to inspire graduate, undergraduate, and pre-collegiate students to pursue careers in science and engineering. As a junior faculty, the PI seeks to leverage the project to help achieve three long-standing goals in education: 1) Enhance the undergraduate education of students by participation in cutting edge research. 2) Increase the participation of members of underrepresented minorities in science. The PI has recruited several minority students for his research group 3) Improve the standard of science education in area high schools, and raise minority students? interest in careers in science and engineering. The PI will help develop a hands-on Career Decision Workshop that the PI will host in his laboratory each semester.  The PI also seeks to enhance core-high school biology. He has teamed up with South Bend New Tech High School teachers to generate the curriculum for a new biotechnology course. Successful establishment of the pioneering biotechnology course in the New Tech high school in South Bend may lead to implementation in New Tech high schools throughout the nation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1263713</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Basar</FirstName>
<LastName>Bilgicer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Basar Bilgicer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bbilgicer@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746311429</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574818</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>824910376</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048994727</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName>Notre Dame</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565612</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1417</Code>
<Text>Interfacial Engineering Progra</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>007E</Code>
<Text>Biological Separation Processes</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~314431</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Antibodies are employed in a vast array of applications, from diagnostic to therapeutic, while new applications for their implementation are continuously being explored. It has been of particular interest for research in pharmaceutical industry since the first FDA approved therapeutic antibody, muromonab, was introduced to the clinic in 1986. Currently, over 60 monoclonal antibodies and several antibody-drug conjugates (ADC) have been approved by the FDA for use in treatment of many diseases, ranging from autoimmune diseases to various cancers. Even though all of these antibody therapies prove to be very effective in treatment with fewer side effects than more traditional therapies, because of the high cost associated, many patients cannot afford these treatments. A major contributor to the cost of antibody pharmaceuticals is mostly linked to the downstream production process, or more specifically the purification steps. A classical antibody purification process requires four to five independent downstream process steps that reportedly contribute to more than 50-80% of the total cost of protein production. Therefore, a new cheaper and effective technology that would replace the existing expensive procedures could significantly reduce the cost of pharmaceutical antibody production, in turn, this would reduce the cost reflected to the patients making these treatments available to a larger patient population.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Furthermore, because antibodies are used in all levels of life-sciences research, both in industry and academia, a reduction in the cost of antibody molecules available for research purposes would potentially give research in many fields a boost as well.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>With this motivation, we initiated our research program with the funds provided from NSF, and today we have accomplished everything we had proposed in the original proposal and demonstrated that our strategy for antibody purification is as effective and significantly cheaper than the existing methods. Furthermore, we also investigated additional uses for the technology that was developed in our laboratory and engineered a noval method for functionalizing antibody molecules with higher efficiency improves biosensing applications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The results of our studies had been reported as peer-reviewed scientific publications as well as multiple seminars that I, as the PI, and my students have presented. Since the beginning of this funding, we <strong>published a total of 9 articles</strong> in highly respectable journals of the field, have <strong>presented 8 abstracts at national meetings</strong> and I have given <strong>10 invited talks</strong> at reputable institutes and national/international meetings. I believe the ultimate goal has been achieved, and we thank the NSF for the funding support. Nevertheless, the technology still needs to be optimized for industrial applications, but the next steps are beyond the scope of academic research, and needs to be performed in an industrial setting.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2017<br>      Modified by: Basar&nbsp;Bilgicer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Antibodies are employed in a vast array of applications, from diagnostic to therapeutic, while new applications for their implementation are continuously being explored. It has been of particular interest for research in pharmaceutical industry since the first FDA approved therapeutic antibody, muromonab, was introduced to the clinic in 1986. Currently, over 60 monoclonal antibodies and several antibody-drug conjugates (ADC) have been approved by the FDA for use in treatment of many diseases, ranging from autoimmune diseases to various cancers. Even though all of these antibody therapies prove to be very effective in treatment with fewer side effects than more traditional therapies, because of the high cost associated, many patients cannot afford these treatments. A major contributor to the cost of antibody pharmaceuticals is mostly linked to the downstream production process, or more specifically the purification steps. A classical antibody purification process requires four to five independent downstream process steps that reportedly contribute to more than 50-80% of the total cost of protein production. Therefore, a new cheaper and effective technology that would replace the existing expensive procedures could significantly reduce the cost of pharmaceutical antibody production, in turn, this would reduce the cost reflected to the patients making these treatments available to a larger patient population.     Furthermore, because antibodies are used in all levels of life-sciences research, both in industry and academia, a reduction in the cost of antibody molecules available for research purposes would potentially give research in many fields a boost as well.     With this motivation, we initiated our research program with the funds provided from NSF, and today we have accomplished everything we had proposed in the original proposal and demonstrated that our strategy for antibody purification is as effective and significantly cheaper than the existing methods. Furthermore, we also investigated additional uses for the technology that was developed in our laboratory and engineered a noval method for functionalizing antibody molecules with higher efficiency improves biosensing applications.     The results of our studies had been reported as peer-reviewed scientific publications as well as multiple seminars that I, as the PI, and my students have presented. Since the beginning of this funding, we published a total of 9 articles in highly respectable journals of the field, have presented 8 abstracts at national meetings and I have given 10 invited talks at reputable institutes and national/international meetings. I believe the ultimate goal has been achieved, and we thank the NSF for the funding support. Nevertheless, the technology still needs to be optimized for industrial applications, but the next steps are beyond the scope of academic research, and needs to be performed in an industrial setting.          Last Modified: 08/31/2017       Submitted by: Basar Bilgicer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
