<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site at Kent State University: Liquid Crystals and Advanced Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbushey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924938</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The REU Site is co-funded by the Department of Defense in partnership with the NSF REU program. This award supports a Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Site led by Professors Robert J. Twieg and Torsten Hegmann both at Kent State University. The Site is located in the Department of Chemistry &amp; Biochemistry and the Liquid Crystal Institute (LCI) at Kent State University (KSU). The research projects supported at this Site entitled, "Liquid Crystals and Advanced Materials", brings a diverse group of students from two year and four year institutions in various parts of the country to KSU to interact with a local cohort of KSU students. Mentors work closely with these students as they pursue scientific discovery involving advanced materials from liquid crystals and soft condensed matter physics to biomaterials. The students will participate in all aspects of the scientific process, from design and execution of their project to interpretation and dissemination of research results, all in a cooperative and collegial atmosphere.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Early participation in a research experience has been identified as an important component of student engagement in science. The provision of a unique first research experience is at the heart of this REU program, which will have a lasting impact on this group of students. Aside from exposure to a multidisciplinary research culture, this experience will create new friendships, networks, and aspirations that will endure long after the summer is completed. This REU Program will directly impact both science success and people success. There will be immediate science productivity enhanced by the participation of these new scientists and a still larger long-term impact as they evolve into their own distinct pursuits.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1263087</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Twieg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert J Twieg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rtwieg@lci.kent.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3306722791</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000333651</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Torsten</FirstName>
<LastName>Hegmann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Torsten Hegmann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>thegmann@kent.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3306727770</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000614906</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kent State University</Name>
<CityName>KENT</CityName>
<ZipCode>442420001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3306722070</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF THE COMPTROLLER</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO BOX 5190]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041071101</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KENT STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041071101</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Kent State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Kent</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>442420001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1986</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>L644</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O266</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>n532</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7736</Code>
<Text>DOD ASSURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9162</Code>
<Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As a result of the awarded NSF program "REU Site at Kent State University: Liquid Crystals and Advanced Materials"&nbsp;a total of 56 undergraduate students participated in our program at KSU over the three summers of 2013-2015.&nbsp; Of this group, the NSF directly supported 32 students chosen from a wide range of universities, colleges and community colleges across the country.&nbsp; Because of the existence of this NSF program KSU generously supported a total of 22 local KSU undergraduates who did research along with the NSF supported students.&nbsp; In addition, we had 2 more international students supported by the government of Brazil join the program in its last year.&nbsp; As such, in addition to the research experience gained, all these students benefitted greatly from interactions with their national and international coworkers.</p> <p>The main topical emphasis of the KSU REU program was in Materials Science and especially soft matter related activities in Chemistry, Physics and Biology. &nbsp;Most of the faculty advisors were from the Kent State Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry and the Liquid Crystal Institute. Many of our KSU graduate students also played an important role in the program and benefitted from their interactions with this group of undergraduate researchers.</p> <p>A primary goal of our REU program was to provide a research experience, which will have a life long impact. Each student was immersed in a ten-week research project that had all the critical attributes of a full-fledged research project. Initially the students participated in the planning of their individual projects and during the first week summarized the project goals before all the participants. In the course of the actual subsequent execution of the research the students received hands on experience in the lab with new concepts, techniques and hardware. The students collected the data generated and were responsible for the interpretation of the results. Finally, the students were involved in the reporting of the results of their projects at a local research symposium and, when warranted, they participated in the preparation of manuscripts submitted to the scientific literature. Overall, the students were immersed in a research environment wherein they collaborated in an established research group with all of its various functions and responsibilities.</p> <p>The students were also provided with a number of additional activities to augment the concentration on research. &nbsp;Career guidance was one of the main supplemental activities and we used our local people resources in these career-building activities. &nbsp;For example, our own undergraduate and graduate students who had successfully recently transitioned into their own careers were brought back to campus to participate in lectures and Q&amp;A sessions with the REU students. We have found that these returning students were able to provide the most up to date and relevant career information to share with the REU students. Our students also visited a local startup company to have a first hand look at that career environment. We also provided a seminar on ethics, which has proved very popular. &nbsp;Our program has always had a very strong social component outside of the lab. &nbsp;We provided a number of activities including picnics, local travel to parks, concerts and museums and the like that the students all enjoyed together with many of the advisors.</p> <p>Amongst the metrics of success of the program at this juncture 17 of our students are entering or are now in graduate studies, 5 students are in pharmacy or medical school, 6 are employed in the public or private sector workforce and 18 are still pursuing their undergraduate degrees. Thus far 21 publications that include student coauthors have appeared with more forthcoming. All in all, this program was a great investment in the lives of these students.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/19/2016<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;J&nbsp;Twieg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1470756276815_DSC_0170--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1470756276815_DSC_0170--rgov-800width.jpg" title="KSU REU 2015 Group Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1470756276815_DSC_0170--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="KSU REU 2015 Group Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Each year on the initiation date of the REU project an organizational meeting is held and a group photo is taken. Here is the photograph of the 2015 group of NSF supported students, KSU supported students and their advisors.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Erin Michael-McLauglin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;J&nbsp;Twieg</div> <div class="imageTitle">KSU REU 2015 Group Photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1470756557747_20150609_131034--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1470756557747_20150609_131034--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU Student Instrumentation Training"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1470756557747_20150609_131034--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU Student Instrumentation Training"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Many students who enter the REU program are not familiar with scientific instrumentation. All students are provided with an introduction to scientific instruments they may encounter in the course of their research.  Here Prof. Jake Shelley trains a group of REU students on the mass spectrometer.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Erin Michael-McLauglin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;J&nbsp;Twieg</div> <div class="imageTitle">REU Student Instrumentation Training</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1470756953812_20150708_103614--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1470756953812_20150708_103614--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU Students at the Industrial Lab Tour"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1470756953812_20150708_103614--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU Students at the Industrial Lab Tour"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">As part of the career development component of the REU program students have the opportunity to meet with students who have left KSU for graduate school or a permanent job.  Here the REU students visit Alpha-Micron, a local research startup.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Erin Michael-McLauglin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;J&nbsp;Twieg</div> <div class="imageTitle">REU Students at the Industrial Lab Tour</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1470757534982_DSC_0406--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1470757534982_DSC_0406--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Northeast Ohio Undergraduate Research Symposium"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1470757534982_DSC_0406--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Northeast Ohio Undergraduate Research Symposium"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Each year our REU students present the results of their research along with students from other local research organizations. The 2015 symposium was held at NASA-Glenn in Cleveland. Here a KSU student presents her poster to other students at the symposium.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Erin Michael-McLauglin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;J&nbsp;Twieg</div> <div class="imageTitle">Northeast Ohio Undergraduate Research Symposium</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1472328108673_20150617_194556--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1472328108673_20150617_194556--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU students participate in a hike at Cuyahoga National Park"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1472328108673_20150617_194556--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU students participate in a hike at Cuyahoga National Park"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Social activities outside the lab and university are an important part of the REU program. For example, we often have a group hikes and a canoe trip in the countryside here in northeast Ohio.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Erin Michael-McLauglin</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;J&nbsp;Twieg</div> <div class="imageTitle">REU students participate in a hike at Cuyahoga National Park</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1472328707343_20150806_184213--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1472328707343_20150806_184213--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU students play volleyball at the farewell picnic"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1263087/1263087_10250141_1472328707343_20150806_184213--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU students play volleyball at the farewell picnic"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">After ten weeks together the students know each other very well and will stay in touch long after the program is complete.  Here the students participate in a volleyball game at the farewell picnic held during the last week of the program.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Erin Michael-McLauglin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;J&nbsp;Twieg</div> <div class="imageTitle">REU students play volleyball at the farewell picnic</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As a result of the awarded NSF program "REU Site at Kent State University: Liquid Crystals and Advanced Materials" a total of 56 undergraduate students participated in our program at KSU over the three summers of 2013-2015.  Of this group, the NSF directly supported 32 students chosen from a wide range of universities, colleges and community colleges across the country.  Because of the existence of this NSF program KSU generously supported a total of 22 local KSU undergraduates who did research along with the NSF supported students.  In addition, we had 2 more international students supported by the government of Brazil join the program in its last year.  As such, in addition to the research experience gained, all these students benefitted greatly from interactions with their national and international coworkers.  The main topical emphasis of the KSU REU program was in Materials Science and especially soft matter related activities in Chemistry, Physics and Biology.  Most of the faculty advisors were from the Kent State Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry and the Liquid Crystal Institute. Many of our KSU graduate students also played an important role in the program and benefitted from their interactions with this group of undergraduate researchers.  A primary goal of our REU program was to provide a research experience, which will have a life long impact. Each student was immersed in a ten-week research project that had all the critical attributes of a full-fledged research project. Initially the students participated in the planning of their individual projects and during the first week summarized the project goals before all the participants. In the course of the actual subsequent execution of the research the students received hands on experience in the lab with new concepts, techniques and hardware. The students collected the data generated and were responsible for the interpretation of the results. Finally, the students were involved in the reporting of the results of their projects at a local research symposium and, when warranted, they participated in the preparation of manuscripts submitted to the scientific literature. Overall, the students were immersed in a research environment wherein they collaborated in an established research group with all of its various functions and responsibilities.  The students were also provided with a number of additional activities to augment the concentration on research.  Career guidance was one of the main supplemental activities and we used our local people resources in these career-building activities.  For example, our own undergraduate and graduate students who had successfully recently transitioned into their own careers were brought back to campus to participate in lectures and Q&amp;A sessions with the REU students. We have found that these returning students were able to provide the most up to date and relevant career information to share with the REU students. Our students also visited a local startup company to have a first hand look at that career environment. We also provided a seminar on ethics, which has proved very popular.  Our program has always had a very strong social component outside of the lab.  We provided a number of activities including picnics, local travel to parks, concerts and museums and the like that the students all enjoyed together with many of the advisors.  Amongst the metrics of success of the program at this juncture 17 of our students are entering or are now in graduate studies, 5 students are in pharmacy or medical school, 6 are employed in the public or private sector workforce and 18 are still pursuing their undergraduate degrees. Thus far 21 publications that include student coauthors have appeared with more forthcoming. All in all, this program was a great investment in the lives of these students.          Last Modified: 09/19/2016       Submitted by: Robert J Twieg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
