<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site for Oregon Marine Science: From upper estuaries to the deep sea</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1053452.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1163155</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Rom</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>elrom@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927709</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides renewed funding for a Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program at Oregon State University (OSU). The program will provide 20 students with a 10-week active learning experience each summer for five years, for a total of 100 students over the duration of the program.  Each summer, ten interns will work with scientists from the Hatfield Marine Science Center (HMSC) in Newport, Oregon, and ten interns will work at the OSU main campus in Corvallis with mentors from the College of Earth, Ocean and Atmospheric Sciences (CEOAS). The major field for this REU site is broadly defined as marine science, ranging from marine and estuarine biology and ecology (at HMSC) through the physical sciences (marine aspects of physics, geology, and climate at CEOAS) to provide a diverse range of undergraduate research opportunities and faculty mentors. The major objectives of the REU program are to i) provide students with the opportunity to experience research in marine science and an understanding of its interdisciplinary nature; ii) provide students with a unique educational opportunity and exposure to a wide range of marine science; and iii) increase participation in and access to marine science for under-represented groups and students lacking access to STEM research. Interns have directed research projects, a required report and oral presentation, and are encouraged to present at regional or national meetings. Additional activities include seminars, fieldwork, interaction with graduate students and related intern programs, career development training, scientific ethics discussions, and exchanges to learn about other interdisciplinary research conducted in Oregon's diverse environments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The site is co-funded by the Department of Defense in partnership with the NSF REU program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1263349</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Itchung</FirstName>
<LastName>Cheung</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Itchung S Cheung</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>itchung.cheung@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417374933</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000490640</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kaplan</FirstName>
<LastName>Yalcin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kaplan Yalcin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yalcink@geo.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417374933</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000628007</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1690</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION/HUMAN RESOURCES,OCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7699</Code>
<Text>Integrat &amp; Collab Ed &amp; Rsearch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>L644</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>N532</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O266</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1733</Code>
<Text>GEOSCIENCE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7736</Code>
<Text>DOD ASSURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~192860</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~303471</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~218356</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~448468</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 1-year no-cost extension to this project was to support four participants in our REU site at Oregon State University located on the Oregon coast at Hatfield Marine Science Center (HMSC) in Newport, Oregon. The major field for this REU site is broadly defined as marine science, ranging from diverse biological and ecological topics through the physical sciences (marine aspects of physics, geology, chemistry, and atmospheric science).</p> <p>The major objectives of our REU program are to:</p> <p>1) provide students an opportunity for the highest quality research experience in marine science and an understanding of its interdisciplinary nature;</p> <p>2) provide students with a educational opportunity and unique exposure to a wide range of marine science; and</p> <p>3) increase participation in and access to marine studies for traditionally underrepresented students.</p> <p>Interns have directed research projects, a required report and oral presentation, and are encouraged to present at regional and/or national meetings. Additional activities include seminar series, field sampling, interaction with graduate students and related intern programs, career development training, scientific ethics discussions, and exchanges to learn about other interdisciplinary research conducted in Oregon?s diverse environments.</p> <p>Research projects undertaken by REU students provided a full range of experience in scientific methods from field observation, data collection and sampling to experimentation, processing and analysis of data in laboratory settings. During the first week, activities were focused on orienting students to their labs, relevant scientific literature and preparing them to become active participants in research. With training and guidance from their mentors and program staff, the students developed written research proposals, learned how to design and carry out experiments, and gained skills and experience covering a wide range of scientific techniques and practices, such as:</p> <ul> <li>Employing microsatellite genotyping to understand the structure and composition of the mixed stocks of humpback whales feeding off the California coast.</li> <li>Using Argos satellite system to receive location data from tagged marine mammals</li> <li>Using an existing set of population models of two oceanographically distinct regions of the California coast to evaluate the utility of different metrics for MPA planning.</li> <li>Using DNA profiles for assignment of humpback whales from California feeding grounds to Distinct Population Segments</li> </ul> <p>Student training and development culminated in final papers and oral presentations. In addition to skills specific to REU intern research projects, adjunct activities were planned into the REU program schedule to help students maximize the 10-weeks in a marine lab and expose them to a wide range of people who have chosen careers in marine science, shown in the table below. During the first week of the program, both the Hatfield Marine Science Center (HMSC) and the College of Earth, Ocean and Atmospheric (CEOAS) REU students attended the Markham Symposium and poster session, where graduate students present research projects completed (and also in progress) to the marine science community. For the REU interns, the symposium serves as an opportunity to see the products of graduate-level research and examples of science communication presentations expected of them at the end of the 10-week program.<br /><br />Our REU internship model continues to set the structure for other undergraduate research internship programs in marine science at OSU.&nbsp;The REU students? final project presentations and final papers demonstrated a considerable level of learning and achievement over the course of the 10-week program. Several research projects were exemplary and are planned for publication and/or presentation as posters at scientific meetings, as has been the case in previous years. The program has continued to encourage and support REU interns to present their summer research at scientific meetings. One of the four interns supported by the 1-year no-cost extension presented at the 2019 ASLO meeting in San Juan, PR.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/24/2020<br>      Modified by: Itchung&nbsp;S&nbsp;Cheung</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263349/1263349_10237063_1598319643312_ScreenShot2020-08-24at6.35.09PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263349/1263349_10237063_1598319643312_ScreenShot2020-08-24at6.35.09PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="HMSC Overhead view"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263349/1263349_10237063_1598319643312_ScreenShot2020-08-24at6.35.09PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="HMSC Overhead view"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">HMSC Campus Overhead view</div> <div class="imageCredit">Hatfield Marine Science Center</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Itchung&nbsp;S&nbsp;Cheung</div> <div class="imageTitle">HMSC Overhead view</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 1-year no-cost extension to this project was to support four participants in our REU site at Oregon State University located on the Oregon coast at Hatfield Marine Science Center (HMSC) in Newport, Oregon. The major field for this REU site is broadly defined as marine science, ranging from diverse biological and ecological topics through the physical sciences (marine aspects of physics, geology, chemistry, and atmospheric science).  The major objectives of our REU program are to:  1) provide students an opportunity for the highest quality research experience in marine science and an understanding of its interdisciplinary nature;  2) provide students with a educational opportunity and unique exposure to a wide range of marine science; and  3) increase participation in and access to marine studies for traditionally underrepresented students.  Interns have directed research projects, a required report and oral presentation, and are encouraged to present at regional and/or national meetings. Additional activities include seminar series, field sampling, interaction with graduate students and related intern programs, career development training, scientific ethics discussions, and exchanges to learn about other interdisciplinary research conducted in Oregon?s diverse environments.  Research projects undertaken by REU students provided a full range of experience in scientific methods from field observation, data collection and sampling to experimentation, processing and analysis of data in laboratory settings. During the first week, activities were focused on orienting students to their labs, relevant scientific literature and preparing them to become active participants in research. With training and guidance from their mentors and program staff, the students developed written research proposals, learned how to design and carry out experiments, and gained skills and experience covering a wide range of scientific techniques and practices, such as:  Employing microsatellite genotyping to understand the structure and composition of the mixed stocks of humpback whales feeding off the California coast. Using Argos satellite system to receive location data from tagged marine mammals Using an existing set of population models of two oceanographically distinct regions of the California coast to evaluate the utility of different metrics for MPA planning. Using DNA profiles for assignment of humpback whales from California feeding grounds to Distinct Population Segments   Student training and development culminated in final papers and oral presentations. In addition to skills specific to REU intern research projects, adjunct activities were planned into the REU program schedule to help students maximize the 10-weeks in a marine lab and expose them to a wide range of people who have chosen careers in marine science, shown in the table below. During the first week of the program, both the Hatfield Marine Science Center (HMSC) and the College of Earth, Ocean and Atmospheric (CEOAS) REU students attended the Markham Symposium and poster session, where graduate students present research projects completed (and also in progress) to the marine science community. For the REU interns, the symposium serves as an opportunity to see the products of graduate-level research and examples of science communication presentations expected of them at the end of the 10-week program.  Our REU internship model continues to set the structure for other undergraduate research internship programs in marine science at OSU. The REU students? final project presentations and final papers demonstrated a considerable level of learning and achievement over the course of the 10-week program. Several research projects were exemplary and are planned for publication and/or presentation as posters at scientific meetings, as has been the case in previous years. The program has continued to encourage and support REU interns to present their summer research at scientific meetings. One of the four interns supported by the 1-year no-cost extension presented at the 2019 ASLO meeting in San Juan, PR.       Last Modified: 08/24/2020       Submitted by: Itchung S Cheung]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
