<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Interdisciplinary Research Experiences for Undergraduates on Bioenergy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>326364.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>326364</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This interdisciplinary Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) site at South Dakota State University will allow ten undergraduate students for 10 weeks during the summers of 2013 to 2015 to learn research skills and to participate in unique research experiences related to biofuels and bioenergy crops. Bioenergy is not only an emergent area in science and engineering with profound implications for the U.S. economy, but it is also an excellent training ground in multidisciplinary research. The industry is still developing, and it can be expected that the demands for scientists in this area and a trained work force will increase in the near future. Field trips to industry partners will allow students to learn about potential careers in the bioenergy industry. This project links together faculty mentors from 6 different departments (biology and microbiology, agricultural and biosystems engineering, plant science, chemistry, economics, geospatial sciences) with active research programs on bioenergy, and this will provide a multidisciplinary research environment for the participants of the program. Students in chemistry, biology, engineering, and economics will get actively involved in projects representing the whole spectrum of state of the art bioenergy research from feedstock genomics, to new technologies in bioprocessing and the conversion of bioenergy crops into biofuels, to ecological and environmental sustainability of agricultural crop production, but will also consider the societal and economic impacts of global bioenergy production. Students will also participate in seminars and various workshops, such as ethics training and responsible conduct in research. The students are selected based on their academic record, letters of recommendation, and their motivation to work in a multidisciplinary research environment. A common assessment tool will be used to evaluate the gains of the students in different research relevant areas after the program. The students are tracked to determine their continued interest in their academic field of study, their career paths, and the lasting influences of the research experience. More information is available by visiting the web page of the program (http://www.sdstate.edu/biomicro/REU/index.cfm), or by contacting sdsu.reu.bioenergy@sdstate.edu, the PI (Dr. Heike Bücking at heike.bucking@sdstate.edu) or the co-PI (Dr. Jose Gonzalez at jose.gonzalez@sdstate.edu) of the program.&lt;br/&gt;The site is co-funded by the Department of Defense in partnership with the NSF REU program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1263335</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heike</FirstName>
<LastName>Bucking</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Heike Bucking</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>heike.bucking@sdstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6056885463</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000319655</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/01/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
<LastName>Gonzalez Hernandez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jose L Gonzalez Hernandez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jose.gonzalez@sdstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6056886907</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000079194</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/01/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>South Dakota State University</Name>
<CityName>Brookings</CityName>
<ZipCode>570070001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6056886696</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1015 Campanile Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Box 2201, SAD 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>929929743</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTH DAKOTA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>929538999</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[South Dakota State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>570070001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>L644</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>N532</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O266</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7736</Code>
<Text>DOD ASSURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~106739</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~109885</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~109740</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>To provide future generations with innovative and environmentally sustainable solutions for food or renewable bioenergy production is a great challenge that will require the training of next generation scientists and engineers to think beyond their disciplinary bounds. More and more frequently, innovation occurs at the intersection of disciplines, and traditional undergraduate education often does not prepare students for interdisciplinary work environments. The major goal of this interdisciplinary REU (Research experiences for undergraduates) site at South Dakota State University was to to provide students with an opportunity to experience cutting-edge research over a wide range of various disciplines and emphases (agriculture, biochemistry, bioprocessing, chemistry, engineering, genomics, microbiology, molecular biology, soil science) and to broaden their perspectives on a research career in the academic sciences. The award allowed 38 students (many recruited from underrepresented groups in the sciences, and from smaller academic institutions with only limited research capabilities) to work with their mentors on research projects related to different aspects of bioenergy research. The undergraduate students were for example involved in the development of efficient feedstocks for biofuel production through bioengineering; in the development of bioprocessing strategies to increase ethanol recovery from different feedstocks; and in the development of technologies to improve the environmental sustainability of bioenergy production systems. The students visited ethanol plants and were exposed to all key steps in the bioethanol production chain, were trained in state of the art technologies and in mentoring of high school students, and learned important scientific skills that are important to be successful in a competitive graduate program. Most students experienced for the first time authentic &ldquo;real life&rdquo; scientific research and worked independently on a research project. This undergraduate research program exposed the students to career choices outside of the biomedical field, contributed to a clarification of potential career paths, demonstrated to the students that they have an aptitude for scientific research, and strengthened the confidence of the students for research careers and graduate school careers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Heike&nbsp;Bucking</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ To provide future generations with innovative and environmentally sustainable solutions for food or renewable bioenergy production is a great challenge that will require the training of next generation scientists and engineers to think beyond their disciplinary bounds. More and more frequently, innovation occurs at the intersection of disciplines, and traditional undergraduate education often does not prepare students for interdisciplinary work environments. The major goal of this interdisciplinary REU (Research experiences for undergraduates) site at South Dakota State University was to to provide students with an opportunity to experience cutting-edge research over a wide range of various disciplines and emphases (agriculture, biochemistry, bioprocessing, chemistry, engineering, genomics, microbiology, molecular biology, soil science) and to broaden their perspectives on a research career in the academic sciences. The award allowed 38 students (many recruited from underrepresented groups in the sciences, and from smaller academic institutions with only limited research capabilities) to work with their mentors on research projects related to different aspects of bioenergy research. The undergraduate students were for example involved in the development of efficient feedstocks for biofuel production through bioengineering; in the development of bioprocessing strategies to increase ethanol recovery from different feedstocks; and in the development of technologies to improve the environmental sustainability of bioenergy production systems. The students visited ethanol plants and were exposed to all key steps in the bioethanol production chain, were trained in state of the art technologies and in mentoring of high school students, and learned important scientific skills that are important to be successful in a competitive graduate program. Most students experienced for the first time authentic "real life" scientific research and worked independently on a research project. This undergraduate research program exposed the students to career choices outside of the biomedical field, contributed to a clarification of potential career paths, demonstrated to the students that they have an aptitude for scientific research, and strengthened the confidence of the students for research careers and graduate school careers.       Last Modified: 05/30/2017       Submitted by: Heike Bucking]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
