<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FRG: Collaborative Research: Analysis of the Einstein Constraint Equations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>202173.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>202173</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS 1265187, 1262982, 1263431, 1263544&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI:  Rafe R Mazzeo, Stanford University &lt;br/&gt;PI:  Michael Holst, University of California - San Diego &lt;br/&gt;PI:  Jim Isenberg, University of Oregon &lt;br/&gt;PI:  David Maxell, University of Alaska&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to understand the extent to which one can parametrize and construct initial data sets for the Einstein  evolution equations. We plan to capitalize on the recent progress using the conformal method to obtain new existence results in the  nonconstant mean curvature (non-CMC) setting, to understand the limits of these methods, and then to develop alternate techniques toward these same goals, including degree theory, a priori estiimates, and gluing methods. The Lichnerowicz equation, central  to the conformal method, is a semilinear elliptic equation. Due to  the mixed sign of its nonlinear exponents, it is of a type not yet fully understood. The full Lichnerowicz-Choquet-Bruhat-York set of equations is a more difficult coupled system which incorporates  features presenting new analytic subtleties. The ultimate aim is to  provide a complete parametrization of initial data sets, particularly  in the non-CMC setting, not only on compact backgrounds but also  for manifolds with asymptotically Euclidean, hyperbolic or cylindrical ends, all of which are highly relevant for physical applications.  In exploring new methods, we plan to use new and advanced analytical tools, as well as increasingly accurate and flexible numerical simulation techniques. Technical advances made in the course of  this project should have a substantial application to many other  equations of this general type which play important roles in other  parts of pure and applied mathematics and mathematical physics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Einstein's gravitational field theory is a remarkably accurate mathematical model of gravitational physics, which does an excellent job  of predicting and modeling gravitational phenomena at both the  astrophysical and cosmological scales. It is consistent with every  known gravitational observation and experiment. From the point of  view of underlying mathematics, Einstein's theory involves two very  distinct types of equations. The study of dynamics of gravitational  fields involves the analysis of the Einstein equations as a nonlinear  system of time-dependent evolution partial differential equations  (PDE), while the study of initial data sets representing gravitational states involves Riemannian geometry and the study of the Einstein  constraint equations as a nonlinear system of time-independent  PDE.The last decade has witnessed remarkable progress in under- standing both equations. This project focuses on developing a  more complete understanding of the constraint equations. The study of the Einstein equations presents a very important point of contact  between mathematics and physics, one which has motivated many  advances in differential geometry and PDE on the one side, and  which also has provided a compelling and accurate model of the  physical world, both on the astrophysical and on the cosmological  scales. This project has the potential for settling significant open  questions in this area.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1263431</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Isenberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James A Isenberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>isenberg@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5413464725</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000211357</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
<CityName>Eugene</CityName>
<ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079289626</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049793995</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oregon Eugene]]></Name>
<CityName>Eugene</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>974031222</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1222 University of Oregon]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1616</Code>
<Text>FOCUSED RESEARCH GROUPS IN MATH SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~202173</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This FRG grant focused on initial data sets for Einstein's gravitational field equations. Such initial data sets must satisfy the Einstein constraint equations, which constitute an underdetermined system of four equations for the metric, the second fundamental form, and relevant matter fields. For initial data sets which have constant mean curvature, the conformal method has been very effective for constructing and parameterizing the space of solutions of the Einstein constraint equations. This effectiveness extends to near-constant mean curvature data sets as well. However, for data sets with far from constant mean curvature, the conformal method has significant difficulties. Our FRG grant, in collaboration with Rafe Mazzeo, David Maxwell, Michael Holst, James Dilts, Paul Allen, Iva Stavrov, and Jack Lee, explored these difficulties extensively, both analytically and numerically.</p> <p>We also spent considerable effort seeking alternatives to the conformal method. Our results show that for many sets of "seed data", the conformal method has either many solutions or no solutions. We also&nbsp;studied blow up behavior near the seed data with many or no solutions.</p> <p>This FRG grant also supported research focused on asymptotically hyperbolic data sets which are "shear free". This condition is necessary for the data to generate solutions of the full Einstein evolution equations with proper "Scri" behavior at infinity. We showed that the conformal method can be adapted to construct shear free initial data solutions of the constraint equations.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/20/2019<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;A&nbsp;Isenberg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes     This FRG grant focused on initial data sets for Einstein's gravitational field equations. Such initial data sets must satisfy the Einstein constraint equations, which constitute an underdetermined system of four equations for the metric, the second fundamental form, and relevant matter fields. For initial data sets which have constant mean curvature, the conformal method has been very effective for constructing and parameterizing the space of solutions of the Einstein constraint equations. This effectiveness extends to near-constant mean curvature data sets as well. However, for data sets with far from constant mean curvature, the conformal method has significant difficulties. Our FRG grant, in collaboration with Rafe Mazzeo, David Maxwell, Michael Holst, James Dilts, Paul Allen, Iva Stavrov, and Jack Lee, explored these difficulties extensively, both analytically and numerically.  We also spent considerable effort seeking alternatives to the conformal method. Our results show that for many sets of "seed data", the conformal method has either many solutions or no solutions. We also studied blow up behavior near the seed data with many or no solutions.  This FRG grant also supported research focused on asymptotically hyperbolic data sets which are "shear free". This condition is necessary for the data to generate solutions of the full Einstein evolution equations with proper "Scri" behavior at infinity. We showed that the conformal method can be adapted to construct shear free initial data solutions of the constraint equations.       Last Modified: 08/20/2019       Submitted by: James A Isenberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
