<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site:  The Environmental and Earth Systems Research Experiences for Undergraduates Program at Biosphere</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>405000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>475756</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030203</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aisha Morris</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>armorris@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927081</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Biosphere 2 Research Education for Undergraduates site: the Environmental and Earth Systems Research at Biosphere 2 (B2- EESR REU) program leverages the unique nature of the University of Arizona Biosphere 2 (B2). B2 serves as a laboratory for controlled scientific studies that monitor global environmental change and that allow integration across spatial and temporal scales. The goals for students in this summer REU program are to: (1) develop research skills; (2) experience the cross-disciplinary collaborations that characterize work in Earth system science;  (3) develop an understanding of practical aspects of pursuing a career in science, including the nature of graduate school., and (4) receive training and experience communicating research to the public. Research projects conducted through this program contribute to an interdisciplinary understanding of the Earth system with particular focus on the critical zone, how ecosystems respond to environmental variation and anthropogenic change, and how physical and biological elements of systems are integrated. Projects draw from several disciplines, including, ecology, biology, geosciences, hydrology, soil science, climate and atmospheric sciences.  Students work with a faculty mentor on an individual field or laboratory project, participate in weekly training sessions on career skills, and present their research to the public and scientific peers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This REU site investigates the responses of the Earth's ecosystems to variation and human-induced changes by linking physical and biological processes and linking model and real-world systems. Through active research, students learn first-hand how model and real world systems are used to generate scientific understanding.  The program trains the next generation of scientists to tackle environmental issues with necessary skills that bridge disciplines and with the ability to communicate research findings to the public and policy makers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The REU site is co-funded by the Department of Defense in partnership with the NSF REU program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/25/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1263251</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katerina</FirstName>
<LastName>Dontsova</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katerina Dontsova</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dontsova@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206266000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000536865</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katerina</FirstName>
<LastName>Dontsova</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katerina Dontsova</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dontsova@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206266000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000536865</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/25/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/03/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mitchell</FirstName>
<LastName>Pavao Zuckerman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mitchell Pavao Zuckerman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mpzucker@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014051178</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000154564</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/25/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/03/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072459266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Oracle</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>856230001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[32540 S. Biosphere Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1575</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>L644</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>N532</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O266</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7736</Code>
<Text>DOD ASSURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~133728</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~134996</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~136276</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~70756</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) programs allow students to explore the exciting and creative world of scientific research as potential future career. This short report covers the multi-year renewal of the REU site at Biosphere 2: &nbsp;Environmental and Earth Systems Research. The site allows undergraduate students with limited opportunities to do research at their home institutions to conduct 10-week guided summer research at Biosphere 2, on the University of Arizona campus, and at field sites around Tucson including the Jemez Basin and Santa Catalina Critical Zone Observatory.&nbsp; Biosphere 2 is a unique research facility for experimentation at large scales with high levels of control and measurement. The flagship project at Biosphere 2 is LEO, the Landscape Evolution Observatory with three highly instrumented model watersheds for examining the movement of water and dissolved matter on the hillslopes and biological and abiotic processes that remove carbon from the atmosphere, combatting climate change.</p> <p>The goal of the REU program at Biosphere 2 is for students to develop research skills; improve their understanding of Earth systems science and interdisciplinary collaborations in this broad area of research; develop relationships with faculty working in the scientific field; develop lasting relationships with their peers and future colleagues; become exposed to practical aspects of pursuing a career in science; and learn to clearly communicate science to different audiences.</p> <p>Students work on research projects with their faculty mentors, postdoctoral scientists, and graduate students working in their labs, and participate in professional development activities. They learn about their area of science inquiry and other related disciplines through their research and weekly seminars. Daily interactions with graduate students inform expectations about graduate school and focused workshops teach them how to apply effectively to graduate school. Training activities and practice allow participating students to learn best practices for public speaking and communicating scientific information. Biosphere 2 has 100,000 public visitors annually, and an additional 10,000 K-12 school children, giving students the opportunity to practice and hone communication skills.</p> <p>Students live on the Biosphere 2 campus adjacent to the Santa Catalina Mountains in the scenic Sonoran Desert upland habitat, providing an opportunity to develop close friendships and build a strong, supportive cohort. Students also take advantage of UArizona Undergraduate Research Opportunities Consortium (UROC) activities providing interactions with scores of other undergraduate students immersed in research on the University of Arizona campus.</p> <p>The summer concludes with a poster presentation symposium that unites undergraduate students participating in research from across the University of Arizona campus under the UROC umbrella and recognizes all their summer achievements. Later in the fall or spring, all participating Biosphere 2 REU students have a funded opportunity to present their work at the scientific meeting of their choice, with the majority of students choosing the American Geophysical Union annual meeting.</p> <p>Thirty four students were supported directly by the grant and nine more were partially supported in conjunction with other sources of funding between 2013 and 2016.&nbsp; Over the four years of the program, sixty percent of the summer REU participants came from institutions without graduate programs or significant opportunities for research, including community colleges; and about half of the students were minority students including Hispanic, Indigenous, and African American students. We were successful in increasing the number of minority students participating in the program compared to the 1<sup>st</sup> grant for the site (2010-2012).&nbsp; As the Biosphere 2 summer research program continues, an increasing number of participating students graduate, are being accepted into graduate programs, start careers in STEM, and get faculty positions in the sciences. The Biosphere 2 REU program trains the next generation of diverse scientists entering the workforce who are aware of the close interactions between disciplines in Environmental and Earth Systems Science and are able to communicate science to both scientific and non-scientific audiences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Katerina&nbsp;Dontsova</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588224080844_IMG_3720--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588224080844_IMG_3720--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2016 cohort at the end of program event"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588224080844_IMG_3720--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2016 cohort at the end of program event"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2016 cohort at the end of program event</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kevin Bonine</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Katerina&nbsp;Dontsova</div> <div class="imageTitle">2016 cohort at the end of program event</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588205931653_IMG_3158--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588205931653_IMG_3158--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Alana Dixon, a member of the 2015 cohort, presenting her outreach project to Biosphere 2 visitor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588205931653_IMG_3158--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Alana Dixon, a member of the 2015 cohort, presenting her outreach project to Biosphere 2 visitor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Alana Dixon, a member of the 2015 cohort, presenting her outreach project to Biosphere 2 visitor</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mitchell Pavao-Zuckerman</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Katerina&nbsp;Dontsova</div> <div class="imageTitle">Alana Dixon, a member of the 2015 cohort, presenting her outreach project to Biosphere 2 visitor</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588224172471_JanePoynter1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588224172471_JanePoynter1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Meeting with Jane Poynter, one of the original Biospherians"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588224172471_JanePoynter1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Meeting with Jane Poynter, one of the original Biospherians"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Meeting with Jane Poynter, one of the original Biospherians</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kevin Bonine</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Katerina&nbsp;Dontsova</div> <div class="imageTitle">Meeting with Jane Poynter, one of the original Biospherians</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588224347008_2015cohortattheUROCevent--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588224347008_2015cohortattheUROCevent--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2015 cohort at the Undergraduate Research Opportunities Consortium  event"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588224347008_2015cohortattheUROCevent--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2015 cohort at the Undergraduate Research Opportunities Consortium  event"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2015 cohort at the Undergraduate Research Opportunities Consortium event</div> <div class="imageCredit">Donna Treloar</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Katerina&nbsp;Dontsova</div> <div class="imageTitle">2015 cohort at the Undergraduate Research Opportunities Consortium  event</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588228911131_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588228911131_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Biosphere 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1263251/1263251_10242668_1588228911131_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Biosphere 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Biosphere 2</div> <div class="imageCredit">Biosphere 2</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Katerina&nbsp;Dontsova</div> <div class="imageTitle">Biosphere 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1263251/1263251_10242668_1534536890875_IMG_3654-2016--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1263251/1263251_10242668_1534536890875_IMG_3654-2016--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Students presenting their work at the 2016 Undergraduate Research Opportunities Consortium  symposium"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1263251/1263251_10242668_1534536890875_IMG_3654-2016--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Students presenting their work at the 2016 Undergraduate Research Opportunities Consortium  symposium"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students presenting their work at the 2016 Undergraduate Research Opportunities Consortium symposium</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kevin Bonine</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Katerina&nbsp;Dontsova</div> <div class="imageTitle">Students presenting their work at the 2016 Undergraduate Research Opportunities Consortium  symposium</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) programs allow students to explore the exciting and creative world of scientific research as potential future career. This short report covers the multi-year renewal of the REU site at Biosphere 2:  Environmental and Earth Systems Research. The site allows undergraduate students with limited opportunities to do research at their home institutions to conduct 10-week guided summer research at Biosphere 2, on the University of Arizona campus, and at field sites around Tucson including the Jemez Basin and Santa Catalina Critical Zone Observatory.  Biosphere 2 is a unique research facility for experimentation at large scales with high levels of control and measurement. The flagship project at Biosphere 2 is LEO, the Landscape Evolution Observatory with three highly instrumented model watersheds for examining the movement of water and dissolved matter on the hillslopes and biological and abiotic processes that remove carbon from the atmosphere, combatting climate change.  The goal of the REU program at Biosphere 2 is for students to develop research skills; improve their understanding of Earth systems science and interdisciplinary collaborations in this broad area of research; develop relationships with faculty working in the scientific field; develop lasting relationships with their peers and future colleagues; become exposed to practical aspects of pursuing a career in science; and learn to clearly communicate science to different audiences.  Students work on research projects with their faculty mentors, postdoctoral scientists, and graduate students working in their labs, and participate in professional development activities. They learn about their area of science inquiry and other related disciplines through their research and weekly seminars. Daily interactions with graduate students inform expectations about graduate school and focused workshops teach them how to apply effectively to graduate school. Training activities and practice allow participating students to learn best practices for public speaking and communicating scientific information. Biosphere 2 has 100,000 public visitors annually, and an additional 10,000 K-12 school children, giving students the opportunity to practice and hone communication skills.  Students live on the Biosphere 2 campus adjacent to the Santa Catalina Mountains in the scenic Sonoran Desert upland habitat, providing an opportunity to develop close friendships and build a strong, supportive cohort. Students also take advantage of UArizona Undergraduate Research Opportunities Consortium (UROC) activities providing interactions with scores of other undergraduate students immersed in research on the University of Arizona campus.  The summer concludes with a poster presentation symposium that unites undergraduate students participating in research from across the University of Arizona campus under the UROC umbrella and recognizes all their summer achievements. Later in the fall or spring, all participating Biosphere 2 REU students have a funded opportunity to present their work at the scientific meeting of their choice, with the majority of students choosing the American Geophysical Union annual meeting.  Thirty four students were supported directly by the grant and nine more were partially supported in conjunction with other sources of funding between 2013 and 2016.  Over the four years of the program, sixty percent of the summer REU participants came from institutions without graduate programs or significant opportunities for research, including community colleges; and about half of the students were minority students including Hispanic, Indigenous, and African American students. We were successful in increasing the number of minority students participating in the program compared to the 1st grant for the site (2010-2012).  As the Biosphere 2 summer research program continues, an increasing number of participating students graduate, are being accepted into graduate programs, start careers in STEM, and get faculty positions in the sciences. The Biosphere 2 REU program trains the next generation of diverse scientists entering the workforce who are aware of the close interactions between disciplines in Environmental and Earth Systems Science and are able to communicate science to both scientific and non-scientific audiences.          Last Modified: 04/30/2020       Submitted by: Katerina Dontsova]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
