<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Studies of Magnetosphere-Ionosphere Coupling and Space Weather Using the Magnetometer Array for Cusp and Cleft Studies (MACCS)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>425919.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>428949</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020202</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Meriwether</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmeriwet@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927212</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project consists of two activities. The first will continue the operation and data distribution of observations from the Magnetometer Array for Cusp and Cleft Studies (MACCS). The second is a research program using the MACCS data along with SuperDARN radar, the Relocatable Atmospheric Observatory in Resolute Bay, nominally conjugate stations in the Antarctic and GPS TEC receivers at two of the MACCS sites. Data from the AMPERE satellites also will be used. The proposal identifies four topics:  &lt;br/&gt;* Performing detailed studies of dayside high-latitude ULF waves and transient events, using multi-instrument ground-based and satellite data. &lt;br/&gt;* Providing observational and theoretical support for the recently-launched Radiation Belt Storm Probes mission by investigating the role of ULF waves in energizing or depleting radiation belt electrons during magnetic storms, in part using the recently developed ULF index. &lt;br/&gt;* Investigating the high-latitude field-aligned current structures associated with both transient events and steady convection, using magnetic field and GPS TEC data along with global data from the AMPERE project. &lt;br/&gt;* Using the combination of MACCS data with simultaneous data from both low-orbiting and high-orbiting satellites to separate spatial and temporal variations in magnetospheric and ionospheric processes, and carrying out theoretical and modeling studies of the excitation and propagation of ULF waves through the global magnetosphere-ionosphere system. This study will use the BATS-R-US global magnetohydrodynamic simulation code. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The MAACS data are freely distributed to the entire science community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1264146</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Engebretson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark J Engebretson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>engebret@augsburg.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7634129743</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000380464</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Viacheslav</FirstName>
<LastName>Pilipenko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Viacheslav A Pilipenko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pilipenk@augsburg.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>0954383985</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000164854</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Murr</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David L Murr</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>murrdl@augsburg.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6123301068</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000382585</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Augsburg University</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554541338</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6123301184</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2211 Riverside Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078679347</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AUGSBURG UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>078679347</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Augsburg College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554541338</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5750</Code>
<Text>MAGNETOSPHERIC PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~149721</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~140651</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~138577</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>NSF Grant AGS-1264146, awarded to Augsburg College, together with NSF Grant AGS-1265651, awarded to the University of Michigan, continued collaborative efforts to operate and distribute data from the Magnetometer Array for Cusp and Cleft Studies (MACCS), a longitudinal array of fluxgate magnetometers covering the eastern Canadian Arctic region at high latitudes (75-85&deg;N), and use magnetic field data from this and other magnetometer arrays to study Earth&rsquo;s space environment.&nbsp; MACCS has contributed to the study of ultra-low frequency (ULF) waves and transients at these extreme latitudes as well as to large cooperative studies of magnetosphere-ionosphere coupling, ionospheric convection, and magnetic storm and substorm processes.&nbsp; MACCS data are freely distributed to the entire science community.&nbsp;</p> <p>During the period of this grant members of the Augsburg team were first authors of 7 published refereed papers and were co-authors of 6 more.&nbsp; Highlights include a theoretical study of several possible mechanisms for the ULF modulation of ionospheric total electron content, which is now routinely monitored using GPS receivers [Pilipenko et al., 2014], an ongoing series of empirical modeling studies of the dependence of relativistic electron fluxes in the outer Van Allen radiation belts on ULF waves and other factors in Earth&rsquo;s magnetosphere and in the solar wind [Simms et al., 2014, 2015, 2016, and two studies submitted for publication in late 2017], and a coupled set of theoretical and observational papers showing a close relation between the location of long-period resonant ULF waves and the auroral oval [Pilipenko et al., 2017, Kozyreva et al., 2017].&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;J&nbsp;Engebretson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF Grant AGS-1264146, awarded to Augsburg College, together with NSF Grant AGS-1265651, awarded to the University of Michigan, continued collaborative efforts to operate and distribute data from the Magnetometer Array for Cusp and Cleft Studies (MACCS), a longitudinal array of fluxgate magnetometers covering the eastern Canadian Arctic region at high latitudes (75-85&deg;N), and use magnetic field data from this and other magnetometer arrays to study Earth?s space environment.  MACCS has contributed to the study of ultra-low frequency (ULF) waves and transients at these extreme latitudes as well as to large cooperative studies of magnetosphere-ionosphere coupling, ionospheric convection, and magnetic storm and substorm processes.  MACCS data are freely distributed to the entire science community.   During the period of this grant members of the Augsburg team were first authors of 7 published refereed papers and were co-authors of 6 more.  Highlights include a theoretical study of several possible mechanisms for the ULF modulation of ionospheric total electron content, which is now routinely monitored using GPS receivers [Pilipenko et al., 2014], an ongoing series of empirical modeling studies of the dependence of relativistic electron fluxes in the outer Van Allen radiation belts on ULF waves and other factors in Earth?s magnetosphere and in the solar wind [Simms et al., 2014, 2015, 2016, and two studies submitted for publication in late 2017], and a coupled set of theoretical and observational papers showing a close relation between the location of long-period resonant ULF waves and the auroral oval [Pilipenko et al., 2017, Kozyreva et al., 2017].        Last Modified: 02/01/2018       Submitted by: Mark J Engebretson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
