<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Fundamentals of biomass upgrading to fuels and chemicals over catalytic bimetallic nanoparticles</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199985.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>211985</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccabe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924826</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;#1264453&lt;br/&gt;Simon G. Podkolzin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Promising new technologies for biomass conversion into fuels and chemical feedstocks rely on production of bio-oils, which need to be upgraded in order to remove oxygen from oxygen-containing organic molecules such as organic acids and phenols. A high oxygen concentration makes bio-oils acidic and corrosive, unstable during storage, and less energetically valuable per unit weight than petroleum-derived hydrocarbons. Although there are effective commercializable processes for the production of bio-oils, there are no efficient catalytic commercializable technologies for their upgrading. Current research and development technologies have started with traditional petroleum refining catalysts, which are not optimized for biomass processing, and as a result, are not very effective.  New catalytic upgrading technologies are, therefore, urgently needed for the successful development of sustainable energy resources. Parallels may be sought with petroleum refining processes, where catalyst advances, such as using bimetallic or multimetallic catalysts, have led to very efficient delivery of low contaminant fuels. Development of such new catalytic technologies for bio-oils, however, is severely hindered by a lack of fundamental understanding of how oxygen-containing hydrocarbons derived from biomass interact with promising bimetallic catalysts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The National Science Foundation  Catalysis &amp; Biocatalysis Program will make an award to fund a collaborative effort between Professors Simon Podkolzin and Adeniyi Lawal of Stevens Institute of Technology, Hoboken, NJ, and Professor Bruce Koel of Princeton University to advance the molecular-level understanding of how oxygen-containing molecules from bio-oils adsorb and react on catalytic bimetallic nanoparticles. The obtained fundamentals will be used to identify: (a) preferred chemistries for bio-oil upgrading, (b) improved catalyst formulations, and (c) optimized reaction conditions. The program will synergistically combine single-crystal surface science experiments, characterization and testing of supported metal catalysts, and quantum-chemical calculations with vibrational analyses for interpretation of experimental vibrational spectra and transition state calculations for reaction mechanisms studies. Recognizing that many studies are being funded in this area, research will be conducted in close cooperation with Department of Energy biomass conversion programs at the Institute for Integrated Catalysis operating within the Pacific Northwest National Laboratory. This should result in reduced duplication of efforts and synergy in moving to successful achievement of biomass conversion efforts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This collaborative project will establish one basis for the transformative development of new efficient and environmentally friendly technologies for the production of renewable energy and chemical industry feedstocks. The fundamental and applied knowledge from this research will advance the rational design of catalytic nanomaterials and, more widely, will benefit highly diverse and rapidly developing technologies that vitally rely on the interaction between oxygen-containing organic molecules and metal nanoparticles, ranging from sensors to medical diagnostics, and from drug delivery to fuel cells. The researchers will be engaged in several undergraduate and K-12 educational outreach programs. For example, the investigators will develop teaching modules on metal nanoparticles for green chemistry and sustainability which they will use in a summer camp for more than 300 high school students from across the U.S.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1264453</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adeniyi</FirstName>
<LastName>Lawal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adeniyi Lawal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alawal@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2012168241</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000101053</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Simon</FirstName>
<LastName>Podkolzin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Simon G Podkolzin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Simon.Podkolzin@Stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2012168074</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000519288</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stevens Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>HOBOKEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>070305991</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2012168762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CASTLE POINT ON HUDSON</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064271570</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>STEVENS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (INC)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>064271570</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stevens Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Hoboken</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>070305991</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Castle Point on Hudson]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>044E</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~199985</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Promising new technologies for biomass conversion into fuels and chemical feedstocks rely on production of bio-oils, which need to be upgraded in order to remove oxygen-containing hydrocarbons and water. A high oxygen concentration makes bio-oils acidic and corrosive, unstable during storage, and less energetically valuable per unit weight than petroleum-derived hydrocarbons. Although there are efficient processes for the production of bio-oils, there are no efficient technologies for their upgrading. Current technologies utilize traditional petroleum refining catalysts, which are not optimized for biomass processing. New upgrading technologies are, therefore, urgently needed for development of sustainable energy resources. Development of such new technologies, however, is severely hindered by a lack of fundamental understanding of how oxygen and oxygen-containing hydrocarbons derived from biomass interact with promising metal catalysts. In this study, kinetic reaction measurements, catalyst characterization and quantum chemical calculations using density functional theory were combined for determining adsorption modes and reaction mechanisms of hydrocarbons in the presence of oxygen on surfaces of catalytic metal nanoparticles. The results show for the first time that addition of molybdenum to platinum catalysts has a synergistic effect in catalytic hydrodeoxygenation of acetic acid, which serves as a model biomass compound. While molybdenum catalysts have negligible activity, addition of molybdenum to platinum significantly improves catalytic activity, selectivity and stability. The results were used for developing improved catalyst formulations and for optimization of reaction conditions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The fundamental results that describe interactions of oxygen and hydrocarbons with metal catalysts were extended to other reactions and fields of study. A new reaction mechanism was identified that better describes hydrocarbon reactions with hydrogen (hydrogenation, dehydrogenation and hydrogen transfer) on pure platinum and platinum-bimetallic catalytic surfaces. In addition, carbon monoxide surface species on cobalt catalysts widely used in the conversion of synthesis gas into valuable hydrocarbon products were identified under reaction conditions. The newly obtained results demonstrate at the molecular level how bimetallic catalytic surfaces can be altered in order to tune the properties of catalytic sites and change reaction mechanisms. The effect of adsorbed oxygen and changing the extent of surface oxidation for catalytic metals was clarified with a spectroscopic probe using ultra-high sensitive experimental measurements and quantum-chemical calculations. The experimental and computational studies of oxygen and hydrocarbon adsorption on multiple metal surfaces were further extended to water formation and adsorption. These additional studies identified preferential mechanisms of water formation and showed how these mechanisms change in the presence of gas-phase hydrogen and hydrocarbon.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The obtained information about supported metal nanoparticles, oxygen and hydrocarbon adsorption modes and their dependences on the extent of metal surface oxidation and adsorbate coverage is useful beyond catalysis and technologies for biomass conversion into fuels and chemicals. The project results are useful in the development of ultra-sensitive spectroscopic sensor applications and in synthesis and characterization of nanomaterials. Moreover, the newly obtained information on adsorption and reactivity of oxygen species on surfaces of metal nanoparticles is of fundamental importance in multiple and diverse areas of science and technology. The identification of oxygen species on catalytic metal nanoparticles and description of their properties will have a direct impact on the development of improved techniques for bio imaging of living cells, better understanding of spin-flip scattering processes of itinerant electrons in solid-state physics, advancing optical detection methods at the single-molecule level at room temperature, and in the development of improved lithium batteries.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project results were presented at multiple national and international conferences and published in high-impact peer-reviewed journals. The project provided opportunities for training, development and mentoring of graduate and undergraduate students. In addition, high school students learned about challenges and research activities in sustainable and renewable energy through educational outreach programs. The outreach programs included lectures as well as hands-on experimental and computational training modules.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/01/2017<br>      Modified by: Simon G.&nbsp;Podkolzin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Promising new technologies for biomass conversion into fuels and chemical feedstocks rely on production of bio-oils, which need to be upgraded in order to remove oxygen-containing hydrocarbons and water. A high oxygen concentration makes bio-oils acidic and corrosive, unstable during storage, and less energetically valuable per unit weight than petroleum-derived hydrocarbons. Although there are efficient processes for the production of bio-oils, there are no efficient technologies for their upgrading. Current technologies utilize traditional petroleum refining catalysts, which are not optimized for biomass processing. New upgrading technologies are, therefore, urgently needed for development of sustainable energy resources. Development of such new technologies, however, is severely hindered by a lack of fundamental understanding of how oxygen and oxygen-containing hydrocarbons derived from biomass interact with promising metal catalysts. In this study, kinetic reaction measurements, catalyst characterization and quantum chemical calculations using density functional theory were combined for determining adsorption modes and reaction mechanisms of hydrocarbons in the presence of oxygen on surfaces of catalytic metal nanoparticles. The results show for the first time that addition of molybdenum to platinum catalysts has a synergistic effect in catalytic hydrodeoxygenation of acetic acid, which serves as a model biomass compound. While molybdenum catalysts have negligible activity, addition of molybdenum to platinum significantly improves catalytic activity, selectivity and stability. The results were used for developing improved catalyst formulations and for optimization of reaction conditions.     The fundamental results that describe interactions of oxygen and hydrocarbons with metal catalysts were extended to other reactions and fields of study. A new reaction mechanism was identified that better describes hydrocarbon reactions with hydrogen (hydrogenation, dehydrogenation and hydrogen transfer) on pure platinum and platinum-bimetallic catalytic surfaces. In addition, carbon monoxide surface species on cobalt catalysts widely used in the conversion of synthesis gas into valuable hydrocarbon products were identified under reaction conditions. The newly obtained results demonstrate at the molecular level how bimetallic catalytic surfaces can be altered in order to tune the properties of catalytic sites and change reaction mechanisms. The effect of adsorbed oxygen and changing the extent of surface oxidation for catalytic metals was clarified with a spectroscopic probe using ultra-high sensitive experimental measurements and quantum-chemical calculations. The experimental and computational studies of oxygen and hydrocarbon adsorption on multiple metal surfaces were further extended to water formation and adsorption. These additional studies identified preferential mechanisms of water formation and showed how these mechanisms change in the presence of gas-phase hydrogen and hydrocarbon.     The obtained information about supported metal nanoparticles, oxygen and hydrocarbon adsorption modes and their dependences on the extent of metal surface oxidation and adsorbate coverage is useful beyond catalysis and technologies for biomass conversion into fuels and chemicals. The project results are useful in the development of ultra-sensitive spectroscopic sensor applications and in synthesis and characterization of nanomaterials. Moreover, the newly obtained information on adsorption and reactivity of oxygen species on surfaces of metal nanoparticles is of fundamental importance in multiple and diverse areas of science and technology. The identification of oxygen species on catalytic metal nanoparticles and description of their properties will have a direct impact on the development of improved techniques for bio imaging of living cells, better understanding of spin-flip scattering processes of itinerant electrons in solid-state physics, advancing optical detection methods at the single-molecule level at room temperature, and in the development of improved lithium batteries.     The project results were presented at multiple national and international conferences and published in high-impact peer-reviewed journals. The project provided opportunities for training, development and mentoring of graduate and undergraduate students. In addition, high school students learned about challenges and research activities in sustainable and renewable energy through educational outreach programs. The outreach programs included lectures as well as hands-on experimental and computational training modules.       Last Modified: 05/01/2017       Submitted by: Simon G. Podkolzin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
