<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference:   Keystone Symposium on "Precision Genome Engineering and Synthetic Biology" to be held in Breckenridge, CO from March 17-22, 2013</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>8400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>8400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070700</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Susanne von Bodman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI David Woodland, Keystone Symposia on Molecular and Cellular Biology&lt;br/&gt;Title: Conference: Keystone Symposium on "Precision Genome Engineering and Synthetic Biology" to be held in Breckenridge, CO from March 17-22, 2013&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Keystone Symposia conference on Precision Genome Engineering and Synthetic Biology: Designing Genomes and Pathways will bring together scientists who: 1) develop tools for precision genome engineering; 2) use those tools for specific purposes in a wide range of organisms, including humans; 3) create whole synthetic genomes with prospects for wholesale reengineering; and 4) engineering cells with novel pathways and properties. Exchange of cutting-edge information regarding approaches, accomplishments and ambitions will augment the capabilities of each group. The meeting will provide an outstanding forum for students, postdoctoral fellows, and senior investigators who envision careers in genome and pathway design.&lt;br/&gt;The specific objectives of this meeting are as follows: 1. To collect leaders in genome engineering and synthetic biology and make them aware of current technologies and opportunities. 2. To stimulate ongoing interactions and collaborations between these disciplines. 3. To encourage the development of new approaches that will accelerate progress in the target areas. 4. To enlist trainees into these emerging fields, so they will drive future uses and developments. Intellectual merit: Both precision genome engineering and synthetic biology are relatively new fields of research that are developing rapidly, but largely independently of each other. This meeting is designed to bring together the goals, approaches, technologies and leaders in these areas to encourage cross-fertilization and collaboration. Keystone Symposia provides an internationally recognized platform as well as resources to ensure the success of this meeting, and the organizers are well-recognized leaders in the fields of genome engineering and synthetic biology. Broader Impacts: This meeting aims to encourage extension of pathway engineering into a broader range of organisms through genome editing and to stimulate the development of expanded tools of genome manipulation for multi-gene modifications. Moreover, this meeting will enhance infrastructure by fostering networking and initiation of collaborations. The following educational benefits are anticipated: acquaint trainees and investigators new to the field with the state-of-the-art; critical scientific feedback; and career development for trainees and new investigators, including opportunities both to see successful scientists presenting cutting-edge science and to network with prospective mentors and others who might contribute to their scientific and professional development.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1265353</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Woodland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Woodland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>davidw@keystonesymposia.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9702621230</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000627052</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Keystone Symposia on Molecular and Cellular Biology</Name>
<CityName>Silverthorne</CityName>
<ZipCode>804981630</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9702621230</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>PO Box 1630</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079780750</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KEYSTONE SYMPOSIA ON MOLECULAR AND CELLULAR BIOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Beaver Run Resort]]></Name>
<CityName>Breckenridge</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>804242115</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[620 Village Road, P.O.B. 2115]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~8400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;The Keystone Symposia meeting on &ldquo;Precision Genome Engineering and Synthetic Biology: Designing Genomes and Pathways&rdquo; was conceived and organized around the central goal of bringing together scientists who are: 1) developing tools for precision genome engineering; 2) using those tools for specific purposes in a wide range of organisms, including humans; 3) creating whole synthetic genomes with prospects for wholesale reengineering; and 4) engineering cells with novel pathways and properties.&nbsp; This 4-day meeting was designed to foster innovation at the interface of disciplines by bridging methodological and disciplinary boundaries, and gathered physical scientists, applying biophysical approaches to complex systems, and biologists, seeking deeper mechanistic understanding of fundamental cellular processes.&nbsp; Plenary and short talks, workshops, poster sessions and unstructured informal discussions were all used to address key issues in synthetic biology and genome engineering research.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;More specifically, the meeting program<em> </em>explicitly encouraged participants to consider the extension of pathway engineering into a broader range of organisms through genome editing, with the aim of stimulating the development of expanded tools of genome manipulation for multi-gene modifications. &nbsp;Applications to both permanent gene modification and to transient control of gene expression were emphasized.&nbsp; And, while some talks emphasized technology development, the principal focus of the meeting was on the results that have been obtained and the long-term goals of biological engineering.&nbsp; Thus, the meeting provided a unique forum for scientists working in genome engineering and synthetic biology, and sought to foster enduring interactions and collaborations between these disciplines.&nbsp; We anticipated that the conference would lead to unanticipated creative collisions between biologists and engineers, <em>in silico</em> designers, genome precision slicers and genome synthesizers.&nbsp; Indeed, 77% of post-conference survey respondents agreed that &ldquo;I made a contact at this conference that I anticipate will lead to a collaboration or sharing of information, data or techniques&rdquo;.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;There were 228 total attendees at the meeting.&nbsp; Attendees at this meeting were diverse with regard to gender, ethnicity, stage of career, and institutional affiliation.&nbsp; More specifically, 20% of the meeting participants were female researchers, and ~2% of all attendees (or ~4% of attendees who were US citizens or permanent residents) self-identified as scientists from under-represented minority groups.&nbsp; The meeting was highly international, drawing 36% non-US attendees.&nbsp; Approximately 30% of attendees were students and postdoctoral fellows.&nbsp; The meeting provided ample opportunity for training and professional development.&nbsp; Trainees and newer investigators were exposed to dozens of high-quality oral presentations by more senior investigators, who served as models for high-quality research and communication skills.&nbsp; Plenary sessions also included short talks drawn from submitted abstracts and the majority of the presenters were students, postdoctoral trainees and newer investigators (e.g., Rachel Haurwitz, Ahmad Khalil, Marcus Noyes).&nbsp; In addition, two workshops featured presentations by junior investigators (e.g., Thomas Armel, Kamila Gwiazda, Andrew Mercer).&nbsp; Two poster sessions provided opportunities for trainees and newer investigators to share their research and to discuss this research with more experienced investigators.&nbsp; Finally, the unstructured portions of the meeting and the retreat-like venue provided significant and generous opportunities for productive informal interactions between trainees, newer invest...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      The Keystone Symposia meeting on "Precision Genome Engineering and Synthetic Biology: Designing Genomes and Pathways" was conceived and organized around the central goal of bringing together scientists who are: 1) developing tools for precision genome engineering; 2) using those tools for specific purposes in a wide range of organisms, including humans; 3) creating whole synthetic genomes with prospects for wholesale reengineering; and 4) engineering cells with novel pathways and properties.  This 4-day meeting was designed to foster innovation at the interface of disciplines by bridging methodological and disciplinary boundaries, and gathered physical scientists, applying biophysical approaches to complex systems, and biologists, seeking deeper mechanistic understanding of fundamental cellular processes.  Plenary and short talks, workshops, poster sessions and unstructured informal discussions were all used to address key issues in synthetic biology and genome engineering research.         More specifically, the meeting program explicitly encouraged participants to consider the extension of pathway engineering into a broader range of organisms through genome editing, with the aim of stimulating the development of expanded tools of genome manipulation for multi-gene modifications.  Applications to both permanent gene modification and to transient control of gene expression were emphasized.  And, while some talks emphasized technology development, the principal focus of the meeting was on the results that have been obtained and the long-term goals of biological engineering.  Thus, the meeting provided a unique forum for scientists working in genome engineering and synthetic biology, and sought to foster enduring interactions and collaborations between these disciplines.  We anticipated that the conference would lead to unanticipated creative collisions between biologists and engineers, in silico designers, genome precision slicers and genome synthesizers.  Indeed, 77% of post-conference survey respondents agreed that "I made a contact at this conference that I anticipate will lead to a collaboration or sharing of information, data or techniques".        There were 228 total attendees at the meeting.  Attendees at this meeting were diverse with regard to gender, ethnicity, stage of career, and institutional affiliation.  More specifically, 20% of the meeting participants were female researchers, and ~2% of all attendees (or ~4% of attendees who were US citizens or permanent residents) self-identified as scientists from under-represented minority groups.  The meeting was highly international, drawing 36% non-US attendees.  Approximately 30% of attendees were students and postdoctoral fellows.  The meeting provided ample opportunity for training and professional development.  Trainees and newer investigators were exposed to dozens of high-quality oral presentations by more senior investigators, who served as models for high-quality research and communication skills.  Plenary sessions also included short talks drawn from submitted abstracts and the majority of the presenters were students, postdoctoral trainees and newer investigators (e.g., Rachel Haurwitz, Ahmad Khalil, Marcus Noyes).  In addition, two workshops featured presentations by junior investigators (e.g., Thomas Armel, Kamila Gwiazda, Andrew Mercer).  Two poster sessions provided opportunities for trainees and newer investigators to share their research and to discuss this research with more experienced investigators.  Finally, the unstructured portions of the meeting and the retreat-like venue provided significant and generous opportunities for productive informal interactions between trainees, newer investigators and more senior investigators.          We assessed outcomes with regard to attendee perceptions of the quality and impact of this meeting through post-conference surveys sent via email.  We received responses from 75 (33%) attendees.  The survey result...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
