<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: SI2-CHE:Developing First Principles Monte Carlo Methods for Reactive Phase and Sorption Equilibria in the CP2k Software Suite</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>137775.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>137775</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Evelyn Goldfield</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>egoldfie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An international research team consisting of Ilja Siepmann, Ben Lynch (University of Minnesota), Neeraj Rai (Mississippi State University), Troy Van Voorhis (Massachusetts Institute of Technology), Ben Slater (University College London), Michiel Sprik (University of Cambridge), Adam Carter (Edinburgh Parallel Computing Centre), Jürg Hutter (University of Zurich), I-Feng Kuo (Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory), Christopher Mundy (Pacific Northwest National Laboratory), Joost VandeVondele (ETH Zurich), and Rodolphe Vuilleumier (University Pierre &amp; Marie Curie Paris) is collaborating to develop and implement new theoretical methods in the CP2K computational chemistry software suite.  These new methodologies enable the predictive modeling of reactive multi-phase systems, including free energy landscapes and product yields, where the system interactions are described by Kohn-Sham density functional theory with van der Waals and hybrid functionals.  Markov chain Monte Carlo approaches utilizing smart moves with asymmetric underlying matrices, such as the aggregation-volume-bias and configurational-bias Monte Carlo methods, and the Gibbs ensemble framework are employed for efficient exploration of the phase space for reactive single- and multi-phase equilibria in bulk and in confinement.  The U.S. based research team is supported jointly by the Chemistry Division in MPS and the Office of Cyberinfrastucture. Funds for the UK based research team are provided by the EPSRC.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The software infrastructure is advanced by the development of efficient and accurate methodologies for reactive phase and sorption equilibria that are applicable to chemical processes in diverse science and engineering applications.  The extensively validated methodologies will be incorporated into the open-source CP2K software suite to make them available to a large user base.  The new software can be used to identify optimal reaction conditions and separation processes for sustainable chemistry.  The collaborative research team plans to use the new software for the investigation of reactive processes that address critical needs of society (fertilizers for food supply, fuels from renewable sources, and environmentally benign chemical processes).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/02/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1265624</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Troy</FirstName>
<LastName>Van Voorhis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Troy Van Voorhis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tvan@MIT.EDU</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172531488</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000270024</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8004</Code>
<Text>Software Institutes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5918</Code>
<Text>FRANCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5946</Code>
<Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5950</Code>
<Text>SWITZERLAND</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8009</Code>
<Text>Scientifc Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~137775</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award was primarily concerned with the computation of sorption equilibria in the condensed phase using hte Cp2K package. As such, the computation of weak intermolecular interactions was extremely important. &nbsp;These ineractions are very difficult to compute using first principles techniques and we developed one of the leading density functionals (VV10) that is designed to accurately describe these forces. &nbsp;Within this proposal, we tested out a new implementation of VV10 (revised VV10, rVV10) in the CP2K program package and found that it was both vastly quicker than the original version would have been and also essentailly as accurate. Thus, accurate intermolecular forces can now be computed using CP2K and these interactions were crucial to subsequent simulations by our collaborators. In particular, this work culminated with a powerful proof-of-principle set of simulations of the reactions of nitrogen and oxygen in compressed vapors. The resulting ab initio predictions agreed well with the experimentally derived data on this complex mixture.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Beyond the direct scientific advances in this project, there were also key contributions made to software development in the freely available CP2K program package. &nbsp;In particular, the code now has both the ability to treat weak intermolecular interactions with rVV10 and also absorption equilibria using the RxFPMC technique. &nbsp;In addition to being freely available, this code has a wide user base and a substaintial supply of documentation online making it an accessible tool for the broader community.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/02/2016<br>      Modified by: Troy&nbsp;Van Voorhis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award was primarily concerned with the computation of sorption equilibria in the condensed phase using hte Cp2K package. As such, the computation of weak intermolecular interactions was extremely important.  These ineractions are very difficult to compute using first principles techniques and we developed one of the leading density functionals (VV10) that is designed to accurately describe these forces.  Within this proposal, we tested out a new implementation of VV10 (revised VV10, rVV10) in the CP2K program package and found that it was both vastly quicker than the original version would have been and also essentailly as accurate. Thus, accurate intermolecular forces can now be computed using CP2K and these interactions were crucial to subsequent simulations by our collaborators. In particular, this work culminated with a powerful proof-of-principle set of simulations of the reactions of nitrogen and oxygen in compressed vapors. The resulting ab initio predictions agreed well with the experimentally derived data on this complex mixture.     Beyond the direct scientific advances in this project, there were also key contributions made to software development in the freely available CP2K program package.  In particular, the code now has both the ability to treat weak intermolecular interactions with rVV10 and also absorption equilibria using the RxFPMC technique.  In addition to being freely available, this code has a wide user base and a substaintial supply of documentation online making it an accessible tool for the broader community.       Last Modified: 12/02/2016       Submitted by: Troy Van Voorhis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
