<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The nonlinear Schrodinger equation, its physical origins, and the spectral measures of random matrices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>236001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>236001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The main purpose of the proposed research is to further the mathematical understanding of several standard simple physical models: the nonlinear Schrodinger equation and its connections to many-body quantum mechanics; the scattering resonances of a random black-box system; and the spectral measure of CMV matrices with random decaying coefficients. A major theme of the NLS portion of the project is to investigate the effect of obstacles.  This is a concrete and challenging model case for the investigation of NLS in general geometries. Examples of dispersive equations that are scaling-critical but on the very cusp of super-criticality will also be investigated; this is an ideal proving ground for existing energy- and mass-critical techniques. Two classes of physically motivated NLS models with combined attractive and repulsive nonlinearities will be investigated.  These models have already started to reveal interesting and unusual variational and dynamical structures that warrant further investigation. Additionally, the distribution of resonances associated to finite dimensional quantum systems (chosen uniformly at random, respecting time-reversal symmetry) will be investigated.  Related methods will be employed to investigate the fine spectral properties for discrete Dirac equations with decaying random potentials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theory of random matrices is driven by empirical data as surely as any physical science: Its roots lie in statistical analysis (specifically, ANOVA) and the analysis of experimental energy-level data. More recently, random matrix statistics have been observed in the vibrations of drums and the behaviour of the prime numbers. The researches of this project are aimed at helping to elucidate and explain the results of these truly mathematical experiments. Although the nonlinear Schrodinger equation is used as a simple effective model for several physical phenomena, the goal of this project is to further our understanding of the behaviour of solutions to this equation principally as a  model for general evolution equations.  As a step towards the vicissitudes of laboratory science/engineering, we will consider evolution in the presence of obstacles and other irregularities as well as incorporating more complicated nonlinear effects that cannot be described by a simple power law.  The training of graduate students as educators and researchers in the mathematical sciences is also a significant portion of the project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1265868</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rowan</FirstName>
<LastName>Killip</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rowan B Killip</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>killip@math.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3102068490</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488125</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951555</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6363 Math Sciences Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~78330</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~78740</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~78931</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The rate and manner in which excited systems relax to their quiescent state can best be expressed in terms of special `energy levels' called resonances. &nbsp;A key outcome of the project was the development of a simplified framework for studying the resonances of complex systems; specifically, those modelled via the classical ensembles of random matrices.</p> <p>The project produced a large body of work (both from PI directly, as well as from his students) on the problem of broken symmetries in the behaviour of dispersive waves. &nbsp;Naturally, the matematical theory of wave motion has a history streaching across several centuries. &nbsp;The specific progress achieved in this project relates to the common assumption that the wave motion takes place in a perfectly flat, homogeneous, unobstructed environment; indeed, such assumptions have played a crucial role in the recent analysis of the class of `scaling-critical' problems. &nbsp;Through the study of carefully selected concrete models, the participants in this project have developed a diverse armory of tools for proceeding in situations without such perfect symmetry.</p> <p><span>The youthful field of symplectic geometry offers profound insight into what motions are possible (or impossible) for a mechanical system (going far beyond mere conservation of energy). &nbsp;This field has focussed most intently on systems with finitely many degrees of freedom. &nbsp;But many physical theories (e.g. electromagnetism &amp; quantum mechanics) can be viewed as instances of Newtonian mechanics with infinitely many degrees of freedom. &nbsp;In a series of two joint papers written as part of this project, the PI has shown how results from symplectic geometry can be adapted to the setting of systems of infinitely many particles moving in a region of infinite expanse.</span></p> <p>The project supported the research and travel of five graduate students (A. Azzam, C. Jao, J. Murphy, S. Xu, and Y. Zhang). &nbsp;Three graduated during this period, all of whom were able to secure prestigious postdoctoral positions on the basis of work performed in the furtherance of this project.</p> <p>Travel (both foreign and domestic) conducted in connection with this project brought the PI into contact with numerous young scientists with whom he exchanged both scientific ideas and career guidance.</p> <p>Minicourses were given on work supported by grant, including one in Beijing and another in Paris.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/10/2016<br>      Modified by: Rowan&nbsp;B&nbsp;Killip</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The rate and manner in which excited systems relax to their quiescent state can best be expressed in terms of special `energy levels' called resonances.  A key outcome of the project was the development of a simplified framework for studying the resonances of complex systems; specifically, those modelled via the classical ensembles of random matrices.  The project produced a large body of work (both from PI directly, as well as from his students) on the problem of broken symmetries in the behaviour of dispersive waves.  Naturally, the matematical theory of wave motion has a history streaching across several centuries.  The specific progress achieved in this project relates to the common assumption that the wave motion takes place in a perfectly flat, homogeneous, unobstructed environment; indeed, such assumptions have played a crucial role in the recent analysis of the class of `scaling-critical' problems.  Through the study of carefully selected concrete models, the participants in this project have developed a diverse armory of tools for proceeding in situations without such perfect symmetry.  The youthful field of symplectic geometry offers profound insight into what motions are possible (or impossible) for a mechanical system (going far beyond mere conservation of energy).  This field has focussed most intently on systems with finitely many degrees of freedom.  But many physical theories (e.g. electromagnetism &amp; quantum mechanics) can be viewed as instances of Newtonian mechanics with infinitely many degrees of freedom.  In a series of two joint papers written as part of this project, the PI has shown how results from symplectic geometry can be adapted to the setting of systems of infinitely many particles moving in a region of infinite expanse.  The project supported the research and travel of five graduate students (A. Azzam, C. Jao, J. Murphy, S. Xu, and Y. Zhang).  Three graduated during this period, all of whom were able to secure prestigious postdoctoral positions on the basis of work performed in the furtherance of this project.  Travel (both foreign and domestic) conducted in connection with this project brought the PI into contact with numerous young scientists with whom he exchanged both scientific ideas and career guidance.  Minicourses were given on work supported by grant, including one in Beijing and another in Paris.       Last Modified: 08/10/2016       Submitted by: Rowan B Killip]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
