<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Low-Lying Zeros of L-functions and Problems in Additive Number Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>135610.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>135610</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI plans on studying several projects on zeros of L-functions, as well as problems in additive number theory. The main research concerns the behavior of zeros near the central point. While these zeros have been known to be related to arithmetic problems since Riemann, in the last few decades connections have been observed with high energy nuclear physics and random matrix theory (RMT) as well. Thus investigations in one of these topics can be fruitfully used in the others. The additive number theory problems have a similar flavor; many of them concern density of states as well as gaps between events. Similar techniques are used in the analysis here as in some of the number theory and random matrix theory investigations. Specifically, the PI proposes to study: (1) the n-level densities of low-lying zeros of GL(2) L-functions (including level 1 Maass forms and increasing the support for holomorphic cuspidal newforms by deriving alternatives to the Katz-Sarnak determinantal expansions that are more amenable for comparing number theory and random matrix theory), (2) the n-level densities of Dirichlet and number field L-functions (which involves exploring and extending our understanding of the finer properties of the distribution of certain classes of primes), (3) finding random matrix theory analogues to Rankin-Selberg convolutions (to extend the predictive ability of RMT), (4) additional consequences of the L-function Ratios Conjecture and other arithmetic conjectures, (5) the density of states and behavior of the eigenvalues of structured random matrix ensembles (with special emphasis on the resulting combinatorics, which is frequently related to other problems of interest), (6) generalized Zeckendorf decompositions and the gaps between summands, (7) generalized sum and difference sets (especially phase transitions from different models of randomness, behavior in subsets of highly structured sets, and results in non-abelian cases), and finally (8) Benford's law of digit bias.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The central questions in this proposal involve studying how events are distributed in diverse systems, such as energy levels of heavy nuclei, prime numbers and zeros of L-functions, leading digits in sets of data, and summands in generalized Zeckendorf decompositions. Similar to the Central Limit Theorem, there seem to be a few universal spacing laws that govern these and other phenomena; thus studies in one of these topics can frequently provide useful insights in the others. Understanding these systems requires the development of tools and techniques in complex analysis, Fourier analysis, number theory and probability. Some of the projects have real world applications; for example, the IRS uses Benford?s law to locate corporate tax fraud. Many of these projects have components that are amenable to numerical experimentation; these and tractable special cases will be investigated with undergraduate research assistants. The PI will also continue his extensive work in math education. In addition to providing numerous mentoring opportunities to his students (such as arranging for them to referee for journals, write reviews for MathSciNet, write expository articles for journals, and co-organize AMS special sessions), the PI will also involve them with expanding his math riddles page (http://mathriddles.williams.edu/). This site is frequently one of the top hits when searching for math riddles, and is used in junior high and high schools around the world to excite students to mathematics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1265673</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven J Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sjm1@williams.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135973293</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000179517</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Williams College</Name>
<CityName>Williamstown</CityName>
<ZipCode>012672600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135974352</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>880 Main St.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Hopkins Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020665972</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT &amp; TRUSTEES OF WILLIAMS COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020665972</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Williams College]]></Name>
<CityName>WILLIAMSTOWN</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>012672600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[18 HOXSEY ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~135610</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The PI and his students studied several problems on zeros of L-functions, as well as problems in additive number theory, with over 60 papers accepted and over 100 talks given. Below is a subset of the results.</p> <p>The main research concerns the behavior of zeros near the central point.While these zeros have been known to be related to arithmetic problems since Riemann, in the last few decades connections have been observed with high energy nuclear physics and random matrix theory as well. We have found many more instances of agreement, both in main and in lower order terms, between these two areas.</p> <p>Another area of research is in additive number theory. An alternative definition of the Fibonacci numbers is that they are the unique sequence such that every integer can be written uniquely as a sum of non-adjacent terms. We have explored other sequences and decomposition laws, proving a variety of results on uniqueness of decomposition, Gaussian behavior in the number of summands, geometric decay in the number of gaps, and strong concentration in the longest gap between summands.</p> <p>We also explored problems in Benford's law; in many systems the probability of a first digit is not 1/9th but instead approximately 30%. Most work to date involves systems of independent random variables; we developed new techniques to show Benfordness with dependencies.</p> <p>Over 50 students and several graduate students, post-docs and junior faculty were mentored.&nbsp;</p> <p>Outreach activities include several survey articles, textbooks (cryptography, Benford's law, and probability), and talks at local schools and high school, middle school and elementary school math camps.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/02/2017<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;J&nbsp;Miller</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The PI and his students studied several problems on zeros of L-functions, as well as problems in additive number theory, with over 60 papers accepted and over 100 talks given. Below is a subset of the results.  The main research concerns the behavior of zeros near the central point.While these zeros have been known to be related to arithmetic problems since Riemann, in the last few decades connections have been observed with high energy nuclear physics and random matrix theory as well. We have found many more instances of agreement, both in main and in lower order terms, between these two areas.  Another area of research is in additive number theory. An alternative definition of the Fibonacci numbers is that they are the unique sequence such that every integer can be written uniquely as a sum of non-adjacent terms. We have explored other sequences and decomposition laws, proving a variety of results on uniqueness of decomposition, Gaussian behavior in the number of summands, geometric decay in the number of gaps, and strong concentration in the longest gap between summands.  We also explored problems in Benford's law; in many systems the probability of a first digit is not 1/9th but instead approximately 30%. Most work to date involves systems of independent random variables; we developed new techniques to show Benfordness with dependencies.  Over 50 students and several graduate students, post-docs and junior faculty were mentored.   Outreach activities include several survey articles, textbooks (cryptography, Benford's law, and probability), and talks at local schools and high school, middle school and elementary school math camps.       Last Modified: 08/02/2017       Submitted by: Steven J Miller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
