<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:   cliques, stable sets and approximate structure</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>240000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal deals with a number of problems in graph theory related to the study of graphs with certain induced subgraphs excluded. The first problem is the famous Erdos-Hajnal conjecture, and its tournament version due to Alon, Pach and Solymosi. Following recent results, the PI plans to combine structural methods with techniques related to Szemeredi's regularity lemma to make further progress. The second set of problems is a conjecture of Gyarfas and Sumner, and questions related to chi-boundedness. In particular, the PI plans to study tournament versions of some of the related classical questions. The last proposed research direction is the general question of the structure of graphs with forbidden induced subgraphs, where particular emphasis is placed on perfect graphs. The PI's have extensive experience in the area, in combination with recent ideas of ``extreme decompositions'', is likely to lead to new results.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal deals with three problems in graphs theory. All three are about graphs with certain forbidden substructures (called "induced subgraphs") excluded; and different aspects of graph behavior are studied in each of the problems. The first two questions considered in the proposal are known conjectures in the field; their solution, or any progress on them, will be of interest to many researchers. The last research direction is more of a "theory building" question, where a general approach, that can be used for a large number of problems, will be developed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1265563</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Seymour</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul D Seymour</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pds@math.princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092584685</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000277476</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085430036</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Fine Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7970</Code>
<Text>Combinatorics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;It is believed, but not proved, that for any fixed graph, every other graph that does not contain this fixed graph has a large clique or stable set. &nbsp;This is the "Erdos-Hajnal conjecture", first proposed in 1989. A great deal of research has gone into it by many different groups of researchers, but the results so far are surprisingly unimpressive. For instance, it is not known to be true when the fixed graph is a five-vertex path, or a five-vertex cycle. Most of the effort of this award went into several problems related to the Erdos-Hajnal conjecture.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;It is known that for a path of any length, all graphs that contain neither the path nor its complement do have the desired large clique or stable set. A first result, joint with A. Liebenau, M. Pilipczuk and S. Spirkl: we proved the same length with &ldquo;path&rdquo; replaced by a more general type of tree. It is enough that all vertices of degree at least three lie in a path. The proof method involved showing that for any such tree, all graphs not containing it or its complement have two sets of vertices, both of linear size, with either no edges between them or all possible edges between them.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Second, in joint work with M. Chudnovsky, A. Scott and S. Spirkl, we extended this approach to its limit; we proved that the same conclusion holds for any tree whatsoever. It is known that this is not true for any more general type of graph, it only works when a tree is excluded.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;A third result: there is a conjecture of Conlon, Fox and Sudakov that something similar is true when any graph <em>H </em>is excluded; that there must be two sets, one of linear size and the other &ldquo;large&rdquo;, with either no edges between them or all possible edges between them. It is known that to prove this in general, it is enough to prove it when the large graph is &ldquo;sparse&rdquo;; and in this sparse case, we did prove it for many graphs <em>H</em>, though not all. (Joint work with M. Chudnovsky, J. Fox, A. Scott and S. Spirkl.)</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;In particular, we proved it for the five-vertex cycle. We used this fact for our fourth result, that every graph not containing a five-vertex cycle has a large clique or stable set; not as large as the Erdos-Hajnal conjecture predicts, but much larger than was previously known.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Fifth, in joint work with Chudnovsky, Scott and Spirkl, we proved that for any fixed <em>H</em>, all graphs not containing a subdivision of <em>H </em>or a subdivision of its complement have two linear sets with either no edges between them or all possible edges between them.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/11/2018<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;D&nbsp;Seymour</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      It is believed, but not proved, that for any fixed graph, every other graph that does not contain this fixed graph has a large clique or stable set.  This is the "Erdos-Hajnal conjecture", first proposed in 1989. A great deal of research has gone into it by many different groups of researchers, but the results so far are surprisingly unimpressive. For instance, it is not known to be true when the fixed graph is a five-vertex path, or a five-vertex cycle. Most of the effort of this award went into several problems related to the Erdos-Hajnal conjecture.       It is known that for a path of any length, all graphs that contain neither the path nor its complement do have the desired large clique or stable set. A first result, joint with A. Liebenau, M. Pilipczuk and S. Spirkl: we proved the same length with "path" replaced by a more general type of tree. It is enough that all vertices of degree at least three lie in a path. The proof method involved showing that for any such tree, all graphs not containing it or its complement have two sets of vertices, both of linear size, with either no edges between them or all possible edges between them.       Second, in joint work with M. Chudnovsky, A. Scott and S. Spirkl, we extended this approach to its limit; we proved that the same conclusion holds for any tree whatsoever. It is known that this is not true for any more general type of graph, it only works when a tree is excluded.       A third result: there is a conjecture of Conlon, Fox and Sudakov that something similar is true when any graph H is excluded; that there must be two sets, one of linear size and the other "large", with either no edges between them or all possible edges between them. It is known that to prove this in general, it is enough to prove it when the large graph is "sparse"; and in this sparse case, we did prove it for many graphs H, though not all. (Joint work with M. Chudnovsky, J. Fox, A. Scott and S. Spirkl.)       In particular, we proved it for the five-vertex cycle. We used this fact for our fourth result, that every graph not containing a five-vertex cycle has a large clique or stable set; not as large as the Erdos-Hajnal conjecture predicts, but much larger than was previously known.       Fifth, in joint work with Chudnovsky, Scott and Spirkl, we proved that for any fixed H, all graphs not containing a subdivision of H or a subdivision of its complement have two linear sets with either no edges between them or all possible edges between them.             Last Modified: 10/11/2018       Submitted by: Paul D Seymour]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
