<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Structure and photoemission dynamics of negative ions via photoelectron imaging spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>413250.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>413250</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Through this award, funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics, and Mechanisms - A Program of the Division of Chemistry, Prof. Andrei Sanov from the University of Arizona will investigate the electronic structure of stable isolated molecules, as well as that of molecules undergoing chemical change or interacting with neighboring species. This goal will be achieved through targeted applications of photoelectron imaging and photofragment spectroscopy to molecular and cluster anions. The combination of these experimental techniques focuses on both the electron emission and anionic fragmentation processes, as both pathways are essential for unraveling the complete picture of negative-ion chemistry. The experiments will specifically target heterocyclic organic radicals, diradicals (carbenes), and strong electron acceptors (such as organocyanides). In addition, the fundamental understanding of photodetachment processes will be advanced by contrasting the experimental observations with predictions of theoretical models that describe photoelectron angular distributions. The interactions with neighboring molecules will be studied using cluster anions as well-defined microscopic solvation environments, recognizing that the reactivity of negative ions is strongly affected by intermolecular interactions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Chemical bonding is controlled by electrons, as it is their behavior that determines molecular structures and controls the outcomes of chemical reactions. Negative ions play important roles in many natural and technological processes and their unique properties are vital to understanding the chemistry of solutions, bio-, environmental, and astrochemistry. Furthermore, the process of removing the electron from the negative ion provides access to important neutral species, such as atmospheric and combustion radicals and other reactive intermediates. This research will provide knowledge relevant to several areas of physical sciences, such as combustion and electronic devices. The methods used in this study provide conceptual views of bonding that ultimately hold all matter together and define a new approach for introducing students and the general public to important concepts in physics and chemistry. These pursuits will allow student participants to acquire specialized training in experimental physical chemistry, preparing them for advanced careers in science, industry, and education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1266152</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrei</FirstName>
<LastName>Sanov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrei Sanov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sanov@u.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206268399</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488914</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072459266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857210041</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1306 E University Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9101</Code>
<Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms A</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5914</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE, OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9162</Code>
<Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~413250</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Maintext"><em>The broadly defined objec&shy;tive </em>of this research program is to attain a molecular-level view of the essence of chemistry: the behavior of electrons both in stable molecules and in molecules undergoing chemical change. As chemical bonding is con&shy;trolled by electrons, it is their pro&shy;per&shy;ties that control the molecular bonding structures and the outcomes of chemical reactions.</p> <p class="Maintext">The general directions of the project were threefold. First, the researchers in the Sanov group char&shy;ac&shy;ter&shy;ized the electronic structure of several important anions and the corresponding neutral molecules. Second, they studied the interactions of anions with neighboring molecules in microscopic solvation environ&shy;ments. Third, they advanced the fundamental understanding of the physics of pho&shy;to&shy;detachment processes by contrasting the experimental observations with pre&shy;dic&shy;tions of prac&shy;ti&shy;cal models that describe the photoelectron angular distributions.</p> <p class="Maintext">Nega&shy;tive ions are important in many natural and tech&shy;no&shy;lo&shy;gi&shy;cal processes. Their properties are vital to under&shy;stand&shy;ing the chemistry of solu&shy;tions, bio- and environ&shy;mental chemistry. The anions targeted in this work are chosen not only for their fundamental pro&shy;per&shy;ties, but also their practical significance. The main experimental method employed was&nbsp;photoelectron im&shy;ag&shy;ing spectroscopy, enhanced by time-of-flight mass-spectroscopic characterization of the precursor anions and their fragments. As part of this project, the Sanov group devel&shy;op&shy;ed the utility of photoelectron imaging in the studies of the electronic struc&shy;ture, photo&shy;de&shy;tach&shy;ment, and time-resolved dynamics of molecu&shy;lar&zwnj; and cluster anions and focused con&shy;sider&shy;able effort on under&shy;standing the experimental &ldquo;sig&shy;na&shy;tures&rdquo; of molecular orbitals.</p> <p class="Maintext">As specific examples, the project yielded important structural and thermochemical properties of several organic radicals (for example, chlorocyanomethyl and oxazolyl) and carbenes (e.g., chlorocyanocarbene). Photoelectron im&shy;ag&shy;ing was used to determine the electron affinities and the molecular-orbital properties of several closed-shell molecules and reactive intermediates, such as glyoxal and methylglyoxal, fumaronitrile, cyclopentadienone, benzonitrile, as well as some of the corresponding molecular clusters.</p> <p class="Maintext">New breakthroughs have been achieved in developing the fundamentals of electron photodetachment. A particular important outcome is the practical model (the l-mixing model) for understanding and quantitative analysis of photoelectron angular distributions in the photodetachment from hybrid molecular orbitals.</p> <p class="Maintext">The project yielded more than a dozen of original research articles published in leading peer-reviewed journals.</p> <p class="Maintext">In addition to scientific output, this research program serves as a vehicle for academic and pro&shy;fes&shy;sional advancement of students and postdocs. During the previous funding period, three graduate students graduated with Ph.D. degrees. One undergraduate student completed her Honor&rsquo;s thesis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/25/2018<br>      Modified by: Andrei&nbsp;Sanov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The broadly defined objec&shy;tive of this research program is to attain a molecular-level view of the essence of chemistry: the behavior of electrons both in stable molecules and in molecules undergoing chemical change. As chemical bonding is con&shy;trolled by electrons, it is their pro&shy;per&shy;ties that control the molecular bonding structures and the outcomes of chemical reactions. The general directions of the project were threefold. First, the researchers in the Sanov group char&shy;ac&shy;ter&shy;ized the electronic structure of several important anions and the corresponding neutral molecules. Second, they studied the interactions of anions with neighboring molecules in microscopic solvation environ&shy;ments. Third, they advanced the fundamental understanding of the physics of pho&shy;to&shy;detachment processes by contrasting the experimental observations with pre&shy;dic&shy;tions of prac&shy;ti&shy;cal models that describe the photoelectron angular distributions. Nega&shy;tive ions are important in many natural and tech&shy;no&shy;lo&shy;gi&shy;cal processes. Their properties are vital to under&shy;stand&shy;ing the chemistry of solu&shy;tions, bio- and environ&shy;mental chemistry. The anions targeted in this work are chosen not only for their fundamental pro&shy;per&shy;ties, but also their practical significance. The main experimental method employed was photoelectron im&shy;ag&shy;ing spectroscopy, enhanced by time-of-flight mass-spectroscopic characterization of the precursor anions and their fragments. As part of this project, the Sanov group devel&shy;op&shy;ed the utility of photoelectron imaging in the studies of the electronic struc&shy;ture, photo&shy;de&shy;tach&shy;ment, and time-resolved dynamics of molecu&shy;lar&zwnj; and cluster anions and focused con&shy;sider&shy;able effort on under&shy;standing the experimental "sig&shy;na&shy;tures" of molecular orbitals. As specific examples, the project yielded important structural and thermochemical properties of several organic radicals (for example, chlorocyanomethyl and oxazolyl) and carbenes (e.g., chlorocyanocarbene). Photoelectron im&shy;ag&shy;ing was used to determine the electron affinities and the molecular-orbital properties of several closed-shell molecules and reactive intermediates, such as glyoxal and methylglyoxal, fumaronitrile, cyclopentadienone, benzonitrile, as well as some of the corresponding molecular clusters. New breakthroughs have been achieved in developing the fundamentals of electron photodetachment. A particular important outcome is the practical model (the l-mixing model) for understanding and quantitative analysis of photoelectron angular distributions in the photodetachment from hybrid molecular orbitals. The project yielded more than a dozen of original research articles published in leading peer-reviewed journals. In addition to scientific output, this research program serves as a vehicle for academic and pro&shy;fes&shy;sional advancement of students and postdocs. During the previous funding period, three graduate students graduated with Ph.D. degrees. One undergraduate student completed her Honor?s thesis.          Last Modified: 09/25/2018       Submitted by: Andrei Sanov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
