<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SusChEM: Rational Design of Chiral Bipyridine N-Oxides for the Catalytic Propargylation of Aromatic Aldehydes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>239636.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>239636</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gjanini@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928840</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The NSF Chemical Catalysis Program supports the efforts of Professor Steven E. Wheeler of Texas A&amp;M University Main Campus to rationally design highly stereoselective catalysts for the propargylation of aromatic aldehydes. These design efforts are facilitated by the development of a set of computational tools for the rapid and reliable prediction of the stereoselectivities of these reactions. The team seeks to accurately predict the stereoselectivity provided by a given catalyst within a 24-hour time frame, which allows for the relatively rapid screening of potential new catalysts. Propargylation catalysts are designed based on the concept that the stereoselectivities of bipyridine N-oxide catalyzed alkylation reactions are dictated primarily by the chiral arrangement of ligands around a hexacoordinate silicon transition state. Notably, only certain ligand arrangements are stereoselective, and catalysts are designed to adopt these inherently stereoselective configurations. To maximize the impact of these studies and to validate the computational predictions, propargylation catalysts predicted to be highly stereoselective are synthesized and tested by an experimental collaborator, Professor Martin Kotara of Charles University in Prague, Czech Republic. This collaboration provides valuable feedback while also ensuring that new catalysts developed are immediately applied in natural product syntheses. These metal-free catalysts for asymmetric organic reactions promise new, more environmentally friendly routes to important chiral molecules, including natural products and pharmaceuticals and thus, represent important efforts in sustainable chemistry. An additional outcome of this research is the development of a computational toolkit for the prediction of stereoselectivities of N-oxide alkylation catalysts. This project lays the foundation for a general toolkit for computational catalyst design, which is distributed freely under an open-source license.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The NSF Chemical Catalysis Program supports the efforts of Professor Steven E. Wheeler of Texas A&amp;M University Main Campus to develop new catalysts and improve existing metal-free catalysts for valuable and sustainable chemical syntheses used in producing natural products and pharmaceuticals. The development of new catalysts requires a detailed understanding of the underlying reaction mechanisms and the myriad of factors that control stereoselectivity. Computational chemistry, by providing structural and energetic information about not only the operative reaction pathway but also higher-lying transition states, provides key insights into the origin of stereoselectivity of such organocatalyzed reactions. This effort focuses on the use of computational resources for the preparation of metal-free catalysts thereby making the materials more environmentally friendly than previous routes. Undergraduate and graduate students receive extensive hands-on training in computational organic chemistry as well as more formal training in quantum chemistry and electronic structure theory. Close collaborations with a synthetic organic collaborator exposes the students to a broad range of topics in modern organic chemistry and teaches them to clearly communicate their results to a non-computational audience. The computational methods that are developed are freely distributed under an open-source license so that others in the scientific community may benefit.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1266022</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Wheeler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven E Wheeler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wheeler@chem.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7065421544</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000598592</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020271826</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433255</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3255 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5914</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE, OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL CATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~239636</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Metal-free catalysts for asymmetric organic reactions promise new, more environmentally- friendly routes to important chiral molecules, including natural products and pharmaceuticals. The development of new catalysts and the improvement of existing catalysts require a detailed understanding of the underlying reaction mechanisms and the myriad factors that control stereoselectivity.&nbsp; The development of such catalysts is typically a long, expensive process requiring the experimental synthesis and testing of many potential catalysts. The primary aim of this project was to use modern tools of computational quantum chemistry to understand the origin of stereoselectivity of Lewis base promoted alkylation reactions and related reactions and to then leverage this knowledge for the design of new catalysts.&nbsp; The primary target is the development of a highly selective catalyst for the asymmetric propargylation of benzaldehyde, which is an important carbon-carbon bond forming reaction.&nbsp; Driving these efforts was the development of an automated computational toolkit (AARON) that enables rapid predictions of these stereoselectivies.</p> <p>We successfully developed AARON (Automated Alkylation Reaction Optimizer for N-oxides), which has opened the door for the computational design of bipyridine N-oxide derived catalysts for asymmetric alkylation reactions.&nbsp; As proof of principle, we used AARON to screen 60 potential catalysts for the asymmetric propargylation of benzaldehyde, identifying a dozen catalysts for which the predicted selectivity exceeds that of any currently available catalyst.&nbsp; This initial version of AARON, along with complementary studies of a wide range of asymmetric organocatalyzed reactions, has laid the foundation for a more general and more powerful version of AARON currently under development.</p> <p>The proposed work provided extensive training for graduate and undergraduate students in computational organic chemistry, organocatalysis, and electronic structure theory. Many of the undergraduates that received training under this award have gone on to top graduate and medical schools. AARON was developed to be user-friendly and is now available for free as an open-source software package, providing a powerful tool for the broader chemical community.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;E&nbsp;Wheeler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1266022/1266022_10272158_1511985078995_TOC_figure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1266022/1266022_10272158_1511985078995_TOC_figure--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Computational Screening of Catalyst Designs"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1266022/1266022_10272158_1511985078995_TOC_figure--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Computational Screening of Catalyst Designs"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Using AARON, one can automatically screen potential catalysts for asymmetric alkylation reactions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven E. Wheeler</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;E&nbsp;Wheeler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Computational Screening of Catalyst Designs</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Metal-free catalysts for asymmetric organic reactions promise new, more environmentally- friendly routes to important chiral molecules, including natural products and pharmaceuticals. The development of new catalysts and the improvement of existing catalysts require a detailed understanding of the underlying reaction mechanisms and the myriad factors that control stereoselectivity.  The development of such catalysts is typically a long, expensive process requiring the experimental synthesis and testing of many potential catalysts. The primary aim of this project was to use modern tools of computational quantum chemistry to understand the origin of stereoselectivity of Lewis base promoted alkylation reactions and related reactions and to then leverage this knowledge for the design of new catalysts.  The primary target is the development of a highly selective catalyst for the asymmetric propargylation of benzaldehyde, which is an important carbon-carbon bond forming reaction.  Driving these efforts was the development of an automated computational toolkit (AARON) that enables rapid predictions of these stereoselectivies.  We successfully developed AARON (Automated Alkylation Reaction Optimizer for N-oxides), which has opened the door for the computational design of bipyridine N-oxide derived catalysts for asymmetric alkylation reactions.  As proof of principle, we used AARON to screen 60 potential catalysts for the asymmetric propargylation of benzaldehyde, identifying a dozen catalysts for which the predicted selectivity exceeds that of any currently available catalyst.  This initial version of AARON, along with complementary studies of a wide range of asymmetric organocatalyzed reactions, has laid the foundation for a more general and more powerful version of AARON currently under development.  The proposed work provided extensive training for graduate and undergraduate students in computational organic chemistry, organocatalysis, and electronic structure theory. Many of the undergraduates that received training under this award have gone on to top graduate and medical schools. AARON was developed to be user-friendly and is now available for free as an open-source software package, providing a powerful tool for the broader chemical community.       Last Modified: 11/29/2017       Submitted by: Steven E Wheeler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
