<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I/UCRC:  Collaborative Research: I/UCRC Center for Configuration Analytics and Automation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>531375.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>728145</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Behrooz Shirazi</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bshirazi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928343</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The center seeks to establish a new Industry/University Cooperative Research Center (I/UCRC) in order to conduct research to improve configuration analytics and automation capabilities in order to enable their integration for efficient, accurate and timely operations, management and defense of complex networked information technology (IT) systems and environments. By addressing the challenges of configuration analytics and automation, the center intends to improve enterprise IT system and service manageability, performance, assurability, security and sustainability.  The effort plans to apply innovative analytics and automation to complex networked systems including: enterprise networking of clouds and data centers, software defined networking, hybrid and cyber-physical systems, smart critical infrastructures, mission-oriented networks (sensor-actuator networks), virtual overlays, social networks and mobile systems.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Future system complexity and the potential of misconfiguration is likely&lt;br/&gt;to increase significantly as technology progresses toward "smart" cyber infrastructure and ?open? configurable platforms making configuration analytics and automation essential for realizing continued productivity and competitiveness improvements from the cyber-economy.  Working with its Industrial Advisory Board, the center plans to have a significant impact in this area and provide a source of talented graduates to industry. The center plans to have a strong educational component that includes training undergraduate and graduate students in this area, creating a new multidisciplinary certificate on Configuration Analytics at UNCC, and involving minority and under-represented students through courses, seminars, workshops and research projects.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1266360</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bei-Tseng</FirstName>
<LastName>Chu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bei-Tseng Chu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Billchu@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046878661</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000476026</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ehab</FirstName>
<LastName>Al-Shaer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ehab S Al-Shaer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ealshaer@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6308900225</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000107327</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9201 University City Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066300096</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHARLOTTE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Charlotte]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlotte</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9201 University City Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O271</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>p356</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>170E</Code>
<Text>Interagency Agreements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8039</Code>
<Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~112275</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~112275</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~242825</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~149095</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~102275</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~9400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The mission of CCAA is to build the critical mass of inter-disciplinary academic researchers and industry partners for advancing the science and state-of-the-art of cybersecurity analytics and automation by developing and integrating innovative sense-making and decision-making capabilities for automated adaptive cyber defense that requires minimal human involvement with provable and measurable security and resiliency properties.&nbsp;</p> <p>With the increasing frequency and sophistication of cyber attacks, cyber warfare has become a major threat to national security. Despite the progress made in cybersecurity in both research and industry, the state of the art is still far from providing sufficient protection not only for Internet enterprise services but also for critical infrastructure services, such as in the financial and energy sectors. Cyber risk has been growing faster than cyber defense innovation.</p> <p>UNCC-CCAA completed several projects, published many refereed journals and conference/workshop papers, and graduated a number of PhD&nbsp; and master students. UNCC-CCAA developed a number of cybersecurity analytics tools deployed in CCAA Analytics Store for members to use, and developed several plans for transition to practice .&nbsp; The PI of UNCC CCAA have presented/demonstrated their CCAA work in national cybersecurity venues including NSA/DHS IACD, FS-ISAC, RSA and SINET.&nbsp; &nbsp;UNCC-CCAA contributed significantly to CCAA research and quality evolution.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/24/2020<br>      Modified by: Ehab&nbsp;S&nbsp;Al-Shaer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The mission of CCAA is to build the critical mass of inter-disciplinary academic researchers and industry partners for advancing the science and state-of-the-art of cybersecurity analytics and automation by developing and integrating innovative sense-making and decision-making capabilities for automated adaptive cyber defense that requires minimal human involvement with provable and measurable security and resiliency properties.   With the increasing frequency and sophistication of cyber attacks, cyber warfare has become a major threat to national security. Despite the progress made in cybersecurity in both research and industry, the state of the art is still far from providing sufficient protection not only for Internet enterprise services but also for critical infrastructure services, such as in the financial and energy sectors. Cyber risk has been growing faster than cyber defense innovation.  UNCC-CCAA completed several projects, published many refereed journals and conference/workshop papers, and graduated a number of PhD  and master students. UNCC-CCAA developed a number of cybersecurity analytics tools deployed in CCAA Analytics Store for members to use, and developed several plans for transition to practice .  The PI of UNCC CCAA have presented/demonstrated their CCAA work in national cybersecurity venues including NSA/DHS IACD, FS-ISAC, RSA and SINET.   UNCC-CCAA contributed significantly to CCAA research and quality evolution.           Last Modified: 01/24/2020       Submitted by: Ehab S Al-Shaer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
