<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-UCRC:  The University of Texas at Austin Site of the I-UCRC on Intelligent Maintenance Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>335996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Behrooz Shirazi</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bshirazi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928343</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of Texas at Austin site for the I/UCRC for Intelligent Maintenance Systems (IMS) intends to pursue and understand methods addressing the scientific and practical challenges of condition-based and predictive maintenance of complex engineering systems.  The site plans to expand the on-going IMS research with new ideas and foci including predictive maintenance in semiconductor manufacturing, vehicle technologies, oil industry, renewable energy, power plants and biomedicine. The University of Texas at Austin site intends to complement existing IMS efforts through focus on new approaches to diagnostics and prognostics in complex engineering systems, utilization of advanced diagnostics and predictive maintenance methods for monitoring of systems in a human body, and maintenance decision-making in distributed systems, with limited availability of distributed resources and uncertain supply and demand characteristics.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is estimated that the US economy spends more than $1 trillion for maintenance of critical assets, with more than 33% of these costs being wasted on ineffective maintenance. Optimization of these maintenance systems has the potential to greatly improve overall industrial productivity.  The University of Texas at Austin Site of IMS intends to extend the research outcomes it brings to the center to new industries that have formerly not benefited from predictive maintenance research. The site plans to broadly disseminate research results through regular meetings with industrial partners, short courses on diagnostics and maintenance open to industry and academe, regular participation and publication in relevant conferences, and partnerships with universities in the US and abroad. They intend to actively promote diversity among students and researchers by leveraging the tremendous infrastructure UT offers in this regard.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1266279</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Bryant</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael D Bryant</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mbryant@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124714870</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000296813</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dragan</FirstName>
<LastName>Djurdjanovic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dragan Djurdjanovic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dragand@me.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5122320815</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000331503</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787137726</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 7726]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8039</Code>
<Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~59999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~79999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~59999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~76000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~59999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Center description:</strong> The University of Texas site of the NSF Industry University Cooperative Research Center for Intelligent Maintenance Systems (UT IMS Center) conducted cutting edge research in the domain of maintenance science as it applies to engineering and biomedical systems. We explored new methods for transforming raw sensory data into useful information about the condition of the underlying system, and further into decisions that enable proper operation of those systems. Applications included condition monitoring and maintenance of semiconductor manufacturing equipment, oil and gas extraction assets, medical testing machines and human neuromusculoskeletal systems. The following companies supported the UT IMS Center with memberships: Intel, Samsung, TSMC, Lam Research, National Instruments, MathWorks, Canrig Drilling, Abbot Diagnostics and GTI Spindle Technologies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual merit:</strong> Research at the UT IMS Center was organized into following thrusts: a) New methods for diagnostics and prognostics in complex systems; b) Active process and quality control; c) Performance monitoring of human body systems using machine monitoring paradigms and d) Integrated maintenance and operational decision-making.</p> <p>a)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In this thrust, we explored modeling, monitoring and prediction of condition degradation in highly distributed systems in which direct observations of the underlying condition could not be made based on the available sensor readings, but must rather be inferred from those readings. Chamber condition in plasma-based semiconductor manufacturing tools, such as Plasma-Enhanced Chemical Vapor Deposition (PECVD) tools, or etch tools, is a quintessential example of such systems and our research facilitated significant breakthroughs in plasma condition monitoring. We used the concept of Hidden Markov Models (HMM) to model plasma condition, with hidden HMM states describing those directly unobservable degradation conditions, while observable HMM symbols represented the available sensor readings. Our research proved convergence of Bayesian estimation for the resulting unidirectional (non-ergodic) HMMs and the use of such HMMs yielded tremendous improvements in PECVD and etch tool monitoring over the use of traditional multivariate statistical process control approaches.</p> <p>b)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The research in this thrust enabled a novel approach for automatic parsing of process signals into an exhaustive and mutually exclusive set of steady-state and transient segments, out of which descriptive statistics-based and dynamics-inspired signatures can be extracted. These signatures enabled superior modeling of process quality characteristics, regardless of what modeling tool was used to relate process characteristics to the resulting product quality. In addition, our research led to novel dynamic models for further improvements in Virtual Metrology and defectivity prediction (see Fig. 1).</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Furthermore, data-driven modeling and robust process control was used to enable active control of product quality in multistage manufacturing processes, such as semiconductor lithography overlay. Dramatic improvements over the traditional ?Run-to-Run? control approaches were demonstrated using production-level process model and data from one of our member companies (see Fig. 2).</p> <p>c)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In our center, we addressed the problem of using machine monitoring techniques to enable monitoring the performance of human NMS systems. Rather than focusing on analysis of the relevant signals, we pursued the system-based approach to modeling and tracking of NMS performance by building dynamic models that relate muscle signatures (inputs) to the relevant limb movements and forces (outputs). Tracking of these models rather than signals led to the ability to continuously and quantitatively track the behavior of the relevant NMS systems in various motions. The underlying concept is illustrated in Fig. 3.</p> <p>d)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This thrust focused on detailed modeling of systems operations using discrete-event simulations, based on which metaheuristic optimization was used to lead to ever-improving maintenance and operational decisions. Such an approach which de-emphasized tractability, but enabled tackling of large optimization problems in which we jointly optimized various operational aspects in manufacturing and logistic systems. &nbsp;We showed that the newly developed integrated approaches that jointly optimize maintenance, production and logistic decisions robustly and consistently outperform the traditional approaches which tackle those operational aspects separately.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Educational and broader impact outcomes:</strong> UT IMS Center provided a unique educational environment for graduate and undergraduate students. Our center produced 6 graduated Ph.D. students, 4 MS students, while our REU grant supported 4 undergraduate students in their research. Furthermore, the PI developed an industry-oriented workshop on ?Condition-Based Maintenance ? Transformation of Data into Information and Decisions?, which was offered 5 times during the life of the center. Finally, the PI gave talks in numerous conferences and industrial seminars. One should especially note participation as a panelist in 2 panels on human body performance, which were organized by the Prognostics and Health Management society.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Let us also note that the UT IMS Center research received significant international attention. This led to collaborative efforts with Shanghai Jiao Tong University, China, Technical University of Munich, Germany, University of Belgrade, Serbia and Politecnico di Milano, Italy. Such international exposure and interaction was tremendously useful for realizing broader impacts of our center and disseminating the results of our research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/02/2019<br>      Modified by: Dragan&nbsp;Djurdjanovic</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1266279/1266279_10235194_1551584868090_MainFigure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1266279/1266279_10235194_1551584868090_MainFigure--rgov-800width.jpg" title="UT IMS team working with industrial partners"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1266279/1266279_10235194_1551584868090_MainFigure--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="UT IMS team working with industrial partners"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">UT IMS members and collaborators from a member company collecting data from a modern semiconductor manufacturing tool.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dragan Djurdjanovic</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dragan&nbsp;Djurdjanovic</div> <div class="imageTitle">UT IMS team working with industrial partners</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1266279/1266279_10235194_1551585183882_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1266279/1266279_10235194_1551585183882_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Improvements in Virtual Metrology enabled the the UT IMS research."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1266279/1266279_10235194_1551585183882_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Improvements in Virtual Metrology enabled the the UT IMS research."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1: Improvements in Virtual Metrology (VM) model accuracies enabled by the novel (augmented) feature set containing automatically generated statistics-based and dynamics-inspired signatures.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dragan Djurdjanovic</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dragan&nbsp;Djurdjanovic</div> <div class="imageTitle">Improvements in Virtual Metrology enabled the the UT IMS research.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1266279/1266279_10235194_1551585421393_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1266279/1266279_10235194_1551585421393_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Active process control results in applied to control of lithography overlay errors."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1266279/1266279_10235194_1551585421393_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Active process control results in applied to control of lithography overlay errors."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2: Heat maps illustrating the improvements in overlay  errors yielded by the multistage process control methods developed in the UT IMS Center. The traditional Run-to-Run (R2R) control results are shown in the upper row, the bottom two rows show results obtained using the UT IMS methods.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dragan Djurdjanovic</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dragan&nbsp;Djurdjanovic</div> <div class="imageTitle">Active process control results in applied to control of lithography overlay errors.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1266279/1266279_10235194_1551585508634_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1266279/1266279_10235194_1551585508634_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Systems based approach to NMS performance modeling and tracking."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1266279/1266279_10235194_1551585508634_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Systems based approach to NMS performance modeling and tracking."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3: Conceptual illustration of the systems-based approach to modeling and tracking of human NMS performance developed in the UT IMS Center.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dragan Djurdjanovic</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dragan&nbsp;Djurdjanovic</div> <div class="imageTitle">Systems based approach to NMS performance modeling and tracking.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Center description: The University of Texas site of the NSF Industry University Cooperative Research Center for Intelligent Maintenance Systems (UT IMS Center) conducted cutting edge research in the domain of maintenance science as it applies to engineering and biomedical systems. We explored new methods for transforming raw sensory data into useful information about the condition of the underlying system, and further into decisions that enable proper operation of those systems. Applications included condition monitoring and maintenance of semiconductor manufacturing equipment, oil and gas extraction assets, medical testing machines and human neuromusculoskeletal systems. The following companies supported the UT IMS Center with memberships: Intel, Samsung, TSMC, Lam Research, National Instruments, MathWorks, Canrig Drilling, Abbot Diagnostics and GTI Spindle Technologies.     Intellectual merit: Research at the UT IMS Center was organized into following thrusts: a) New methods for diagnostics and prognostics in complex systems; b) Active process and quality control; c) Performance monitoring of human body systems using machine monitoring paradigms and d) Integrated maintenance and operational decision-making.  a)     In this thrust, we explored modeling, monitoring and prediction of condition degradation in highly distributed systems in which direct observations of the underlying condition could not be made based on the available sensor readings, but must rather be inferred from those readings. Chamber condition in plasma-based semiconductor manufacturing tools, such as Plasma-Enhanced Chemical Vapor Deposition (PECVD) tools, or etch tools, is a quintessential example of such systems and our research facilitated significant breakthroughs in plasma condition monitoring. We used the concept of Hidden Markov Models (HMM) to model plasma condition, with hidden HMM states describing those directly unobservable degradation conditions, while observable HMM symbols represented the available sensor readings. Our research proved convergence of Bayesian estimation for the resulting unidirectional (non-ergodic) HMMs and the use of such HMMs yielded tremendous improvements in PECVD and etch tool monitoring over the use of traditional multivariate statistical process control approaches.  b)    The research in this thrust enabled a novel approach for automatic parsing of process signals into an exhaustive and mutually exclusive set of steady-state and transient segments, out of which descriptive statistics-based and dynamics-inspired signatures can be extracted. These signatures enabled superior modeling of process quality characteristics, regardless of what modeling tool was used to relate process characteristics to the resulting product quality. In addition, our research led to novel dynamic models for further improvements in Virtual Metrology and defectivity prediction (see Fig. 1).       Furthermore, data-driven modeling and robust process control was used to enable active control of product quality in multistage manufacturing processes, such as semiconductor lithography overlay. Dramatic improvements over the traditional ?Run-to-Run? control approaches were demonstrated using production-level process model and data from one of our member companies (see Fig. 2).  c)     In our center, we addressed the problem of using machine monitoring techniques to enable monitoring the performance of human NMS systems. Rather than focusing on analysis of the relevant signals, we pursued the system-based approach to modeling and tracking of NMS performance by building dynamic models that relate muscle signatures (inputs) to the relevant limb movements and forces (outputs). Tracking of these models rather than signals led to the ability to continuously and quantitatively track the behavior of the relevant NMS systems in various motions. The underlying concept is illustrated in Fig. 3.  d)    This thrust focused on detailed modeling of systems operations using discrete-event simulations, based on which metaheuristic optimization was used to lead to ever-improving maintenance and operational decisions. Such an approach which de-emphasized tractability, but enabled tackling of large optimization problems in which we jointly optimized various operational aspects in manufacturing and logistic systems.  We showed that the newly developed integrated approaches that jointly optimize maintenance, production and logistic decisions robustly and consistently outperform the traditional approaches which tackle those operational aspects separately.      Educational and broader impact outcomes: UT IMS Center provided a unique educational environment for graduate and undergraduate students. Our center produced 6 graduated Ph.D. students, 4 MS students, while our REU grant supported 4 undergraduate students in their research. Furthermore, the PI developed an industry-oriented workshop on ?Condition-Based Maintenance ? Transformation of Data into Information and Decisions?, which was offered 5 times during the life of the center. Finally, the PI gave talks in numerous conferences and industrial seminars. One should especially note participation as a panelist in 2 panels on human body performance, which were organized by the Prognostics and Health Management society.              Let us also note that the UT IMS Center research received significant international attention. This led to collaborative efforts with Shanghai Jiao Tong University, China, Technical University of Munich, Germany, University of Belgrade, Serbia and Politecnico di Milano, Italy. Such international exposure and interaction was tremendously useful for realizing broader impacts of our center and disseminating the results of our research.          Last Modified: 03/02/2019       Submitted by: Dragan Djurdjanovic]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
