<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Coloring-related problems for  graphs and hypergraphs with degree restrictions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>269919.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>375289</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A (proper) coloring of vertices of a graph or hypergraph G is a partition of the vertex set of G into sets (called color classes) such that no edge of G is fully contained in any of the classes. The basic coloring problem is to find such a partition with the fewest color classes. The aim of this project is to study  extremal problems related to coloring of (hyper)graphs involving degrees of vertices, a number of whose arose during the work of the PI and co-PI with students at the University of Illinois. It is expected that the joint work and combinations of the ideas and approaches of the PI and the co-PI will allow to get the results that will make an essential step in understanding of these problems. Among important topics are   color-critical graphs with small average degree, list colorings,  improper colorings, coloring of graphs embedded into surfaces, equitable coloring, bounds on the independence number, and hypergraph coloring. Among promising tools is the language of potentials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Coloring deals with the fundamental problem of partitioning a set of objects into classes that avoid certain conflicts. This model has many applications, for example, in time tabling, scheduling, frequency assignment and sequencing problems. The theory of graph and hypergraph coloring has a central position in discrete mathematics. It relates to other important areas of combinatorics, such as Ramsey theory, graph minors, independence number of graphs and hypergraphs, orientations of graphs, and packing of graphs. The PI and the co-PI plan to make significant advances in developing the theory of coloring of sparse graphs and hypergraphs. They will involve into work a number of graduate students and very recent graduates of the University of Illinois. The research guidance and involvement of graduate students contributes to their professional development and reputation. The results will be published in leading international journals in the field and presented at international scientific conferences. This will support the reputation of the University of Illinois. The results  will be used in graduate courses  and discussed at research seminars at the University of Illinois.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1266016</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexandr</FirstName>
<LastName>Kostochka</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexandr V Kostochka</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kostochk@math.uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172658037</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000190764</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bernard</FirstName>
<LastName>Lidicky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bernard Lidicky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lidicky@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000626237</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7970</Code>
<Text>Combinatorics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1515</Code>
<Text>MINORITY GRADUATE EDUC ACTIVIT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~109929</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~140920</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~79995</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~44445</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A (proper) coloring of vertices of a graph or hypergraph G is a partition of the vertex set of G into sets (called&nbsp; color classes) such that no edge of G is fully contained in any of the classes. The basic coloring problem is to find such a partition with the fewest color classes. This model has many applications, for example, in time tabling, scheduling, frequency assignment and sequencing problems.&nbsp; It also relates to other important areas of combinatorics and other parts of mathematics. The aim of the project was to study&nbsp; extremal problems related to coloring of (hyper)graphs involving degrees of vertices.<br />&nbsp;Among important topics were&nbsp;&nbsp; color-critical graphs with small average degree, list colorings,&nbsp; improper colorings, coloring of graphs embedded <br />into surfaces, equitable coloring, bounds on the independence number, and hypergraph coloring.<br /><br />The PIs managed to obtain signicant results on the topics of the grant. Some of these results are:<br />(1) The extremal graphs in a Conjecture of Gallai from 1963 on the minimum number of edges in n-vertex k-critical graphs are described.<br />(2) The 4-critical planar graphs with four triangles are described, which settles a question by Aksenov from the seventies and&nbsp; of Erdos from 1990.<br />(3) A conjecture by Erdos from 1992 on odd cycles of many different lengths in triangle-free color-critical graphs was proved in a stronger and more general form.<br />(4) The question of Dirac from 1963 on the description of the (2k-1)-connected multigraphs with at most k-1 disjoint cycles is fully answered in a more general form.<br />(5) The stability versions of classical Theorems&nbsp; of Erdos and Gallai from 1959 on the most edges in n-vertex graphs with no paths or cycles of length at least k were obtained.<br />(6) A conjecture by Erdos and Sos&nbsp; on the maximum number&nbsp; of rainbow triangles in 3-edge-colored complete graphs on n vertices is proved <br />for large n and for all n of the form n=4^k.<br />(7) The new notion of list packing was introduced, studied and used to prove an approximate version of a conjecture by Zak on graph packing.</p> <p>(8) A conjecture by Kurek and Rucinski from 1994 on improper colorings is settled.</p> <p>The PIs&nbsp; involved into work a number of graduate students and very recent graduates&nbsp; of the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, in particular&nbsp; M. Santana, M. Yancey, J. Kim, I. Choi, K. Jao, E. Yeager, B. Reiniger,&nbsp; P. Hu, H. Liu, M. Delcourt,&nbsp; A. McConvey, D. Yager, A. Bernstehn, R. Luo.&nbsp; The research guidance and involvement of graduate students contributed to their professional development and reputation. All graduates included the results obtained while working on the grant in their Ph. D. Theses, and for some of them it was an essential part of their Ph.D. Theses.<br />On the base of the grant research, the PIs and the research assistant have written and submitted 36 scientific papers. Some of these papers are already accepted by leading combinatorial international journals.<br />The results also were delivered by the PIs in their talks at some prestitigious international and AMS conferences and will be used in graduate courses and seminars in the Mathematics Department of the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/23/2016<br>      Modified by: Alexandr&nbsp;V&nbsp;Kostochka</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A (proper) coloring of vertices of a graph or hypergraph G is a partition of the vertex set of G into sets (called  color classes) such that no edge of G is fully contained in any of the classes. The basic coloring problem is to find such a partition with the fewest color classes. This model has many applications, for example, in time tabling, scheduling, frequency assignment and sequencing problems.  It also relates to other important areas of combinatorics and other parts of mathematics. The aim of the project was to study  extremal problems related to coloring of (hyper)graphs involving degrees of vertices.  Among important topics were   color-critical graphs with small average degree, list colorings,  improper colorings, coloring of graphs embedded  into surfaces, equitable coloring, bounds on the independence number, and hypergraph coloring.  The PIs managed to obtain signicant results on the topics of the grant. Some of these results are: (1) The extremal graphs in a Conjecture of Gallai from 1963 on the minimum number of edges in n-vertex k-critical graphs are described. (2) The 4-critical planar graphs with four triangles are described, which settles a question by Aksenov from the seventies and  of Erdos from 1990. (3) A conjecture by Erdos from 1992 on odd cycles of many different lengths in triangle-free color-critical graphs was proved in a stronger and more general form. (4) The question of Dirac from 1963 on the description of the (2k-1)-connected multigraphs with at most k-1 disjoint cycles is fully answered in a more general form. (5) The stability versions of classical Theorems  of Erdos and Gallai from 1959 on the most edges in n-vertex graphs with no paths or cycles of length at least k were obtained. (6) A conjecture by Erdos and Sos  on the maximum number  of rainbow triangles in 3-edge-colored complete graphs on n vertices is proved  for large n and for all n of the form n=4^k. (7) The new notion of list packing was introduced, studied and used to prove an approximate version of a conjecture by Zak on graph packing.  (8) A conjecture by Kurek and Rucinski from 1994 on improper colorings is settled.  The PIs  involved into work a number of graduate students and very recent graduates  of the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, in particular  M. Santana, M. Yancey, J. Kim, I. Choi, K. Jao, E. Yeager, B. Reiniger,  P. Hu, H. Liu, M. Delcourt,  A. McConvey, D. Yager, A. Bernstehn, R. Luo.  The research guidance and involvement of graduate students contributed to their professional development and reputation. All graduates included the results obtained while working on the grant in their Ph. D. Theses, and for some of them it was an essential part of their Ph.D. Theses. On the base of the grant research, the PIs and the research assistant have written and submitted 36 scientific papers. Some of these papers are already accepted by leading combinatorial international journals. The results also were delivered by the PIs in their talks at some prestitigious international and AMS conferences and will be used in graduate courses and seminars in the Mathematics Department of the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.       Last Modified: 08/23/2016       Submitted by: Alexandr V Kostochka]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
