<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Low Power Silicon Electro-Optic Micro-Switch</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lawrence S. Goldberg</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0300387&lt;br/&gt;Lipson&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Silicon-based optoelectronic switches and modulators at 1.3 and 1.55-um fiber-optic&lt;br/&gt;communications-wavelengths for fiber-to-home interconnects and local area&lt;br/&gt;networks (LAN) offer the possibility of integrating optical elements and advanced&lt;br/&gt;electronics on a silicon substrate using bipolar or complementary metal-oxide&lt;br/&gt;semiconductor (CMOS) technology. Most of the proposed Si electro-optic (E-O)&lt;br/&gt;switches, however, require long interaction distance and high drive powers for obtaining&lt;br/&gt;a significant modulation depth. Long interaction lengths are undesirable in order to&lt;br/&gt;achieve high levels of integration and miniaturization. High electrical powers may induce&lt;br/&gt;competing thermo-optic effects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI proposes a new class of micrometer-size planar Si electro-optic switches with&lt;br/&gt;low power consumption and high modulation depth.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The device is based on a planar Fabry-Perot (F-P) microcavity. Free-carrier&lt;br/&gt;plasma dispersion effect [1,2] is used to modulate the refractive index of the cavity region&lt;br/&gt;by using a lateral p-i-n diode. Both optical field and injected carriers are strongly&lt;br/&gt;confined in the microcavity using high-index-contrast Si/SiO2 distributed Bragg&lt;br/&gt;reflectors (DBR) and trench isolation. The optical confinement accounts for the small&lt;br/&gt;size of the structure and its high modulation depth. The carrier confinement accounts for&lt;br/&gt;the device low power consumption.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs preliminary calculations show that a 20-micron long device can have 80%&lt;br/&gt;modulation depth under 25 microwatt power drives. To the best of their knowledge this&lt;br/&gt;corresponds to the first practical Si integrated photonic active device.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This new class of active devices will function as a building block for active on-chip&lt;br/&gt;Si devices. These devices include tunable filters, tunable grating, modulators,&lt;br/&gt;switches, adaptive couplers among others. All-optical systems on a chip could become a&lt;br/&gt;reality where inexpensive, compact active and passive devices could be integrated and&lt;br/&gt;monolithically grown on a chip.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/18/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/18/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0300387</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michal</FirstName>
<LastName>Lipson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ml292@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/18/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0206000</Code>
<Name>Telecommunications</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
