<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Asymptotic Geometry of Eigenfunctions and Polynomials</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>183000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>183000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ASYMPTOTIC GEOMETRY OF EIGENFUNCTIONS AND POLYNOMIALS&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is concerned with the asymptotics of eigenfunctions and &lt;br/&gt;eigenvalues of the Laplacian on Riemannian manifold, and analogues&lt;br/&gt;for the complex Laplacian on Kahler manifolds.  Using methods of&lt;br/&gt;semi-classical analysis (the mathematics of the classical limit of&lt;br/&gt;quantum mechanics), the high frequency limit of eigenfunctions is related&lt;br/&gt;to the dynamics of the geodesic flow.  The first application is to the&lt;br/&gt;well-known inverse spectral problem for analytic plane domains.&lt;br/&gt;The new idea is to use an exact&lt;br/&gt;formula for the Dirichlet resolvent and  a Feynman&lt;br/&gt;diagram analysis of  its trace.&lt;br/&gt; One obtains for the first time explicit formulae for so-called&lt;br/&gt;wave trace invariants in terms of the Taylor coefficients of the domain at&lt;br/&gt;endpoints of a bouncing ball orbit. From these one seeks to recover the&lt;br/&gt;Taylor coefficients and hence an analytic domain.  So far the best result&lt;br/&gt;is that one can recover a mirror symmetric analytic domain from its&lt;br/&gt;spectrum.&lt;br/&gt; The second application&lt;br/&gt;is to geometry of eigenfunctions. Sogge and the proposer proved that &lt;br/&gt;the maximum possible  growth rate of sup-norms of eigenfunctions&lt;br/&gt; only&lt;br/&gt;occurs  on boundarlyless&lt;br/&gt;Riemannian manifolds  which contain recurrent points, such that&lt;br/&gt;a positive measure of geodesics leaving the point return in a fixed&lt;br/&gt;time.  &lt;br/&gt;One project is to prove this (if true) for bounded domains. A similar &lt;br/&gt;analysis is interesting for boundary values of eigenfunctions, which&lt;br/&gt;are important&lt;br/&gt;in boundary control theory. Hassell and the proposer have recently&lt;br/&gt;proved&lt;br/&gt;the ergodicity of boundary values of eigenfunctions when the billiard&lt;br/&gt;flow&lt;br/&gt;of the domain is ergodic, and this gave the first asymptotic estimates&lt;br/&gt;of&lt;br/&gt;even the L2 norms of the boundary values.  Methods developed in that&lt;br/&gt;paper&lt;br/&gt;should have further applications to the geometry of eigenfunctions. The&lt;br/&gt;third project,&lt;br/&gt;joint with B. Shiffman&lt;br/&gt;is to apply semiclassical methods to statistical algebraic geometry,&lt;br/&gt;i.e., to&lt;br/&gt;finding statistical patterns in the zeros of polynomials.  Among the&lt;br/&gt;patterns found&lt;br/&gt;so far are that zeros of systems of polynomials tend to repel in&lt;br/&gt;dimension one,&lt;br/&gt;be liike a neutral gas in dimension two and attract in higher&lt;br/&gt;dimensions. New&lt;br/&gt;problems are to explore the dependence of the distribution of zeros on&lt;br/&gt;the Newton&lt;br/&gt;polytope or on the number of monomials, as in Khovanski's fewnomial&lt;br/&gt;theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Semiclassical analysis is the area of mathematics which explores the&lt;br/&gt;classical&lt;br/&gt;limit of quantum mechancs,  i.e.the  limit where the fuzzy, jumpy small&lt;br/&gt;scale behavior&lt;br/&gt;of atoms and molecules merges with the solid, mechanical world we&lt;br/&gt;experience.&lt;br/&gt;Planck's constant h measures the length scale. Although it arose in&lt;br/&gt;physics,&lt;br/&gt;the same limit, as h tends to zero, arises in many problems in&lt;br/&gt;mathematics and&lt;br/&gt;science, often quite disconnected from the original physical&lt;br/&gt;background. This&lt;br/&gt;proposal is concerned with several problems of this kind. Several are&lt;br/&gt;traditional&lt;br/&gt;and well-known problems, for instance trying to determine a domain from&lt;br/&gt;its&lt;br/&gt;frequencies of vibration.  Using semiclassical analysis of a kind more&lt;br/&gt;familiar to&lt;br/&gt;physicists than mathematicians (Balian-Bloch methods, Feynman&lt;br/&gt;diagrams), &lt;br/&gt;the first project is to obtain the best results to date on the problem,&lt;br/&gt;can one&lt;br/&gt;hear the shape of a drum.  The results so far indicate that this method&lt;br/&gt;is better&lt;br/&gt;than any prior method. Another project is to view the degree of a&lt;br/&gt;polynomial&lt;br/&gt;as 1/h (inverse Planck constant)  and to use semiclassical methods to&lt;br/&gt;find new&lt;br/&gt;statistical patterns in zeros and critical points of polynomials.  One&lt;br/&gt;result is&lt;br/&gt;that the exponents which occur in the polynomials have a big impact on&lt;br/&gt;the&lt;br/&gt;positions of the zeros, leading to a tunnelling theory of zeros&lt;br/&gt;analogous&lt;br/&gt;to the tunnelling theory of electrons through barriers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0302518</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steve</FirstName>
<LastName>Zelditch</LastName>
<EmailAddress>zelditch@math.northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/08/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212182686</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439971898</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1101 E 33rd St</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0103</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
