<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dynamics From Forced Symmetry-Breaking</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>123838.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>123838</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Warchall</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Systems with symmetries arise frequently in applications. Such systems exhibit behavior&lt;br/&gt;that is not typical of nonsymmetric systems. Even though this behavior may be more complex&lt;br/&gt;than expected techniques from equivariant bifurcation theory permit one to analyze its&lt;br/&gt;origin and properties. However, in many applications the presence of symmetry is an&lt;br/&gt;idealization. It is important therefore to understand which aspects of the dynamics of the&lt;br/&gt;symmetric system are robust with respect to small symmetry-breaking imperfections. In many&lt;br/&gt;cases the loss of both discrete and continuous symmetries introduces global bifurcations&lt;br/&gt;into the dynamics and hence the possibility of chaotic time-dependence. This project&lt;br/&gt;proposes a study of such symmetry-breaking perturbations in several important classes of&lt;br/&gt;systems arising incontinuum mechanics (fluid flow, chemically reacting systems etc) with&lt;br/&gt;emphasis on identifying robust behavior both near threshold of a primary instability and&lt;br/&gt;further away from it. The former gives rise to low-dimensional systems with broken&lt;br/&gt;symmetry via center manifold reduction, while the latter require a study of partial&lt;br/&gt;differential equations. Special emphasis is placed on understanding the effects of&lt;br/&gt;breaking both reflection symmetry and translation invariance (both separately and&lt;br/&gt;simultaneously). Phenomena arising from the breaking of time-translation invariance due to&lt;br/&gt;parametric forcing and the loss of Galilean invariance will also be studied. The goal of&lt;br/&gt;the project is to gain a deep understanding of the limitations on the applicability of&lt;br/&gt;idealized models and to provide a description of the type of behavior that is typical of&lt;br/&gt;''nearly-symmetric'' systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project aims at understanding the basic principles behind robust behavior. For&lt;br/&gt;example, understanding the effects of broken reflection symmetry is essential when&lt;br/&gt;studying the effects of a small inclination of an apparatus to the horizontal, and the&lt;br/&gt;effects of through-flow or rotation on transitions from one state to another. Problems of&lt;br/&gt;this type arise in microscopic situations (thin films on horizontal or inclined&lt;br/&gt;substrates) in geophysics (for example in oceanography) and everywhere in between.&lt;br/&gt;Similarly, understanding the trapping of wavelike disturbances by spatial inhomogemeities&lt;br/&gt;is of importance not only in catalysis where the inhomogeneities may be on atomic scale,&lt;br/&gt;and in the trapping of weather patterns by topography.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0305968</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edgar</FirstName>
<LastName>Knobloch</LastName>
<EmailAddress>knobloch@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/30/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
