<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI:Hyperbolic 3-Manifolds and Knots</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>144219</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In 1978, William Thurston revolutionized low-dimensional topology by&lt;br/&gt;demonstrating that many 3-manifolds have hyperbolic metrics. The Mostow&lt;br/&gt;Rigidity Theorem then implies that these metrics can be used to generate&lt;br/&gt;interesting invariants to distinguish hyperbolic 3-manifolds.  A tremendous&lt;br/&gt;number of results have come out of these ideas. The goal of this proposal&lt;br/&gt;is to further understand hyperbolic 3-manifolds. In particular, there are a&lt;br/&gt;set of invariants that come out of the cusps of hyperbolic 3-manifolds, and&lt;br/&gt;hyperbolic knots, including the cusp volume, the meridian length and the&lt;br/&gt;longitude length. The plan is to continue to work on these invariants,&lt;br/&gt;delineating better their possible range of values and determining their&lt;br/&gt;implications for the rest of the hyperbolic structure. Moreover, recent&lt;br/&gt;work has demonstrated the existence of totally geodesic surfaces in&lt;br/&gt;hyperbolic knot complements. Their existence is suprising and exciting. It&lt;br/&gt;is hoped that a determination can be made as to which knots possess such&lt;br/&gt;surfaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding hyperbolic 3-manifolds has implications for determining the&lt;br/&gt;shape of the spatial universe.  These invariants will be the kind that&lt;br/&gt;cosmologists may use to empirically identify the universe. Although recent&lt;br/&gt;measurements of the cosmic background radiation point to a curvature very&lt;br/&gt;close to flat, this could mean that the universe is hyperbolic, but very&lt;br/&gt;large. Then more subtle hyperbolic invariants will be necessary to&lt;br/&gt;determine its topological shape.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0306211</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colin</FirstName>
<LastName>Adams</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Colin.Adams@williams.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Williams College</Name>
<CityName>Williamstown</CityName>
<ZipCode>012672600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135974352</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>880 Main St.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
