<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Complex Flows In Porous Media</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Fluid flows in porous materials are ubiquitous in natural, industrial &lt;br/&gt;and biological settings.  These range from relatively simple flows &lt;br/&gt;through homogeneous media with uniform and well-characterized properties &lt;br/&gt;to very complex flows in strongly heterogeneous media, or in reactive &lt;br/&gt;and/or deformable porous media in which the thermochemistry of the fluid &lt;br/&gt;and the dynamics of the flow can significantly alter the properties of the &lt;br/&gt;media which in turn then further complicate the flow.  Three such complex &lt;br/&gt;flows form the scientific basis for this proposal.  The first, a materials&lt;br/&gt;science application, arises during the solidification of a ternary alloy.  &lt;br/&gt;Here the porous medium is made up of dendritic crystals that solidify or &lt;br/&gt;melt depending on local thermodynamic conditions of the interstitial fluid.  &lt;br/&gt;The fluid flow and solidification processes are tightly coupled in this &lt;br/&gt;reactive porous medium.  The second project arises in response to interest &lt;br/&gt;by environmental scientists in developing strategies for the removal or &lt;br/&gt;containment of groundwater contaminants in nonhomogeneous porous media.  &lt;br/&gt;The proposed work addresses gravity-driven flow through spatially nonuniform &lt;br/&gt;porous media using asymptotic homogenization methods in order to identify &lt;br/&gt;effective media properties which characterize a relatively complex porous &lt;br/&gt;media by a much simpler description.  The third project involves fluid flow&lt;br/&gt;through a porous medium whose porous matrix can be deformed by the fluid &lt;br/&gt;moving through it.  Such flows appear in soils, in tissues, organs and &lt;br/&gt;tumors in the human body and in industrial applications such as injection &lt;br/&gt;molding, filtration and inkjet printing.  The proposed work attempts to &lt;br/&gt;extend mathematical modeling tools for inkjet printing technology and to &lt;br/&gt;connect these ideas to other application areas. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The proposed research is of an interdisciplinary nature that through&lt;br/&gt;the use of applied mathematical techniques addresses directly problems &lt;br/&gt;in materials processing, environmental science and industrial printing &lt;br/&gt;technologies.  Applications impacted directly by this research include &lt;br/&gt;industrial alloy processing, strategies for the removal or containment of &lt;br/&gt;groundwater contaminants and related environmental hazards, and flows &lt;br/&gt;arising during industrial applications such as inkjet printing.  This &lt;br/&gt;work may indirectly impact the understanding of geophysical flows that &lt;br/&gt;occur in the earth's core or during the formation and melting of sea ice, &lt;br/&gt;other industrial applications such as injection molding and filtration, &lt;br/&gt;and biological applications involving the transport of fluid in tissues, &lt;br/&gt;organs and tumors in the human body.  The work proposed by the PI at &lt;br/&gt;George Mason University will involve collaboration with researchers at &lt;br/&gt;the University of Tennessee, the University of North Carolina as well &lt;br/&gt;as with researchers in the United Kingdom and at the National Institute &lt;br/&gt;of Standards and Technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0306996</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Anderson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>danders1@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/31/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Mason University</Name>
<CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
<ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
