<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Multiscale theory for paraxial waves with applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150811.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150811</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Warchall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hwarchal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924861</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Award Abstract: DMS-0307011, Knut Solna, University of California-Irvine&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: Multiscale theory for paraxial waves with applications&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;  When a laser beam propagates&lt;br/&gt;  through the atmosphere it is affected by bad whether and&lt;br/&gt;  turbulence. Similarly wireless communication systems,&lt;br/&gt;  remote sensing systems and imaging algorithms are affected&lt;br/&gt;  by medium fluctuations.&lt;br/&gt;  This proposal aims at developing a theory for waves propagating in&lt;br/&gt;  random and multiscale media that is needed to describe&lt;br/&gt;  and analyze such phenomena and at applying this theory&lt;br/&gt;  for optimal design of systems involving waves&lt;br/&gt;  in complicated and multiscale media.&lt;br/&gt;  The medium heterogeneity is modeled&lt;br/&gt;  by a random field and one aims at&lt;br/&gt;  analyzing  the statistical character of &lt;br/&gt;  the waves that have propagated through the medium.&lt;br/&gt;  Two regimes are considered. First, a regime with a clear&lt;br/&gt;  ``scale separation'' where the medium variations&lt;br/&gt;  take place on a microscale,&lt;br/&gt;  a scale that is much smaller than the wave length for instance.&lt;br/&gt;  Second, the case with variations on a continuum of&lt;br/&gt;  scales, like in turbulence, is being considered.&lt;br/&gt;  Despite the importance of this regime there is no&lt;br/&gt;  general theory that describes how the medium&lt;br/&gt;  affects the wave pulse in this case.&lt;br/&gt;  In the novel approach set forth here one aims to analyze&lt;br/&gt;  these regimes in a unified&lt;br/&gt;  framework in which the medium fluctuations are described&lt;br/&gt;  by a Brownian field and  then one aims to develop a general&lt;br/&gt;  scaling theory for such a  white noise model. That is, a description&lt;br/&gt;  of moments of the wave field and how these&lt;br/&gt;  depend on for instance the relative propagation distance.&lt;br/&gt;  The analysis involves stochastic differential equations&lt;br/&gt;  driven by the Brownian field and how the moments of the&lt;br/&gt;  solution can be described in various regimes using martingale&lt;br/&gt;  theory, this is a topic of general interest in stochastic analysis.&lt;br/&gt;  In the analysis the parabolic or forward scattering approximation&lt;br/&gt;  that leads to a random Schr\"odinger equation as well&lt;br/&gt;  as acoustic and electromagnetic waves will be considered.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;  In the atmosphere &lt;br/&gt;  small scale fluctuations of&lt;br/&gt;  temperature, pressure and humidity caused&lt;br/&gt;  by the turbulence of air velocities &lt;br/&gt;  lead to complicated and multiscale spatial and temporal variations&lt;br/&gt;  in the wave-speed.&lt;br/&gt;  The turbulence results therefore in &lt;br/&gt;  phenomena like wave  beam wander, beam broadening&lt;br/&gt;  and intensity fluctuation (scintillation).&lt;br/&gt;  The proposed work that will characterize such effects&lt;br/&gt;  is important for the design of imaging and&lt;br/&gt;  communication algorithms and several applications&lt;br/&gt;  will be considered.&lt;br/&gt;  The work regarding propagation and communication  &lt;br/&gt;  in the turbulent atmosphere is particularly important&lt;br/&gt;  due to the significance of associated applications&lt;br/&gt;  like laser communication and tracking and since so far&lt;br/&gt;  little theory is available.&lt;br/&gt;  The theory is needed for design&lt;br/&gt;  of for instance optimal communication protocols, multiple-input-multiple-output&lt;br/&gt;  antenna systems for wireless communication, for design of secure&lt;br/&gt;  communication algorithms and robust tracking algorithms&lt;br/&gt;  through the atmosphere.&lt;br/&gt;  As a part of this work the development&lt;br/&gt;  of Speclab a general purpose software package for&lt;br/&gt;  analysis of multiscale and turbulent data has been initiated&lt;br/&gt;  and it will be further developed.  &lt;br/&gt;  It has so far been used for analysis of atmospheric turbulence&lt;br/&gt;  data (Kirtland Air Force Base) and also for analysis of biomedical data (Harvard University).&lt;br/&gt;  This work is important to guide the modeling of the wave phenomena&lt;br/&gt;  and ensure the relevance of our work. &lt;br/&gt;  The work on waves in multiscale media will also be important for understanding wave-fields&lt;br/&gt;  propagating in the heterogeneous earth, the fluctuating and&lt;br/&gt;  stratified ocean and through biological tissue.&lt;br/&gt;  In these contexts some important applications that will&lt;br/&gt;  be considered relates to medical imaging, imaging through&lt;br/&gt;  foliage and mine detection.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0307011</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Knut</FirstName>
<LastName>Solna</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Knut Solna</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ksolna@math.uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498243154</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488699</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Aldrich Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0103</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0104</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2003~41761</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2004~109050</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
