<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Systematics and Biogeography of the Genus Hysterangium (Basidiomycota, Phallales)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James E. Rodman</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A grant has been awarded to Dr. Joseph Spatafora and Mr. Kentaro &lt;br/&gt;Hosaka at Oregon State University to conduct the study "Systematics &lt;br/&gt;and biogeography of the genus Hysterangium".   Hysterangium is a &lt;br/&gt;genus of mushroom-forming fungi that produces fruiting bodies below &lt;br/&gt;ground. Unlike many of the above ground mushrooms, which can disperse &lt;br/&gt;their spores by wind, Hysterangium's spores are only dispersed when &lt;br/&gt;consumed by animals and deposited with their feces. This fact implies &lt;br/&gt;that long distance (e.g., intercontinental) dispersal of Hysterangium &lt;br/&gt;is improbable. The distribution of Hysterangium, however, is &lt;br/&gt;worldwide. This can be explained by the hypothesis that Hysterangium &lt;br/&gt;is a rather ancient organism and its present distribution was caused &lt;br/&gt;by the breakup of the supercontinent Pangaea. Importantly, &lt;br/&gt;Hysterangium forms mycorrhizae (beneficial relationships with the &lt;br/&gt;roots) with many different tree species. Because these relationships &lt;br/&gt;are specific, Hysterangium and host trees may have cospeciated. The &lt;br/&gt;overall goal of this study is to develop robust hypotheses for &lt;br/&gt;biogeography and cospeciation of Hysterangium by collecting and &lt;br/&gt;analyzing DNA sequences. To achieve this goal, field expeditions to &lt;br/&gt;previously underrepresented areas, Papua New Guinea, New Caledonia, &lt;br/&gt;and New Zealand, will be conducted with a special emphasis on the &lt;br/&gt;Nothofagus (southern beech) forests.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hysterangium is an important component of forest ecosystems. It &lt;br/&gt;produces abundant fruiting bodies, and many animals are heavily &lt;br/&gt;dependent on such below ground mushrooms in their diet. Also, &lt;br/&gt;mycorrhizal relationships of Hysterangium and host trees are &lt;br/&gt;mutualistic. Surveying the Hysterangium flora of Nothofagus forests &lt;br/&gt;provides a more clear understanding of these ecosystems, which in &lt;br/&gt;turn facilitates more proper forest management. Despite the fact that &lt;br/&gt;fungi are one of the most diverse groups of organisms on earth, &lt;br/&gt;biogeography of fungi is poorly understood. This study will provide &lt;br/&gt;more accurate understanding of biogeographic and cospeciation &lt;br/&gt;patterns of mycorrhizal fungi with Hysterangium as a model organism.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0309412</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Spatafora</LastName>
<EmailAddress>spatafoj@science.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/19/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
