<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Incorporation of Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy Throughout the Chemistry Curriculum</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>52392.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>52392</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>kristina parsons</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Chemistry (12)  NMR methodologies are being incorporated into a discovery-based chemistry curriculum by using NMR experiments, developed at other sites, and adapted to enhance the education of a predominantly female population. The experiments being adapted come from various disciplines and have been published in the Journal of Chemical Education.  However, the experiments also serve to enhance a larger picture of the curriculum.  An Anasazi Instruments Fourier Transform 60 MHz NMR will be acquired to perform the experiments in the different laboratory courses in the curriculum.  In the organic chemistry laboratory students are using the NMR to determine the structures of the products they synthesize. Students performing a large multi-step research synthesis project in the second semester organic course are using the NMR to provide clear evidence of the successful completion of the student-designed syntheses. In the analytical chemistry courses, students are exploring the quantitative capabilities of the NMR spectrometer and the influence of changing acquisition parameters on spectral quality.  In the biochemistry courses, the NMR is being used to explore peptide conformation and the kinetics of glucose metabolism.  The instrumentation obtained for this project is being used in conjunction with instrumentation purchased from previous NSF grants to the department.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0310728</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Ensel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sensel@hood.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/03/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Bennett</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Bennett@Hood.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/03/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hood College</Name>
<CityName>Frederick</CityName>
<ZipCode>217018575</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3016963828</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>401 Rosemont Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7428</Code>
<Text>CCLI-ADAPTATION AND IMPLEMENTA</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7428</Code>
<Text>CCLI-ADAPTATION AND IMPLEMENTA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
