<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Robust Krylov Subspace Methods Based on Multiple Lanczos Procedure</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>73788.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>73788</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Krylov subspace methods are widely used for the iterative solution of large&lt;br/&gt;sparse linear systems that arise in scientific and engineering applications.&lt;br/&gt;The standard Krylov subspace methods have been developed based on either the&lt;br/&gt;single starting Lanczos procedure (SSLP) or Arnoldi procedure.&lt;br/&gt;Since the multiple starting Lanczos procedure (MSLP) was invented,&lt;br/&gt;the superior robustness of MSLP to SSLP has been demonstrated through a variety &lt;br/&gt;of applications. Block Krylov subspace methods for solving linear systems with &lt;br/&gt;multiple right-hand sides have been derived from MSLP. However, there has been &lt;br/&gt;rare study of deriving Krylov subspace methods from MSLP for systems with a &lt;br/&gt;single right-hand side. Of course, multiple right-hand sides includes the single right-hand&lt;br/&gt;side as its special case. The PI, however, expects that finer methods can be&lt;br/&gt;obtained when we focus on the single right-hand side case. Tony Chan and the PI&lt;br/&gt;recently made the first attempt in this direction and methods named ML(n)BiCG&lt;br/&gt;and ML(n)BiCGSTAB, respectively, were developed. This project continues this&lt;br/&gt;trend and aims at (i) generalizing the existing standard methods from SSLP&lt;br/&gt;to MSLP; (ii) reducing the storage requirement of ML(n)BiCGSTAB; (iii) improving &lt;br/&gt;the robustness of ML(n)BiCG. This is the next step toward attainment of the PI's &lt;br/&gt;long-term goal of developing parallel Krylov subspace methods. The feasibility of the &lt;br/&gt;proposed aims have been demonstrated by the PI's preliminary studies of &lt;br/&gt;ML(n)BiCGSTAB and of a transpose-free MSLP algorithm. The approaches employed &lt;br/&gt;to attain the aims are based on certain ways of adapting the derivation of BiCG from SSLP and&lt;br/&gt;the derivation of the BiCGSTAB(n) from BiCG.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results will be tested extensively with industrial databases, for example,&lt;br/&gt;the Harwell-Boeing Sparse Matrix Collection. If successful,&lt;br/&gt;the research proposed will be significant because it will&lt;br/&gt;dramatically improve the robustness of the existing methods and, as a result,&lt;br/&gt;significantly drive down the time and cost in computation. It also allows for&lt;br/&gt;the development of more robust parallel Krylov subspace methods, for example,&lt;br/&gt;by rescheduling the operations into parallelism. The research will also provide &lt;br/&gt;ideal topics for class learning and thesis research. Moreover, the PI once participated&lt;br/&gt;in research in Chemical and Petroleum Engineering, University of Wyoming, on&lt;br/&gt;removing nitrogen oxides from combustion exhaust streams. The resulting&lt;br/&gt;methods of the project will promote the collaboration in future because more robust&lt;br/&gt;algorithms will then be available to use in solving the PDE models&lt;br/&gt;arising from the collaborative study.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0314152</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Manchung</FirstName>
<LastName>Yeung</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Manchung Yeung</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>myeung@uwyo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3077663208</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491211</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wyoming</Name>
<CityName>Laramie</CityName>
<CountyName>ALBANY</CountyName>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3077665320</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 E. University Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2>Department 3355</StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069690956</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WYOMING</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069690956</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wyoming]]></Name>
<CityName>Laramie</CityName>
<CountyName>ALBANY</CountyName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 E. University Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9216</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0103</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2003~73788</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
