<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SGER:  Geotechnical Reconnaissance of the 3 November 2002, Mw 7.9, Denali- Earthquake, Alaska</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>75037.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>75037</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Fragaszy</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A magnitude 7.9 earthquake struck central Alaska on 3 November 2002.  The earthquake resulted from slip on the Denali fault that is comparable in size to California's San Andreas Fault.  The magnitude of the earthquake, and the type and magnitude of the fault rupture are within the range of a maximum credible earthquake that would be expected on the San Andreas Fault.  Thus, this earthquake provides a unique opportunity to study the geotechnical effects of a major strike slip fault rupture with characteristics very similar to those assumed for the San Andreas Fault.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective is to support a rapid-response reconnaissance of the earthquake damage in order to document the geotechnical and engineering geologic features of this major earthquake.  Experience with major earthquakes shows that much of the surface phenomena associated with faulting, landslides, and ground failure such as liquefaction is highly perishable.  In this case, the onset of winter will rapidly obscure many of the surficial features, and spring snowmelt will further obscure most of the surface exposures.  Therefore, it is essential that collection of information commence as soon as can be arranged; to be followed by additional detailed work once the weather permits in the spring.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of the survey are being made available on the web page of the Earthquake Engineering Research Center at the University of California, Berkeley,&lt;br/&gt;http://eerc.berkeley.edu/research/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0314499</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Sitar</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sitar@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/10/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0304000</Code>
<Name>Disaster &amp; Natural Hazard</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1636</Code>
<Text>Geotechnical Engineering and M</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9237</Code>
<Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
