<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>High Magnetic Fields: Future Directions For Science, Engineering and Technology</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>335000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070011</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Guebre X. Tessema</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is a study to assess current work in the science and technology associated with high magnetic fields.  The purpose of the study is to identify drivers for future research and to provide guidance for future scientific developments and magnet technology.  The study will be carried out by a committee appointed by the National Academies, and the results will be published by the National Academies Press.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;High magnetic fields are essential for scientific investigations in a wide range of areas.  They have traditionally been important in studies of the physical properties of semiconductors and other forms of condensed matter.  However, applications of high fields have now expanded to include research in areas of biology, chemistry, and geophysics, among others.  For example, strong magnetic fields are essential for nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR, the research aspect of magnetic resonance imaging, or MRI), which is being used to study the structure of proteins and polymers.  In addition, high fields are used to investigate magnetic data storage, with obvious applications to information technology, and to study the properties of high-temperature superconductors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The technology necessary to produce magnets with very high field strengths is at the forefront of engineering practice, leading current industrial capabilities.  Because the high fields generate extremely strong forces within the magnet structure itself, it is necessary to employ carefully designed, high-strength materials in their construction.  Further, because non-superconducting magnets generate considerable heat - and because superconducting magnets must be maintained at extremely low temperatures - it is essential to design such magnets to allow for efficient cooling.  These features push the frontiers of engineering and materials science beyond their current states.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Because of the importance of the science and technology associated with high magnetic fields, and because of the high cost of research in these areas, it is essential to plan future research efforts carefully.  This study, under the auspices of the National Academy of Science, will be conducted by a group of scientists and engineers with expertise spanning the wide range of disciplines that are involved in high-field magnet research.  It will provide a "roadmap" for research in these areas over the coming decade.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0318562</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Lancaster</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jlancaster@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/13/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1743</Code>
<Text>NATIONAL FACILITIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
