<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: The Molecular Comb: A Novel Tool for Protein Analysis on a Chip</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Om P. Sahai</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovative Research (SBIR) Phase I project proposes to develop a novel microscale technology to aid researchers in understanding the function of proteins in disease. The Molecular Comb technology, invented at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) and exclusively licensed by the company, utilizes semiconductor photoelectrochemistry to transport charged biomolecules inside a  channel - less &lt;br/&gt;microfluidic chip. The key innovation of the proposed work is to demonstrate the feasibility of using a chemically modified hydrophobic surface gradient in concert with the Molecular Comb biomolecular transport technology to reproducibly separate proteins on the microscale. While many of the tools for protein analysis have been in place for decades, current techniques such as two-dimensional gel electrophoresis, lack the integration, automation, and speed of analysis required by research scientists. If successfully developed, the Molecular Comb technology has the potential to fulfill this unmet market need by providing substantial performance advantages over competing protein analysis techniques,&lt;br/&gt;including automation, improved data quality, and direct integration with a mass spectrometer.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The commercial application of this project is in the area of protein separation and analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/09/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0320594</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>Sega</LastName>
<EmailAddress>garyasega@aol.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/20/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>QGENICS Biosciences, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379310000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659270043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11020 Solway School Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9107</Code>
<Text>BIOELECTRONICS AND BIONETWORKS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9216</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
