<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI/RUI Acquisition of an additional low-energy grating for the existing monochromator on the atomic and molecular physics beam line 10.0.1 at the Advanced Light Source</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>61335</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen McCloud</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This MRI award is for instrumentation is to further advance a collaborative effort between Loras College and the University of Nebraska-Lincoln (UNL) in research on atomic photoionization at the Advanced Light Source.   The research involves crossing an atomic beam with the low-energy x-rays from beam line 10 at the ALS to singly ionize argon atoms.  Excitation of the ion requires an interaction between electrons, since the energy of the ionizing photon must be partitioned between the ejected photoelectron and the residual excited electrons.  Angular momentum partitioning during this electron-electron interaction is studied by analyzing the polarization as well as the wavelength of the subsequent fluorescent decay of the residual excited ion.  The low-energy grating provided through this award will increase the spectral capabilities of the beam line.  At the same time, it will offer additional opportunities for undergraduate students at Loras College to participate in research in the rich environment of a national laboratory.  The instrumentation will also become part of the infrastructure open to all researchers proposing experiments on the beam line.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0321055</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>McLaughlin</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kenneth.mclaughlin@loras.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Loras College</Name>
<CityName>Dubuque</CityName>
<ZipCode>520014327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5635887336</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1450 Alta Vista</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
