<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Computer Science and Mathematics Scholarships</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>395934.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>395934</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lesia L. Crumpton-Young</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Interdisciplinary (99)-This project is providing scholarships for 30 talented but financially disadvantaged students to encourage and enable their achievement of baccalaureate degrees in Computer Science and Information Systems (CSIS) or Mathematics. In addition to financial support, the students are receiving academic and nonacademic support in order to improve their knowledge and skills, to increase their retention, to improve their professional development and preparation for employment, and to increase their placements in graduate school. Academic support is being provided by a new, 1-credit course "Bridges Connecting Computer Science and Calculus", an existing  "Women in Computing" course, new tutoring support in computer programming, internship opportunities, and a research seminar. Two mathematics professors designed the "Bridges" course especially for CSIS majors to complement and to be taken in conjunction with the standard Calculus course. The purpose of the new course is to clearly demonstrate connections between calculus and computing, and give students extra practice and motivation in a female and minority friendly setting. The "Women in Computing" course targets freshmen and serves to recruit women into CSIS. Nonacademic support is being provided by several activities: a new mentoring program, the Computer Society, and other existing on-going programs. The mentoring program is the hallmark activity of the nonacademic support. Five mentors from the CSIS Math faculties have groups consisting of 6 students each and they meet monthly. The group meetings are providing the students the opportunity to bond with each other, to share problems and solutions, and to ask questions. The students, in consultation with their mentors, are preparing Individual Educational Plans (IEP) that include academic courses to be taken, internships, club memberships, leadership roles, and preparation for graduate school. The project team personnel select the students with inputs from Financial Aid Office personnel. The students are selected for the program based on their financial need and the other CSEMS eligibility criteria. Specifically, the program is intended for all currently enrolled Math and/or CSIS majors with a cumulative GPA of 3.0+, and new academically talented students. Special consideration is given to members of groups that are typically underrepresented.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The project improves students' learning in computer science through participation in a seminar that bridges the gap between calculus and computer science, and enrollment in a course on "Women in Computing". Students will gain deeper understanding of computer science content areas through a new tutoring program and special seminars. The project results from a team effort among computer science and mathematics faculty who together have organized its activities for synergistic effects that improve students' cognitive and affective skills.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The diversity of computer science students will be increased as a result of this project. Additionally, this endeavor will draw together faculty and students from several disciplines, creating new alliances for a common goal of improving computer science and mathematics graduation rates. The mentoring and tutoring programs will increase retention of students. Placement in graduate school will be increased by the capstone research project. All of these features will produce better-prepared students and graduates which will enhance their employability.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0323917</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chia-Lin</FirstName>
<LastName>Wu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chia-Lin Wu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Chia-Lin.Wu@stockton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6096524428</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000489394</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jill</FirstName>
<LastName>Gerhardt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jill Gerhardt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gerhardj@stockton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6096524477</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000201546</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohamed</FirstName>
<LastName>Neilforoshan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mohamed Neilforoshan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>neilform@stockton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6096521776</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000354720</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Saralyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Mathis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Saralyn Mathis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mathisl@stockton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6096521776</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000261874</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Olan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael J Olan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>olanm@stockton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6096521776</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000324255</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stockton University</Name>
<CityName>Galloway</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>082059441</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6096524844</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>101 Vera King Farris Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>119839082</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>STOCKTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>119839082</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stockton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Galloway</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>082059441</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 Vera King Farris Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>CSEMS--CS, ENG &amp; MATH SCHOLAR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2003~395934</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
