<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Post-Earthquake Geotechnical Reconnaissance Working Group</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>155705.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>172705</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Fragaszy</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;Documenting and compiling the key lessons learned from major earthquake events around the world contributes significantly to advancing research and practice in geotechnical earthquake engineering.  Many of the current design procedures are based on empirical methods that require re-evaluation and updating as important case histories emerge.  However, much of the data and information generated by major earthquake is perishable and therefore must be collected within a few days or weeks of the occurrence of the earthquake.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This action is to support the formation of the Post-Earthquake Geotechnical Reconnaissance (GeoRecon) Working Group, a small working group of researchers with experience in post-earthquake geotechnical investigations.  The activities of this working group will rely heavily on telecommunication and Internet usage - such as teleconferences, e-mail, and posting to web sites; however it will also meet twice a year for face-to-face discussions.  In addition, the GeoRecon Working Group will receive guidance from a broad-based Advisory Panel, a larger group of prominent geotechnical engineers, earthquake engineers and scientists in related fields, and personnel belonging to organizations that also actively participate in post-earthquake reconnaissance.  The GeoRecon activity will broaden, diversify, and train a new generation of geotechnical engineers in post-earthquake reconnaissance and learning from such earthquakes.  It will also consider new technologies and techniques that can effectively contribute to post-earthquake reconnaissance, such as GPS (Global Positioning System), Airborne LIDAR (LIght Detection And Ranging), and satellite SAR (Synthetic Aperture Radar).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NSF has regularly supported geotechnical earthquake engineers, and separately, tsunami coastal engineers, who have self-assembled to form effective post-earthquake and post-tsunami reconnaissance teams.  The goal of the GeoRecon Working Group is to better define these activities, and to interface more effectively with other teams and organizations that also participate in post-earthquake reconnaissance visits.  For example, the Earthquake Engineering Research Institute (EERI), and the US Geological Survey (USGS) are other organizations that actively engage in post-earthquake investigations.  These organizations each have a particular mission; but do not focus on geotechnical issues.  Past geotechnical reconnaissance teams have interacted and collaborated effectively with other reconnaissance teams, and it is expected that this interaction will be more effective with the formation of the GeoRecon Working Group.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Moreover, the GeoRecon activity will serve as a model for other disciplines regarding the valuable data that can be captured immediately after a natural hazard.  By joining with other professions who have also developed effective procedures and sharing the results of this research with other communities, documentation of the effects of natural hazards will improve overall.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/05/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0323914</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Bray</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bray@ce.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/05/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0304000</Code>
<Name>Disaster &amp; Natural Hazard</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1636</Code>
<Text>Geotechnical Engineering and M</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1039</Code>
<Text>RENEWAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
