<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ITR Collaborative Research: Pervasively Secure Infrastructures (PSI): Integrating Smart Sensing, Data Mining, Pervasive Networking, and Community Computing.</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Xiaoyang Wang</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>        This project addresses homeland security, an issue of the highest national priority, with a goal of monitoring, preventing, and recovering from natural and inflicted disasters. In particular, in collaboration with team from UT Arlington, Penn State University and the University of Kentucky, the project will create a novel technology-enabled security framework, called Pervasively Secure Infrastructures (PSI), that will make use of such advanced technologies as smart sensors, wireless networks, pervasive computing, mobile agents, data mining, and profile-based learning in an integrated, collaborative and distributed manner. The uniqueness of this multi-disciplinary, multi-university proposal lies in the synergistic combination of the proposed research in (i) efficient data collection and aggregation from heterogeneous sensors and monitors; (ii) novel techniques for real-time, secured, authenticated information transmission and sharing, and (ii) intelligent situation awareness (e.g., threat detection and security services) through new learning, data mining, and knowledge discovery techniques. The project will mainly focus on authentication and secure data transmission in wireless networks. The project will integrate these research efforts in the novel paradigm of pervasive community computing that can efficiently handle dynamically changing information, adapt to changing situations, and provide scalability in terms of the number of users, devices, and data sizes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0324836</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mukesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Singhal</LastName>
<EmailAddress>singhal@cs.uky.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raphael</FirstName>
<LastName>Finkel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>raphael@cs.uky.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Lexington</CityName>
<ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0104000</Code>
<Name>Information Systems</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1687</Code>
<Text>ITR MEDIUM (GROUP) GRANTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1655</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION MANAGEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9216</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
