<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Scholarships for Students in Mathematics, Engineering and Computer Science</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>206252</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sheryl A. Sorby</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The College of St. Scholastica (CSS) seeks to increase the number of students graduating in CSEMS fields and to better prepare these graduates for their careers.  The program targets talented but financially disadvantaged youth with a special emphasis on women, minorities, and people with disabilities.  The projects objectives are: &lt;br/&gt;1) to increase the number of well-educated and skilled employees in technical areas of national need by encouraging exploration of graduate level study and/or improving professional development and job seeking skills. Students are receiving guidance and support as they consider the next step in their careers.  Activities include: mentoring, tutoring, internships, and summer research opportunities.  Workshops are being provided that address such topics as graduate school exploration, professionalism, resume preparation, and research skills. As a result of these activities, 100% of CSEMS program graduates are either enrolling in graduate school or finding employment. &lt;br/&gt;2) To improve educational opportunities for students pursuing a bachelor's degree in computer science, engineering, or mathematics. The program is designed to support 15 participants during each year of the four-year project period.  Program applicants are required to have a GPA of 3.00 or greater and must be formally accepted into one the following programs: Computer Science, Engineering, or Mathematics.&lt;br/&gt;3) Increase retention rates and degree attainment among CSEMS program participants. Activities&lt;br/&gt;related to this objective include faculty mentoring, tutoring, and individual counseling sessions. At least 90% of the program participants will attain a bachelor's degree in a CSEMS discipline.&lt;br/&gt;4) Strengthen the partnership between CSS and related employers in the fields of computer science, engineering, and mathematics.  By coordinating with local businesses and state agencies, at least ten new internship/research opportunities are being established.&lt;br/&gt;5) Maintain strong student support programs at CSS.  Over the past two years of program operation, the Co-PI's have integrated the CSEMS objectives with the College's pre-existing student support programs.  Formative and summative evaluation ensure the strength of these services.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This project is advancing knowledge and understanding in the CSEMS fields by diversifying the pool of young graduates and ensuring that they are well-prepared for the next step in their careers.  The qualifications of the Co-PI's are reflected in the 100% retention rate of CSEMS participants over the past two years. The combination of activities and services represents a unique and comprehensive program that is necessary to meet the needs of the target population. Participants have access to a wide range of lab equipment, services, technology, and mentors.  Broader Impacts: The project is designed to encourage active learning by promoting research and internship opportunities.  CSS has a long history of providing educational opportunities for underserved populations; these efforts are supported by the College's Student Diversity Advocate, the Minority Recruiter, and the Ojibwe Coordinator, who are all actively involved in this project.  The CSEMS project fits into the College's effort to increase both undergraduate student research and internship opportunities and is having a broad impact by matching the needs of the high technology workplace with well-prepared but traditionally underserved youth.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0324115</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Cargill</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kcargill@css.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/31/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/08/2005</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Guanshen</FirstName>
<LastName>Ren</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gren@css.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/31/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosato</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Jrosato@css.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/08/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>College of Saint Scholastica</Name>
<CityName>Duluth</CityName>
<ZipCode>558114199</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2187236072</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 Kenwood Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>CSEMS--CS, ENG &amp; MATH SCHOLAR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
