<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>TSE: Catalysts for the Selective, Low Temperature Functionalization of Alkanes and Arenes</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>443000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090005</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Carol Bessel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Roy Periana, University of Southern California, is supported by the Inorganic, Bioinorganic and Organometallic Chemistry Program for the development and study of new catalysts. The focus of the proposed work is the rational design of homogeneous catalysts for the conversion of hydrocarbons, such as methane and benzene, to the corresponding alcohols with higher selectivities and lower temperatures than existing processes. These homogeneous catalytic systems involve transition metals, often platinum or iridium, supported by carefully designed ligand systems that will stabilize the catalysts to the protic media and redox as well as geometry changes inherent in hydrocarbon functionalization catalysis to generate alcohol products. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is made through the NSF-EPA Partnership for Environmental Research, Technology for a Sustainable Environment Program (TSE). This research will advance the discovery, development, and use of innovative technologies and approaches to avoid or minimize the generation of pollutants at the source. Students trained by this project will gain expertise in synthetic, mechanistic and spectroscopic&lt;br/&gt;methods as well as an understanding of "green" chemical manufacturing.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0328121</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Roy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Periana</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rperiana@scripps.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/01/2003</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Southern California</Name>
      <CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
      <ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
