<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Starter Grant: Circadian Rhythms in Cyanobacteria</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patrick P. Dennis</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The circadian clock is a ubiquitous cellular mechanism that allows organisms to&lt;br/&gt;temporally regulate gene expression and biological function. Organisms at all levels of&lt;br/&gt;biological complexity, from prokaryotes to humans, temporally organize their cellular&lt;br/&gt;functions to allow them to capitalize on the environmental conditions (light, temperature)&lt;br/&gt;at any given time of day. Despite approximately 30 years of study on circadian&lt;br/&gt;phenomena, little is known about the fundamental mechanism of the circadian clock.&lt;br/&gt;Historically, model systems in circadian biology have been limited to complex eukaryotic&lt;br/&gt;organisms. However, recently it was discovered that the single-celled photosynthetic&lt;br/&gt;prokaryote, Synechococcus elongatus PCC 7942, has a circadian pacemaker comprised of&lt;br/&gt;the products of at least three genes, kaiA, kaiB, and kaiC. The kai locus is expressed from&lt;br/&gt;two promoters, one upstream of kaiA (monocistronic message) and one upstream of kaiB&lt;br/&gt;(dicistronic kaiBC message), that are expressed in the same circadian phase in wild-type&lt;br/&gt;cells. Previous work has shown that KaiA is required for expression from the kaiBC&lt;br/&gt;promoter, and that overexpression of kaiA enhances expression from kaiBC, suggesting&lt;br/&gt;that KaiA is a positive activator of the kaiBC promoter. KaiC is required for normal&lt;br/&gt;levels of expression from its own promoter; however, overexpression of kaiC blocks&lt;br/&gt;expression from kaiBC, suggesting a role in negative autoregulation. Although these data&lt;br/&gt;suggest that there is transcriptional regulation at the kai locus promoters, there is no&lt;br/&gt;direct evidence to suggest that KaiA or KaiC directly bind to kai promoters to regulate&lt;br/&gt;transcription. Pervious work (funded by the NSF Fellowship for Microbial Biology)&lt;br/&gt;identified a putative negative element within the kaiBC promoter region, whose presence&lt;br/&gt;is required for normal levels of KaiB production within the cyanobacterial cell. Studies&lt;br/&gt;proposed here aim to better define this negative element within the kaiBC promoter&lt;br/&gt;region, and subsequently identify trans-acting factors involved in kaiBC expression.&lt;br/&gt;The specific aims proposed here offer many opportunities that will contribute to&lt;br/&gt;the development of a successful independent research laboratory in the field of&lt;br/&gt;cyanobacterial circadian biology at The University of St. Thomas (a comprehensive&lt;br/&gt;liberal arts co-educational undergraduate university). Results of the experiments proposed&lt;br/&gt;here should advance our knowledge of the molecular mechanisms by which&lt;br/&gt;cyanobacteria tell time by identifying new components required for prokaryotic circadian&lt;br/&gt;timekeeping, while at the same time offering undergraduate students at The University of&lt;br/&gt;St. Thomas the opportunity to obtain invaluable training in microbial genetics and&lt;br/&gt;molecular biology (using the cyanobacterial circadian clock as a model system) by&lt;br/&gt;getting hands-on experience by directly addressing the questions proposed in this grant.&lt;br/&gt;In addition, students will have the opportunity to study prokaryotic circadian biology in&lt;br/&gt;light of mammalian circadian model systems. Dr. Dwight Nelson, Professor, Department&lt;br/&gt;of Biology, The University of St. Thomas, uses mice as a model system to study light&lt;br/&gt;input into the circadian clock. St. Thomas students will have the opportunity to&lt;br/&gt;investigate the scientific question of how organisms tell time utilizing diverse model&lt;br/&gt;systems. In addition, students will learn the importance of collaborative efforts between&lt;br/&gt;universities by working with Professor Susan S. Golden, Texas A&amp;M University, to&lt;br/&gt;annotate the S. elongatus PCC 7942 genome.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0329366</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jayna</FirstName>
<LastName>Ditty</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jlditty@stthomas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/07/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of St. Thomas</Name>
<CityName>St. Paul</CityName>
<ZipCode>551051096</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6519626038</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2115 Summit Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1108</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1108</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1156</Code>
<Text>MICROBIAL GENETICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7186</Code>
<Text>MICROBIAL BIO STARTER GRANT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
