<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SGER: Interaction between Near-Wall Turbulent Flows and Compliant Surfaces with Shear-Stress Coupling</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>46667</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael W. Plesniak</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PROPOSAL NO.: CTS-0330320&lt;br/&gt;PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATORS: DIETMAR REMPFER&lt;br/&gt;INSTITUTION:  ILLINOIS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;INTERACTION BETWEEN NEAR-WALL TURBULENT FLOWS AND COMPLIANT SURFACES WITH SHEAR-STRESS COUPLING&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research will be conducted concerning the interaction between wall-generated turbulence and complex compliant surfaces using analysis and direct numerical simulation. The question of whether such interactions are possible is a long-standing and as of yet unresolved issue.  One of the main goals is to achieve the ability to design compliant walls that can optimally reduce turbulent sound production and turbulent drag.  One of the main objectives is an improved understanding of the dynamical mechanisms at work in such a situation. Ultimately, this understanding then will be used to manipulate the turbulent flow such that some of its characteristics are altered in a desirable way.  The goals are to reduce the turbulent drag generated by such boundary layers, and also to attenuate the noise that is generated by the turbulent flow.&lt;br/&gt;If the design of a compliant wall as proposed can successfully reduce turbulent drag, these findings will facilitate economically attractive methods for improving the efficiency of a large number of technical systems.  The most promising candidates would be devices that depend on or are affected by turbulent flow of dense fluids, like water, petroleum, or other liquids.  It could be possible to achieve substantial drag reduction for ships and submarines, and it may also be possible to reduce pressure losses in pipelines. In addition, a graduate student will be trained in the field of turbulent research and numerical simulation of turbulent flows, and who will be able to apply the knowledge gained in the process to a wide variety of applications in technology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0330320</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dietmar</FirstName>
<LastName>Rempfer</LastName>
<EmailAddress>drempfer@pnw.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/03/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Illinois Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606163717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125673035</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10 West 35th Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9237</Code>
<Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
