<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>LSAMP:  Texas A&amp;M System Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation, Phase III Program:  Cultivating the Future</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5421413</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>A.  Hicks</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The  Texas  A&amp;M  System  Louis  Stokes  Alliance  for  Minority  Participation  Phase  III &lt;br/&gt;(TAMUS  LSAMP  III) program proposes to  nurture the future. The program will &lt;br/&gt;endeavor to sustain and extend hard-won academic gains in retention and learning &lt;br/&gt;outcomes for under-represented minority (URM) students in science, technology, &lt;br/&gt;engineering and math (STEM) disciplines, which have been achieved in partner &lt;br/&gt;institutions  during  TX  LSAMP  Phase  I  and  II.  However,  the  foremost  aim  of  the &lt;br/&gt;proposed program will be, to advance the preparation of under-represented minority &lt;br/&gt;(URM) students in science, technology,  engineering  and math (STEM) fields for &lt;br/&gt;progression to STEM graduate degree programs and to K-12 teaching in STEM subjects. &lt;br/&gt;Led by three veteran TX  LSAMP partners, and the Office of the Vice Chancellor for &lt;br/&gt;Academic  and Student Affairs Texas A&amp;M University System (TAMU System) the &lt;br/&gt;proposed Texas  LSAMP Phase  III program  will extend participation in its central &lt;br/&gt;activities to the students of six additional TAMU System universities.   &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The proposed TAMUS LSAMP III will be a five-year, three-pronged program.  &lt;br/&gt;The first prong  of  the  program  features  initial  two-year  pilot  strategies  for &lt;br/&gt;conducting and modeling new, and institutionalizable .Pipeline  Repair. tactics, which &lt;br/&gt;are  intended  to  help  renew  endangered  URM  STEM  enrollment  of  new  students  at &lt;br/&gt;TAMU  and  Prairie  View,  because  these  institutions  enroll  and  graduate  the  largest &lt;br/&gt;populations of URM STEM undergraduates in the TAMU system.  &lt;br/&gt;The second prong of the TAMUS  LSAMP  III program will include the core &lt;br/&gt;.Undergraduate  Student  Development.  strategies, which  will  be open  to  students  of &lt;br/&gt;all Alliance institutions. The strategies of this prong will operate throughout the five &lt;br/&gt;years of the TAMUS LSAMP III program. This prong will aim first, to advance retention, &lt;br/&gt;and academic attainment by improving the self-direction (self efficacy) of STEM URM &lt;br/&gt;students, and then, to improve the quality of learning for URM STEM students, and &lt;br/&gt;hence their persistence toward  graduation,  and progression, through undergraduate &lt;br/&gt;research and teaching experiences.  &lt;br/&gt;The  third  prong may  be characterized as  .Graduate  School  and  Teaching &lt;br/&gt;Articulation..    It  will  consist  of  strategies  for  proactively  negotiating  an  assisted &lt;br/&gt;transition of TAMUS  LSAMP students to STEM graduate programs,  and preferably &lt;br/&gt;those with strong systems to support URM student success, as well as encouraging and &lt;br/&gt;assisting URM STEM students pursue professional K-12 teaching. These strategies of &lt;br/&gt;this prong will be implemented in years three through five and will be made available to &lt;br/&gt;target population students from all TAMU System  LSAMP campuses. What all three-&lt;br/&gt;program  prongs  will  have  in  common  is  the  commitment  to  seeding  URM  STEM &lt;br/&gt;students with forward-looking, ambitious perspectives toward life-long learning.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/25/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0331686</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diana</FirstName>
<LastName>Marinez</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dmarinez@falcon.tamucc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/27/2007</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karan</FirstName>
<LastName>Watson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>watson@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Giardino</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jrg@vprmail.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/27/2007</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Pezold</LastName>
<EmailAddress>frank.pezold@tamucc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/29/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leo</FirstName>
<LastName>Sayavedra</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sayavedra@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/29/2007</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Butler-Purry</LastName>
<EmailAddress>klbutler@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/27/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Milton</FirstName>
<LastName>Bryant</LastName>
<EmailAddress>M_Bryant@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/29/2007</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kendall</FirstName>
<LastName>Harris</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ktharris@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/29/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9133</Code>
<Text>Alliances-Minority Participat.</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7204</Code>
<Text>DoE-NSF LABORATORY FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
