<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Symposium JJ "Combinatorial and Artificial Intelligence Methods in Materials Science II"  held at the Materials Research Society (MRS); Boston, MA; December 1-5, 2003</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>3000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070007</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Nelson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Materials Research Society Symposium on Combinatorial and Artificial Intelligence Methods in Materials Science II will be held in Boston, MA December 1-5, 2003.  The goal of the conference is to facilitate multidisciplinary interactions and information exchange within a broad spectrum of researchers, to include graduate students, post doctoral scholars and junior faculty working in priority areas of the broad field of combinatorial and high throughput materials science. The NSF funds will be used exclusively to offset the expenses associated with attending the symposium for U.S. participants, specifically graduate students, postdoctoral scholars, junior faculty and selected plenary speakers in this new area of materials research. &lt;br/&gt;%%% &lt;br/&gt;The materials research community continues to have a direct impact on important technological areas  that are crucial to advancing society through the design, synthesis and application new materials. Such areas include the fundamental scientific aspects as well as advanced applications of combinatorial materials science, artificial intelligence needs for automation, data mining and knowledge discovery. Since these technical areas are of very high priority to industry, students educated and trained in these multidisciplinary areas compete very well in the job market and go on  to contribute in many significant ways to the global economy.&lt;br/&gt;***&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/24/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/24/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0331478</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Pachavis</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pachavis@mrs.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>11/24/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Materials Research Society</Name>
<CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
<ZipCode>150867573</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>506 KEYSTONE DR</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1762</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
