<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SENSE Workshop:  Sample Environments for Neutron Scattering Experiments in Tallahassee, FL, September 24-26, 2003</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>38580.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>38580</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070011</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Guebre Tessema</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is a workshop on Sample Environments for Neutron Scattering Experiments (SENSE).  It is action-oriented, with the goals of (1) exploring the science drivers that impact issues concerning the development of advanced sample environments for neutron scattering - primarily focused on the Spallation Neutron Source (SNS) - and (2) developing a roadmap to address these needs.  Scientists who are new to the use of neutron scattering are encouraged to attend a tutorial session at the beginning of a companion NSFCHEMBIO workshop targeted at the chemistry and biology communities.  The SENSE workshop proper begins with a plenary session to consider the science case for advanced sample environments; that is, environments that provide control of the sample temperature, pressure, magnetic-field environment, and chemical environment.  The workshop continues with a series of parallel oral presentations on scientific research and on the technical aspects of leading sample environments worldwide.  This is followed by user-focused interactive sessions.  The SENSE workshop also includes a tour of the NHMFL and joint sessions with the parallel NSFCHEMBIO workshop.  Because the SENSE workshop is intended to launch the development of a science-driven roadmap for national sample-environment initiatives, it concludes with summaries by the workshop section chairs and "concept teams" and the identification of follow-up action items.  In addition to engaging experts in the field, the SENSE workshop is involving the broader community, specifically including graduate students, postdocs, and junior faculty members, as well as scientists who are new to the technique of neutron scattering.  Two of the plenary lecturers are women, and the organizers are also reaching out to several HBCUs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Neutrons with low energies are useful probes of the properties of matter, being especially responsive to structural and dynamical properties on spatial scales ranging from atomic dimensions to micro-meters.  These are scales characteristic of, for example, polymers, grains in metals and alloys, and living cells.  Neutrons also provide unique probes of magnetic properties on similar scales.  The properties of materials depend upon conditions in their environment, however.  For example, the ambient temperature, pressure, and magnetic-field environment all affect the properties of physical materials.  This is obvious near the melting or freezing point of a substance.  Similarly, the properties of living cells are affected by temperature, pressure, and the chemical environments in which they find themselves.  Up to this point, however, it has not generally been possible to provide sample environments that allow wide-ranging control of such parameters.  The purpose of this workshop is to explore the needs of the various scientific communities for advanced sample environments and to develop a plan of action to enable them to be realized.  This project is especially timely now, as the Spallation Neutron Source (SNS) approaches completion at Oak Ridge National Laboratory in 2006.  &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0335615</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Linda (Lee)</FirstName>
<LastName>Magid</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lmagid@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/15/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/28/2004</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Takeshi</FirstName>
<LastName>Egami</LastName>
<EmailAddress>egami@tennessee.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/28/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379163801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1331 CIR PARK DR</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1743</Code>
<Text>NATIONAL FACILITIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>Chemical Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9166</Code>
<Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY-GOVT LAB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
