<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Graduate Student-University-School Collaborative for Science, Mathematics, Engineering and Technology-II (GraSUS-II)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>2072059</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonia Ortega</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Graduate Student.University.School (GraSUS) Collaborative for Science, &lt;br/&gt;Mathematics, Engineering, and Technology-II &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Title of Project:  Graduate Student-University-School Collaborative for Science, &lt;br/&gt;Mathematics, Engineering and Technology-II. &lt;br/&gt;Institution:  North Dakota State University. &lt;br/&gt;PI/Co-PI:  Dogan Comez, PI; Co-PI.s: James P. Bartlett, Edward L. Deckard, Canan &lt;br/&gt;Bilen Green, David W. Haney, William O. Martin, Lisa Montplaisir, Donald P. Schwert, &lt;br/&gt;Alan R. White. &lt;br/&gt;Number of Fellows per year: 13 fellows per year. &lt;br/&gt;School District Partners: All seven Public School districts in Cass County, ND, and &lt;br/&gt;Moorhead School District, MN. &lt;br/&gt;Target Audience:  High school and Middle School. &lt;br/&gt;Setting:  Urban and rural. &lt;br/&gt;NSF Supported Disciplines Involved: Biology, Chemistry, Earth Science, General &lt;br/&gt;Science, Mathematics, Life Sciences, Physics, Physical Science, Pre-engineering.  &lt;br/&gt;   &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit. The GraSUS-II at the North Dakota State University is a project in which graduate and advanced undergraduate students and faculty work with science and mathematics teachers in grades 6-12 in urban and rural schools in Cass County, ND, and western Minnesota to enhance student achievement in math and science as measured against state and local standards. The project focuses on inquiry-based learning to promote students' learning, problem-solving skills, creative thinking, and teamwork.  It builds upon the accomplishments of and lessons learned from the prior GK-12 award [008445], and expands geographically, departmentally, and in scope to establish sustainable university-school partnerships that improve STEM education. This project provides professional development of teachers and fellows, and designs standards linked instructional strategies appropriate for grades 6-12. There is a special focus on enhancing the participation of underrepresented groups,  particularly the participation of women in STEM teaching and learning. Women are well represented in the current cadre of fellows, and special consideration will be given to maintain and even increase this representation in GraSUS-II.  &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact. The project fosters working relationships between districts, higher education, and industry, focusing on broadly improving mathematics and science achievement. The project includes: (a) recruitment activities, including incentives for participating teachers; (b) professional development and dissemination activities designed to establish the project goals; and (c) comprehensive formative and summative evaluations to monitor and help direct the project activities and document its impact. The project establishes a summer institute to develop programs and an organizational structure integrated with existing partnerships planned to continue beyond grant funding. The project will also develop an ongoing fellow support program that uses NDSU resources and service learning to involve NDSU science, math, and engineering students in sustaining GraSUS activities permanently in local public schools. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Results of Prior Project:  Teachers report their content knowledge has increased as a result of interacting with the Fellows, while their teaching skills have been enhanced by the extra materials provided by the project. One veteran physics teacher commented that working with the Fellow energized both his physics and his love of teaching. The Fellows report improved ability to discuss complex problems with a relatively naive audience and the K-12 students have gained a better understanding of the subject matter (science and mathematics) covered as well as an appreciation of who scientists are and what they do.  It has as well helped build stronger partnerships between the university and the school district.  This project is partially supported by funds from the Directorate for Mathematical and Physical Sciences. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/29/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0338128</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Schwert</LastName>
<EmailAddress>donald.schwert@ndsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/29/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dogan</FirstName>
<LastName>Comez</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dogan.comez@ndsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/29/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
<LastName>Deckard</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Edward_Deckard@ndsu.nodak.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/29/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Martin</LastName>
<EmailAddress>william.martin@ndsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/29/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Bartlett</LastName>
<EmailAddress>James.Bartlett@ndsu.nodak.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/29/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Dakota State University Fargo</Name>
<CityName>FARGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>581086050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7012318045</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Dept 4000 - PO Box 6050</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7179</Code>
<Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7179</Code>
<Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
