<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Physics and Mechanics of the Breakup of Warm Antarctic Sea Ice: In-Situ Experiments and Modeling</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>720924</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter J. Milne</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is a study of how the antarctic sea ice cover responds to stresses applied by wind and ocean waves, and how the temperature distribution within the sea ice affects these responses.  Experiments will be conducted on the deformation and fracture of warm sea ice in McMurdo Sound in the austral Spring by applying a series of controlled stresses and observing their effects.  It is known that large ice floes are affected by microstructural anisotropies, but do not fracture in the same way as small ones do, therefore it is necessary to carry out experiments on the scale of tens of meters in order to validly extrapolate the fracture process to the larger scales that have applications to engineering problems of breaking ice.  Crucial elements for this study are the obtaining of detailed information on the microstructure of the ice, such as crystal structure, brine channels, and other flaws in the ice fabric, and having a sound theoretical framework to guide the experimental work and subsequent model development. These findings will give important insight into the underlying mechanisms of ice breakup and will signi.cantly improve the reliability of models of this process. This work will improve the understanding of and ability to model the deformation and fracture of Antarctic sea ice at scales applicable to the breakup of ice sheets.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0338226</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
