<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>US-France Cooperative Research: Controlled Optoelectronic Properties of Hybrid Dioxythiophene Polymers</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Pearl</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0339735&lt;br/&gt;Reynolds&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;In this three-year U.S.-France cooperative research project, the research groups of John Reynolds at the University of Florida, and Pierre Audebert at the Ecole Normale Superieure-Cachan will investigate the development of new dioxyheterocycle-based hybrid conjugated polymers.  The U.S. team has expertise in the dioxythiophene and dioxypyrrole polymer systems.  This is complemented by French specialization in tetrazine, triazine, and cyclophane systems. The goals are to study the optoelectronic and redox properties of these polymer systems.  Four properties, which may have special impact, are targeted: n-Type doping, multi-color electrochromism, combined  electrochromic/photochromic materials, and controlled luminescence.  Instrumentation for photochromic and fluorescence experiments is available in the French laboratory.   &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The project will advance our understanding in polymer design and has potential to lead to new electrochromic/photochromic materials with applications in optics and electronics.  U.S. students will be trained in international research and have the opportunity to establish early on in their careers international research connections.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF) and the Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS).  NSF provides funds for visits to France by the investigators and graduate students.  The CNRS will support visits to the United States by the French team.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/08/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/08/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0339735</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Reynolds</LastName>
<EmailAddress>reynolds@chemistry.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/08/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5918</Code>
<Text>FRANCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5980</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0104</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
