<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>US-Germany Cooperative Research: Mechanistic Investigation of the Ribosomal Peptidyl Transferase Reaction</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>16000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Pearl</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0339595&lt;br/&gt;Strobel&lt;br/&gt;This award supports Scott A. Strobel and students from Yale University in a collaboration with Marina Rodnina of the Institute for Physical Biochemistry at the University of Witten/Herdecke, Germany.  The focus of the collaborative research will be the catalytic mechanism of the ribosomal peptidyl transferase reaction.  Recent structural results from ribosome crystallography have identified the location of the peptidyl transferase center and suggested which rRNA bases are most likely to be involved in catalysis.  However, functional identification of catalytic groups by quantitative measurements is lacking for a series of challenging technical reasons.  The collaboration between the German and US groups aims to solve these problems by combining the technical expertise of the two research groups.  The mechanistic investigation will be undertaken by combining rapid kinetic methods (German group) with the affinity purification of native ribosomal mutants, and the use of new synthetic substrate analogues (US group).  This award will also facilitate interaction and collaboration between the young scientists in the two research groups.  The international experience will provide two graduate students and one postdoctoral associate with a broader perspective of science and culture. It will also help them to see their research projects in the expanded context of an international collaboration.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/16/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0339595</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Strobel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>scott.strobel@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/18/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5936</Code>
<Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5980</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0104</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
