<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Biomathematics: Developing a Textbook and Case Study Manual for Teaching Introductory Courses in Mathematical Biology</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>74994.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74994</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel Udovic</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>There is a recognized national need for increased application of mathematical techniques to problems in biology.  In order for advanced research programs integrating mathematics and biology to succeed, strong interdisciplinary preparation is necessary and should begin early in the undergraduate years.  Currently, there are few appropriate published textbooks in biomathematics for sophomore level undergraduates.  Project principal investigators are developing a textbook entitled Biomathematics, along with a laboratory manual of hands-on, computer-assisted case study projects.  Written by a team of Sweet Briar College professors and University of Virginia researchers, the material in the text and laboratory manual is unique because it is written at a level that requires minimal prerequisites, teaches the specific approaches and problem solving skills used in biomathematics, emphasizes multiple approaches to solving some problems, and includes case studies based largely on current research projects that will heighten student interest. As colleges and universities add biomathematics courses to their curricula, the need is growing for a range of new educational materials in biomathematics, particularly at the introductory level.  The textbook and laboratory manual are appropriate for use in a first course in biomathematics, to supplement existing biology and mathematics courses, and as a source for student research projects.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0340930</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
<LastName>Davies</LastName>
<EmailAddress>davies@sbc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/05/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Kirkwood</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jrkirkwood@sbc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/05/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raina</FirstName>
<LastName>Robeva</LastName>
<EmailAddress>robeva@sbc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/05/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Sweet Briar College</Name>
<CityName>Sweet Briar</CityName>
<ZipCode>245955001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4343816100</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>134 Chapel Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7427</Code>
<Text>CCLI-EDUCATIONAL MATERIALS DEV</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
