<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Proof-of-concept Web-delivered Exploration and Production Simulations for the Introductory Geoscience Laboratory</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74994</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jill K. Singer</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Geology (42) This proof-of-concept project is developing interactive, discovery-based computer simulations for Web and wireless delivery to undergraduate students enrolled in a physical geology science laboratory course.  Students work in collaborative working groups (student corporations) to address map-based realistic problems (quarry development and oil and gas exploration) that integrate with and extend traditional geoscience laboratory topics, as well as practical business concepts such as budgets, time-constrained deadlines, and committee consensus.  In the quarry simulation, students virtually drill a landscape to determine the extent and volume of mine able industrial rock for stone production.  In the oilfield simulation, students compete for property leases required for exploration of limited oil and gas pools.  The exercises require analysis of different types of information (text, numbers, maps), and provide multiple opportunities for students to refine cognitive skills. Server-based and wireless computer technology is delivering these materials via the Web through wireless access points for personal digital assistants (PDA's) so as to override constraints in the traditional classroom of restricted mobility in time and space.  Intellectual merits of this project include students learning geologic concepts in an economic/business context, receiving quick feedback on risk/reward decisions, and providing flexible Internet access to the materials.  Broader impacts of this project include addressing societally relevant geoscience issues and targeting a non-traditional urban student population (at the PI institution).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0341541</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Brande</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sbrande@uab.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/22/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama at Birmingham</Name>
<CityName>Birmingham</CityName>
<ZipCode>352940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2059345266</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>AB 1170</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7427</Code>
<Text>CCLI-EDUCATIONAL MATERIALS DEV</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
