<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Educating All of One Nation:     Addressing a National Imperative - Why We Can't Wait; October 23-25, 2003; Atlanta, GA</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sherrie Green</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>OIA-0342851&lt;br/&gt;Harvey&lt;br/&gt;American Council on Education&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will enhance mutual goals of advancing the participation of all Americans in higher education, including science, mathematics, and engineering. The "Educating All of One Nation" conference, sponsored by the American Council on Education, will convene an action-focus summit on October 23-25, 2003, promoting diverse participation at all levels of higher education.  Senior-level administrators, faculty members and other higher education decision makers will assemble in Atlanta, GA to explore critical topics related to the current status of underrepresented participation in postsecondary education, and to develop strategies on how to sustain, expand and replicate successful models that provide opportunities for a diverse population of students. By contributing to the development of a diverse, internationally competitive and globally engaged workforce that includes the STEM workforce, and a well prepared citizenry, will enable the US to remain competitive and preserve its leadership in the vast, rapidly, changing world economy.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0342851</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
