<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>A Coevolutionary Theory of Male and Female Alternative Reproductive Behaviors: Combining Phenotypic and Genetic Aapproaches</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>296849</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08090300</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Godfrey R. Bourne</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>A Coevolutionary Theory of Male and Female Alternative Reproductive Behaviors: Combining Phenotypic and Genetic Approaches&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Suzanne H. Alonzo&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Extensive research has focused on explaining diversity within and between species. Male alternative reproductive behaviors are one of the most striking and well-studied examples of individual variation within a population. However, debate still exists regarding how this kind of discrete variation is maintained in populations. Two critical factors exist that have received little attention but need to be considered. First, it is generally assumed that competition between males usually leads to the evolution of discrete variation in male behavior. However, female behavior and interactions between the sexes can also affect male reproductive behavior. Second, discrete variation in female reproductive patterns is observed, but currently no theory exists predicting when female alternative reproductive behaviors are expected to evolve and what patterns are expected. This research will develop a general theoretical approach and generate new theory that examines how interactions within and between the sexes affect patterns of diversity within a sex. An increased understanding of individual variation in reproductive behavior has broad application to conservation, fisheries and management. This research will also involve training two undergraduate students and one graduate student in the use of various modeling.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/09/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0343417</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Suzanne</FirstName>
      <LastName>Alonzo</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>shalonzo@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/09/2004</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
      <CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1160</Code>
      <Text>IBN ANIMAL BEHAVIOR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
