<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Investigations into the Developmental, Genetic and Molecular Events Underlying Changes in Floral Morphology Associated with Speciation and Sex in Plants</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>432500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chris T. Amemiya</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Title:  Investigations into the Genetic, Developmental and Molecular Events Underlying Changes in Floral Morphology Associated with Speciation and Sex in Plants&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;P.I.  &lt;br/&gt;Steven D. Tanksley (Cornell University)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Reward Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Sex in plants and animals has presumably evolved as a way to control mating and (in the long term) to avoid inbreeding depression and maintain genetic variation. For this reason, most animal species possess both male and female sexes.   In contrast, most plant species do not display discrete sexes.   Nonetheless, plants have evolved very effective mechanisms to promote cross fertilization and avoid self-fertilization.   One of these mechanisms involves changes in flower structure that can   promote either self pollination or cross pollination.   The developmental and molecular processes underlying these  changes in floral structure are not well understood.  Using tomato, and its wild relatives, as a model, we will begin to isolate  and characterize the genes and developmental mechanisms underlying the changes in floral morphology that affect mating behavior in plants.  Moreover, we will try to determine whether common developmental processes have been involved in the evolution of mating systems throughout the plant kingdom.  Hence, this work will provide a starting point for researchers interested in the genetic and ecological bases for mating behavior in plants.   On the practical side, understanding the basis for mating control is key to agriculture as all plant breeding techniques and most commercial hybrids rely on controlling mating behavior. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0343078</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Tanksley</LastName>
<EmailAddress/>
<StartDate>12/11/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell Univ - State: AWDS MADE PRIOR MAY 2010</Name>
<CityName>Ithica</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502488</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1080</Code>
<Text>Evolution of Develp Mechanism</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7471</Code>
<Text>DEVELOPMENTAL BIOLOGY CLUSTER</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1111</Code>
<Text>DEVELOPMENTAL SYSTEMS CLUSTER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
