<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Theoretical Stable Isotope Geochemistry of Alkaline-Earth Elements</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>247951</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030101</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Enriqueta Barrera</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Recent advances in mass-spectrometric techniques and instrumentation have enabled&lt;br/&gt;accurate stable isotope measurements of many heavy elements. In order to realize the full&lt;br/&gt;potential of these new measurements, it is important to develop a thorough understanding of the&lt;br/&gt;basic mechanisms causing heavy-element isotopic fractionation through careful theoretical&lt;br/&gt;studies and laboratory experiments. Here, a systematic theoretical exploration of the equilibrium&lt;br/&gt;stable isotope geochemistry of the alkaline-earth elements (magnesium, calcium, strontium, and&lt;br/&gt;barium) is proposed. All of the elements in the proposed field of study lack systematic theoretical&lt;br/&gt;characterization, and the role of equilibrium isotopic fractionations in producing observed isotope&lt;br/&gt;abundance variations is not known. These elements are logical choices because of their relevance&lt;br/&gt;to geology and low-temperature geochemistry, because major uncertainties exist regarding the&lt;br/&gt;underlying causes of observed fractionations, and because of the relative ease with which they&lt;br/&gt;can be modeled. Studies will focus on materials that are subjects of current and likely future&lt;br/&gt;isotope measurements, including carbonates, silicates, and aqueous species.&lt;br/&gt;The alkaline-earth elements all have relatively simple electronic structures and a single&lt;br/&gt;dominant oxidation state, making them ideal test cases for determining the effects of coordination&lt;br/&gt;number and hydration on isotopic fractionations. Because of their simple electronic structures,&lt;br/&gt;these elements are amenable to many theoretical treatments, particularly ab initio modeling of&lt;br/&gt;crystals using density functional perturbation theory (DFPT). Ab initio computational chemistry&lt;br/&gt;and empirical force-fields will be used to estimate the vibrational frequencies of isotopically&lt;br/&gt;substituted crystals, molecules, and solvated clusters, providing the necessary input data for&lt;br/&gt;quantum-statistical calculations of equilibrium stable isotope fractionation factors. Materials with&lt;br/&gt;well known vibrational spectra, like MgO and CaO, will also be modeled to check whether the&lt;br/&gt;calculated vibrational properties are reasonable and accurate. Vibrational models generated in this&lt;br/&gt;project will also become the nucleus of an animated mineral vibration database for use in&lt;br/&gt;mineralogy instruction. A successful research program devoted to these elements will provide a&lt;br/&gt;basic geochemical framework for designing and interpreting stable isotope measurements in a&lt;br/&gt;wide variety of natural samples.&lt;br/&gt;NSF Merit Review Criteria:&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The proposed research will be of broad interest in studies of the&lt;br/&gt;paleoclimate records preserved in mineral precipitates, in searching for robust biosignatures in&lt;br/&gt;minerals and biological molecules, in tracing alteration processes in the seafloor and their&lt;br/&gt;contributions to global geochemical cycles in the mantle and subduction zones, and in meteoritic&lt;br/&gt;studies of the origin of the solar system. The proposed research is also relevant to basic studies in&lt;br/&gt;stable-isotope geochemistry, because so little is known about the natural isotopic fractionations of&lt;br/&gt;elements heavier than sulfur, and in particular for very heavy elements like barium and strontium.&lt;br/&gt;The project will also adapt ab initio techniques from computational chemistry and materials&lt;br/&gt;science that will be broadly applicable to theoretical studies of the stable isotope geochemistry of&lt;br/&gt;other main-group elements like silicon, sulfur and lithium. The PI is highly qualified to perform&lt;br/&gt;the proposed research, having previously modeled stable isotope fractionations of iron, chlorine,&lt;br/&gt;and chromium in molecules, crystals and aqueous complexes.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This project will advance graduate education by supporting thesis&lt;br/&gt;research. Undergraduate education will also be enhanced through hands-on summer research&lt;br/&gt;opportunities. The proposed work involves the adaptation of modeling techniques from&lt;br/&gt;computational chemistry and materials science, and will partially support a computer modeling&lt;br/&gt;laboratory, improving the infrastructure for research and interdisciplinary cross-fertilization. The&lt;br/&gt;online database of mineral vibrations is intended to advance mineralogical research and&lt;br/&gt;education, particularly in the areas of infrared and Raman spectroscopy, thermodynamics and&lt;br/&gt;heat transfer, and displacive phase transformations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0345433</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edwin</FirstName>
<LastName>Schauble</LastName>
<EmailAddress>schauble@ess.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/19/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>GEOBIOLOGY &amp; LOW TEMP GEOCHEM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
