<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ACT/SGER:      Modeling the Morphology and Phase Behavior of Organic/Inorganic Nanocomposite Thin Films</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070007</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Lovinger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alovinge@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924933</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal is to develop new computational and analytical models to determine the equilibrium morphologies of block copolymer/nanoparticle mixtures that are confined between two hard surfaces and thereby establish guidelines for creating nanostructured organic/inorganic thin films through self-assembly.  Thin films that contain layers of organic polymers and inorganic particles can exhibit both the optical, electrical, magnetic and mechanical properties of the nanoparticles and the processibility and flexibility of the polymers.  In effect, the interleafing of layers of polymers and inorganic nanoparticles can yield durable, flexible, and lightweight films with high energy densities.  These thin nanocomposites form materials for fabricating portable batteries, photovoltaic devices and sensors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed studies will have a broader impact by facilitating the fabrication of technologically important materials in cost-effective, efficient methods.  The results of our studies will alleviate the need for creating nanocomposite thin films through slow, multi-step, layer-by-layer (LBL) deposition or adsorption processes.  In particular, the research will provide guidelines for creating spatially ordered nanocomposites films in a minimal number of processing steps that rely solely on self-assembly.  Furthermore, these films can display a variety of architectures, not just the lamellar structures that are typically produced by LBL methods.  The fabrication of nanocomposite films with various morphologies can lead to coating with new functionalities.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addressing critical needs outlined by the ACT announcement, the results of these studies also have the potential to contribute to national security.  As an example, one aim of the proposed research is to design thin films that contain a periodic array of particle "nanowires", which are separated by nanoscale polymer domains.  Such lightweight, high energy density materials are vital for the fabrication portable electronic, photonic and sensing devices that can be used by soldiers in the field.  This award is supported jointly by the NSF and the Intelligence Community.  The Approaches to Combat Terrorism Program in the Directorate for Mathematics and Physical Sciences supports new concepts in basic research and workforce development with the potential to contribute to national security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0346280</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Balazs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna C Balazs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>balazs@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126489250</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000123954</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 Murdoch Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>V117</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7243</Code>
<Text>FUND RES TO ENHANCE NATIONAL SEC (FRENS)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7276</Code>
<Text>APPROACHES TO COMBAT TERRORISM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9237</Code>
<Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0103</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2003~100000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
