<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:  Application-Driven Combustion and Fluid Flow Imaging</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>454453</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Arvind Atreyae Atreya</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CAREER: Application-driven Combustion and Fluid Flow Imaging, CTS-0348208&lt;br/&gt;Lester K. Su, Department of Mechanical Engineering, Johns Hopkins University&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work encompasses the development and application of planar laser imaging techniques for investigating problems in combustion and turbulent fluid flows. It pays particular attention to molecular mixing, with an eye to rigorous experimental assessment of models used in simulations of non-premixed, turbulent combustion. Planar imaging methods are capable of direct visualization of turbulent flow structures and are thus inherently well suited for assessing simulation methods (such as large-eddy simulation) that are rooted conceptually in the structural organization of turbulent flows.  This work includes the development of a velocimetry technique for gas-phase turbulent flows that is based on scalar field measurements, which can be applied in a priori testing of mixing and combustion models, and the use of Rayleigh scattering and planar laser-induced fluorescence methods to investigate differential molecular diffusion in multi-species turbulent mixing problems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this research program will contribute to increased efficiency and reduced environmental impact of combustion systems by improving the understanding of the underlying turbulent mixing process and facilitating the development of more accurate simulation methods. Combustion of fossil fuels will remain significant to the industrial economy for the foreseeable future, and efficient and clean combustion is crucial for sustainable development. In the course of this work, the PI also addresses the issue of stagnant enrollments in university engineering departments. New courses are being developed to make engineering education reflect current trends in engineering practice, and the issue of diversity in engineering is addressed in a way that recognizes the different obstacles faced by different under-represented groups.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/04/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0348208</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lester</FirstName>
<LastName>Su</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lester.su@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/04/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212182686</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439971898</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1101 E 33rd St</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1406</Code>
<Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1407</Code>
<Text>Combustion &amp; Fire Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>061E</Code>
<Text>Fire</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
