<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: X-Ray Diffraction Studies of Semiconductor and Metal Thin Film Growth</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>606864</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070004</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Z.  Ying</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This CAREER project aims to develop a leading research and education activity in the area of metal/semiconductor growth, and self-organized pattern formation on surfaces. Through integra-tion of innovative research with a broad education and outreach effort, the project expects to dramatically advance fundamental understanding of organic and inorganic thin-film growth and etching kinetics. A series of experiments are aimed at producing methods of controlling the structure of thin films for the next generation of devices in several materials systems related to information technology. Key areas include: (i) Kinetics of pulsed laser Molecular Beam Epitaxy. Important issues are the formation and ultimate limits of non-equilibrium alloys, and the interplay of structure with carrier transport and magnetic properties. (ii) Patterning of surfaces by ion etch-ing. This research seeks methods for self-organized fabrication of nanostructured thin films and control of the structure of interfaces between materials. (iii) Organic electronics, where it is of paramount importance to understand the interplay of crystalline structure and thin film growth kinetics with electrical properties and stability/reliability. The three research areas have a common intellectual theme through greater understanding and development of complementary thin film materials for applications in optoelectronics, magneto-electronics, spintronics, and low cost electronics. &lt;br/&gt;%%%&lt;br/&gt;The project addresses fundamental research issues in electronic materials science having technological relevance. The research plan is closely integrated with an energetic education and outreach program incorporating extensive mentoring. New courses will be developed to provide un-dergraduate and graduate students with a solid background in x-ray physics, materials science, and nanotechnology. In addition to graduate research assistants, undergraduate students will be involved in the research program, providing them with valuable opportunities to complement their theoretical training. Students at all levels will be encouraged to present results at national meetings. A greater community focusing on thin film electronic materials is envisioned from diverse groups across the campus and at other colleges, universities, national laboratories, and local industry, which will give students the opportunity to experience a multidisciplinary environment. The program will make use of the multi-user facility for X-ray Studies of Materials with Analysis in Real-Time (X-SMART) at the National Synchrotron Light Source (NSLS), as well as facilities at the University of Vermont and at Cornell University. An extended outreach program aimed at K-12 students and teachers, female/minority colleges, and industry, will build on the Vermont HELIX program, extending these benefits to rural Vermont and inner city New York schools. This project will benefit society by creating new knowledge in an important area of science re-lated to modern technology, by producing highly skilled workers for related industries, and by raising the level of community interest in science and technology. &lt;br/&gt;*** &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/02/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0348354</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Randall</FirstName>
<LastName>Headrick</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rheadrick@uvm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/02/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Vermont &amp; State Agricultural College</Name>
<CityName>Burlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>054050160</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8026563660</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>85 South Prospect Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Vermont</StateName>
<StateCode>VT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1682</Code>
<Text>NANO SCI AND ENG - MPS CORE AW</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0104</Code>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0106</Code>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
