<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:   Commercialization of Perfluorocyclobutyl Polymers for Integrated Optics and Other High Performance Applications</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>655980</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This SBIR Phase II project proposes to pursue commercialization of perfluorocyclobutyl (PFCB) polymer products successfully developed during Phase I. High performance fluoropolymers, whose structure can be readily adjusted to  achieve  performance  targets  and  which  can  be  easily  processed are in demand  for next  generation technologies including integrated optics, fuel cell membranes, gas separation membranes, and  deep UV lithography.  Tetramer's patented PFCB polymers exhibit superior processing and performance advantages including  excellent  molding  and  extrusion  capability,  unmatched  thermal  stability,  zero  by-products  during  polymerization  and  fabrication,  and  the  ability  to  tune  properties  for  these  large market  applications  that  promise  significant  growth  from  to  their  global  economic  attractiveness  and  strategic  military  importance  to  the  United  States.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This distinctive activity will enhance scientific and technological knowledge in both academia and industry for  such  diverse  technically  driven  fields  as  lower  cost  higher  data  rate  integrated  optics,  fuel  cell  membranes, white  light LEDs,  and  gas  separation membranes  and  particularly  the  discipline  of  polymer  chemistry due to its structural versatility. After protecting intellectual property, Tetramer plans to share the results through published papers, and university and industrial seminars. This project will also contribute to US global leadership in the above fields of strategic commercial and military interest. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/09/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/17/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0349519</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Earl</FirstName>
<LastName>Wagener</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ewagener@bellsouth.net</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/09/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>TETRAMER TECHNOLOGIES, L.L.C.</Name>
<CityName>PENDLETON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296701808</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646534339</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>657 S MECHANIC STREET</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1403</Code>
<Text>PROCESS &amp; REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9163</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY - INDUSTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
