<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:     Analysis and Properties of Co-continuous Blends - A Numerical and Experimental Investigation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>404000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>484800</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A joint theoretical, numerical and experimental study of co-continuous polymer blends under processing flow conditions is performed.  Co-continuous blends consist of distinct continuous phases that form under appropriate conditions of flow and mass compositions near the phase-inversion point.  This co-continuous regime leads to synergistic properties of the materials after processing, such as high electrical conductivity coupled to light weight and optimal mechanical response.  This study is aimed at the development of criteria for detection, conditions for production, and to a better understanding of the stability of co-continuous blends.  The Newtonian flow regime is investigated and the effect of a third component, i.e. surfactants, is studied.  To perform this study, novel, state-of-the-art numerical methods are developed and applied to perform large-scale simulations.  In parallel, experiments are targeted to provide insight and validation of the mathematical models, simulations and theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A joint theoretical, computational and experimental study of co-continuous polymer blends is performed.  Co-continuous polymer blends consist of distinct sponge-like phases where one of the phases plays the role of the sponge and the other its complement.  Such blends offer an important route to materials with unique combinations of properties not available in&lt;br/&gt;single polymers or in blends with traditional dispersed (non continuous) droplet morphology.  These unique properties impact strongly applications in the areas of materials and manufacturing, and biotechnology.  For example, mechanical properties such as impact strength and tensile strength can exceed those of either blend component.  Another application of co-continuous polymer blends is products for mass transfer control. In particular, a water-permeable phase containing a desiccant can be used to remove moisture from moisture sensitive products such as food or pharmaceuticals while the other phase provides mechanical strength.  The key to performance in these products is the control of pore size and volume.  This fundamental study brings together state-of-the-art mathematical and numerical analysis, modeling and large-scale scientific computation with an innovative experimental program.  The experiments are targeted to provide insight and validation of the mathematical models, simulations and theory. This research is aimed to provide guidelines for controlling pore size and volume of the blends and thus to optimize the blend properties.  It is expected to lead to significant improvements in the industrial fabrication processes of co-continuous blends and in the properties of the final products.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/07/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0352143</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Lowengrub</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John S Lowengrub</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lowengrb@math.uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9497519700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000290126</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/07/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Aldrich Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1403</Code>
<Text>Proc Sys, Reac Eng &amp; Mol Therm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FD-Fluid Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0103</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0104</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2003~404000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2004~80800</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
