<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>US-Poland Workshop on Diagnostics of Concrete Materials for Infrastructure Facilities; April 2004; Warsaw, Poland</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2003</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19657.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19657</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jorn Larsen-Basse</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;The objective of the proposed Workshop is to review the recent advancements in concrete materials and their applications for civil infrastructure systems in Poland and the United States, identify the most suitable topics for collaboration. The Workshop will focus on materials properties, forms of deterioration and their effects on structural performance, and quantitative analysis of materials. The major areas to be covered include: (1) advanced materials (high-strength/high-performance concrete, composites, fiber-reinforced concrete, smart materials), (2) forms of deterioration for reinforced concrete and prestressed concrete structures, (3) diagnostic procedures (tests, performance monitors, nondestructive techniques, signal processing, integrated sensor systems, acoustic and optical techniques), (4) materials and techniques for repair and rehabilitation of concrete structures (reinforced and prestressed concrete, new composite materials). Accordingly, the Workshop will attempt to review state of the art summary of main topics as viewed on one hand in the U.S. and, on the other hand, in Poland, identify the research needs, in particular, topics for cooperative projects, and derive some recommendations that reflect the needs in manpower, technology transfer and education for the near future. The local organizers will also organize special meetings, lab tours and visits to the construction sites. The results will be presented in the report.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/24/2003</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/24/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0353504</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrzej</FirstName>
<LastName>Nowak</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nowak@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>11/24/2003</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1635</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL MATERIALS AND MECH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
