<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Suoersymmetry, Superstrings and Phenomenology</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>963000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>963000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick Cooper</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;0354401 PI: Mohapatra&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the research being undertaken by the Maryland Particle Theory&lt;br/&gt;Group is to search for the ultimate laws that govern the nature of particles, forces and the Universe. The focus will be to explore the nature of physics beyond the successful standard model of strong, weak and electromagnetic forces using results from neutrino physics and theoretical ideas such as supersymmetry, grand unification and string theory. Neutrino masses have already provided some clues as to the nature of this new physics. The current and planned experiments at various laboratories around the world using neutrinos, protons, electrons and muons are expected to add considerably to this knowledge. The plan is to use these results and predict new ones to test the different theoretical ideas mentioned above. This research will also explore ways to resolve some of the puzzles of cosmology such as nature of dark matter in the universe, origin of matter-anti-matter asymmetry, nature of the expansion of the early universe etc. using the same theoretical ideas and propose ways to test them in different experiments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The hope is that this research will provide answers to some of the outstanding questions of modern physics such as  (i) what is the origin of the mass of fundamental particles; (ii) are all the diverse forces of nature such as gravity, electro-magnetism, weak and nuclear forces really different manifestations of one force that operates at very short distances; (iii) why are some forces weaker than others; (iv) are the most elementary building blocks of matter point-like particles or strings; (v) are there extra hidden space dimensions in nature? There will be strong participation in this research by post-doctoral associates, graduate students as well as undergraduate and high school students. It will therefore provide training for future scientists by bringing them into close contact with the frontier areas of research in this exciting field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0354401</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rabindra</FirstName>
<LastName>Mohapatra</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rmohapat@physics.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/18/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Markus</FirstName>
<LastName>Luty</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mluty@physics.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/18/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>S. James</FirstName>
<LastName>Gates</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sylvester_gates@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/18/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Becker</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mbecker@physics.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/18/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0104</Code>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0106</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
