<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>An RUI Research Proposal on Minimizing Thermal Noise in Advanced LIGO Test Mass Optics and Exploring Bilinear Noise in Initial LIGO Data</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2004</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010700</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Beverly K. Berger</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project will focus primarily on understanding and reducing the mechanical loss in fused silica. Methods of reducing the mechanical loss in large, polished, fused silica optics through careful annealing in inert gas and vacuum will be explored. This technique has already proven successful on small, flame-drawn samples, and is expected to benefit larger samples as well. In addition, a theoretical model for the mechanical loss in fused silica will be developed in collaboration with other LIGO thermal noise researchers . Such a model would greatly aid our understanding of the fundamental loss mechanisms and may provide guidance as to how this loss might be further reduced. Finally, development will continue on a bicoherence data monitor, which is a robust method for separating bilinear noise, burst events, and chirp events from a large background of Gaussian noise.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research on fused silica holds a great deal of promise for Advanced LIGO.  The PI has previously demonstrated that annealing can reduce the mechanical loss in fused silica to a level equal to that of sapphire, the other material proposed for Advanced LIGO optics and better than the requirements for Advanced LIGO. The benefits of using silica include excellent optical qualities and greater experience as an optical material. As the PI has previously shown, the loss in fused silica, when minimized, is entirely in the surface, at least for the geometries measured thus far. In other words, the loss decreases as the size of the optic increases. Therefore it is expected that large optics, when properly annealed, should, despite being polished, have a mechanical loss below the Advanced LIGO requirements. Lowering the thermal noise in the test masses will increase LIGO's astronomical reach in its most sensitive frequency band and enhance the probability for detection and study of gravitational wave events.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2004</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0355118</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Penn</LastName>
<EmailAddress>penn@hws.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/06/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hobart and William Smith Colleges</Name>
<CityName>Geneva</CityName>
<ZipCode>144563397</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3157813754</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>337 Pulteney Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1252</Code>
<Text>LIGO RESEARCH SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
