<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Intelligent Biology and Medicine in 2019: Accelerating Interdisciplinary Education, Collaboration, and Innovation in Data Science and Artificial Intelligence</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17950.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17950</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In the era of data science, covering data process and standardization, algorithm and tool development, statistics, machine learning and related approaches new opportunities for dealing with the amazing data growth rate are critical.  This coupled with new technologies  leads to advances in health and biomedical research.  The 2019 conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine will be held June 9-11 in Columbus, Ohio, led by a stellar field of keynote speakers to address themes of omics- and data-based systems, translational science and personalized medicine.  The conference promotes extensive interaction and provides opportunities for junior faculty and students to participate and learn.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The mission of the International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine (ICIBM) is to promote information science, technology, and education to a great variety of trainees and young investigators, including trainees, faculty, teachers, scientists, and engineers, and to provide a forum for the cross-fertilization of ideas.  ICIBM will provide a forum to accelerate data science method development and application, to explore complex and dynamic functions and regulation in cellular systems and organisms, and to improve algorithms, deep learning, computational tools, knowledgebase, and biotechniques for better diagnosis, prevention, and treatment of diseases.  ICIBM 2019 conference programs will include four distinguished keynote speakers, four eminent scholars' talks, four tutorial and workshop sessions, scientific presentations, a poster session, and other activities.  Top manuscripts will be selected for special journal issues.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/21/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1902617</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhongming</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhongming Zhao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zhongming.zhao@uth.tmc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7135003631</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000571928</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770305400</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7135003999</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7000 FANNIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800771594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS HEALTH SCIENCE CENTER AT HOUSTON, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770305400</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7000 Fannin St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~17950</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine 2019 (ICIBM 2019) took place in Columbus, Ohio, USA on June 9-11, 2019. There were more than 170 attendees from diverse research areas, races/ethnicities, and general backgrounds, and from institutions across the USA and other international institutions. ICIBM 2019 featured twelve regular scientific sessions, five tutorials and workshops, one poster session, four keynote lectures, and four eminent scholars&rsquo; talks. The scientific program covered a wide range of topics, including next-generation sequencing, single-cell analyses, deep learning, metabolomics, genomics, and other omics research, systems biology, medical applications and translational research involving high-throughput data, computational methods and novel applications of computational tools, and others. Both method/tool development and application in genomic research and data science continued to be a main component in the conference, including studies on genomics, functional regulation, pharmacogenomics, modeling, and machine learning. In addition to the four keynote and four eminent scholar talks, ICIBM 2019 had a total of 66 oral presentations in twelve regular sessions in the areas of bioinformatics, genomics, computational biology, systems biology, machine learning, scientific databases, and computational drug discovery. The 2019 scientific program was the largest among all the ICIBM conferences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Four prominent scientists were invited to be the&nbsp;keynote speakers; all of them attended and presented at ICIBM 2019:&nbsp;Dr. Jeremy Edwards, Professor in the Department of Chemistry &amp; Chemical Biology University of New Mexico;&nbsp;Dr. Peter Karp, Director, Bioinformatics Research Group, Artificial Intelligence Center, SRI;&nbsp;Dr. Elaine Mardis, Co-executive Director of the Institute for Genomic Medicine at Nationwide Children&rsquo;s Hospital and the Nationwide Foundation Endowed Chair of Genomic Medicine at The Ohio State University;&nbsp;Dr. T.M. Murali, Professor in the Department of Computer Science, Virginia Tech. These distinguished speakers brought ICIBM 2019 the frontier research in integrative modeling the metabolic system, high-throughput genomic sequencing technology, cancer precision medicine, and computational approaches in constructing human signaling networks</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Twenty travel awards were provided to&nbsp;trainees from&nbsp;diverse backgrounds. Selection of these awardees was&nbsp;based on the quality of the research (paper or abstract), the financial need, and diversity/minority of the attendees.&nbsp;These travel awards encouraged the participation of young scientists in training from a diverse array of both scientific and societal backgrounds. All the travel awardees were able to attend the conference and presented their work. An award ceremony was given during the conference.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>A total of 105 papers and 36 abstracts were submitted to ICIBM 2019. Each paper was reviewed by at least three Program Committee members. High-quality papers were accepted after satisfactory revision. These ICIBM 2019 special issues included:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li>Supplement issue "The International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine (ICIBM) 2019: Bioinformatics methods and applications for human diseases: genomics"&nbsp;<em>BMC Genomics</em>, Vol 20, Supplement 12.&nbsp;<em>&nbsp;</em></li> <li>Supplement issue "The International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine (ICIBM) 2019: Bioinformatics methods and applications for human diseases."&nbsp;<em>BMC Bioinformatics</em>, Vol 20, Supplement 24<em></em></li> <li>Supplement issue &ldquo;The International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine&nbsp;&nbsp;(ICIBM) 2019: Computational methods for drug interactions.&rdquo;&nbsp;<em>BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making</em>.&nbsp;Vol 20, Supplement 2<em></em></li> <li>Supplement issue &ldquo;The International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine (ICIBM) 2019:&nbsp;Computational methods and application in medical genomics (part 1).&rdquo;&nbsp;<em>BMC Medical Genomics</em>.&nbsp;Vol 13, Supplement 5 (two parts)</li> <li>Special Issue "Selected Papers from the International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine (ICIBM 2019)".&nbsp;<em>Genes</em>. 2019 (18 papers)</li> <li>Special Issue "State-of-the art computational methods and tools for analysis of high-dimensional biological and biomedical datasets."&nbsp;<em>International Journal of Computational Biology and Drug Design (IJCBDD)</em>. In progress</li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This NSF fund substantially assisted in making this event quite valuable and successful. Overall, ICIBM 2019 proved to be highly enriching for all attendees, fostering valuable collaborative dialogue between investigators from diverse institutions, disciplines, and backgrounds. Young researchers and students gleaned excellent training and feedback through this event that will continue to encourage high-level knowledge and research in the fields of bioinformatics, systems biology, and intelligent computing. This opportunity for interactions and training at ICIBM 2019 will, in turn, assist in continuing advancements and innovations in these important interdisciplinary fields, thereby furthering successful research in the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/04/2020<br>      Modified by: Zhongming&nbsp;Zhao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine 2019 (ICIBM 2019) took place in Columbus, Ohio, USA on June 9-11, 2019. There were more than 170 attendees from diverse research areas, races/ethnicities, and general backgrounds, and from institutions across the USA and other international institutions. ICIBM 2019 featured twelve regular scientific sessions, five tutorials and workshops, one poster session, four keynote lectures, and four eminent scholars’ talks. The scientific program covered a wide range of topics, including next-generation sequencing, single-cell analyses, deep learning, metabolomics, genomics, and other omics research, systems biology, medical applications and translational research involving high-throughput data, computational methods and novel applications of computational tools, and others. Both method/tool development and application in genomic research and data science continued to be a main component in the conference, including studies on genomics, functional regulation, pharmacogenomics, modeling, and machine learning. In addition to the four keynote and four eminent scholar talks, ICIBM 2019 had a total of 66 oral presentations in twelve regular sessions in the areas of bioinformatics, genomics, computational biology, systems biology, machine learning, scientific databases, and computational drug discovery. The 2019 scientific program was the largest among all the ICIBM conferences.     Four prominent scientists were invited to be the keynote speakers; all of them attended and presented at ICIBM 2019: Dr. Jeremy Edwards, Professor in the Department of Chemistry &amp; Chemical Biology University of New Mexico; Dr. Peter Karp, Director, Bioinformatics Research Group, Artificial Intelligence Center, SRI; Dr. Elaine Mardis, Co-executive Director of the Institute for Genomic Medicine at Nationwide Children’s Hospital and the Nationwide Foundation Endowed Chair of Genomic Medicine at The Ohio State University; Dr. T.M. Murali, Professor in the Department of Computer Science, Virginia Tech. These distinguished speakers brought ICIBM 2019 the frontier research in integrative modeling the metabolic system, high-throughput genomic sequencing technology, cancer precision medicine, and computational approaches in constructing human signaling networks     Twenty travel awards were provided to trainees from diverse backgrounds. Selection of these awardees was based on the quality of the research (paper or abstract), the financial need, and diversity/minority of the attendees. These travel awards encouraged the participation of young scientists in training from a diverse array of both scientific and societal backgrounds. All the travel awardees were able to attend the conference and presented their work. An award ceremony was given during the conference.     A total of 105 papers and 36 abstracts were submitted to ICIBM 2019. Each paper was reviewed by at least three Program Committee members. High-quality papers were accepted after satisfactory revision. These ICIBM 2019 special issues included:     Supplement issue "The International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine (ICIBM) 2019: Bioinformatics methods and applications for human diseases: genomics" BMC Genomics, Vol 20, Supplement 12.   Supplement issue "The International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine (ICIBM) 2019: Bioinformatics methods and applications for human diseases." BMC Bioinformatics, Vol 20, Supplement 24 Supplement issue "The International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine  (ICIBM) 2019: Computational methods for drug interactions." BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making. Vol 20, Supplement 2 Supplement issue "The International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine (ICIBM) 2019: Computational methods and application in medical genomics (part 1)." BMC Medical Genomics. Vol 13, Supplement 5 (two parts) Special Issue "Selected Papers from the International Conference on Intelligent Biology and Medicine (ICIBM 2019)". Genes. 2019 (18 papers) Special Issue "State-of-the art computational methods and tools for analysis of high-dimensional biological and biomedical datasets." International Journal of Computational Biology and Drug Design (IJCBDD). In progress      This NSF fund substantially assisted in making this event quite valuable and successful. Overall, ICIBM 2019 proved to be highly enriching for all attendees, fostering valuable collaborative dialogue between investigators from diverse institutions, disciplines, and backgrounds. Young researchers and students gleaned excellent training and feedback through this event that will continue to encourage high-level knowledge and research in the fields of bioinformatics, systems biology, and intelligent computing. This opportunity for interactions and training at ICIBM 2019 will, in turn, assist in continuing advancements and innovations in these important interdisciplinary fields, thereby furthering successful research in the future.          Last Modified: 04/04/2020       Submitted by: Zhongming Zhao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
