<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Symplectic Representation Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The conference "Symplectic Representation Theory" will take place at the Centre International de Rencontres Mathematiques (https://www.cirm-math.com),  in Marseille, France, from April 1 to April 5, 2019. The subject of the conference is a rapidly developing field in mathematics which connects several disciplines, not only in mathematics but also in physics. The main goals of the conference are to understand the structure of important geometric, physical, and algebraic objects that appear in very many places that generalize the study of semi-simple Lie algebras and the geometry of Lie groups and flag varieties. Important examples included are algebraic objects such as the so-called Cherednik, Hecke, and quiver algebras; geometric objects such as hypertoric and quiver varieties and affine Grassmannians; and physical objects such as moduli spaces of vacua of 3D supersymmetric quantum field theories. Recently many important developments have occurred, making physical objects precise in mathematics, resolving mathematical conjectures about Koszul duality, mirror symmetry, and quantum cohomology, and finding geometric constructions of quantum groups and representations as well as Lie-theoretic objects and new generalizations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aim of the proposed conference is to bring participants to the forefront of knowledge in this fast moving field. The keynote speakers are chosen because they are responsible for much of this recent progress. These speakers to give research talks about: 1) The definition, and fundamental properties, of the Coulomb branch, its quantizations, and three-dimensional mirror symmetry; 2) Breakthroughs in our understanding of quantum cohomology, and its K-theoretic counterpart; 3) (Geometric) categorification, and applications to combinatorial representation theory; 4) The role of gauge theory, topological field theories, and categories of branes in symplectic representation theory; and 5) The classification and structure of symplectic singularities, their symplectic resolutions, and quantizations.  The conference website has the URL https://conferences.cirm-math.fr/1956.html.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/15/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/15/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1906141</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Ben-Zvi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David D Ben-Zvi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>benzvi@math.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124718151</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000183201</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/15/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121202</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Mathematics]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Symplectic representation theory is an active new area of mathematics at the intersection of several important subjects.&nbsp; &nbsp;Representation theory is an area of mathematics that seeks to understand symmetries of spaces or structures and their generalizations, often arising from geometry or physics, using matrices and vectors. Symplectic geometry is the mathematical study of the type of spaces that arise in Hamilton's formulation of classical mechanics: for three-dimensional space, one adds in three momentum coordinates, and describes Newton's equations of motion via the energy function on the resulting six-dimensional space.&nbsp; Symplectic representation theory constructs new representations (symmetries) using symplectic geometry. The conference "Symplectic Representation Theory" took place April 1--5, 2019 in Marseille, France.&nbsp; It was a major international gathering that included world renowned experts, with the goal of fostering new discoveries in the field. It was attended by 57 mathematicians, at all levels from PhD students through senior researchers, lodged at the prestigious Centre International de Rencontres Mathematiques (CIRM). A select group of senior and junior researchers presented cutting-edge developments. Furthermore, all junior researchers were&nbsp; given the opportunity to briefly present their research to the entire group. The intimate atmosphere offered many opportunities for interaction and discussion. Finally, all (but two) talks were posted online to youtube, benefiting many mathematicians who could not attend. The conference thus served the purpose of initiating the next generation of mathematicians to certain aspects of current high level research. NSF funding allowed many American researchers, particularly junior ones, to attend and meet international experts.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/11/2020<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;D&nbsp;Ben-Zvi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Symplectic representation theory is an active new area of mathematics at the intersection of several important subjects.   Representation theory is an area of mathematics that seeks to understand symmetries of spaces or structures and their generalizations, often arising from geometry or physics, using matrices and vectors. Symplectic geometry is the mathematical study of the type of spaces that arise in Hamilton's formulation of classical mechanics: for three-dimensional space, one adds in three momentum coordinates, and describes Newton's equations of motion via the energy function on the resulting six-dimensional space.  Symplectic representation theory constructs new representations (symmetries) using symplectic geometry. The conference "Symplectic Representation Theory" took place April 1--5, 2019 in Marseille, France.  It was a major international gathering that included world renowned experts, with the goal of fostering new discoveries in the field. It was attended by 57 mathematicians, at all levels from PhD students through senior researchers, lodged at the prestigious Centre International de Rencontres Mathematiques (CIRM). A select group of senior and junior researchers presented cutting-edge developments. Furthermore, all junior researchers were  given the opportunity to briefly present their research to the entire group. The intimate atmosphere offered many opportunities for interaction and discussion. Finally, all (but two) talks were posted online to youtube, benefiting many mathematicians who could not attend. The conference thus served the purpose of initiating the next generation of mathematicians to certain aspects of current high level research. NSF funding allowed many American researchers, particularly junior ones, to attend and meet international experts.       Last Modified: 07/11/2020       Submitted by: David D Ben-Zvi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
