<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: High-Fidelity Modeling of Poromechanics with Strong Discontinuities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>36288</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Poromechanics with strong discontinuities has numerous important applications such as simulating fluid flow in natural static and hydraulic dynamic fractures, fracture analysis of aging bones, multiple-network poroelastic theory arising in dementia and Alzheimer's disease, and evaluation of accelerated degradation of ceramic matrix composites in aerospace shuttles. Here mathematical modeling is challenging because it involves not only coupled chemical reactions, diffusion, and deformation but also initiation, propagation, and branching of cracks in the bulk matrix as well as fluid flowing through cracks. To address these challenges, high fidelity numerical schemes and multiphysics models must be coupled in order to simulate these processes and their interactions accurately and efficiently. This project will benefit public and decision makers including energy producers, health providers, aerodynamicists, and hydrogeologists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this project is to study the following fundamental relationships linking flow, chemistry, and mechanics: stability, a priori, and a posteriori error estimation of dynamic discontinuous Galerkin discretizations, physically consistent material models for the deformation and failure of the media, efficient and accurate material solution techniques, and scaling characteristics of mechanical properties.  This knowledge will be used in the design of locally conservative finite element methods coupling porous media flow, reactive transport, and mechanics that run efficiently on high-performance computing platforms.  The team will investigate: (1) Development of fundamental understanding of poromechanics with strong discontinuities in the setting of chemo-mechanical coupled models; (2) Formulation and analyses of flow, mechanical, and reactive transport models solved using high-fidelity numerical algorithms; (3) Developing error estimates for iterative coupling solution techniques; (4) Verifying and validating fluid structure interactions using published data from target data sets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1911325</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ruijie</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ruijie Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ruijie.liu@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2104585511</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000731511</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at San Antonio</Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2104584340</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One UTSA Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Grants, Contracts & Ind. Agr.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800189185</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT SAN ANTONIO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Texas at San Antonio]]></Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One UTSA Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~36287</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Crack/Fracture propagation in porous media has numerous important applications such as simulating fluid flow in natural static and hydraulic dynamic fractures, fracture analysis of aging bones, multiple-network poroelastic theory arising in dementia and Alzheimer's disease, and evaluation of accelerated degradation of ceramic matrix composites in aerospace shuttles. &nbsp;Mathematical modeling is challenging because it involves not only coupled diffusion, and deformation but also initiation, propagation, and branching of cracks in the bulk matrix as well as fluid flowing through cracks. To address these challenges, a high fidelity numerical scheme based on Discontinuous Galerkin finite element method was investigated to simulate these processes and their interactions accurately and efficiently. This project would benefit public and decision makers including energy producers, health providers, aerodynamicists, and hydrogeologists.<br /> <br /> The team has carried out: (1) Development of fundamental understanding of poromechanics with strong discontinuities in the setting of three coupled models including solid, fluid flow in solid bulk, and fluid flow in apertures resulting from fractures in solid phase; (2) Formulation and implementation of the Incomplete Interior Penalty Galerkin (IIPG) method for this three-field problem; (3) Incorporation of a more physical rigid cohesive law for crack openings; (4) Adoption of a crack surface traction relaxation scheme to handle the crack opening in media with large plastic deformation; (5) Verifying a hydraulic fracture model using KGD model; (6) Numerical demonstrations of &nbsp;a good capability of the proposed DG scheme in modeling multiple cracks in composites where large plastic deformation occurs and the interaction of multiple hydraulic fractures.</p> <p>The research outcome can be used in the design of robust and &nbsp;conservative finite element methods in modeling of &nbsp;porous media where the difficult crack/fracture events are focused.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/25/2020<br>      Modified by: Ruijie&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Crack/Fracture propagation in porous media has numerous important applications such as simulating fluid flow in natural static and hydraulic dynamic fractures, fracture analysis of aging bones, multiple-network poroelastic theory arising in dementia and Alzheimer's disease, and evaluation of accelerated degradation of ceramic matrix composites in aerospace shuttles.  Mathematical modeling is challenging because it involves not only coupled diffusion, and deformation but also initiation, propagation, and branching of cracks in the bulk matrix as well as fluid flowing through cracks. To address these challenges, a high fidelity numerical scheme based on Discontinuous Galerkin finite element method was investigated to simulate these processes and their interactions accurately and efficiently. This project would benefit public and decision makers including energy producers, health providers, aerodynamicists, and hydrogeologists.    The team has carried out: (1) Development of fundamental understanding of poromechanics with strong discontinuities in the setting of three coupled models including solid, fluid flow in solid bulk, and fluid flow in apertures resulting from fractures in solid phase; (2) Formulation and implementation of the Incomplete Interior Penalty Galerkin (IIPG) method for this three-field problem; (3) Incorporation of a more physical rigid cohesive law for crack openings; (4) Adoption of a crack surface traction relaxation scheme to handle the crack opening in media with large plastic deformation; (5) Verifying a hydraulic fracture model using KGD model; (6) Numerical demonstrations of  a good capability of the proposed DG scheme in modeling multiple cracks in composites where large plastic deformation occurs and the interaction of multiple hydraulic fractures.  The research outcome can be used in the design of robust and  conservative finite element methods in modeling of  porous media where the difficult crack/fracture events are focused.       Last Modified: 10/25/2020       Submitted by: Ruijie Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
