<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Electrochemical Separation Device for Co-Ni Recovery from Li-ion Batteries</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224773.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224773</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady-Estevez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will address a critical need for a new source of strategic materials for the clean energy and electronics markets. The U.S. is a major consumer of cobalt, a critical component in rechargeable lithium-ion batteries. Over the next five years, the rapid increase in electric vehicles on the road will cause a drastic shift in the market, becoming the largest and fastest growing end-use of this critical material. This projected increase in demand, combined with the unstable global supply and difficulties with scaling mining productions, puts our cobalt supply at high risk. Discarded lithium ion batteries could be a viable secondary source of cobalt if viable recycling technologies were available. Achieving efficient, low-cost recycling of Li-ion batteries will facilitate a secure source of cobalt for our U.S.-based manufacturers with large societal impact, offering a high net-benefit concerning air emissions and climate protection, and incentives for collecting high priority waste. The commercial impact of this technology will enable further innovation for clean energy technologies where humans ability to literally wield power where and when they want it that will not be limited by the availability of critical metals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will provide a recycling technology for the li-ion battery market, helping to solve the supply crisis for cobalt in the electronics and clean energy sector. Currently, there are no viable alternatives for cobalt separation and capture, except for large, expensive, and energy consumptive hydrometallurgical and pyrometallurgical processes. While these techniques work well, they require high capital and material transportation costs. The technique proposed here provides a new and efficient method for separating and reclaiming cobalt oxide for direct reuse in advanced manufacturing, designed with a small footprint so that it can be added onto existing recycling and manufacturing processes to capture these metals, without large upfront capital cost. The research objectives of this SBIR project will demonstrate feasibility of recovering cobalt from Li-ion battery waste using a plug-and-play, high-throughput electrochemical deposition method. To achieve this, we will utilize high surface area, flexible carbon material to enhance the selectivity and efficiency of our process. The anticipated technical results include a 5-10x reduction in cost and 1-4x reduction in CO2 emissions compared to incumbent recycling technologies, ultimately redefining our current wastes as resources, providing a secure source of cobalt to the U.S. market.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1913628</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Megan</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Connor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Megan P O'Connor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>oconnor@nthcycle.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5185340562</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000759507</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chad</FirstName>
<LastName>Vecitis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chad D Vecitis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vecitis@nthcycle.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5185340562</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000793443</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/08/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Nth Cycle, LLC</Name>
<CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>379194432</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5185340562</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>844 POETS CORNER WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080858704</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NTH CYCLE, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Nth Cycle, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>379194432</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[844 POETS CORNER WAY]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~224773</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Phase I project helped advance a sustainable, energy efficient metal processing technology for low-cost recycling of li-ion batteries. Here, the bench scale technology was validated, demonstrating a new electrochemical precipitation technology could process spent batteries into valuable products for li-ion battery manufacturing supply chains. The tasks completed for the NSF SBIR Phase 1 Award achieved all four Go/No-Go benchmarks, demonstrating the system can produce a high-quality cobalt hydroxide at a 75% reduction in cost, a 75% reduction in GHG emissions, and a 60% reduction in energy use compared to competitive technologies. In addition to hitting all technology milestones, a techno-economic analysis was also completed, indicating high profitability, fast payback periods with the current business model, and areas for improvement as the device is scaled during Phase II.</p> <p>These outcomes significantly reduce the technical risk while helping to identify the next steps towards commercialization. In addition, the NSF I-Corps support during this project helped define our value proposition in this growing market space, indicating our modularity, clean operations, and production grade outputs at a fraction of the cost are our main differentiators. This technology will not only help mitigate the low incentive to recycle by providing a profitable system for li-ion battery management, but it will also: (1) reduce the need for mining in politically unstable regions thus decreasing national security risk, (2) lower demand for primary battery materials and reducing the environmental impact (3) reduce manufacturing costs with fewer refining steps, and most importantly, (4) significantly reduce the GHG emissions from this industry by utilizing secondary materials instead of primary materials for manufacturing.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/18/2021<br>      Modified by: Megan&nbsp;P&nbsp;O'connor</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Phase I project helped advance a sustainable, energy efficient metal processing technology for low-cost recycling of li-ion batteries. Here, the bench scale technology was validated, demonstrating a new electrochemical precipitation technology could process spent batteries into valuable products for li-ion battery manufacturing supply chains. The tasks completed for the NSF SBIR Phase 1 Award achieved all four Go/No-Go benchmarks, demonstrating the system can produce a high-quality cobalt hydroxide at a 75% reduction in cost, a 75% reduction in GHG emissions, and a 60% reduction in energy use compared to competitive technologies. In addition to hitting all technology milestones, a techno-economic analysis was also completed, indicating high profitability, fast payback periods with the current business model, and areas for improvement as the device is scaled during Phase II.  These outcomes significantly reduce the technical risk while helping to identify the next steps towards commercialization. In addition, the NSF I-Corps support during this project helped define our value proposition in this growing market space, indicating our modularity, clean operations, and production grade outputs at a fraction of the cost are our main differentiators. This technology will not only help mitigate the low incentive to recycle by providing a profitable system for li-ion battery management, but it will also: (1) reduce the need for mining in politically unstable regions thus decreasing national security risk, (2) lower demand for primary battery materials and reducing the environmental impact (3) reduce manufacturing costs with fewer refining steps, and most importantly, (4) significantly reduce the GHG emissions from this industry by utilizing secondary materials instead of primary materials for manufacturing.          Last Modified: 02/18/2021       Submitted by: Megan P O'connor]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
