<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Harnessing Natural Language Processing for Scalable Text-based Behavioral Health Care</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224835.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224835</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to address a systematic behavioral health and substance use provider shortage, cost-effectively improve patient retention in treatment, and proactively treat chronic behavioral health patients. Left untreated, these conditions cost over $1 trillion annually and result in countless early deaths. Peer support is an effective tool to engage patients unwilling or unable to access clinical care, particularly in marginalized populations.  However, scaling peer support is challenging, with current online support forums rife with trolling and abuse. Our Natural Language Processing (NLP) tools can extrapolate the emotional sentiment of text messages, automatically flagging clinically relevant or critical content. This allows clinicians to easily moderate groups by focusing their time on the patients most in need, while peers generate the touchpoints necessary for day-to-day engagement.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will greatly enhance the ability of clinicians to track the mental health of patients within a support group. Currently, a challenge in managing peer groups is identifying the health of a group as a whole - some groups can be far more constructive than others. Given the volume of messages generated in an online support group, together with expected caseloads for care manager and peer support specialists, who may be managing dozens of groups, this is an impossible task without the aid of technology. To achieve this goal we focus on three main areas: 1) improving the performance of our existing NLP algorithms by developing novel techniques to identify and track multiple conversations that might be co-occurring in the group, 2)  developing a method of tracking the overall health and stability of a group by analyzing interactions among peers and 3) design new interfaces that effectively display all of the insights generated by the algorithms. These NLP tools will power a platform to give patients more access to support. Providers will have access to a novel high-fidelity data source to better triage outreach and personalize care.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1913999</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Satya Prateek</FirstName>
<LastName>Bommaraju</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Satya Prateek Bommaraju</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>satya@marigoldhealth.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4697742381</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000783254</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>BEACON TECH INC.</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>021082111</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9082559419</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>55 Court Street Ste 231</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080502643</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BEACON TECH INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[BEACON TECH INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021111750</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2 Ave de Lafayette]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~224835</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>90% of Americans with SUD are not in treatment. When patients receive care, they do so inconsistently. The average length of time an American spends in treatment before seeing a full year of recovery is 8 years. Peer Support is proven to be effective at engaging patients who are unwilling to engage with traditional treatment. Marigold is a virtual peer support program for patients with substance use disorders (SUD). Patients work 1-1 with one of Marigold's peer specialists to create individualized wellness plans but much of the engagement is via 24/7 text-based support groups where patients message each other anonymously. Marigold can guarantee the quality and safety of these groups due to proprietary natural language processing (NLP) algorithms that analyze the messages sent by patients within the groups. In our Phase I proposal we improved the ability of our NLP to predict message sentiment even in large groups where multiple conversations are occurring simultaneously. We developed NLP tools to identify healthy communities in the app and built technology to deliver automated SMS interventions to patients. Finally, we built a dashboard to render the results of our analytics to providers. Marigold's asynchronous model is designed for accessibility and has shown evidence that it can reach patients with higher medical needs. For example, over 85% of the patients engaging with the system to date have been on Medicaid. Our work fills an urgent need for more available &amp; effective behavioral health care in the wake of the ongoing Opioid Crisis and COVID-19 pandemic.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Satya Prateek&nbsp;Bommaraju</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ 90% of Americans with SUD are not in treatment. When patients receive care, they do so inconsistently. The average length of time an American spends in treatment before seeing a full year of recovery is 8 years. Peer Support is proven to be effective at engaging patients who are unwilling to engage with traditional treatment. Marigold is a virtual peer support program for patients with substance use disorders (SUD). Patients work 1-1 with one of Marigold's peer specialists to create individualized wellness plans but much of the engagement is via 24/7 text-based support groups where patients message each other anonymously. Marigold can guarantee the quality and safety of these groups due to proprietary natural language processing (NLP) algorithms that analyze the messages sent by patients within the groups. In our Phase I proposal we improved the ability of our NLP to predict message sentiment even in large groups where multiple conversations are occurring simultaneously. We developed NLP tools to identify healthy communities in the app and built technology to deliver automated SMS interventions to patients. Finally, we built a dashboard to render the results of our analytics to providers. Marigold's asynchronous model is designed for accessibility and has shown evidence that it can reach patients with higher medical needs. For example, over 85% of the patients engaging with the system to date have been on Medicaid. Our work fills an urgent need for more available &amp; effective behavioral health care in the wake of the ongoing Opioid Crisis and COVID-19 pandemic.          Last Modified: 07/28/2021       Submitted by: Satya Prateek Bommaraju]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
