<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Development Of A Sensor System For Feedback Guided Manual Ventilation With A Bag Valve Mask.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>223363.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>248363</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Bag-valve masks are simple, squeezable tools for manual ventilation of patients and are the most common manual method used in both emergencies and routine surgical procedures. The simplicity and minimal cost of BVMs have contributed to their widespread use and sales of approximately 13.1 million disposable resuscitators annually in the U.S. alone. Despite the regular use of BVMs, providers of any training level regularly deliver ineffective ventilation or uncontrolled, inadvertent, forced over-inflation. Studies show that, while using a standard BVM, 88.4% of trained users exceeding the recommended pressure and 73.8% exceeding the recommended volume range2 Improper ventilation for even short periods can lead to two major complications 1) Lung injury from over-stretching (called volutrauma); too much air and 2) Lung injury from over-pressurization (called barotrauma); too much pressure. These conditions can lead to life-threatening conditions as well as prolonged and expensive hospital stays with costs approaching $170,000 (CAD) per injury. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When used in emergency situations, execution of proper BVM technique is required to provide optimal oxygenation during CPR. Devices to monitor the depth and rate of CPR compressions are widely available and are soon to be required in all training centers by the AHA.  However, no technologies exist to provide similar feedback for manual ventilation. It is likely that real-time feedback can reduce or eliminate the rate of dangerous ventilation among caregivers of all levels and that BVM training with feedback can lead to improved skill retention. Thus, a novel  technique and complementary device have been developed to provide real time feedback to trained and training personnel and ensure they meet guidelines from the American Heart Association (AHA) and European Resuscitation Council (ERC). This project is a comprehensive system development pathway composed of three aims that will refine our sensor system and initiate studies into the benefits of real-time feedback during BVM usage. This method utilizes a unique sensor system that can be coupled to a bag valve mask to measure the air pressure and volume delivered to a patient. Using these metrics for each squeeze of the bag, this device can alert users of both excessive pressure and volume in real time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/02/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1913943</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Restaino</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen M Restaino</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smrestaino@mddevelopmentcenter.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7572878752</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000783756</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/20/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Gair</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey L Gair</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>j.gair.jr@scineticsinc.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4439611121</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000811437</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>PNEUMICO, LLC</Name>
<CityName>BALTIMORE</CityName>
<ZipCode>212016512</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4434614414</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 W PRATT ST STE 200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>081276062</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PNEUMICO, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[PNEUMICO, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212016512</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 W. Pratt Street Suite 200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~223363</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~25000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Pneumico is developing technologies to improve the safety and quality of manual ventilation, a technique that is lifesaving, but potentially deadly if performed incorrectly. Under this Phase I SBIR award, our goal was to refine, verify, and validate the capabilities of a ventilation monitor and real-time feedback system for manual ventilation delivered via a bag-valve mask. We designed an improved sensor system that reduced ventilation measurement error from &plusmn;30% to &plusmn;2.16% for adult tidal volumes, well below the industry standard of &plusmn;10%. The device was used in a series of quantified manual ventilation studies conducted with participants of varied backgrounds and expertise, with an aim to understand both the scope of inadequate hand ventilation technique, as well as the efficacy of such a device in training and correcting injurious technique.<br /><br />Device testing with 37 participants demonstrated a significant reduction in tidal volume error when users were provided with a GUI feedback system (intervention trial). In 5% of cases, we saw dramatic differences in outcomes between the intervention and control trials, indicating that the device would prevent lung injury caused by inappropriate ventilation. In our study, the device allowed lay resuscitators to perform comparably to those with the highest level of training in airway management. Lastly, ventilation skills were not retained at 1 week after CPR class, but at this time point the device was able to guide delivery of consistent and predictable tidal volumes that were closer to the recommended values, and certainly within the non-injurious bounds.<br /><br />Ultimately, we found that the Pneumico device produced improvements in ventilation performance on average, even with highly trained personnel, and led to dramatic improvements in isolated cases. Prolific use of bag-valve masks on COVID patients during inter-hospital and intra-hospital transport intensifies the need for such a product.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;L&nbsp;Gair</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Pneumico is developing technologies to improve the safety and quality of manual ventilation, a technique that is lifesaving, but potentially deadly if performed incorrectly. Under this Phase I SBIR award, our goal was to refine, verify, and validate the capabilities of a ventilation monitor and real-time feedback system for manual ventilation delivered via a bag-valve mask. We designed an improved sensor system that reduced ventilation measurement error from &plusmn;30% to &plusmn;2.16% for adult tidal volumes, well below the industry standard of &plusmn;10%. The device was used in a series of quantified manual ventilation studies conducted with participants of varied backgrounds and expertise, with an aim to understand both the scope of inadequate hand ventilation technique, as well as the efficacy of such a device in training and correcting injurious technique.  Device testing with 37 participants demonstrated a significant reduction in tidal volume error when users were provided with a GUI feedback system (intervention trial). In 5% of cases, we saw dramatic differences in outcomes between the intervention and control trials, indicating that the device would prevent lung injury caused by inappropriate ventilation. In our study, the device allowed lay resuscitators to perform comparably to those with the highest level of training in airway management. Lastly, ventilation skills were not retained at 1 week after CPR class, but at this time point the device was able to guide delivery of consistent and predictable tidal volumes that were closer to the recommended values, and certainly within the non-injurious bounds.  Ultimately, we found that the Pneumico device produced improvements in ventilation performance on average, even with highly trained personnel, and led to dramatic improvements in isolated cases. Prolific use of bag-valve masks on COVID patients during inter-hospital and intra-hospital transport intensifies the need for such a product.       Last Modified: 01/01/2021       Submitted by: Jeffrey L Gair]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
