<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  CLEAR: Reducing Claims Denials in Healthcare Through Blockchain and Machine Learning</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady-Estevez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is to create transparency around the business logic used by stakeholders in the healthcare system to make transactional decisions as well as create alignment around the current status of healthcare transactions that are part of the work in process. To most people who interact with the healthcare system, it functions more or less as a "black box" with decisions that sometimes defy logic and common sense. Our goal is to use Blockchain and Machine Learning technology to convert this "black box" into a "glass box." The commercial impact of this project could be an up to 25% reduction in claims processing costs for healthcare providers by the elimination of redundant work, re-work and errors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR Phase 1 project proposes two innovations: 1) claims transaction and reason codes managed through a Blockchain so that Providers and Payers can confidently know the accurate status of a claim, and 2) sophisticated statistical and deep learning algorithms for predicting the likelihood of a claim denial with natural language processing of associated notes and appeals. Our product is a mathematically driven software service that utilizes and innovates with multiple technologies: Blockchain distributed ledgers, smart contracts and tokens, and prediction, recommendation, forecasting, non-linear optimization and natural language processing engines within a privacy-preserving data management system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1914203</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Prabhudev</FirstName>
<LastName>Konana</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Prabhudev Konana</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pkonana@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124715219</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485944</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sriram</FirstName>
<LastName>Vishwanath</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sriram Vishwanath</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sriramuniverse@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124711190</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000487326</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/06/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tejwansh</FirstName>
<LastName>Anand</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tejwansh S Anand</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tej@brilliant.md</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6508234072</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000793403</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/05/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah B Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sarah@brilliant.md</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2146970454</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000830335</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>BRILLIANTMD, LLC</Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>787045418</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6508234072</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2607 EUCLID AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>081244418</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BRILLIANTMD, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas, Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787120100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Univ Sta C0803]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-954999a4-7fff-a879-4abc-ee6a464d3f0e"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Health care billing in the U.S. is extremely inefficient. Health care providers spend $496 billion per year on Revenue Cycle Management, with almost fifty percent of that deemed excessive. After health care services are provided, the process of billing insurers and health plans for those services is complex. The claims submission process is long, arduous, error prone and subjective, with an average claim taking 2-6 months to get paid. Initial, first pass denial rates average 7-14% with up to 65% of claims never reworked or resubmitted. For those claims that are reprocessed, final denial rates, still average between 5% and 7.5%.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>BrilliantMD delivers an integrated AI/ML/Blockchain platform that utilizes best in class NLP (Natural Language Processing) and ML(Machine Learning) technologies coupled to a state-of-the-art Blockchain infrastructure. BrilliantMD develops and deploys proprietary algorithms that increase RCM efficiencies and enhance claim transaction transparency. BrilliantMD technology augments and improves RCM workflows, simplifies and prioritizes claims processing and uses Blockchain-backed tokens to incentivize productivity.</span></p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>During BrilliantMD?s Phase I STTR grant, we designed and implemented a solution, CLEAR (Claims Error Analysis and Reconciliation), that successfully confirmed our thesis that AI and Blockchain technology can increase revenue and efficiency in the health care claims process. CLEAR uses AI-powered insights that allow Revenue Cycle Management teams to more effectively manage claim denials. CLEAR?s advanced ML algorithms analyze and rank denied claims, based on dollar amount and probability of payment, and optimize workflow, backed by token-based productivity incentives to drive the claim to adjudication and payment.</span></p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>For our initial pilot customer, these technologies delivered the following results:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>? Overall revenue per claim worked increased by 44%.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>? Total amount collected within 30 and 60 days increased by 79% and 41% respectively.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>? The number of eligible and compliant submittable claims increased by 28%.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In addition to CLEAR, implemented during Phase 1, BrilliantMD also developed the first iteration of our second product, the Natural Language Processing (NLP) tool, LUCID. LUCID extracts key concepts from unstructured notes to derive knowledge to support claims, automating an aspect of the claims process that has relied on manual work.</span></p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>All the outcomes and technology development performed in Phase 1 enable us to implement our blockchain incentivization framework, COLLECT. COLLECT uses token incentives to drive optimal claim management backed by improved data collection, accuracy, analytics and machine learning.</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/20/2021<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;B&nbsp;Brown</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Health care billing in the U.S. is extremely inefficient. Health care providers spend $496 billion per year on Revenue Cycle Management, with almost fifty percent of that deemed excessive. After health care services are provided, the process of billing insurers and health plans for those services is complex. The claims submission process is long, arduous, error prone and subjective, with an average claim taking 2-6 months to get paid. Initial, first pass denial rates average 7-14% with up to 65% of claims never reworked or resubmitted. For those claims that are reprocessed, final denial rates, still average between 5% and 7.5%.    BrilliantMD delivers an integrated AI/ML/Blockchain platform that utilizes best in class NLP (Natural Language Processing) and ML(Machine Learning) technologies coupled to a state-of-the-art Blockchain infrastructure. BrilliantMD develops and deploys proprietary algorithms that increase RCM efficiencies and enhance claim transaction transparency. BrilliantMD technology augments and improves RCM workflows, simplifies and prioritizes claims processing and uses Blockchain-backed tokens to incentivize productivity.   During BrilliantMD?s Phase I STTR grant, we designed and implemented a solution, CLEAR (Claims Error Analysis and Reconciliation), that successfully confirmed our thesis that AI and Blockchain technology can increase revenue and efficiency in the health care claims process. CLEAR uses AI-powered insights that allow Revenue Cycle Management teams to more effectively manage claim denials. CLEAR?s advanced ML algorithms analyze and rank denied claims, based on dollar amount and probability of payment, and optimize workflow, backed by token-based productivity incentives to drive the claim to adjudication and payment.   For our initial pilot customer, these technologies delivered the following results: ? Overall revenue per claim worked increased by 44%. ? Total amount collected within 30 and 60 days increased by 79% and 41% respectively. ? The number of eligible and compliant submittable claims increased by 28%. In addition to CLEAR, implemented during Phase 1, BrilliantMD also developed the first iteration of our second product, the Natural Language Processing (NLP) tool, LUCID. LUCID extracts key concepts from unstructured notes to derive knowledge to support claims, automating an aspect of the claims process that has relied on manual work.   All the outcomes and technology development performed in Phase 1 enable us to implement our blockchain incentivization framework, COLLECT. COLLECT uses token incentives to drive optimal claim management backed by improved data collection, accuracy, analytics and machine learning.               Last Modified: 04/20/2021       Submitted by: Sarah B Brown]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
