<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Student Travel Support for 2019 International Conference on Very Large Databases (VLDB)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wei-Shinn Ku</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>weiku@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928318</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides support for 12-20 students from U.S.-based academic institutions to attend and participate in the 45th International Conference on Very Large, held in Los Angeles, California, USA, August 26-30, 2019. VLDB, started in 1975 and is the premier international database conference, held annually. Different countries ranging from China to India, Germany, Brazil and USA have hosted VLDB and the conference provides a forum for researchers and practitioners to exchange and share results, providing tremendous opportunities for technological and entrepreneurial innovation. VLDB 2019 has a separate but equally prestigious research and industry tracks for the papers, more than ten timely workshops to co-locate with VLDB, and includes a Ph.D. workshop track that attracts students in their early career phase and allows the open discussion of their research ideas. The VLDB conference thus contributes directly to training the next generation of scientists who are both consumers and developers of technology in database management system design and implementation. The student support will have direct impact in creating a highly-qualified workforce who can take on the emerging data science challenges of the future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;VLDB conference introduced numerous influential concepts such as "Big Data", "Data Science", and "Cloud" computing. For almost half a century and after an explosive growth in the computing industry, VLDB remains the home for the latest cutting-edge research and industrial innovation in the data arena.  The aims of the conference are multi-fold: (1) provide an international forum for sharing research results related to the investigation of major challenges in next-generation database research; (2) stimulate interactive discussions on research in the database area through panels, posters, tutorials, student scholar roundtables, etc.; (3) to motivate and engage future generations of researchers via the many conference and workshop presentations, interactive poster sessions, and panel and breakout sessions.  VLDB highly cited papers are published in The Proceedings of the VLDB Endowment (PVLDB).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1914904</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shahram</FirstName>
<LastName>Ghandeharizadeh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shahram Ghandeharizadeh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shahram@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137404781</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000339767</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900890701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~25000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-881875c5-7fff-281f-77b8-cc475de4b950"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>VLDB is a premier annual international forum for data management and database researchers, vendors, practitioners, application developers, and users.&nbsp; It has introduced numerous influential concepts such as "Big Data", "Data Science", and "Cloud" before these names became widely used. Some of the seminal and highly cited research papers in these topics were published in VLDB.&nbsp; For almost half a century and after an explosive growth in the computing industry, VLDB remains the home for the latest cutting-edge research and industrial innovation in the data arena. Even today, the technology and research presented at our conference is typically 5 to 10 years ahead of its time.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Project outcome</strong><span>:&nbsp; This grant provided support for 20 graduate students enrolled in US universities to participate in the VLDB conference held at Los Angeles, California from August 26th to 30th, 2019.&nbsp; There were several applicants with excellent credentials, but only a few could be supported.  In making the selection, priority was given to those with full research papers, followed by demo and workshop papers; but equally, we took into account funding availability from other sources since the goal of these grants was to support those who did not have access to sufficient funds from other sources (as declared by the applicant/nominator and supplemented by research grant information online) as well as the diversity of the students supported in order to increase the diversity of VLDB's student participants.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><strong>Intellectual merit</strong>:</span><span>&nbsp; The 45</span><span><span>th</span></span><span> VLDB program featured selected high-quality technical papers with broad international participation and included multiple keynotes, an industry track, panels on cutting-edge topics, tutorials, workshops, a Ph.D. forum, and discussion sessions. This project promoted the next generation of students and researchers to identify scientific foundations for building large-scale database management systems that can work ever more effectively. The proposed effort also brought together students and senior researchers from academia and industry with a global perspective; this was of immense intellectual value to the area and to the students who engage in database research.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><strong>Broader impact</strong>:&nbsp; </span><span>The VLDB endowment's SPEND committee made special efforts to facilitate the participation of a diverse group of US researchers. In particular, efforts will be made to engage and encourage researchers with a view towards broadening the participation of researchers from groups including women, minorities, and other underrepresented groups. The conference contributed to training the next generation of scientists, engineers, and database application designers who are both consumers and developers of data management&nbsp; technologies.  VLDB 2019 papers are disseminated using electronic online proceedings of 12th volume of VLDB, see </span><a href="http://www.vldb.org/pvldb/vol12.html"><span>http://www.vldb.org/pvldb/vol12.html</span></a><span> for details.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Scientific research requires the free exchange of ideas, open-minded thinking, and unrestricted access to knowledge. One of the benefits of this visit to VLDB may be international scientific research collaboration, which can go beyond the understanding and discovery of knowledge. International collaborations foster cultural understanding and strengthen human relationships among nations. They broaden the opportunities for bright, inquiring people as they prepare to participate in life in the twenty-first century.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/08/2020<br>      Modified by: Shahram&nbsp;Ghandeharizadeh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   VLDB is a premier annual international forum for data management and database researchers, vendors, practitioners, application developers, and users.  It has introduced numerous influential concepts such as "Big Data", "Data Science", and "Cloud" before these names became widely used. Some of the seminal and highly cited research papers in these topics were published in VLDB.  For almost half a century and after an explosive growth in the computing industry, VLDB remains the home for the latest cutting-edge research and industrial innovation in the data arena. Even today, the technology and research presented at our conference is typically 5 to 10 years ahead of its time. Project outcome:  This grant provided support for 20 graduate students enrolled in US universities to participate in the VLDB conference held at Los Angeles, California from August 26th to 30th, 2019.  There were several applicants with excellent credentials, but only a few could be supported.  In making the selection, priority was given to those with full research papers, followed by demo and workshop papers; but equally, we took into account funding availability from other sources since the goal of these grants was to support those who did not have access to sufficient funds from other sources (as declared by the applicant/nominator and supplemented by research grant information online) as well as the diversity of the students supported in order to increase the diversity of VLDB's student participants. Intellectual merit:  The 45th VLDB program featured selected high-quality technical papers with broad international participation and included multiple keynotes, an industry track, panels on cutting-edge topics, tutorials, workshops, a Ph.D. forum, and discussion sessions. This project promoted the next generation of students and researchers to identify scientific foundations for building large-scale database management systems that can work ever more effectively. The proposed effort also brought together students and senior researchers from academia and industry with a global perspective; this was of immense intellectual value to the area and to the students who engage in database research. Broader impact:  The VLDB endowment's SPEND committee made special efforts to facilitate the participation of a diverse group of US researchers. In particular, efforts will be made to engage and encourage researchers with a view towards broadening the participation of researchers from groups including women, minorities, and other underrepresented groups. The conference contributed to training the next generation of scientists, engineers, and database application designers who are both consumers and developers of data management  technologies.  VLDB 2019 papers are disseminated using electronic online proceedings of 12th volume of VLDB, see http://www.vldb.org/pvldb/vol12.html for details. Scientific research requires the free exchange of ideas, open-minded thinking, and unrestricted access to knowledge. One of the benefits of this visit to VLDB may be international scientific research collaboration, which can go beyond the understanding and discovery of knowledge. International collaborations foster cultural understanding and strengthen human relationships among nations. They broaden the opportunities for bright, inquiring people as they prepare to participate in life in the twenty-first century.          Last Modified: 01/08/2020       Submitted by: Shahram Ghandeharizadeh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
