<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference on Science at the Sanford Underground Research Facility 2019 May 15-17, 2019 in Lead, South Dakota.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan Whitmore</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide partial support for the "Conference on Science at the Sanford Underground Research Facility 2019." The conference will be held May 15-17, 2019 at the South Dakota School of Mines and Technology, Rapid City, South Dakota and will have an impact on the broader field including particle and nuclear physics. It will have a particular focus on early career scientists (including graduate students). This award will provide participant travel support for these students to be able to participate in the symposium. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CoSSURF 2019 conference will bring together both theoreticians and experimentalists across various fields in nuclear and particle physics, as well as material scientists, geologists, and biologists. It is expected that there will be a thriving exchange between all participants on the latest developments in underground science and engineering topics. While scientists are planning next-generation experiments at SURF and around the world, face-to-face discussions on the experimental and theoretical status and expectations will benefit the underground science community in their planning of future programs at SURF.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/13/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1914835</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xinhua</FirstName>
<LastName>Bai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xinhua Bai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Xinhua.Bai@sdsmt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6053945198</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000539043</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Strieder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frank Strieder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>frank.strieder@sdsmt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6053941227</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000702443</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>South Dakota School of Mines and Technology</Name>
<CityName>Rapid City</CityName>
<ZipCode>577013995</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6053941218</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>501 East Saint Joseph Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>929928018</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTH DAKOTA SCHOOL OF MINES &amp; TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>929538999</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[South Dakota School of Mines and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Rapid City</CityName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>577013995</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[501 East Saint Joseph Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1234</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR PRECISION MEASUREMENTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1285</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1288</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics &amp; Cosmol</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7235</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Undergro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 3<sup>rd</sup> Conference on Science at the Sanford Underground Research Facility took place on May 14<sup>th</sup> to 17<sup>th</sup>, 2019 on the campus of the South Dakota School of Mines and Technology (South Dakota Mines) in Rapid City, South Dakota. Eighty researcher from all over the U.S. as well as some colleagues from Europe and Australia attended the conference and engaged in fruitful discussion on the current status and the future of the scientific projects at the Sanford Underground Research Facility in Lead, South Dakota.</p> <p>The general conference program consisted of plenary talks in the morning of each day followed by parallel sessions in the afternoon. The topics covered by presentations from leading experts in their field (plenary talks) and contributed oral presentations by mainly young postdocs and graduate students were neutrino oscillations with focus on science with the Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment (DUNE), dark matter search with priority on the LUX-Zeplin (LZ) experiment, neutrinoless double beta-decay search (Majorana Demonstrator), nuclear astrophysics (CASPAR and DIANA), and geology research (SIGMA-V). The focus in each field was on research related to the Sanford Underground Research Facility, but other complementary experiments were also well represented in the conference program. The conference was started on the first day with a workshop on Low Background Screening and Applications</p> <p>One of the highlights of the conference during the first day was a presentation by a representative of the South Dakota Lakota Tribe about Sacred Sites in the Black Hills for the Native American Community. This inclusive presentation was a great opportunity to increase the awareness of the scientists of the importance and sacredness of the area for the local Lakota Community and was a great way to learn more about Lakota culture, tradition and history. Scientists should understand the entire history of the place and area they use for their important experiments and respect the culture and tradition this place is embedded in.</p> <p>A comprehensive report on the Sanford Underground Research Facility by SURF?s Science Director, Dr. Jaret Heise, summarized the current status of the laboratory infrastructure and the future of the facility in particular with respect to the excavations needed for the DUNE project. In parallel to the afternoon sessions on Thursday, May 16<sup>th</sup> an underground laboratory tour of the Sanford Underground Research Facility was organized and many participants took advantage of this opportunity.</p> <p>In the evening of Wednesday, May 15<sup>th</sup> a public lecture for local high school students was organized with the title ?Whispers in the Dark?. The lecture on research in dark matter search was presented by one of the dark matter plenary speaker, Prof. Jodi Cooley of Southern Methodist University. She was the 2019 recipient of the American Association of Physics Teacher?s Klopsteg Memorial Award and is an inspiring teacher for the next generation. The presentation was well received by local high school students with about half of them being female students asking many interesting questions about dark matter search.</p> <p>Travel awards for 11 graduate students and 5 young postdocs were granted through the support by the National Science Foundation. The travel grants allowed for an increased participation of young researchers in the field and guaranteed a successful mixture of experience scientists, many of them giving great overview talks, and the next generation scientists during this conference.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2020<br>      Modified by: Frank&nbsp;Strieder</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914835/1914835_10592633_1601245834427_2019-CoS-at-SURF-groupshot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914835/1914835_10592633_1601245834427_2019-CoS-at-SURF-groupshot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Conference Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914835/1914835_10592633_1601245834427_2019-CoS-at-SURF-groupshot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Conference Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conference participants on SD Mines campus.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Brian Hill (SD Mines)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Frank&nbsp;Strieder</div> <div class="imageTitle">Conference Photo</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 3rd Conference on Science at the Sanford Underground Research Facility took place on May 14th to 17th, 2019 on the campus of the South Dakota School of Mines and Technology (South Dakota Mines) in Rapid City, South Dakota. Eighty researcher from all over the U.S. as well as some colleagues from Europe and Australia attended the conference and engaged in fruitful discussion on the current status and the future of the scientific projects at the Sanford Underground Research Facility in Lead, South Dakota.  The general conference program consisted of plenary talks in the morning of each day followed by parallel sessions in the afternoon. The topics covered by presentations from leading experts in their field (plenary talks) and contributed oral presentations by mainly young postdocs and graduate students were neutrino oscillations with focus on science with the Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment (DUNE), dark matter search with priority on the LUX-Zeplin (LZ) experiment, neutrinoless double beta-decay search (Majorana Demonstrator), nuclear astrophysics (CASPAR and DIANA), and geology research (SIGMA-V). The focus in each field was on research related to the Sanford Underground Research Facility, but other complementary experiments were also well represented in the conference program. The conference was started on the first day with a workshop on Low Background Screening and Applications  One of the highlights of the conference during the first day was a presentation by a representative of the South Dakota Lakota Tribe about Sacred Sites in the Black Hills for the Native American Community. This inclusive presentation was a great opportunity to increase the awareness of the scientists of the importance and sacredness of the area for the local Lakota Community and was a great way to learn more about Lakota culture, tradition and history. Scientists should understand the entire history of the place and area they use for their important experiments and respect the culture and tradition this place is embedded in.  A comprehensive report on the Sanford Underground Research Facility by SURF?s Science Director, Dr. Jaret Heise, summarized the current status of the laboratory infrastructure and the future of the facility in particular with respect to the excavations needed for the DUNE project. In parallel to the afternoon sessions on Thursday, May 16th an underground laboratory tour of the Sanford Underground Research Facility was organized and many participants took advantage of this opportunity.  In the evening of Wednesday, May 15th a public lecture for local high school students was organized with the title ?Whispers in the Dark?. The lecture on research in dark matter search was presented by one of the dark matter plenary speaker, Prof. Jodi Cooley of Southern Methodist University. She was the 2019 recipient of the American Association of Physics Teacher?s Klopsteg Memorial Award and is an inspiring teacher for the next generation. The presentation was well received by local high school students with about half of them being female students asking many interesting questions about dark matter search.  Travel awards for 11 graduate students and 5 young postdocs were granted through the support by the National Science Foundation. The travel grants allowed for an increased participation of young researchers in the field and guaranteed a successful mixture of experience scientists, many of them giving great overview talks, and the next generation scientists during this conference.       Last Modified: 09/27/2020       Submitted by: Frank Strieder]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
