<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Student Travel Grant for 2019 ACM SIGSIM Conference on Principles of Advanced Discrete Simulation (PADS)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alan Sussman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alasussm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927563</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Discrete simulations are widely employed across a variety of settings, from the large-scale models that are commonplace in national laboratories (e.g., to simulate particles or populations) to industrial applications (e.g., in healthcare or transportation). The growing interest in simulations is also fueled by dynamic research in big data, which is both used and generated by simulations. In line with ongoing national efforts to train and diversify the workforce in science, this award supports students in the United States to attend the annual Conference on Principles of Advanced Discrete Simulation held in Chicago in June, 2019, with special emphasis on members of under-represented groups such as female and minorities. This serves the national interest, as stated by NSF's mission, to promote the progress of science as it provides a forum to disseminate research efforts, connect researchers, and train the next generation of scholars.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Selected students have access to traditional opportunities to support their career success and gain tools that support the advancement of science in theoretical as well as applied research on discrete simulations. Such traditional opportunities include presenting their work at the event (through oral presentations as well as posters), developing their scientific networks, and acquiring new state-of-the-art methods. Although the conference builds on a rich history dating back to 1985, the innovative format of the 2019 edition goes beyond traditional opportunities offered to students. In particular, the conference actively supports workforce development and the advancement of science by organizing (i) panels on careers beyond a doctoral program, with contributors from national laboratories, liberal arts colleges, and research universities; and (ii) round tables with editors of several prominent journals in the field. The funding provided by NSF thus has a significant impact on the careers of the future generation of researchers in discrete simulation, while encouraging diversity in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/21/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1914715</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dong</FirstName>
<LastName>Jin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dong Jin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dongjin@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2178409842</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000654118</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philippe</FirstName>
<LastName>Giabbanelli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philippe Giabbanelli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>giabbapj@miamioh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5135290340</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000745871</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Illinois Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606163717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125673035</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10 West 35th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 7D71]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042084434</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ILLINOIS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042084434</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Illinois Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606163732</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7361</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION AND WORKFORCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>026Z</Code>
<Text>NSCI: National Strategic Computing Initi</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This overarching goal of this project is to contribute to the training of young scholars in the field of Modeling and Simulation (M&amp;S). The award specifically seeks to support approximately five students, with an emphasis on under-represented groups, in attending the 2019 ACM SIGSIM-PADS conference held in Chicago, Illinois from June 3 to June 5, 2019. While this annual event was established in 1985, it is the first time that a project explicitly aims at promoting diversity and supporting the career success of young scholars through this preeminent technical conference. The organization of the conference changed with the 2019 edition to provide a range of opportunities to new scholars, beyond the traditional poster sessions and ability to attend sessions or discuss research with established researchers. New opportunities include oral presentations for all accepted posters, round tables with journal editors, and a panel on careers. The award thus supports a diverse body of students in developing essential skills in written, oral, and visual communication as they pertain to Modeling &amp; Simulation.</p> <p><br />A conference proceeding was developed to serve as an official record of ACM SIGSIM-PADS 2019. It includes a brief introduction about ACM SIGSIM-PADS 2019, the technical program, organization committee, a list of reviewer and contributors, sponsors, copyright information, technical articles, etc. The conference proceedings have been distributed through ACM Digital Library.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/24/2019<br>      Modified by: Dong&nbsp;Jin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This overarching goal of this project is to contribute to the training of young scholars in the field of Modeling and Simulation (M&amp;S). The award specifically seeks to support approximately five students, with an emphasis on under-represented groups, in attending the 2019 ACM SIGSIM-PADS conference held in Chicago, Illinois from June 3 to June 5, 2019. While this annual event was established in 1985, it is the first time that a project explicitly aims at promoting diversity and supporting the career success of young scholars through this preeminent technical conference. The organization of the conference changed with the 2019 edition to provide a range of opportunities to new scholars, beyond the traditional poster sessions and ability to attend sessions or discuss research with established researchers. New opportunities include oral presentations for all accepted posters, round tables with journal editors, and a panel on careers. The award thus supports a diverse body of students in developing essential skills in written, oral, and visual communication as they pertain to Modeling &amp; Simulation.   A conference proceeding was developed to serve as an official record of ACM SIGSIM-PADS 2019. It includes a brief introduction about ACM SIGSIM-PADS 2019, the technical program, organization committee, a list of reviewer and contributors, sponsors, copyright information, technical articles, etc. The conference proceedings have been distributed through ACM Digital Library.       Last Modified: 07/24/2019       Submitted by: Dong Jin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
