<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Lower Extremity Injury Prediction Neuromuscular Algorithm</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 1 project is provision of a scientifically-based, muscle-specific, mobile first, injury reduction protocol for professional and collegiate athletes who experience lower distal non-contact injuries. This application will overcome barriers to currently available stationary technologies by enabling key insights to relieve athletes before the incident of injury occurs.  60% of injuries for professional and collegiate sports are related to the lower extremities, costing professional organizations $10 M annually in recovery and salary sunk cost and consequently a $1.2 B injury market.  We will develop a solution to the prevention care triple aim of 1) Improving the accuracy of diagnosing injuries; 2) Improving treatment recommendations accuracy; 3) Forecasting specific muscle and joint injuries based on the environment. The application is a timely business opportunity starting with a recurring software subscription model that will provide better service, at a lower occurrence of non-contact lower distal injuries. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 1 Project will translate the core modules of neuromuscular activity and computer vision into a comprehensive, athlete-centered, mobile friendly solution to reduce ankle sprains and ACL tears.  We hypothesize that the use of computer vision in combination with the analysis of neuromuscular activity will result in a machine learning human movement index with the ability to model neuromuscular work and approximate time of muscle fatigue.  We have demonstrated that the use of the neuromuscular activity data illuminates a direct line of pathology of injury for the main stabilizers within the lower extremity.  Testing over 300 athletes and collecting 36 million neuromuscular data samples, we have discovered risk factors that correlate with injuries.  By utilizing technologies such as tensor flow, neuromuscular activity muscle activity produces a rich data set identifying muscle and joint inefficiencies via camera on the mobile phone.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1914139</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kehlin</FirstName>
<LastName>Swain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kehlin Swain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kehlin.swain@xplosionlive.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2819891508</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000794171</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>HX INNOVATIONS, INC.</Name>
<CityName>MIDDLETOWN</CityName>
<ZipCode>197098341</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3024945680</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>372 NORTHHAMPTON WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>117103500</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HX INNOVATIONS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hx Innovations, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Middletown</CityName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197098341</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[372 Northhampton Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-ca12380e-7fff-94b5-f35b-3d50ea3a5124"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 1 Project was funded to fine tune and program the lower extremity injury prediction neuromuscular algorithm and translate the core modules of neuromuscular activity and computer vision into a comprehensive mobile friendly Human Optimization Movement Ergonomics Report.&nbsp; Our specific aim was to enhance our lower extremity injury prediction algorithm through the combined use of IMUs, Computer Vision, and EMG sensors.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The evolution of our technology began with the development of a lab based model made up of 3 different biosensors. Our Phase 1 award has enabled our scientist to extend our knowledge and understanding of building machine learning algorithms into computer vision programs using biofeedback from 3 different physiological systems in the human body. &nbsp; Initially, we tested our computer vision model using Google PoseNet. We discovered that in comparison to data collected from our IMU sensors, the PoseNet program revealed significant spatial speed limitations during data collection of simple low speed single joint body movements. As a result, we concluded that PoseNet would not have the capability to gather the high-speed tri-planal movements needed for The Homer Technique</span><span><span>TM </span></span><span>(?THT?). To remedy the limitations of PoseNet, we transitioned to Microsoft Kinect as it includes dual depth sensors, a motorized pivot, and software to capture motion and gestures. Collectively, these sensors have helped us overcome the pixel-to-distance tracking issue found in PoseNet. See Figure 1.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Preliminary results gathered showed strong correlation between contributing physiological factors of joint torque and neuromuscular work, which led to significant advancement in our technology. Demonstration of correlation factors torque and neuromuscular work can be seen in Figure 2. THT technology has demonstrated capabilities that match what is currently commercially available and fit our target market needs.&nbsp; Further risk assessment of our technology and target market led to continual development of additional technical objectives that exceed Phase 1 specific aims.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;The use of neuromuscular activity data illuminates a direct line of pathology of injury for main stabilizers within the lower extremity. Testing over 400 athletes and collecting 48 million neuromuscular data samples, we have discovered risk factors that correlate with injuries. By utilizing technologies such as tensor flow, neuromuscular and muscle activity produced a rich data set identifying muscle and joint inefficiencies.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Moreover, our development efforts have continued to connect the commercial and technological accomplishments achieved during Phase 1.&nbsp; Past our PoseNet discovery, continual modification of the technology as it relates to the commercialization of our product has allowed us to, identify an image tracking system better suited for our software and capture rate capability; initiate training of computer vision model with one dimensional kinematic parameters; complete a database to store raw captured data and; complete development of an application programming interface (API) designed to feed into our deep machine learning algorithm and connect to our user interface platform for metrics to be displayed. Our Phase II objectives are projected to have a large impact in the evolution of our technology. We expect to completely replace the use of IMU/EMG sensors within our service process with fully programmed computer vision and machine learning mobile cameras.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-58145d94-7fff-09fb-9160-87ddf776df23"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The final product, which incorporates the novel algorithm, will allow researchers and/or the general public to utilize THT to determine how efficiently one maintains neuromuscular balance of the lower extremities within a certain environment (i.e., shod, unshod). Our innovative approach relies on characterization of the central and peripheral neurological systems and its effect on the musculoskeletal system. Computational neuroscience and neuro-biomechanics are both used together to create a metric which represents one?s level of comfort, postural stability and movement safety.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Human Optimization Movement Ergonomics Report is specifically designed to summarize the efficacy of footwear and its materials within stereotyped human movement patterns to, improve the accuracy of footwear comfort and function standards; determine the efficacy on human fatigue and movement safety and; forecast specific muscle and joint injuries based on these principal components of human locomotion. See Figure 3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/23/2020<br>      Modified by: Kehlin&nbsp;Swain</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914139/1914139_10632171_1598227021679_michaelSlatory-balance--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914139/1914139_10632171_1598227021679_michaelSlatory-balance--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914139/1914139_10632171_1598227021679_michaelSlatory-balance--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3 Provided a snapshot of The Human Optimization Movement Ergonomics Report for (1) subject completing the Y-balance test. Optimization scores are weighted configured in correspondence with Y-balance composite scores.  Neuromuscular effort is configured based on Minimal, Submaximal and Maximal</div> <div class="imageCredit">Von Homer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kehlin&nbsp;Swain</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914139/1914139_10632171_1598226883511_Figure6Plot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914139/1914139_10632171_1598226883511_Figure6Plot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914139/1914139_10632171_1598226883511_Figure6Plot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2: EMG and IMU sensors are fused with a less-than-5 sample difference in peaks. The green boxes represent each calf raise and identify if the peaks amplitudes between the two sensors have a-less-than-5 sample difference. In short, it indicates a high level of accuracy between the two sensors?</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kehlin Swain</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kehlin&nbsp;Swain</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914139/1914139_10632171_1598226818793_y-Balanace--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914139/1914139_10632171_1598226818793_y-Balanace--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914139/1914139_10632171_1598226818793_y-Balanace--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Microsoft Kinect computer vision model programmed to collect and display accurate low to medium speed tripanal kinematics</div> <div class="imageCredit">Von Homer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kehlin&nbsp;Swain</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 1 Project was funded to fine tune and program the lower extremity injury prediction neuromuscular algorithm and translate the core modules of neuromuscular activity and computer vision into a comprehensive mobile friendly Human Optimization Movement Ergonomics Report.  Our specific aim was to enhance our lower extremity injury prediction algorithm through the combined use of IMUs, Computer Vision, and EMG sensors. The evolution of our technology began with the development of a lab based model made up of 3 different biosensors. Our Phase 1 award has enabled our scientist to extend our knowledge and understanding of building machine learning algorithms into computer vision programs using biofeedback from 3 different physiological systems in the human body.   Initially, we tested our computer vision model using Google PoseNet. We discovered that in comparison to data collected from our IMU sensors, the PoseNet program revealed significant spatial speed limitations during data collection of simple low speed single joint body movements. As a result, we concluded that PoseNet would not have the capability to gather the high-speed tri-planal movements needed for The Homer TechniqueTM (?THT?). To remedy the limitations of PoseNet, we transitioned to Microsoft Kinect as it includes dual depth sensors, a motorized pivot, and software to capture motion and gestures. Collectively, these sensors have helped us overcome the pixel-to-distance tracking issue found in PoseNet. See Figure 1. Preliminary results gathered showed strong correlation between contributing physiological factors of joint torque and neuromuscular work, which led to significant advancement in our technology. Demonstration of correlation factors torque and neuromuscular work can be seen in Figure 2. THT technology has demonstrated capabilities that match what is currently commercially available and fit our target market needs.  Further risk assessment of our technology and target market led to continual development of additional technical objectives that exceed Phase 1 specific aims.  The use of neuromuscular activity data illuminates a direct line of pathology of injury for main stabilizers within the lower extremity. Testing over 400 athletes and collecting 48 million neuromuscular data samples, we have discovered risk factors that correlate with injuries. By utilizing technologies such as tensor flow, neuromuscular and muscle activity produced a rich data set identifying muscle and joint inefficiencies. Moreover, our development efforts have continued to connect the commercial and technological accomplishments achieved during Phase 1.  Past our PoseNet discovery, continual modification of the technology as it relates to the commercialization of our product has allowed us to, identify an image tracking system better suited for our software and capture rate capability; initiate training of computer vision model with one dimensional kinematic parameters; complete a database to store raw captured data and; complete development of an application programming interface (API) designed to feed into our deep machine learning algorithm and connect to our user interface platform for metrics to be displayed. Our Phase II objectives are projected to have a large impact in the evolution of our technology. We expect to completely replace the use of IMU/EMG sensors within our service process with fully programmed computer vision and machine learning mobile cameras.       The final product, which incorporates the novel algorithm, will allow researchers and/or the general public to utilize THT to determine how efficiently one maintains neuromuscular balance of the lower extremities within a certain environment (i.e., shod, unshod). Our innovative approach relies on characterization of the central and peripheral neurological systems and its effect on the musculoskeletal system. Computational neuroscience and neuro-biomechanics are both used together to create a metric which represents one?s level of comfort, postural stability and movement safety. The Human Optimization Movement Ergonomics Report is specifically designed to summarize the efficacy of footwear and its materials within stereotyped human movement patterns to, improve the accuracy of footwear comfort and function standards; determine the efficacy on human fatigue and movement safety and; forecast specific muscle and joint injuries based on these principal components of human locomotion. See Figure 3.                  Last Modified: 08/23/2020       Submitted by: Kehlin Swain]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
