<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Paramagnetic Spin-Probes for Corrosion Inhibition</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady-Estevez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project addresses a mechanism to optimize corrosion inhibition for projects covering the oil and gas industry and beyond. Corrosion costs US industries alone an estimated $170 billion a year. The oil and gas industry takes an above average share of these costs because of its complex and demanding production techniques, and the environmental threat should components fail. Today, the standard inhibition mechanism for the oil and gas industry is to inject a chemical inhibitor, typically a surfactant, that can coat the interior of the oilfield tubular and avoid corrosion. Because of the high cost of failure, it is extremely common to over-inject surfactant quantities resulting in excessive costs and the waste of unwanted chemicals sent to the refinery. Unfortunately, there has not previously been a good way to tell when too much surfactant was in fact too much. That is the specific new aspect brought by this innovation. It proposes a mechanism to detect in real-time that there is sufficient surfactant by taking advantage of quantum chemical properties of those surfactants when they are subject to very large magnetic fields and GHz radio-frequency excitation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to extract a chemical spectrum from a specially designed reagent that can be added to a sample of produced fluid, where that chemical spectrum will change depending on whether there is sufficient surfactant to cause corrosion inhibition. More specifically it is going to measure some quantum chemical properties of the reagent called its hyperfine structure that will change in the presence of surfactant micelles. Essentially the micelles form a containment barrier around free radical electrons within that reagent and thereby change the way those electrons can resonate in the combination of the magnet and RF excitation. Phase 1 of the project will resolve multiple challenges in this approach, including the choice of reagent and the development of robust algorithms to convert hyperfine data into quantification of critical micelle concentration, where the algorithm needs to be able to tolerate typical impurities found in oilfield fluids. Phase 1 will also validate a spectroscopic approach that can result in the hyperfine data being sent to the cloud where AI-based algorithms can reduce the spectral information to actionable information for the operator.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1914258</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Lovell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Lovell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>john.lovell@microsiliconinc.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8324591210</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000782998</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>MICROSILICON INC</Name>
<CityName>KATY</CityName>
<ZipCode>774942085</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8327103030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7706 BULRUSH CANYON TRL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>088509728</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICROSILICON INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[MICROSILICON INC]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770422829</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2101 CityWest Blvd, Techspace]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A micelle is an aggregate of molecules in colloidal suspension where each end of the molecule has a different polarity, e.g., one end might be hydrophobic and the other hydrophilic. In water, such molecules will tend to cluster with the hydrophobic tips in the center and the hydrophilic outside. Because one end may have a net positive [or negative] charge, for the tips to come together they must also overcome charge repulsion. Below a certain dosage, the critical-micelle-concentration (cmc), few micelles will form, while above they will become increasingly common. Micelle creation tends to create an inflection point in relationships between physical properties, such as viscosity or surface tension vs concentration.</p> <p>Achieving cmc is important in day-to-day activities, such as the amount of detergent a washing machine needs to clean with minimal suds. In the oil industry, cmc determines the level of corrosion inhibitors needed. Standard practice is to take periodic samples of the produced fluid, send it to a lab and determine the inhibitor concentration. Because of environmental and economic risks due to pipe failure, normal practice is to overdose inhibitor to stay on the &ldquo;safe side&rdquo;. This increases costs which are then passed onto the customer as part of operator&rsquo;s price calculation.</p> <p>There is significant interest in&nbsp;avoiding laboratory sampling by using a permanently installed device enabled with a real-time technique to identify whether an additive was above its cmc. This would allow real-time optimization of the inhibitor amount.</p> <p>The bulk of our experiments were performed with sodium-dodecyl-sulphate (SDS), who&rsquo;s chemical behaviour matches that of many inhibitors. We found a micelle property amenable to real-time monitoring, specifically, its rotational correlation time: i.e., the&nbsp;average time for an individual micelle to rotate one radian. This measurement could not be made directly, but could be measured by adding to the water a very small amount of a reagent, called a spin-probe.</p> <p>We investigated four spin-probes derived from stearic acid. They have nitroxide radicals (an outer orbital containing just one electron) shown by the solid dot in Figure 1. This electron is amenable to real-time analysis.</p> <p>The spin-probes have long organic chains and are insoluble in water, so it might seem counterintuitive to choose them, but, in the presence of micelles, the compounds have an opportunity to &ldquo;hide&rdquo; from the water by burrowing their organic tails into the micelle interior. This bonds the spin-probe to the micelle and makes it rotate at the same speed as its host micelle.</p> <p>In the presence of high magnetic fields and radio frequency excitation, an outer electron will resonate. The resonance is modified by nearby nuclei (e.g. nitrogen in these spin-probes). Fixing the frequency while sweeping the magnet strength gives a spectrum of reflected voltage whose peaks reveal electron interaction with its surroundings, a principle known as Electron Paramagnetic Resonance (EPR).</p> <p>Figure 2 shows 9.5 GHz spectra for 16-DSE added to different molar concentrations of SDS in water. Also plotted are synthetic calculations for a nitroxide-spin probe where the only parameter changed between the curves is the rotational correlation time. The match for each curve is excellent and provides the basis for a possible oil well process: mechanically separate the water component, add nitroxide spin-probe, derive a paramagnetic spectrum from EPR and determine the rotational correlation time.</p> <p>This research project showed that such a device can be created by modifying the existing oilfield apparatus shown in Figure 3. It uses EPR to quantify the amount of asphaltene flowing in a well, but was not designed to measure a full spectrum but only the height of the middle peak - all that was required for asphaltene.</p> <p>To optimize the magnetic field sweep, the frequency was dropped from 9.5GHz to 4.25GHz. We showed that frequency change did not affect ability of the spin-probes to measure correlation time. We also determined the required resolution of the magnetic sweep for real-time micelle analysis.</p> <p>Rotational correlation has uses by itself. Einstein (!) had proven the time was proportional to viscosity times particle size, which hints at a real-time measurement of micelle size. But correlation times are not immediately translatable into cmc. The principle of a second algorithm follows by examining the derived correlation time against SDS concentration.</p> <p>Reaching cmc creates both a change in micro-viscosity and a sudden increase in the number of micelles of a large-enough size, so the correlation time shows a dramatic inflection point (Figure 4). &nbsp;This gives rise to a robust algorithm wherein a smart wellbore system need not to check for a specific time but instead could alert for sudden changes in that value. The algorithm viability was demonstrated with commercial corrosion inhibitors in addition to SDS.</p> <p>The net result of the project is a demonstration how to convert a real-time paramagnetic apparatus into a smart device for real-time monitoring of corrosion inhibitor micelles.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/08/2020<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;Lovell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914258/1914258_10613753_1594211464891_Figure3_Project_Outcome--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914258/1914258_10613753_1594211464891_Figure3_Project_Outcome--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Correlation Time vs Concentration"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914258/1914258_10613753_1594211464891_Figure3_Project_Outcome--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Correlation Time vs Concentration"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 4: A plot of correlation time vs concentration shows an inflection point at the cmc. In this case of SDS in water, the cmc is 8.2mM. The correlation time is derivable from real-time EPR device.</div> <div class="imageCredit">MicroSilicon Inc</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;Lovell</div> <div class="imageTitle">Correlation Time vs Concentration</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914258/1914258_10613753_1594211256775_Figure2_Project_Outcome--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914258/1914258_10613753_1594211256775_Figure2_Project_Outcome--rgov-800width.jpg" title="EPR spectrum vs SDS Molar Concentration"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914258/1914258_10613753_1594211256775_Figure2_Project_Outcome--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="EPR spectrum vs SDS Molar Concentration"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2: The EPR spectrum of 16-DSE bonded to SDS in water depends upon the molar concentration of SDS. For each of the six curves, we also plot a synthetic result where all models use the same parameters except for rotational correlation time.</div> <div class="imageCredit">MicroSilicon Inc</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;Lovell</div> <div class="imageTitle">EPR spectrum vs SDS Molar Concentration</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914258/1914258_10613753_1594210603774_Figure1_Project_Outcome--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914258/1914258_10613753_1594210603774_Figure1_Project_Outcome--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Stearic-acid based probes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914258/1914258_10613753_1594210603774_Figure1_Project_Outcome--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Stearic-acid based probes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig 1: Four spin-probes based on stearic acid were used for this analysis. The nitroxide radical is indicated by a dot on the chemical formula. Resonance of that radical reveals properties of the molecule to which the spin-probe is attached.</div> <div class="imageCredit">MicroSilicon Inc</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;Lovell</div> <div class="imageTitle">Stearic-acid based probes</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914258/1914258_10613753_1594211992915_Figure3_Project_Outcome--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914258/1914258_10613753_1594211992915_Figure3_Project_Outcome--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Real-Time EPR device at wellhead"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1914258/1914258_10613753_1594211992915_Figure3_Project_Outcome--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Real-Time EPR device at wellhead"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3: An existing EPR device at the wellhead is configured to monitor asphaltenes. Enhancing its resolution allows it to provide a full EPR spectrum. By adding spin-probes to extracted water phase it is possible to determine rotational correlation times of micelles, and hence cmc.</div> <div class="imageCredit">MicroSilicon Inc</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;Lovell</div> <div class="imageTitle">Real-Time EPR device at wellhead</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A micelle is an aggregate of molecules in colloidal suspension where each end of the molecule has a different polarity, e.g., one end might be hydrophobic and the other hydrophilic. In water, such molecules will tend to cluster with the hydrophobic tips in the center and the hydrophilic outside. Because one end may have a net positive [or negative] charge, for the tips to come together they must also overcome charge repulsion. Below a certain dosage, the critical-micelle-concentration (cmc), few micelles will form, while above they will become increasingly common. Micelle creation tends to create an inflection point in relationships between physical properties, such as viscosity or surface tension vs concentration.  Achieving cmc is important in day-to-day activities, such as the amount of detergent a washing machine needs to clean with minimal suds. In the oil industry, cmc determines the level of corrosion inhibitors needed. Standard practice is to take periodic samples of the produced fluid, send it to a lab and determine the inhibitor concentration. Because of environmental and economic risks due to pipe failure, normal practice is to overdose inhibitor to stay on the "safe side". This increases costs which are then passed onto the customer as part of operator’s price calculation.  There is significant interest in avoiding laboratory sampling by using a permanently installed device enabled with a real-time technique to identify whether an additive was above its cmc. This would allow real-time optimization of the inhibitor amount.  The bulk of our experiments were performed with sodium-dodecyl-sulphate (SDS), who’s chemical behaviour matches that of many inhibitors. We found a micelle property amenable to real-time monitoring, specifically, its rotational correlation time: i.e., the average time for an individual micelle to rotate one radian. This measurement could not be made directly, but could be measured by adding to the water a very small amount of a reagent, called a spin-probe.  We investigated four spin-probes derived from stearic acid. They have nitroxide radicals (an outer orbital containing just one electron) shown by the solid dot in Figure 1. This electron is amenable to real-time analysis.  The spin-probes have long organic chains and are insoluble in water, so it might seem counterintuitive to choose them, but, in the presence of micelles, the compounds have an opportunity to "hide" from the water by burrowing their organic tails into the micelle interior. This bonds the spin-probe to the micelle and makes it rotate at the same speed as its host micelle.  In the presence of high magnetic fields and radio frequency excitation, an outer electron will resonate. The resonance is modified by nearby nuclei (e.g. nitrogen in these spin-probes). Fixing the frequency while sweeping the magnet strength gives a spectrum of reflected voltage whose peaks reveal electron interaction with its surroundings, a principle known as Electron Paramagnetic Resonance (EPR).  Figure 2 shows 9.5 GHz spectra for 16-DSE added to different molar concentrations of SDS in water. Also plotted are synthetic calculations for a nitroxide-spin probe where the only parameter changed between the curves is the rotational correlation time. The match for each curve is excellent and provides the basis for a possible oil well process: mechanically separate the water component, add nitroxide spin-probe, derive a paramagnetic spectrum from EPR and determine the rotational correlation time.  This research project showed that such a device can be created by modifying the existing oilfield apparatus shown in Figure 3. It uses EPR to quantify the amount of asphaltene flowing in a well, but was not designed to measure a full spectrum but only the height of the middle peak - all that was required for asphaltene.  To optimize the magnetic field sweep, the frequency was dropped from 9.5GHz to 4.25GHz. We showed that frequency change did not affect ability of the spin-probes to measure correlation time. We also determined the required resolution of the magnetic sweep for real-time micelle analysis.  Rotational correlation has uses by itself. Einstein (!) had proven the time was proportional to viscosity times particle size, which hints at a real-time measurement of micelle size. But correlation times are not immediately translatable into cmc. The principle of a second algorithm follows by examining the derived correlation time against SDS concentration.  Reaching cmc creates both a change in micro-viscosity and a sudden increase in the number of micelles of a large-enough size, so the correlation time shows a dramatic inflection point (Figure 4).  This gives rise to a robust algorithm wherein a smart wellbore system need not to check for a specific time but instead could alert for sudden changes in that value. The algorithm viability was demonstrated with commercial corrosion inhibitors in addition to SDS.  The net result of the project is a demonstration how to convert a real-time paramagnetic apparatus into a smart device for real-time monitoring of corrosion inhibitor micelles.          Last Modified: 07/08/2020       Submitted by: John Lovell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
