<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Development of novel sensors to determine health of batteries</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>223095.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>223095</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to improve battery health and predicting hazardous events related to battery performance. This will have an important impact on consumer safety, sustainable energy development via promoting reliable energy storage from solar and wind power, as well as in critical applications related to healthcare. As the power density of the batteries keeps increasing, consumers start seeing evidence of potentially catastrophic battery failures, resulting in fires and explosions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be to validate the preliminary results that sensor sensitivity, dimensions and speed are sufficient to capture subtle changes in the battery's signatures that are indicative of formation of SEI degradation of electrodes, electrolytes and other battery components. It will be based on ex-situ and in-situ measurements, modelling and machine learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1914025</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Wark</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher Wark</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chris@warkenergy.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9175656919</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000782871</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/20/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>FLUXION TECHNOLOGY INC.</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117946044</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6313564675</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Suite 216, 1000 Innovation Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[AERTC]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>081023134</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLUXION TECHNOLOGY INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FLUXION TECHNOLOGY INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117942275</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 Innovation Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1185</Code>
<Text>SENSORY SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~223095</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>According to Bloomberg research, there are many evidences of the battery-powered era affecting everything around us. From electric vehicles populating our freeways to multiple appliances storing solar energy that was until recently a daytime-only power source, it is becoming a pervasive technology in our daily lives. Governments from the US to China are taking steps that will make battery power even more ubiquitous. As the power density of the batteries keeps increasing, consumers start seeing numerous evidences of potentially catastrophic battery failures, resulting in fires and explosions. The most high-profile case is the Samsung Galaxy Note7 phone recall of millions of units after exploding Lithium-ion batteries forced the company to withdraw its product. However, the batteries were in the news for many years as they have caused fires in hoverboards, laptops, other mobile phones, and even in the electrical system of a Boeing 787 Dreamliner jumbo jet. The intellectual merit of this project is in developing a new approach to predict the lifetime of a battery by capturing its thermal signatures. Here we have validated thermal measurements using our first-generation heat-flux sensor with several measurement techniques. For the first time we were able to distinguish thermal signatures of aged and new batteries that has tremendous implications for detecting and predicting deliration of the batteries. Given unprecedentedly small sensor size and potential for its scale up production, the results will allow us to further develop this technology for numerous applications, including the electric vehicles battery diagnostic.&nbsp; The broader impacts of this project are in prevention of catastrophic events related to batteries&rsquo; failure, which can result in loss of lives and tremendous economic damages.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/09/2020<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;Wark</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ According to Bloomberg research, there are many evidences of the battery-powered era affecting everything around us. From electric vehicles populating our freeways to multiple appliances storing solar energy that was until recently a daytime-only power source, it is becoming a pervasive technology in our daily lives. Governments from the US to China are taking steps that will make battery power even more ubiquitous. As the power density of the batteries keeps increasing, consumers start seeing numerous evidences of potentially catastrophic battery failures, resulting in fires and explosions. The most high-profile case is the Samsung Galaxy Note7 phone recall of millions of units after exploding Lithium-ion batteries forced the company to withdraw its product. However, the batteries were in the news for many years as they have caused fires in hoverboards, laptops, other mobile phones, and even in the electrical system of a Boeing 787 Dreamliner jumbo jet. The intellectual merit of this project is in developing a new approach to predict the lifetime of a battery by capturing its thermal signatures. Here we have validated thermal measurements using our first-generation heat-flux sensor with several measurement techniques. For the first time we were able to distinguish thermal signatures of aged and new batteries that has tremendous implications for detecting and predicting deliration of the batteries. Given unprecedentedly small sensor size and potential for its scale up production, the results will allow us to further develop this technology for numerous applications, including the electric vehicles battery diagnostic.  The broader impacts of this project are in prevention of catastrophic events related to batteries’ failure, which can result in loss of lives and tremendous economic damages.          Last Modified: 10/09/2020       Submitted by: Christopher Wark]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
