<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student support for 2019 GSA Thompson Field Forum in Grand Canyon; September 14-21, 2019</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>8500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>8500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephen Harlan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sharlan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927707</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposal provides support for the participation of five students and two early career professionals in the 17th Geological Society of America Thompson Field Forum on the "Age and carving of the Grand Canyon: Towards a resolution of 140 years of debate." The forum will bring together 28 researchers and scientists to discuss evidence for the age and incision history of the Grand Canyon in the context of recent advances and ongoing debates. The goal to promote the next generation of research on this subject, which is of broad interest both to the scientific community and the general public. There has been considerable interest in what seems to be like an old subject, but recent scientific advances have provoked controversy and new ideas regarding the age and formation of the canyon with high-profile publications in the journals, Science and Nature. Controversial ideas to be discussed include: 1) evidence for mantle-to surface hydrologic connections; 2) ongoing mantle-driven uplift of the Colorado Plateau; 3) the contested "bulls-eye" of erosion of the Colorado Plateau; and 4) Causes of major knickpoints as due to incision transients and/or variable strength rock layers. The conference is timely in that the community needs to examine and evaluate the evidence first hand and develop better integrated methodologies to test these and other debates. The students and early career professionals (including four women) will be supported by this activity are actively involved in Grand Canyon research and hence will be knowledgeable and receptive to the nuances of the discussions. They will also get a chance to present their new work for the general discussions. The exposure they will get to high level integrative science will be potentially transformative for their careers. A unique opportunity associated with the Field Forum will be a river trip down the Colorado River through the Grand Canyon with opportunities to discuss scientific questions on the outcrop and at evening seminars. Society benefits from this activity include contributions to STEM education and educator development; development of a diverse, globally competitive workforce; and contributions to the broadening of participation of underrepresented groups in STEM.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/29/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/29/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1915209</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
<LastName>Karlstrom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karl E Karlstrom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kek1@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052774346</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000423259</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/29/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>868853094</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NEW MEXICO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>784121725</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Grand Canyon via UNM]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1572</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~8500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project applied $8,500 in NSF participant support to help fund 5 graduate students to participate in the 2019 (17<sup>th</sup>) Geological Society of America Thompson Field Forum entitled: <em>Age and Carving of Grand Canyon: Towards a resolution of 140 years of debate. </em>&nbsp;This topic has been debated since John Wesley Powell&rsquo;s exploration of the Colorado River in 1869 and there are still major scientific controversies that need to be resolved. The field forum involved 28 researchers and young scientists selected from a pool of 40 applicants by the conveners. Participants included 5 students and 2 young career professionals, all actively involved in Grand Canyon research, 7 international participants, and a representative from Grand Canyon National Parks&rsquo;s science office. All 28 scientists had interdisciplinary expertise in one or more subdisciplines of hydrology, neotectonics, geomorphology, thermochronology, geodynamics, and geochemistry. The field forum took place during an eight-day field trip by raft through the Grand Canyon. It started and ended in Las Vegas, Nevada and covered 280 miles from Lees Ferry to Pearce Ferry under a charter with Grand Canyon Expeditions. Each of the participants gave a field seminar via presentations on the outcrop, &ldquo;plenary&rdquo; presentations at morning and evening seminars, and/or short talks and discussions on the hikes or on the boats at key locations. Each participant prepared ahead of time some reference figures that were compiled into a booklet that facilitated the presentations.</p> <p>The main scientific achievement was the open discussion and debate among high level experts in an informal setting. Scientific consensus was achieved in some, but not all, topics. The process of identifying future challenges was an equally important achievement. The following topics were energetically discussed. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Grand Canyon&rsquo;s incised aquifer system</span> shows complex mixing of meteoric, karst, and CO<sub>2</sub>-rich &ldquo;lower world&rdquo; waters that needs a better baseline for understanding water quantity and quality and groundwater pathways to continue to provide water for the Park&rsquo;s &gt;6 million annual visitors. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Regional uplift </span>of the Rocky Mountain &ndash; Colorado Plateau region took place in several stages over the past 70 million years and much debate focused on evidence for the whether it is ongoing. The proponents of young and ongoing surface uplift proposed a mechanism of <span style="text-decoration: underline;">mantle-driven uplift </span>whereby Earth&rsquo;s topography can be supported in part by mantle flow and buoyancy. The elevation difference needed for rivers to incise landscapes and carve canyons means that uplift history debates are entwined with canyon incision debates. The <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Age of the Colorado River, </span>the time the river reached the Gulf of California,<span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span>is now well known to be about 5 million years based on research by trip participants. The <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Age of Grand Canyon </span>was debated; endmember &ldquo;young&rdquo; canyon models (all post 6 million years old) and &ldquo;old&rdquo; canyon models (70-17 million years old) were not supported on the trip. Instead, a consensus is emerging that integration of the Colorado River took place through some older paleocanyon segments and that Grand Canyon as we see it today was carved in the past 5-6 million years. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Bedrock incision rates</span> in Grand Canyon have been semi-steady at 160 m/Ma over the past 1.2 Ma in the east and 100 m/Ma over 3-4 Ma in the west with the difference accounted for by east-side-up slip on regional faults that may be a signal of Colorado Plateau uplift. Strengths and limitations of <span style="text-decoration: underline;">thermochronology</span> were discussed; it has great potential for reconstructing past, now-eroded, landscapes and its resolution will improve as additional work is done on diffusion kinetics of helium in damaged crystals. The tools of thermochronology, geodynamic modeling, and landscape modeling are all advancing rapidly and Grand Canyon is a key field laboratory for their development.</p> <p>Success in terms of broader impacts outreach involved the trip itself and synergistic meetings that were also held to celebrate the Park&rsquo;s centennial and Powell&rsquo;s sesquicentennial. These included the national meeting of the Geological Society of America in Phoenix immediately after the Field Forum. Most participants flew directly from Las Vegas to the Phoenix meeting such that debates and discussions continued formally, as meeting theme sessions, and informally among the wider geoscience community. The trip was effective for promoting a next generation of research on the evolution and tectonic geomorphology of this iconic region, as well as similar studies globally. One of the student participants, Muhammad Qasim Mahmood, discussed international geoscience outreach. He is originator of two popular social media outlets called &ldquo;Learning Geology&rdquo; and &ldquo;Learning Geology Community&rdquo; that reach 137,000 geoscience learners internationally and provide an ongoing successful example of geoscience outreach through social media. This promises to have an important influence on the education of a large group of young scientists who will be shaping the future of the geosciences globally.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/06/2020<br>      Modified by: Karl&nbsp;E&nbsp;Karlstrom</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1915209/1915209_10588897_1586194371569_COVER_Holmescropped--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1915209/1915209_10588897_1586194371569_COVER_Holmescropped--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Iconic landscapes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1915209/1915209_10588897_1586194371569_COVER_Holmescropped--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Iconic landscapes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A portion of the "Panorama From Point Sublime", lithograph by William Henry Holmes from Clarence E. Dutton, Tertiary History of the Grand Ca?on District with Atlas, USGS Monograph 2, 1882</div> <div class="imageCredit">Public domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karl&nbsp;E&nbsp;Karlstrom</div> <div class="imageTitle">Iconic landscapes</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1915209/1915209_10588897_1586203367288_TFFGroupPhoto_Ladd_sm--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1915209/1915209_10588897_1586203367288_TFFGroupPhoto_Ladd_sm--rgov-800width.jpg" title="17th GSA Thompson Field Forum group picture"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1915209/1915209_10588897_1586203367288_TFFGroupPhoto_Ladd_sm--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="17th GSA Thompson Field Forum group picture"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">GSA 17th Thompson Field Forum group picture at the Lees Ferry launch.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Photo by Gary Ladd</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karl&nbsp;E&nbsp;Karlstrom</div> <div class="imageTitle">17th GSA Thompson Field Forum group picture</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project applied $8,500 in NSF participant support to help fund 5 graduate students to participate in the 2019 (17th) Geological Society of America Thompson Field Forum entitled: Age and Carving of Grand Canyon: Towards a resolution of 140 years of debate.  This topic has been debated since John Wesley Powell’s exploration of the Colorado River in 1869 and there are still major scientific controversies that need to be resolved. The field forum involved 28 researchers and young scientists selected from a pool of 40 applicants by the conveners. Participants included 5 students and 2 young career professionals, all actively involved in Grand Canyon research, 7 international participants, and a representative from Grand Canyon National Parks’s science office. All 28 scientists had interdisciplinary expertise in one or more subdisciplines of hydrology, neotectonics, geomorphology, thermochronology, geodynamics, and geochemistry. The field forum took place during an eight-day field trip by raft through the Grand Canyon. It started and ended in Las Vegas, Nevada and covered 280 miles from Lees Ferry to Pearce Ferry under a charter with Grand Canyon Expeditions. Each of the participants gave a field seminar via presentations on the outcrop, "plenary" presentations at morning and evening seminars, and/or short talks and discussions on the hikes or on the boats at key locations. Each participant prepared ahead of time some reference figures that were compiled into a booklet that facilitated the presentations.  The main scientific achievement was the open discussion and debate among high level experts in an informal setting. Scientific consensus was achieved in some, but not all, topics. The process of identifying future challenges was an equally important achievement. The following topics were energetically discussed. Grand Canyon’s incised aquifer system shows complex mixing of meteoric, karst, and CO2-rich "lower world" waters that needs a better baseline for understanding water quantity and quality and groundwater pathways to continue to provide water for the Park’s &gt;6 million annual visitors. Regional uplift of the Rocky Mountain &ndash; Colorado Plateau region took place in several stages over the past 70 million years and much debate focused on evidence for the whether it is ongoing. The proponents of young and ongoing surface uplift proposed a mechanism of mantle-driven uplift whereby Earth’s topography can be supported in part by mantle flow and buoyancy. The elevation difference needed for rivers to incise landscapes and carve canyons means that uplift history debates are entwined with canyon incision debates. The Age of the Colorado River, the time the river reached the Gulf of California, is now well known to be about 5 million years based on research by trip participants. The Age of Grand Canyon was debated; endmember "young" canyon models (all post 6 million years old) and "old" canyon models (70-17 million years old) were not supported on the trip. Instead, a consensus is emerging that integration of the Colorado River took place through some older paleocanyon segments and that Grand Canyon as we see it today was carved in the past 5-6 million years. Bedrock incision rates in Grand Canyon have been semi-steady at 160 m/Ma over the past 1.2 Ma in the east and 100 m/Ma over 3-4 Ma in the west with the difference accounted for by east-side-up slip on regional faults that may be a signal of Colorado Plateau uplift. Strengths and limitations of thermochronology were discussed; it has great potential for reconstructing past, now-eroded, landscapes and its resolution will improve as additional work is done on diffusion kinetics of helium in damaged crystals. The tools of thermochronology, geodynamic modeling, and landscape modeling are all advancing rapidly and Grand Canyon is a key field laboratory for their development.  Success in terms of broader impacts outreach involved the trip itself and synergistic meetings that were also held to celebrate the Park’s centennial and Powell’s sesquicentennial. These included the national meeting of the Geological Society of America in Phoenix immediately after the Field Forum. Most participants flew directly from Las Vegas to the Phoenix meeting such that debates and discussions continued formally, as meeting theme sessions, and informally among the wider geoscience community. The trip was effective for promoting a next generation of research on the evolution and tectonic geomorphology of this iconic region, as well as similar studies globally. One of the student participants, Muhammad Qasim Mahmood, discussed international geoscience outreach. He is originator of two popular social media outlets called "Learning Geology" and "Learning Geology Community" that reach 137,000 geoscience learners internationally and provide an ongoing successful example of geoscience outreach through social media. This promises to have an important influence on the education of a large group of young scientists who will be shaping the future of the geosciences globally.       Last Modified: 04/06/2020       Submitted by: Karl E Karlstrom]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
