<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI-TT: Novel mobile platform technology to both prevent and respond to teen dating violence</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Partnerships for Innovation - Technology Translation (PFI-TT) PFI project is to develop a smartphone app/platform technology to prevent and respond to dating violence incidences, a significant public health problem affecting over 35% of high school students with long-term health, social and economic consequences. Despite the magnitude of this problem, 68% of high school principals reported lacking formal training on how to assist teen dating violence victims. The proposed technology offers an economically viable dating violence prevention strategy for high schools. The existing mobile apps are not designed for high school students to assist themselves (or a friend) who is a victim of teen dating violence and do not have a have a simple mechanism enabling high school administrators to coordinate and customize the prevention and response messaging their students are accessing. If successful, the proposed technology will fill a gap not addressed by currently available solutions, which are not designed to help the students enrolled in the 35,163 US high schools discretely extricate themselves from situations with the potential to become dangerous. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will consist of three elements that, combined, represent a highly innovative technology solution to a prevalent public health problem. First is the use of existing smartphone capabilities in new ways (e.g., enabling users to appear to receive urgent texts or phone calls, which are, in reality, simulated, to provide a socially sensitive reason for a student to leave a risky situation). Second is the application of extensive evidence-based research to both prevention and response technology features within the app. Third is a simple-to-use dashboard, through which high school administrators can easily customize data in the back-end database, to make it specific to their students and institution, and monitor its use among their students.&lt;br/&gt;The specific feature requirements needed for this interactive mobile platform will be informed by institutional review board (IRB)-reviewed interviews, focus groups and online surveys with students, parents/guardians and school administrators. The proposed hybrid smartphone app will run on Apple iOS and Android operating systems, using Google's Firebase SDK for analytics and accessing data from a back-end SQL database. The app platform will include a simple-to-use dashboard interface to the database, enabling schools to easily customize content to adapt to school and state policies and to monitor anonymous statistics about app use within their institution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1919063</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Potter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharyn Potter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sharyn.potter@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6038623630</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000180769</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Hampshire</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>038243585</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6038622172</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>51 COLLEGE RD SERVICE BLDG 107</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>111089470</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY SYSTEM OF NEW HAMPSHIRE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001765866</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Hampshire]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>038242057</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PIRC 9 Madbury Ave. 405]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PFI-Partnrships for Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the past 18 months, the multidisciplinary team consisting of a sociologist, psychologist, violence prevention practitioners, and technology developers collaborated with high school personnel (administrators, teachers, school counselors and resource officers), students, and parents and guardians to iteratively develop and pilot-test a safe student app and accompanying administrator platform minimum viable product (MVP). After facilitating surveys, interviews, and focus groups with high school personnel and high school students and analyzing the collected data, the project team made the decision to expand the scope of the prevention app from a teen dating violence focus as specified in the PFI-TT application. The data collected from high school personnel and students highlighted the need for tools to educate and prevent students from the five most common types of high school violence, including bullying (e.g., cyber and in-person), hazing, harassment (e.g., identity and sexual), teen dating violence and sexual assault.</p> <p>Previous research details the correlation among the victimization and perpetration of all forms of school violence and the resulting negative mental and physical health and academic outcomes. Other research indicates that perpetrators of school shootings have a history of other forms of school violence. Currently, there is a dearth of high school-specific education, resources, prevention, and response tools focusing on multiple types of school violence. However, the current tools are static, delivered in classrooms, and not well-utilized by students; and there is not a comprehensive system that integrates all of these components. During early stages of data collection, school administrators also identified the need for education, resources, and prevention tools that are easily accessible to both students and staff, and available in one place. Thus, the project team developed and evaluated a minimal viable product (MVP), to deliver education, prevention applications and reporting options for multiple forms of school violence and specific for high school students. These features are in a mobile app and accompanying administrator dashboard available to high school students, administrators, teachers, and community members 24/7.</p> <p>The MVP app has four key features that engage high school students including (1) short, gamified learning modules written in a conversational tone that are research-informed and based on a widely used social-emotional learning framework. (2) A confidential reporting tip line for students to report incidents of school violence that is monitored by school administrators in real time. (3) A prevention feature that empowers users to remove themselves from an uncomfortable situation by sending themselves a fake text or call. (4) Fully customizable school, community, and national resources that are easily accessible to students who may be experiencing harm or who want to learn more about wellness. The MVP online administrator dashboard provides school administrators with a platform to organize, customize, and implement the MVP safe student app in their schools.</p> <p>The MVP dashboard allows school administrators to: (1) Send push notifications to students, providing an additional and instant channel of communication between schools and students. (2) View submitted incident reports of school violence. (3) View anonymous analytics about student app usage. (4) Upload and customize school, community, and national resources. (5) Access implementation resources and promotional materials to support student engagement.</p> <p>The MVP was piloted at seven high schools in a Northeastern state during the Fall 2020 semester, as schools were transitioning between remote, in-person, and hybrid learning. The project team worked with the administrators, teachers, and students in the participating schools to implement the MVP. The project team was able to collect both survey and focus group data on app usage. During the pilot period, 537 students downloaded and used the MVP. Students in the pilot study completed 1,762 education modules and submitted eight incident reports, which were resolved by school administrators. The data collected yielded recommendations for the development and dissemination of a second version of the safe student app and administrator dashboard that the team hopes will be commercially available. In addition to presenting at a conference for school administrators and for the state?s association of school principals, the project team has written one research paper that is currently under review at a peer-reviewed journal and is finishing two additional papers that will be submitted in the next 60 days. A fourth paper on the development of a new healthy relationship scale is also in preparation but requires additional data collection before submission to a peer-reviewed journal.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/21/2021<br>      Modified by: Sharyn&nbsp;Potter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the past 18 months, the multidisciplinary team consisting of a sociologist, psychologist, violence prevention practitioners, and technology developers collaborated with high school personnel (administrators, teachers, school counselors and resource officers), students, and parents and guardians to iteratively develop and pilot-test a safe student app and accompanying administrator platform minimum viable product (MVP). After facilitating surveys, interviews, and focus groups with high school personnel and high school students and analyzing the collected data, the project team made the decision to expand the scope of the prevention app from a teen dating violence focus as specified in the PFI-TT application. The data collected from high school personnel and students highlighted the need for tools to educate and prevent students from the five most common types of high school violence, including bullying (e.g., cyber and in-person), hazing, harassment (e.g., identity and sexual), teen dating violence and sexual assault.  Previous research details the correlation among the victimization and perpetration of all forms of school violence and the resulting negative mental and physical health and academic outcomes. Other research indicates that perpetrators of school shootings have a history of other forms of school violence. Currently, there is a dearth of high school-specific education, resources, prevention, and response tools focusing on multiple types of school violence. However, the current tools are static, delivered in classrooms, and not well-utilized by students; and there is not a comprehensive system that integrates all of these components. During early stages of data collection, school administrators also identified the need for education, resources, and prevention tools that are easily accessible to both students and staff, and available in one place. Thus, the project team developed and evaluated a minimal viable product (MVP), to deliver education, prevention applications and reporting options for multiple forms of school violence and specific for high school students. These features are in a mobile app and accompanying administrator dashboard available to high school students, administrators, teachers, and community members 24/7.  The MVP app has four key features that engage high school students including (1) short, gamified learning modules written in a conversational tone that are research-informed and based on a widely used social-emotional learning framework. (2) A confidential reporting tip line for students to report incidents of school violence that is monitored by school administrators in real time. (3) A prevention feature that empowers users to remove themselves from an uncomfortable situation by sending themselves a fake text or call. (4) Fully customizable school, community, and national resources that are easily accessible to students who may be experiencing harm or who want to learn more about wellness. The MVP online administrator dashboard provides school administrators with a platform to organize, customize, and implement the MVP safe student app in their schools.  The MVP dashboard allows school administrators to: (1) Send push notifications to students, providing an additional and instant channel of communication between schools and students. (2) View submitted incident reports of school violence. (3) View anonymous analytics about student app usage. (4) Upload and customize school, community, and national resources. (5) Access implementation resources and promotional materials to support student engagement.  The MVP was piloted at seven high schools in a Northeastern state during the Fall 2020 semester, as schools were transitioning between remote, in-person, and hybrid learning. The project team worked with the administrators, teachers, and students in the participating schools to implement the MVP. The project team was able to collect both survey and focus group data on app usage. During the pilot period, 537 students downloaded and used the MVP. Students in the pilot study completed 1,762 education modules and submitted eight incident reports, which were resolved by school administrators. The data collected yielded recommendations for the development and dissemination of a second version of the safe student app and administrator dashboard that the team hopes will be commercially available. In addition to presenting at a conference for school administrators and for the state?s association of school principals, the project team has written one research paper that is currently under review at a peer-reviewed journal and is finishing two additional papers that will be submitted in the next 60 days. A fourth paper on the development of a new healthy relationship scale is also in preparation but requires additional data collection before submission to a peer-reviewed journal.       Last Modified: 04/21/2021       Submitted by: Sharyn Potter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
