<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Tomographic Particle Image Velocimetry System</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>288441.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>288441</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Shahab Shojaei-Zadeh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sshojaei@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928045</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the Major Research Instrumentation award, Clarkson University will acquire a tomographic particle image velocimetry system.  Acquisition of the instrument will facilitate advancements in scientific research across a diverse range of topics, such as human voice production, modeling and prediction of sediment and debris transport in hydrology and the impact on biodiversity and ecology, and novel approaches for carbon sequestration.  Ensuring broad and equitable access to the system across the entire campus of Clarkson University will place Clarkson at the forefront of fluid dynamics research capabilities and encourage and promote novel cross-disciplinary research endeavors.  Availability of this instrument will afford educational opportunities at both the undergraduate and graduate levels through classroom instruction on the experimental technique, as well as hands-on laboratory training on the practical use of the system.  Clarkson University serves a significant number of students that are underrepresented in STEM fields and that come from lower socioeconomic backgrounds.  Exposure to, and utilization of, this state-of-the-art measurement system will inspire the next generation of scientists and engineers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary advantage of a tomographic particle image velocimetry system is the ability to simultaneously resolve both the velocity vector and the velocity gradient tensor over all three coordinate directions within a volume. This capability will significantly advance research efforts at Clarkson University in the following specific areas: (1) aero-acoustic sound source identification and fluid-structure interactions in voiced speech production to identify how pathological behaviors impact vocal function, (2) quantification of flow morphologies in rivers arising from ice and debris obstructions with application to mitigating damage arising from flooding events, (3) enhancing ecological function in urban streams through quantification of the physical, biological, and ecologically-relevant sediment transport processes, (4) control of dynamic stall on airfoils to enhance aircraft performance, (5) quantification of multiphase flows through geological fractures to optimize carbon sequestration, (6) drag minimization of juncture flows with application to increasing fuel efficiency in large vehicle transport, and (7) development of a novel technique for estimating pressure fields from experimental velocity fields. It is anticipated that implementing a strategy whereby a percentage of the instrument availability is dedicated to new users, at no cost, will catalyze additional new and exciting cross-disciplinary research efforts across campus.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1919825</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abul</FirstName>
<LastName>Baki</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abul B Baki</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>abaki@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3152684156</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000796697</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
<LastName>Knack</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ian M Knack</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>iknack@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3152684446</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000682309</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Byron</FirstName>
<LastName>Erath</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Byron D Erath</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>berath@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3152686584</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000641483</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Bohl</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas G Bohl</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dbohl@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3152686683</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000114987</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clarkson University</Name>
<CityName>Potsdam</CityName>
<ZipCode>136761401</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3152686475</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8 Clarkson Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041590993</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLARKSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041590993</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clarkson University]]></Name>
<CityName>Potsdam</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>136761401</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[8 Clarkson Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~288441</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
