<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Cryogen-free Cooling System to Enable Multi-Modal Materials Research and Research Training</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>154350.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>154350</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leonard Spinu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lspinu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922665</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The ability to conduct regular, reliable measurements of material properties is a cornerstone of modern materials physics research and training.  The physical property measurement system (PPMS) at CUNY-Brooklyn College currently provides essential measurement of electrical, magnetic and thermodynamic material properties over a wide range of temperature and in magnetic fields of up to 9 Tesla.  The acquisition of a cryogen-free dewar for the PPMS will greatly improve CUNY-Brooklyn College researchers' ability to collaborate and respond to research needs in a timely fashion by eliminating the need to purchase expensive liquid helium to cool the magnet and sample measurement chamber.  Cryogen-free operation of the PPMS will maximize research output, allowing innovation in 3 key areas of energy-related science: pressaure-driven cooling and magnetic cooling, and aluminum ion battery technology.  Cryogen-free operation will also give high school, undergraduate and graduate students, many of whom are from under-represented groups, research training opportunities.  The lifespan of the upgraded instrument will be more than 10 years, while the costs of future operation and maintenance have been carefully assessed and will be reduced significantly. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The acquisition of a cryogen-free dewar for the physical property measurement system (PPMS) at CUNY-Brooklyn College will enable transformative research in 3 areas of energy-related science: (1) investigate the (pressure,temperature) phase diagram of metal-organic molecules and polymeric structures that have spin crossover transitions near room temperature; the aim is to understand the role of different ligands and side-chains in the response of spin crossover compounds to hydrostatic pressure, building on our recent work that has recently demonstrated the first giant barocaloric effect in this class of compounds; (2) adiabatic temperature change measurements using a sensor recently constructed and tested by undergraduates at Brooklyn College; the results will be correlated with total scattering of hard x-rays at synchrotron sources. (3) ionic conductivity and viscosity experiments on electrolytes for next- generation aluminum ion batteries, thereby investigating fundamental characteristics of ion transport that enable better, safer performance than current lithium-based technology.  The research will have societal and technological impact as it is motivated by the need to reduce the environmental footprint of cooling and by seeking improvements in battery technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1920177</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sophia</FirstName>
<LastName>Suarez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sophia Suarez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>SNSuarez@brooklyn.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7189515622</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000587628</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
<LastName>Sandeman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karl Sandeman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>KarlSandeman@brooklyn.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7189515622</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000736432</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Brooklyn College</Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<ZipCode>112102889</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7189515622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research &amp; Sponsored P</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2900 Bedford Ave]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>620127691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Brooklyn College]]></Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112102889</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2900 Bedford Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1712</Code>
<Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~154350</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
