<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Multiscale Generalized Correlation: A Unified Distance-Based Correlation Measure for Dependency Discovery</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/11/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>142651.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>142651</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gabor Szekely</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gszekely@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Detecting relationships between two data sets has long been one of the most important questions in statistics and is fundamental to scientific discovery in the big-data era. By developing an open-source, robust, efficient, and scalable statistical methodology for testing dependence on modern data, this project aims to advance the understanding and utility of testing dependence, tackle a number of related statistical inference questions, and accelerate a broad range of data-intensive research. The project incorporates fundamental research in mathematics, statistics, and computer science to further develop a multiscale generalized correlation framework to enable discovery and decision-making via analysis of large and complex data. The tools under development will allow scientists to better explore and understand high-dimensional, nonlinear, and multi-modal data in a myriad of applications. The project aims to provide a unified framework for discovery of relationships between observations in an efficient and theoretically-sound manner. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Combining the notion of generalized correlation with the locality principle, multiscale generalized correlation (MGC) is a superior correlation measure that equals the optimal local correlation among all possible local scales. By building upon distance correlation and making use of nearest neighbors, the resulting MGC test statistic is a unique dependence measure that is consistent for testing against all dependencies with finite second moment, and it exhibits better performance than existing state-of-art methods under a wide variety of nonlinear and high-dimensional dependencies. By investigating the theoretical aspects of distance-based correlations, this project aims to further improve the finite-sample performance of MGC-style tests, extend its capability to testing dependence on network and kernel data, and broaden its utility to general inferential questions beyond dependence testing such as two-sample testing, outlier detection, and feature screening, as well as applications to brain activity, networks, and text analysis. Overall, this project intends to establish a unified methodology framework for statistical testing in high-dimensional, noisy, big data, through theoretical advancements, comprehensive simulations, and real data experiments.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/08/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1921310</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cencheng</FirstName>
<LastName>Shen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cencheng Shen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shenc@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3028311319</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000736944</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/08/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Delaware]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~9241</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~66774</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~66636</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Detecting relationships between two data sets has long been one of the most important questions in statistics and is fundamental to scientific discovery in the big-data era. In this project, we combined the notion of generalized correlation with the locality principle, and developed a new methodology called Multiscale Graph Correlation (MGC). We proved its theoretical soundness in testing independence, and demonstrated its better performance than existing state-of-art methods under a wide variety of nonlinear and high-dimensional dependencies. We extended the methodology to many statistical and machine learning tasks, including two-sample test, MANOVA, graph testing, kernel testing, dimension reduction, feature screening, and time-series. We also enhanced and improved the algorithm design, so the current methodology can tackle billions of observations and high-dimensional data efficiently and powerfully. We applied the methodology to discover new relationships and identify useful features in several applications, including personality scores, fMRI images of human and mouse, pancreatic cancers, etc. Overall, this project established a unified methodology framework for statistical testing in high-dimensional, noisy, big data, through theoretical advancements, comprehensive simulations, and real data experiments.The developed tools allow scientists to better explore and understand modern big data. A total of 12 manuscripts are completed during this period and all openly accessible on arXiv. The full algorithm package is available in R, Matlab, Python, and openly accessible on Github.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2020<br>      Modified by: Cencheng&nbsp;Shen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Detecting relationships between two data sets has long been one of the most important questions in statistics and is fundamental to scientific discovery in the big-data era. In this project, we combined the notion of generalized correlation with the locality principle, and developed a new methodology called Multiscale Graph Correlation (MGC). We proved its theoretical soundness in testing independence, and demonstrated its better performance than existing state-of-art methods under a wide variety of nonlinear and high-dimensional dependencies. We extended the methodology to many statistical and machine learning tasks, including two-sample test, MANOVA, graph testing, kernel testing, dimension reduction, feature screening, and time-series. We also enhanced and improved the algorithm design, so the current methodology can tackle billions of observations and high-dimensional data efficiently and powerfully. We applied the methodology to discover new relationships and identify useful features in several applications, including personality scores, fMRI images of human and mouse, pancreatic cancers, etc. Overall, this project established a unified methodology framework for statistical testing in high-dimensional, noisy, big data, through theoretical advancements, comprehensive simulations, and real data experiments.The developed tools allow scientists to better explore and understand modern big data. A total of 12 manuscripts are completed during this period and all openly accessible on arXiv. The full algorithm package is available in R, Matlab, Python, and openly accessible on Github.       Last Modified: 09/28/2020       Submitted by: Cencheng Shen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
