<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Graduate Students Travel Support for 2019 International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP) to be Held in  Taipei, Taiwan September 22-25, 2019.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anthony Kuh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this proposal is to request funds to provide support for travel expenses for between 20-25 graduate students of US universities to attend the 26th International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP) with its URL at http://2019.ieeeicip.org/.  The conference will be held in Taipei International Convention Center, Taipei, Taiwan, on September 22-25, 2019. The proposed budget is for participants' travel costs only. This travel grant will serve as a means to facilitate graduate students of U.S. universities to attend the conference, present their most recent research accomplishments, and to have the opportunities to network and to obtain research and career advices from leading international experts in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;Conferences are a fertile ground to foster research collaborations. They provide fruitful opportunities for the participants to interact, exchange ideas, and to share experiences and best practices. Thus, conferences are inherently conducive for advancing knowledge and understanding in their respective technical fields, as well as for cross-fertilization in different fields.  It also represents opportunities for cross-fertilization in all areas. The review criteria for submitted papers specifically includes creativity, innovation, potential impacts on advancing the knowledge in the technical fields, as well as transformative potentials. The proposed travel support is an effective way to encourage graduate students from U.S. universities to participate in this international conference.  Participating in the conference will offer the students valuable experience in networking, exchanging research ideas, and broadening their views. It will improve our graduate students' competitiveness in the global market.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:&lt;br/&gt;The successful careers of graduate students are fundamental to advancing theory and applications in all fields of science and engineering. For the last 25 years, ICIP has been a force for good research in the broad areas of image/video processing. It has helped enhance research activities, foster international collaborations, and provided an educational and informative forum for researchers at all stages of their career.  Participating students will gain valuable experiences through direct interactions with their international peers, and with senior researchers at diverse research institutions from many other countries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1922549</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chung-Chieh Jay</FirstName>
<LastName>Kuo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chung-Chieh Jay Kuo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cckuo@sipi.usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137404658</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000106334</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900892564</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3740 McClintock Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~25000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this project was to provide support for travel expenses of up to twenty-five (25) graduate students of US universities to attend the 26th International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP) with its URL at http://2019.ieeeicip.org/.&nbsp;&nbsp;The conference was held in Taipei International Convention Center, Taipei, Taiwan, on September 22-25, 2019.&nbsp;</p> <p>ICIP is the world's largest and most comprehensive technical conference focused on image and video processing and computer vision. ICIP features world-class speakers, tutorials, and industry sessions, and creates an excellent forum to foster innovation and entrepreneurship, and network with the brightest minds in academia and industry that are working in this field. ICIP is the opportunity for industry executives with diverse experience and activity and researchers in distinct yet complementary areas, to discuss the development of emerging and next-generation in terms of technologies, applications, and services thanks to the workshops, panel discussions, and challenge sessions.</p> <p>ICIP attracts students, professors, as well as researchers and engineers from industry. This includes many graduate students nearing the end of their study seeking new opportunities. For companies interested in recruiting students for full-time employment or internships, ICIP facilitates the exchange of information by organizing a Student Career Luncheon, where students could hear about various companies and employment opportunities, and students have the chance to network with company representatives.</p> <p>This travel grant served as a means to facilitate graduate students of U.S. universities to attend the conference, present their most recent research accomplishments, and to have the opportunities to network and to obtain research and career advices from leading international experts in the field.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/19/2020<br>      Modified by: Chung-Chieh Ja&nbsp;Kuo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this project was to provide support for travel expenses of up to twenty-five (25) graduate students of US universities to attend the 26th International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP) with its URL at http://2019.ieeeicip.org/.  The conference was held in Taipei International Convention Center, Taipei, Taiwan, on September 22-25, 2019.   ICIP is the world's largest and most comprehensive technical conference focused on image and video processing and computer vision. ICIP features world-class speakers, tutorials, and industry sessions, and creates an excellent forum to foster innovation and entrepreneurship, and network with the brightest minds in academia and industry that are working in this field. ICIP is the opportunity for industry executives with diverse experience and activity and researchers in distinct yet complementary areas, to discuss the development of emerging and next-generation in terms of technologies, applications, and services thanks to the workshops, panel discussions, and challenge sessions.  ICIP attracts students, professors, as well as researchers and engineers from industry. This includes many graduate students nearing the end of their study seeking new opportunities. For companies interested in recruiting students for full-time employment or internships, ICIP facilitates the exchange of information by organizing a Student Career Luncheon, where students could hear about various companies and employment opportunities, and students have the chance to network with company representatives.  This travel grant served as a means to facilitate graduate students of U.S. universities to attend the conference, present their most recent research accomplishments, and to have the opportunities to network and to obtain research and career advices from leading international experts in the field.        Last Modified: 03/19/2020       Submitted by: Chung-Chieh Ja Kuo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
