<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Developing a Strategic Vision for the University of Wisconsin-Waukesha Field Station</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter McCartney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmccartn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928470</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of Wisconsin-Waukesha (UWW) requests funding to undertake a visioning and planning process that will result in the development of a new 10- year strategic plan for the UWW Field Station (UWWFS). For the past 50 years the UWWFS has been serving the UWW and larger communities without a comprehensive plan for research, education, data storage, funding, and maintenance. In 2014 the first new director in 50 years was hired, and as of July 1, 2018 the UWW campus (previously a 2-yr undergraduate institution) will merge with UW-Milwaukee (UWM), a major research institution (4-yr undergraduate and graduate). These transitions will come with major administrative changes, but also present exciting opportunities to direct the vision of the UWWFS to increase educational, research, and outreach opportunities to the community. The potential impacts of a comprehensive strategic plan for the UWWFS include expanding formal educational opportunities in science, technology, engineering, art, and mathematics (STEAM) disciplines for a diverse and often under-represented population of K-12 and college students in SE Wisconsin, as well as providing field research and professional development opportunities for their faculty and staff in STEAM and related disciplines.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research at the UWWFS will help in understanding about natural resources as they can be applied to a variety of fields such as climatology, evolutionary biology, restoration ecology, and effective control methods for invasive species. Also, the unique wood-fired Anagama kiln, art classroom, and natural beauty of the station offer myriad opportunities for artists and other users from the humanities disciplines to use the station. The UWWFS resources can provide an ideal outdoor classroom for more informal community STEAM education programming so valuable for citizens in the 21st century. This facility should also serve as a model of sound environmental stewardship in the Kettle Moraine area of SE Wisconsin. Merging with UWM also presents new opportunities such as increased use by researchers from UWM and collaborative projects with the UWM Field Station. This is an opportune time to engage in a strategic planning effort to ensure a sustainable and impactful future for the UWWFS whereby activities at the station will contribute to scientific knowledge and provide environmental education to members of the community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/06/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1923438</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Schueller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Teresa Schueller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>teresa.schueller@uwc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082633191</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000766072</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee</Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<ZipCode>532010340</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4142294853</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P O BOX 340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627906399</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee]]></Name>
<CityName>milwaukee</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>532010340</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[po box 340]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1104</Code>
<Text>FIELD STATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~24997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee at Waukesha Field Station (UWMWFS) has completed a two-year strategic planning and visioning process culminating in the production of a comprehensive ten-year strategic plan that complements and strengthens the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee (UWM) at Waukesha?s mission and vision. The plan includes five strategic initiatives that will positively impact the science, collaborative education, outreach, management, and ecological and financial sustainability of the station.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The initiatives outline a plan that will expand the scientific impact of the station by providing field research and professional development opportunities for UWM and external scientists, and updating station infrastructure to sustain research projects. These research activities will increase the understanding of natural resources in a variety of fields such as climatology, evolutionary biology, restoration ecology, and effective control methods for invasive species.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The plan also includes initiatives to increase educational multi-disciplinary and outreach opportunities in SE Wisconsin for K-12 and college students, as well as the general public, many from audiences that historically have not had access to field station experiences.&nbsp;The plan?s initiatives highlight the UWMWFS?s multi-disciplinary culture, calling for upgrading art facilities and offering opportunities for artists and multi-disciplinary scholars to use the station. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Strategic initiative one??Build a Technical Infrastructure that Sustains the Field Station??emphasizes revitalizing and transforming existing field station spaces, adding new ones, and upgrading station technology to serve as a basis for increasing the multi-disciplinary impact of the station. Action items include adding research laboratory space, housing, and outdoor gathering spaces, as well as upgrading art facilities.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Strategic initiative two??Strengthen Inter-Institutional Higher Education Relationships??outlines a plan to strengthen the relationships and improve communication between the field station and UWM?s administration, facilities management, and foundation. Action items outlined in this initiative include creating an advisory board for the station, and increasing interactions and cooperative activities with other field stations and local non-profit environmental entities.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Strategic initiative three??Maximize the Scientific, Artistic, and Multi-Disciplinary Impact of the Field Station??serves to increase the intellectual impact of the station, describing processes for storing data, archiving artifacts, recording an oral history of the station, and recruiting scientific researchers and multi-disciplinary scholars to pursue research and other activities at the station.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Strategic initiative four?"Improve Teaching and Learning Environment"?serves to increase the educational impact of the station and includes plans for developing a STEAM and multi-disciplinary educational program with faculty recruited to develop and teach courses at the field station, thereby expanding both credit and non-credit continuing education opportunities at the station, and developing a multi-disciplinary curriculum for K-12 students.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Strategic initiative five?"Develop a Strong Community Outreach Program"?provides multi-disciplinary experiences for audiences that historically have not participated in these STEAM-based activities.&nbsp;We plan to expand outreach to the community, build relationships with other area environmental groups and institutions, and create more opportunities for the public, such as events, citizen science activities, classes, and workshops, at the field station.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The plan is the product of a two-year strategic planning process, lead by a five-member planning team comprising of PI Teresa Schueller, and co-PI?s Quintin Bendixen, Ada Duffy, Suzanne Joneson, and William Schneider.&nbsp; The committee engaged with science/education/art instructors and advisors (university and K-12), field station/nature center directors and other experts, land management experts, program managers, foundation personnel, friends of the field station, and other local stakeholders through a series of four intensive strategic planning meetings. The first three planning meetings were day-long, held at the field station, and each focused on one of three key areas: education/art, science/research, and management/infrastructure. These experts helped identify key strengths and ten-year goals for the station within those areas. The fourth meeting was held virtually, and served to solicit feedback from key experts on a draft of the strategic plan.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In addition to the stakeholder meetings, members of the planning committee identified and visited six model field stations?UWM Field Station in Saukville, WI; Carroll University Greene Field Station/Prairie Springs Environmental Education Center in Waukesha, WI; Waupaca Field Station in Waupaca, WI; Michigan State University?s Kellogg Biological Station in Hickory Corners, MI; Pierce Cedar Creek Institute for Environmental Education in Hastings, MI; and UW-Madison?s Kemp Natural Resources Station, in Woodruff, WI. At each of these stations, planning committee members sought advice for best management and operation practices from local experts, toured facilities, learned about field station management procedures, and made important connections with personnel.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/25/2020<br>      Modified by: Teresa&nbsp;Schueller</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[             The University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee at Waukesha Field Station (UWMWFS) has completed a two-year strategic planning and visioning process culminating in the production of a comprehensive ten-year strategic plan that complements and strengthens the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee (UWM) at Waukesha?s mission and vision. The plan includes five strategic initiatives that will positively impact the science, collaborative education, outreach, management, and ecological and financial sustainability of the station.              The initiatives outline a plan that will expand the scientific impact of the station by providing field research and professional development opportunities for UWM and external scientists, and updating station infrastructure to sustain research projects. These research activities will increase the understanding of natural resources in a variety of fields such as climatology, evolutionary biology, restoration ecology, and effective control methods for invasive species.              The plan also includes initiatives to increase educational multi-disciplinary and outreach opportunities in SE Wisconsin for K-12 and college students, as well as the general public, many from audiences that historically have not had access to field station experiences. The plan?s initiatives highlight the UWMWFS?s multi-disciplinary culture, calling for upgrading art facilities and offering opportunities for artists and multi-disciplinary scholars to use the station.                Strategic initiative one??Build a Technical Infrastructure that Sustains the Field Station??emphasizes revitalizing and transforming existing field station spaces, adding new ones, and upgrading station technology to serve as a basis for increasing the multi-disciplinary impact of the station. Action items include adding research laboratory space, housing, and outdoor gathering spaces, as well as upgrading art facilities.              Strategic initiative two??Strengthen Inter-Institutional Higher Education Relationships??outlines a plan to strengthen the relationships and improve communication between the field station and UWM?s administration, facilities management, and foundation. Action items outlined in this initiative include creating an advisory board for the station, and increasing interactions and cooperative activities with other field stations and local non-profit environmental entities.               Strategic initiative three??Maximize the Scientific, Artistic, and Multi-Disciplinary Impact of the Field Station??serves to increase the intellectual impact of the station, describing processes for storing data, archiving artifacts, recording an oral history of the station, and recruiting scientific researchers and multi-disciplinary scholars to pursue research and other activities at the station.               Strategic initiative four?"Improve Teaching and Learning Environment"?serves to increase the educational impact of the station and includes plans for developing a STEAM and multi-disciplinary educational program with faculty recruited to develop and teach courses at the field station, thereby expanding both credit and non-credit continuing education opportunities at the station, and developing a multi-disciplinary curriculum for K-12 students.               Strategic initiative five?"Develop a Strong Community Outreach Program"?provides multi-disciplinary experiences for audiences that historically have not participated in these STEAM-based activities. We plan to expand outreach to the community, build relationships with other area environmental groups and institutions, and create more opportunities for the public, such as events, citizen science activities, classes, and workshops, at the field station.               The plan is the product of a two-year strategic planning process, lead by a five-member planning team comprising of PI Teresa Schueller, and co-PI?s Quintin Bendixen, Ada Duffy, Suzanne Joneson, and William Schneider.  The committee engaged with science/education/art instructors and advisors (university and K-12), field station/nature center directors and other experts, land management experts, program managers, foundation personnel, friends of the field station, and other local stakeholders through a series of four intensive strategic planning meetings. The first three planning meetings were day-long, held at the field station, and each focused on one of three key areas: education/art, science/research, and management/infrastructure. These experts helped identify key strengths and ten-year goals for the station within those areas. The fourth meeting was held virtually, and served to solicit feedback from key experts on a draft of the strategic plan.               In addition to the stakeholder meetings, members of the planning committee identified and visited six model field stations?UWM Field Station in Saukville, WI; Carroll University Greene Field Station/Prairie Springs Environmental Education Center in Waukesha, WI; Waupaca Field Station in Waupaca, WI; Michigan State University?s Kellogg Biological Station in Hickory Corners, MI; Pierce Cedar Creek Institute for Environmental Education in Hastings, MI; and UW-Madison?s Kemp Natural Resources Station, in Woodruff, WI. At each of these stations, planning committee members sought advice for best management and operation practices from local experts, toured facilities, learned about field station management procedures, and made important connections with personnel.       Last Modified: 10/25/2020       Submitted by: Teresa Schueller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
