<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Scripps Institution of Oceanography - Oceanographic Instrumentation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>639395.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>639395</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Holik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jholik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927711</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A request is made to fund Oceanographic Instrumentation for the R/V Roger Revelle, a 273? general purpose Global vessel. The vessel is operated by Scripps Institution of Oceanography as part of the University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System (UNOLS) research fleet.  R/V Roger Revelle is a Global vessel owned by the Navy. She supports multidisciplinary oceanographic research in all the world?s ocean basins. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In 2018, REVELLE completed 262 days, 181 (69%) of which were for NSF. In 2019, Revelle is currently scheduled with 86 days, 72 (84%) of which are for NSF. The reason there are so few days is that Revelle plans to spend most of the year in drydock undergoing a mid-life refit. Much of the instrumentation proposed her would be installed during this period. The prioritized Instrumentation request includes the following:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Portable Multi Channel Seismic System Components  $679,560&lt;br/&gt;1-meter MOCNESS Nets, shared-use infrastructure  $20,972&lt;br/&gt;Virtual Desktop Infrastructure (VDI) R/V Roger Revelle  $214,920&lt;br/&gt;Network Cabling Refurbishment R/V Roger Revelle  $284,014&lt;br/&gt;Laboratory Infrastructure Refurbishment R/V Roger Revelle  $87,136&lt;br/&gt;Acoustic Doppler Current Profiler Array Replacement  $53,158&lt;br/&gt;Mooring Release/Acoustic Modem     $59,488&lt;br/&gt;       $1,399,248&lt;br/&gt;       &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The principal impact of the present proposal is under Merit Review Criterion 2 of the Proposal Guidelines (NSF 13-589). It provides infrastructure support for scientists to use the vessel and its shared-use instrumentation in support of their NSF-funded oceanographic research projects (which individually undergo separate review by the relevant research program of NSF).  The acquisition, maintenance and operation of shared-use instrumentation allows NSF-funded researchers from any US university or lab access to working, calibrated instruments for their research, reducing the cost of that research, and expanding the base of potential researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1923059</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Appelgate</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce Appelgate</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bappelgate@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585342220</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000463246</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lee</FirstName>
<LastName>Ellett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lee Ellett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lellett@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585342434</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000743967</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Univ of California-San Diego]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>175104595</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UC San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5413</Code>
<Text>OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~639395</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Shipboard Technical Support (STS) department at Scripps Institution of Oceanography has operated marine seismic reflection equipment for half a century. Since 2005, the department has operated a portable high resolution multichannel seismic (MCS) system.&nbsp; In 2018 we proposed complete replacement of the aging 48 channel streamer wet-end components and were funded through the Oceanographic Instrumentation program to purchase components that were critical for accomplishing scientific objectives of seagoing projects that were funded in 2018.&nbsp; The existing primary system components are a 48-channel, 12.5m group spacing Geometrics GeoEel liquid digital streamer (purchased in 2005), a 48-channel 6.25m group spacing Geometrics solid digital streamer (2018), four 5010 Ion depth controllers, one 5011 compass depth controller, three Sercel generator injector (GI) sound sources, and the necessary control components. One outcome of this project was to complete the replacement of the digital streamer, replace the streamer depth controllers, and add an additional GI Sound Source to the current inventory.&nbsp; The completed integration of this equipment consisting of streamer components and sound source components replaces aging instrumentation and enhances the capabilities of this portable MCS system to meet the operational needs of funded science programs in 2019 and beyond. We anticipate the service life of this instrumentation to be ten to twelve years.</p> <p>STS has been very active in the support and development of Multiple Opening/Closing Net and Environmental Sensing (MOCNESS) systems used within the U.S. Academic Research Fleet (ARF).&nbsp; A 1m MOCNESS system is offered as shared-use instrumentation through Basic Oceanographic Technical Services on institutional vessels and a 10m MOCNESS is offered as a Specialized Service. For these net systems we maintain an inventory of electronics, including the Plankton Net Interface (PKI) developed by STS as well as stock electronics manufactured by Biological Environmental Sensing Systems.&nbsp; The PKI system was developed to control existing MOCNESS systems using a Seabird 9/11 plus underwater unit common in the ARF and has greatly simplified the level of specialized support required and reliability of these systems.</p> <p>STS has historically loaned our shared-use MOCNESS to institutions or researchers where qualified technicians were available to provide support.&nbsp; With the simplified PKI interface now available this exchange of equipment has become increasingly common.&nbsp; In 2017 the SIO 1m MOCNESS system was used on the R/V <em>Pt. Sur</em>, R/V <em>Sally Ride</em>, R/V <em>Roger Revelle</em>, and R/V <em>Sikuliaq</em> for a total of 85 days.&nbsp; In 2018 the system as used the R/V <em>Roger Revelle</em> and R/V <em>Pt. Sur</em> for a total of 54 days.&nbsp; In 2019 the system was used aboard R/V <em>Atlantis </em>for 43 days for an NSF-sponsored project for Dr. Mark Ohman.</p> <p>We evaluated the option to repair existing nets and concluded they were beyond repair; replacement was needed.&nbsp; The previous nets had been in use for over a decade.&nbsp;&nbsp; The twelve nets purchased through the project have allowed for continued operations for NSF-sponsored research programs requiring the SIO 1m MOCNESS system.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual merit: </strong>&nbsp;The engineering design and equipment supported under this grant significantly enhance the safety, utility and capability of the infrastructure for sea-going research.&nbsp; This project contributed to the advancing safety and utility of NSF-supported oceanographic research vessels by ensuring that shared-use instruments are designed, equipped and maintained at a high level of safety such that they are fit to handle the perils imposed by ocean expeditionary science missions.</p> <p>The intellectual merit of this project is amplified by the combined merit of research projects undertaken aboard NSF-supported ships.&nbsp; Continuous improvement of shared-use instruments used aboard vessels in the U.S. ARF is vital to the success of the U.S. oceanographic research enterprise, and enables a broad range of discovery in the physical and biological sciences.</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts:</strong>&nbsp; The spectrum of research projects enabled by these improvements to NSF-supported research vessels collectively achieves far-reaching broader impacts through the enhancement of infrastructure that is critical to the promotion of training and learning, increasing the participation of underrepresented groups in research, advancing scientific and technological understanding and informing policy making for the benefit of society.</p> <p>For example, research and research training are fundamental elements of the SIO mission that benefit significantly from the proposed improvements. In the five-year period ending in 2018, 1,029 graduate students, 747 undergraduate students, and 27 K-12 and college educators obtained first-hand experience at sea aboard SIO-operated research vessels.&nbsp; Practical experience aboard research vessels is a cornerstone of SIO&rsquo;s exemplary research training program, and this experience has contributed to the Institution&rsquo;s success in producing outstanding new research scientists.&nbsp; As shared-use resources for the U.S. oceanographic research community, SIO-operated vessels host scientists from throughout the country, and contribute similarly to the education and training missions of other institutions.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/06/2020<br>      Modified by: Bruce&nbsp;Appelgate</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Shipboard Technical Support (STS) department at Scripps Institution of Oceanography has operated marine seismic reflection equipment for half a century. Since 2005, the department has operated a portable high resolution multichannel seismic (MCS) system.  In 2018 we proposed complete replacement of the aging 48 channel streamer wet-end components and were funded through the Oceanographic Instrumentation program to purchase components that were critical for accomplishing scientific objectives of seagoing projects that were funded in 2018.  The existing primary system components are a 48-channel, 12.5m group spacing Geometrics GeoEel liquid digital streamer (purchased in 2005), a 48-channel 6.25m group spacing Geometrics solid digital streamer (2018), four 5010 Ion depth controllers, one 5011 compass depth controller, three Sercel generator injector (GI) sound sources, and the necessary control components. One outcome of this project was to complete the replacement of the digital streamer, replace the streamer depth controllers, and add an additional GI Sound Source to the current inventory.  The completed integration of this equipment consisting of streamer components and sound source components replaces aging instrumentation and enhances the capabilities of this portable MCS system to meet the operational needs of funded science programs in 2019 and beyond. We anticipate the service life of this instrumentation to be ten to twelve years.  STS has been very active in the support and development of Multiple Opening/Closing Net and Environmental Sensing (MOCNESS) systems used within the U.S. Academic Research Fleet (ARF).  A 1m MOCNESS system is offered as shared-use instrumentation through Basic Oceanographic Technical Services on institutional vessels and a 10m MOCNESS is offered as a Specialized Service. For these net systems we maintain an inventory of electronics, including the Plankton Net Interface (PKI) developed by STS as well as stock electronics manufactured by Biological Environmental Sensing Systems.  The PKI system was developed to control existing MOCNESS systems using a Seabird 9/11 plus underwater unit common in the ARF and has greatly simplified the level of specialized support required and reliability of these systems.  STS has historically loaned our shared-use MOCNESS to institutions or researchers where qualified technicians were available to provide support.  With the simplified PKI interface now available this exchange of equipment has become increasingly common.  In 2017 the SIO 1m MOCNESS system was used on the R/V Pt. Sur, R/V Sally Ride, R/V Roger Revelle, and R/V Sikuliaq for a total of 85 days.  In 2018 the system as used the R/V Roger Revelle and R/V Pt. Sur for a total of 54 days.  In 2019 the system was used aboard R/V Atlantis for 43 days for an NSF-sponsored project for Dr. Mark Ohman.  We evaluated the option to repair existing nets and concluded they were beyond repair; replacement was needed.  The previous nets had been in use for over a decade.   The twelve nets purchased through the project have allowed for continued operations for NSF-sponsored research programs requiring the SIO 1m MOCNESS system.  Intellectual merit:  The engineering design and equipment supported under this grant significantly enhance the safety, utility and capability of the infrastructure for sea-going research.  This project contributed to the advancing safety and utility of NSF-supported oceanographic research vessels by ensuring that shared-use instruments are designed, equipped and maintained at a high level of safety such that they are fit to handle the perils imposed by ocean expeditionary science missions.  The intellectual merit of this project is amplified by the combined merit of research projects undertaken aboard NSF-supported ships.  Continuous improvement of shared-use instruments used aboard vessels in the U.S. ARF is vital to the success of the U.S. oceanographic research enterprise, and enables a broad range of discovery in the physical and biological sciences.  Broader impacts:  The spectrum of research projects enabled by these improvements to NSF-supported research vessels collectively achieves far-reaching broader impacts through the enhancement of infrastructure that is critical to the promotion of training and learning, increasing the participation of underrepresented groups in research, advancing scientific and technological understanding and informing policy making for the benefit of society.  For example, research and research training are fundamental elements of the SIO mission that benefit significantly from the proposed improvements. In the five-year period ending in 2018, 1,029 graduate students, 747 undergraduate students, and 27 K-12 and college educators obtained first-hand experience at sea aboard SIO-operated research vessels.  Practical experience aboard research vessels is a cornerstone of SIO’s exemplary research training program, and this experience has contributed to the Institution’s success in producing outstanding new research scientists.  As shared-use resources for the U.S. oceanographic research community, SIO-operated vessels host scientists from throughout the country, and contribute similarly to the education and training missions of other institutions.       Last Modified: 11/06/2020       Submitted by: Bruce Appelgate]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
