<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Thinking Globally, Acting Locally: Increasing CS Capacity and Equity by Developing a Regional CS Teacher Community</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299830.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>344753</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allyson Kennedy</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Siena College proposes to leverage and expand an existing researcher-practitioner partnership (RPP) to create a new community-focused professional development (PD) model for preparing high quality computer science (CS) teachers capable of increasing the number and diversity of students in their schools' CS classrooms. Siena College's past work and strong ties to secondary CS and mathematics education in New York State's Tech Valley region are ideal for developing a regional CS teacher community and for addressing, in a significant manner, the problem of underrepresented groups in CS. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The work has five key components: &lt;br/&gt;(1) Community Based PD for In-Service Teachers: A new PD program will prepare in-service math/technology teachers to teach Siena's introductory college level dual-enrollment CS course or a high school level CS course. It will integrate teachers, counselors, administrators and college faculty into a sustainable CS professional learning community via the dual-enrollment program, annual CS outreach events for teachers and their students, and collaboration with the local Computer Science Teachers Association (CSTA) chapter.&lt;br/&gt;(2) Diversity Initiative: Drawing on expertise in the RPP, high school teachers will be assisted in developing and implementing plans for increasing the number and diversity of students in their CS classrooms, customizing their plans based on the unique conditions, opportunities and challenges at their high schools.&lt;br/&gt;(3) In-Service Teacher Second Certification in CS: Pathways will be created for in-service teachers to earn up to fourteen college CS credits over the two year grant period. These credits can count towards New York State's recently approved second certification in CS.&lt;br/&gt;(4) Pre-Service Teacher Initial Certification in CS: A new program for CS initial certification for undergraduates will be established, making it one of the first in New York State. As a tool for recruiting current undergraduates into the program, Siena students will have opportunities to serve as assistants for CS teachers in the RPP. &lt;br/&gt;(5) Community Building Programming: The Siena College CS Department will continue to support and expand its outreach activities which include programs for high school students and sponsorship of the Upstate New York CSTA chapter meetings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1923378</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
<LastName>Flatland</LastName>
<EmailAddress>flatland@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Egan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>maegan@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Matthews</LastName>
<EmailAddress>matthews@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pauline</FirstName>
<LastName>White</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pwhite@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jesse</FirstName>
<LastName>Moya</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jmoya@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Siena College</Name>
<CityName>LOUDONVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>122111462</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5187822322</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>515 LOUDON ROAD</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>005Y</Code>
<Text>STEM + Computing (STEM+C) Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>134Y</Code>
<Text>CSforAll-Computer Sci for All</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>023Z</Code>
<Text>Computer Science for All (CS for All)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
