<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Student Travel Grant for 2019 Workshop on the Economics of Information Security (WEIS)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skiesler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928643</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project supports students attending the 18th Workshop on the Economics of Information Security (WEIS). WEIS is an annual event that serves as a leading forum for interdisciplinary scholarship on information security, combining expertise from the fields of computer science and electrical engineering, economics, social science, business, law, and policy. Participation in WEIS is a critical part of the educational experiences of students with interdisciplinary interests related to security and privacy. WEIS provides them an opportunity to interact with senior researchers and be exposed to leading work in the field. The support requested in this proposal will enable the participation of students who otherwise would face financial challenges to attend WEIS due to travel costs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The student travel grant will support approximately 12 graduate and undergraduate students. Funds will be used to offset airfare, lodging and conference registration fees. The grant will support advanced stage graduate students with papers appearing on the program, students from underrepresented groups including women, undergraduates and underrepresented minorities, and students attending WEIS for the first time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/21/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1927653</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Ransbotham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>III</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel B Ransbotham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ransboth@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175520465</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000597512</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673808</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[140 Commonwealth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025Z</Code>
<Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This travel grant enabled students to attend the 2019 Workshop on the Economics of Information Security (WEIS), the leading forum for interdisciplinary scholarship on information security, combining expertise from the fields of computer science and electrical engineering, economics, social science, business, law, and policy. &nbsp;</span>Awardees furthered their education through exposure to cutting edge interdisciplinary research surrounding information security, interactions with senior researchers in the field, and had an opportunity to gather ideas for potential new research directions and thesis topics and disseminate their own research. <span>There were 15 applications, including 1 incomplete and 1 ineligible. We made awards to all 13 students. (One student did not attend.)&nbsp;</span><span>We used the selection criteria as laid out in the proposal. Ultimately we funded all eligible applicants and factored in distance to travel, whether on the job market / WEIS program, and so forth in determining the size of the award. The award committee consisted of Boston College faculty members without affiliation to the workshop, who did not submitted papers to the workshop, and who did not have students who were involved in the workshop.</span>The grant was kindly extended to cover the 2020 Workshop as well. &nbsp;However, the 2020 workshop met virtually (without registration fees) due to the pandemic and we funded no additional students for 2020.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/20/2021<br>      Modified by: Samuel&nbsp;B&nbsp;Ransbotham</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This travel grant enabled students to attend the 2019 Workshop on the Economics of Information Security (WEIS), the leading forum for interdisciplinary scholarship on information security, combining expertise from the fields of computer science and electrical engineering, economics, social science, business, law, and policy.  Awardees furthered their education through exposure to cutting edge interdisciplinary research surrounding information security, interactions with senior researchers in the field, and had an opportunity to gather ideas for potential new research directions and thesis topics and disseminate their own research. There were 15 applications, including 1 incomplete and 1 ineligible. We made awards to all 13 students. (One student did not attend.) We used the selection criteria as laid out in the proposal. Ultimately we funded all eligible applicants and factored in distance to travel, whether on the job market / WEIS program, and so forth in determining the size of the award. The award committee consisted of Boston College faculty members without affiliation to the workshop, who did not submitted papers to the workshop, and who did not have students who were involved in the workshop.The grant was kindly extended to cover the 2020 Workshop as well.  However, the 2020 workshop met virtually (without registration fees) due to the pandemic and we funded no additional students for 2020.       Last Modified: 04/20/2021       Submitted by: Samuel B Ransbotham]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
