<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Participation Grant for 2019 IEEE Midwest Symposium on Circuits and Systems (MWSCAS)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sabasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927843</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports student travel for attending the 62nd Midwest Symposium on Circuits and Systems (MWCAS) to be held in Dallas, TX in August 2019. The MWCAS is a premier international conference in the field of circuits and systems. Other than tutorials, keynote and plenary lectures by leading experts in the field, the conference will be attended by academic and industry researchers and students to present their recent work both in lecture sessions and poster sessions. The conference will host a student paper competition to encourage the best students to keep abreast of the most modern technologies. Recipients of this grant will selected from the pool of those students presenting papers and will be paid part of their expenses for travel and registration at the conference. US citizens and permanent residents will be given the highest priority in the selection process. The experience gained by the students in the process is going to be an invaluable component of their education. Due to a good number industrial participants in the meeting the experience will also help them to secure positions in industry, thus contributing to the much needed technological workforce of the United States. The selection committee will pay due attention to include women, minority and other underrepresented groups for providing support from this grant.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The technical areas covered by the conference will, in general, be electronic circuits and systems relevant, among other problems, to modern computing hardware technologies. More specifically, the broad spectrum of topics to be covered will include, but will not be limited to: Analog and Mixed Signal Integrated Circuits, Bio-Inspired systems and Green Technologies, Neural Networks &amp; Neuromorphic Engineering, Artificial Intelligence including Deep Learning and Robotics, Internet of Things (IoTs), Autonomous Systems, Radio Frequency Microwave and Optical Systems, Image/Video Processing and Multimedia Systems, Power Management Energy Harvesting and Wireless Power, Trusted Electronics and Security, MEMS and NEMS Technologies, Nano-electronics and Nanotechnology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1927285</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Randall</FirstName>
<LastName>Geiger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Randall L Geiger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rlgeiger@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152947745</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000405087</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<CountyName>STORY</CountyName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<CountyName>STORY</CountyName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500113060</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>104E</Code>
<Text>MEMS/NEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7945</Code>
<Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~15000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
