<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Dating Deformation with Titanite</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>289046.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>289046</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Audrey Huerta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ahuerta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927438</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Much of our understanding of the geologic history of the Earth comes from radiometric dating of Earth processes. Currently, Earth scientists have a difficult time placing narrow constraints on the precise time that a fault occurs deep within the crust of the Earth. This project combines two state-of-the-science techniques to directly date the time of faulting along a key fault zone in southeast Alaska, and thereby date when ancient earthquakes occurred. Development of this new analytical technique will enable considerable future research and understanding of how Earth materials deform. In addition, this research project will provide training and research opportunities for a female graduate student and several undergraduate students. Visits to local elementary schools will enable potential future scientists to experience the methods and results of Earth science research, with direct implications for earthquake hazards. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This collaborative project consists of two principal objectives: 1) develop the mineral titanite as a tool for dating high-temperature deformation by a combined microstructural and microgeochronology approach, and 2) apply this tool to the evolution of the spectacular Coast Shear Zone and Great Tonalite Sill in the Coast Mountains orogen of southeast Alaska. Research methods will incorporate a field study to understand qualitatively the evolution of a mid- to deep crustal intra-arc shear zone and synkinematic sheeted-sill complex exposed in the Coast shear zone of Alaska and Canada. Titanite analyses will include electron-backscatter diffraction maps of titanite microstructure, and laser-ablation split-stream inductively coupled plasma maps of titanite composition that incorporate U-Pb dates. These data will allow assessment of the physical and chemical processes that affected the crystal, and the identification of crystals whose U-Pb distribution reflects high-temperature deformation. Because titanite is a widespread crustal mineral, this technique should have broad application globally and enhance our understanding of how crust deforms and orogens assemble and change through time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1927060</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bradley</FirstName>
<LastName>Hacker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bradley R Hacker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hacker@geol.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058937952</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000460450</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931063060</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Earth Research Institute]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1572</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~289046</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
