<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference Proposal:Summer School  on Aspects of Geometric Group Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>35000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>35000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Krishnan Shankar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kshankar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924703</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A summer school "Aspects of Geometric Group Theory" will be held July 8-19, 2019, at Institut des Hautes Etudes Scientifiques in Bures-sur-Yvette, France. This summer school features a distinguished collection of geometers and geometric group theorists who have been chosen both for their mathematical excellence and their outstanding expository skills. The summer school will attract talented early career mathematicians from around the world. The support from this project shall expose US-based graduate students and postdoctoral assistant professors to a broad spectrum of topics in geometric group theory at an early stage of their career development and to foster intellectual relationships, both with the lecturers and with other graduate students, which will benefit the students throughout their careers. These relationships will have a long-term positive impact on the interactions between the mathematical communities in geometric group theory in the U.S. and Europe. The organizing committee and the principal investigators are committed to funding a diverse group of mathematicians.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Geometric group theory is devoted to exploring connections between algebraic properties of groups and topological and geometric properties of the spaces on which they act. Geometric group theory closely interacts with low dimensional topology, hyperbolic geometry, Lie groups and homogeneous spaces, algebraic topology, computational group theory, and differential geometry. There are also substantial connections with complexity theory, mathematical logic, dynamical systems, probability theory, K-theory, and other areas of mathematics. Geometric group theory is a very broad area, and this project shall focus on geometrical aspects of group actions, for example, actions on trees, curve complexes, cube complexes, and discrete groups arising in geometry, topology and dynamics. More information about the conference can be found at: https://indico.math.cnrs.fr/event/3784/overview&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1928652</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Canary</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard D Canary</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>canary@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347640335</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000336841</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pallavi</FirstName>
<LastName>Dani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pallavi Dani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pdani@math.lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2255781588</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513909</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University</Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075050765</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>940050792</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 Himes Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~35000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A summer school on Aspects of Geometric Group Theory was held from July 8 to July 19, 2019, at the Institut des Hautes Etudes Scientifiques in Bures-sur-Yvette, France.<br /><br />The summer school featured a distinguished collection of geometers and geometric group theorists who were chosen both for their mathematical excellence and their outstanding expository skills. Mini courses were given by Yves Benoist (CNRS and Universit&eacute; Paris-Sud), Kai-Uwe Bux (Universit&auml;t Bielefeld), Ruth Charney (Brandeis University), Fran&ccedil;ois Dahmani (Universit&eacute; Grenoble Alpes), Anna Erschler (CNRS and ENS), Fran&ccedil;ois Gu&eacute;ritaud (CNRS and Universit&eacute; de Lille), Kathryn Mann (Brown University), Yair Minsky (Yale University), Karen Vogtmann (University of Warwick), Genevieve Walsh (Tufts University), Anna Wienhard (Universit&auml;t Heidelberg), and Daniel T. Wise (McGill University). &nbsp;The summer school attracted over 100 talented early career mathematicians from around the world. The goal was to both expose graduate students and early career mathematicians to a broad spectrum of topics in geometry and geometric group theory at an early stage of their career development and to foster intellectual relationships, both with the lecturers and with other early career mathematicians, which will benefit &nbsp;the students throughout their careers. It is expected &nbsp;that these relationships will have a long-term positive impact on the interactions between the mathematical communities in these fields in the U.S. and Europe.<br /><br />Funding from the National Science Foundation allowed 24 U.S.-based graduate students to participate in the summer school. Funding for the speakers and for other participants was provided by eight European funding agencies.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/15/2020<br>      Modified by: Pallavi&nbsp;Dani</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A summer school on Aspects of Geometric Group Theory was held from July 8 to July 19, 2019, at the Institut des Hautes Etudes Scientifiques in Bures-sur-Yvette, France.  The summer school featured a distinguished collection of geometers and geometric group theorists who were chosen both for their mathematical excellence and their outstanding expository skills. Mini courses were given by Yves Benoist (CNRS and Universit&eacute; Paris-Sud), Kai-Uwe Bux (Universit&auml;t Bielefeld), Ruth Charney (Brandeis University), Fran&ccedil;ois Dahmani (Universit&eacute; Grenoble Alpes), Anna Erschler (CNRS and ENS), Fran&ccedil;ois Gu&eacute;ritaud (CNRS and Universit&eacute; de Lille), Kathryn Mann (Brown University), Yair Minsky (Yale University), Karen Vogtmann (University of Warwick), Genevieve Walsh (Tufts University), Anna Wienhard (Universit&auml;t Heidelberg), and Daniel T. Wise (McGill University).  The summer school attracted over 100 talented early career mathematicians from around the world. The goal was to both expose graduate students and early career mathematicians to a broad spectrum of topics in geometry and geometric group theory at an early stage of their career development and to foster intellectual relationships, both with the lecturers and with other early career mathematicians, which will benefit  the students throughout their careers. It is expected  that these relationships will have a long-term positive impact on the interactions between the mathematical communities in these fields in the U.S. and Europe.  Funding from the National Science Foundation allowed 24 U.S.-based graduate students to participate in the summer school. Funding for the speakers and for other participants was provided by eight European funding agencies.       Last Modified: 12/15/2020       Submitted by: Pallavi Dani]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
