<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corp: Surface Engineered Iron Particles for Enhanced Degradation of Chlorinated Contaminants in Groundwater</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this project is to understand the market driving force for a process-based technology to increase the efficacy of remediating chlorinated solvent-contaminated underground environment. Degradation of chlorinated solvents using earth-abundant minerals or metallic reagent is a topic of immense interest due to the prevalent presence of these solvent contaminants at hazardous waste sites and their recalcitrance to natural degradation. More effective and cost-efficient technologies to clean up these sites can generate societal benefits including decreasing the costs of remediation, accelerating the process of restoring land for re-development, and protecting human health and ecological well-being. This project will allow the project team to discover customer segments, identify key attributes of commercially successful remediation methods, and translate research outcomes to products that have commercial competitiveness and are amenable to large-scale implementation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project further develops fundamental understanding of reductive decomposition of chlorinated ethenes on reactive engineered surfaces. While the main research project seeks to explore the potential of adapting the surface properties of engineered materials to create highly reactive and selective surfaces for groundwater decontamination, this project aims to translate the research findings into prototype products or process-based technologies that have relevance to the practical needs of the remediation market and are commercially competitive against the existing remediation methods. This exploratory effort is aligned with the overall goal of advancing science to address the formidable challenges posed by groundwater contamination.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/25/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/25/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1929360</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weile</FirstName>
<LastName>Yan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Weile Yan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>weile_yan@uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9789342256</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000616305</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/25/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas Tech University</Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8067423884</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>349 Administration Bldg</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041367053</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS TECH UNIVERSITY SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041367053</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas Tech University]]></Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[349 Administration Bldg]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Through this I-Corp project, our team conducted interviews with various customer segments (including environment consultants, remediation service contractors, reagent manufacturers, state, regional, or federal statutory, an environmental attorney, and land developers). We conducted these interviews in 12 major cities across 10 states (AZ, CA, WA, TX, IL, MI, PA, NJ, NY and MA). The team also completed I-CORPS trainings that included the opening and closing workshops in Phoenix, AZ, and weekly webinar sessions. Findings from these interviews were logged and business model canvas was revised iteratively based on interview discoveries.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Our customer interviews revealed the prevalent challenges of restoring chlorinated solvent-impacted sites. Crucially, the team learned through these interviews that the nature of the pollution issue varies across regions due to differences in climatological and hydrogeological conditions and different approaches adopted by state governments to oversee the remediation industry. This suggests a significant degree of market segmentation and implies deep involvement of regulatory incentives in the business model. Additionally, the team collected feedbacks on the technical capabilities/limitations of existing remediation technologies. These feedback led to these insights: site complexity implies a collection of complementary techniques are necessary instead of a single solution; a competitive in situ remediation solution should embody optimized reagent as well reagent deployment (injection) methods; degree of knowledge about site characteristics has a dominant impact on the remediation outcomes; for the reasons above, remediation efficiency, particularly efficiency measured in the lab, is not perceived as a strong criterion to adopt unproven technologies. &nbsp;</p> <p>Based upon the results summarized above, the team reached the conclusion that there is not a strong and broad enough product-market fit to suggest a viable start-up opportunity for the proposed business thesis. Nonetheless, the interviews allow the team to map out the current ecosystem of the remediation industry, its market segments, and the interplay between regulations and practice.</p> <p>This project engaged two graduate students in the ENVE program, a master and a PhD student, to formulate business thesis, conduct interviews, and revise/re-iterate the business thesis. The students gained a deep level of industry insights that are entirely orthogonal or complementary to their academic trainings. The experience therefore provides a rare and vital opportunity to glimpse into the gaps between academic research and industrial applications and potential mechanisms to narrow such gaps to make research more impactful from an application point of view.&nbsp; Students and PI are more prepared for a possible future endeavor in STEM entrepreneurship. These insights will be summarized in a future article in a publication that orientates towards remediation professionals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/16/2020<br>      Modified by: Weile&nbsp;Yan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Through this I-Corp project, our team conducted interviews with various customer segments (including environment consultants, remediation service contractors, reagent manufacturers, state, regional, or federal statutory, an environmental attorney, and land developers). We conducted these interviews in 12 major cities across 10 states (AZ, CA, WA, TX, IL, MI, PA, NJ, NY and MA). The team also completed I-CORPS trainings that included the opening and closing workshops in Phoenix, AZ, and weekly webinar sessions. Findings from these interviews were logged and business model canvas was revised iteratively based on interview discoveries.    Our customer interviews revealed the prevalent challenges of restoring chlorinated solvent-impacted sites. Crucially, the team learned through these interviews that the nature of the pollution issue varies across regions due to differences in climatological and hydrogeological conditions and different approaches adopted by state governments to oversee the remediation industry. This suggests a significant degree of market segmentation and implies deep involvement of regulatory incentives in the business model. Additionally, the team collected feedbacks on the technical capabilities/limitations of existing remediation technologies. These feedback led to these insights: site complexity implies a collection of complementary techniques are necessary instead of a single solution; a competitive in situ remediation solution should embody optimized reagent as well reagent deployment (injection) methods; degree of knowledge about site characteristics has a dominant impact on the remediation outcomes; for the reasons above, remediation efficiency, particularly efficiency measured in the lab, is not perceived as a strong criterion to adopt unproven technologies.    Based upon the results summarized above, the team reached the conclusion that there is not a strong and broad enough product-market fit to suggest a viable start-up opportunity for the proposed business thesis. Nonetheless, the interviews allow the team to map out the current ecosystem of the remediation industry, its market segments, and the interplay between regulations and practice.  This project engaged two graduate students in the ENVE program, a master and a PhD student, to formulate business thesis, conduct interviews, and revise/re-iterate the business thesis. The students gained a deep level of industry insights that are entirely orthogonal or complementary to their academic trainings. The experience therefore provides a rare and vital opportunity to glimpse into the gaps between academic research and industrial applications and potential mechanisms to narrow such gaps to make research more impactful from an application point of view.  Students and PI are more prepared for a possible future endeavor in STEM entrepreneurship. These insights will be summarized in a future article in a publication that orientates towards remediation professionals.          Last Modified: 01/16/2020       Submitted by: Weile Yan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
