<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Concepts for Advancing Sustainable Urban Systems (SUS) Research Networks: Sustainable Integration of Urban Automation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandip Roy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>saroy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927096</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to convene faculty, students, and participants from industry, municipalities, and the non-profit sector to discuss groundbreaking topics for research on applications of the integration of new automated technologies into cities and communities. The U.S. is currently at the beginning of an age of advanced automated technology in transportation, energy systems, buildings, agriculture, and infrastructure. For example, sensing and computing technology can improve management of facilities, reduce traffic congestion, enhance community resilience, improve air quality, and inform emergency response decisions -- depending on use, deployment, and systems impacts. There is a critical near-term need to understand the opportunities for, and impacts of, integrating these technologies in communities, and this workshop will contribute to this need by bringing together diverse stakeholders to develop the path forward.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will foster convergence by engaging diverse participants from academia, government, and industry, across a range of disciplines in a focused dialogue that integrates these communities to identify systems-level opportunities for maximizing the benefits and minimizing the consequences of integration of automation technologies into cities and communities. The workshop will recruit a diverse group of junior faculty, postdocs, and emerging graduate students to the workshop, both to benefit from their perspectives and to connect them with collaborators and mentors. The workshop will develop a list of the most promising emerging research opportunities of integrating automation into cities and communities, and develop workshop outputs that can direct research efforts and future investments toward the most critical needs in the next five to ten years.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1929937</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Lowry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory V Lowry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>glowry@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122682948</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000459580</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/14/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mario</FirstName>
<LastName>Berges</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mario Berges</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marioberges@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122681161</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000588353</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/14/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
<LastName>Qian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Z</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sean Z Qian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>seanqian@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122684155</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000650438</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/14/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Constantinos</FirstName>
<LastName>Samaras</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Constantinos Samaras</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>csamaras@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122681658</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000654177</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/14/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WQED Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie-Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133890</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~49998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Automation in buildings, transportation, and infrastructure systems is increasingly being integrated into to urban environments. These sectors have a large impact on urban sustainability outcomes and hence how technology advances in automation affect urban sustainability are critically important to understand. New crosscutting knowledge is needed at the intersection of many fields across engineering, physical and social sciences, economics, humanities, public policy, and others.</p> <p>On July 29-30, 2019, we convened a diverse group of participants from academia, industry, the non-profit sector, and the public sector for workshop at Carnegie Mellon University in Pittsburgh, PA. The workshop was called: SUSTAIN: Sustainable Urban Systems Through Automated Infrastructure Networks. We conducted the workshop using the pseudo-nominal group technique (pseudo-NGT), which ensures that all workshop participants are given the opportunity for intellectual input, facilitates interaction between participants from different disciplines, and enables the participants to generate a prioritized list of opportunities. The workshop identified research opportunities where automation can provide the greatest sustainability benefits and synergies.</p> <p>The overarching goal of the workshop was to stimulate discussion, visioning, and convergence across urban sustainability research in the energy, water, buildings, transportation, sensors, data integration, agri-food, and automation research communities, and to advance the frontiers of imagination of the synergies in these communities. We aimed to identify the scientific, engineering and data challenges, economic and societal barriers that will limit the benefits of urban automation, technologies and research required to maximize the benefits of urban automation. Day one of the workshop generated 14 broad topic areas, and from these the participants consolidated and voted on priority research topics on the second day. The 5 priority research topics developed by the workshop participants were:</p> <ul> </ul> <ul> <li>Applications for Transportation Automation</li> <li>Infrastructure Services Transition and the Design of Adaptive Autonomous Sustainable Urban Systems</li> <li>Tradeoffs at the Systems of Systems Level</li> <li>Governance - Community, Social, Economic, Equity, and Justice Issues </li> <li>Building and the Built Environment, Land Use, &amp; Resilience&nbsp; </li> </ul> <ul> </ul> <p>There is a need to better measure and model general human factors that affect the integration automation into sustainable urban systems. The dynamic interplay of autonomy--human agency, self-rule, self-decision making--within autonomous systems was an important point of tension that workshop attendees discussed. The related key research question is: how do we promote governance of autonomous technologies in an urban environment to ensure sustainability, equity, justice, and maximum positive social and economic impact, and how can technology aid such governance while preserving and respecting human autonomy? A critical need for sustainable urban systems is a resilient, equitable, and flexible governance process that evolves alongside the technology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p>This workshop fostered convergence by engaging participants from academia, government, and industry, across a range of disciplines in a focused dialogue that integrates these communities to identify the greatest systems-level opportunities for maximizing the sustainability benefits and minimizing the consequences of integration of urban automation. New ideas and research directions that will define the path forward were generated by this diverse group of participants.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts</p> <p>The broader impacts of the proposed workshop are vast given the potential for automation to affect the trajectory of urban sustainability and the stakeholder need for information to support decisions. The workshop recruited a diverse group of talented junior faculty, postdocs, and emerging graduate students to the workshop, both to benefit from their perspectives and to connect them with potential multidisciplinary collaborators and mentors. The workshop provided a foundation for the academic community's involvement in supporting and furthering urban sustainability research, and for collaboration in research and education programs, projects, and related activities. It also helped participants to craft innovative research ideas, and contributed to the overall development of early career researchers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/11/2020<br>      Modified by: Constantinos&nbsp;Samaras</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Automation in buildings, transportation, and infrastructure systems is increasingly being integrated into to urban environments. These sectors have a large impact on urban sustainability outcomes and hence how technology advances in automation affect urban sustainability are critically important to understand. New crosscutting knowledge is needed at the intersection of many fields across engineering, physical and social sciences, economics, humanities, public policy, and others.  On July 29-30, 2019, we convened a diverse group of participants from academia, industry, the non-profit sector, and the public sector for workshop at Carnegie Mellon University in Pittsburgh, PA. The workshop was called: SUSTAIN: Sustainable Urban Systems Through Automated Infrastructure Networks. We conducted the workshop using the pseudo-nominal group technique (pseudo-NGT), which ensures that all workshop participants are given the opportunity for intellectual input, facilitates interaction between participants from different disciplines, and enables the participants to generate a prioritized list of opportunities. The workshop identified research opportunities where automation can provide the greatest sustainability benefits and synergies.  The overarching goal of the workshop was to stimulate discussion, visioning, and convergence across urban sustainability research in the energy, water, buildings, transportation, sensors, data integration, agri-food, and automation research communities, and to advance the frontiers of imagination of the synergies in these communities. We aimed to identify the scientific, engineering and data challenges, economic and societal barriers that will limit the benefits of urban automation, technologies and research required to maximize the benefits of urban automation. Day one of the workshop generated 14 broad topic areas, and from these the participants consolidated and voted on priority research topics on the second day. The 5 priority research topics developed by the workshop participants were:    Applications for Transportation Automation Infrastructure Services Transition and the Design of Adaptive Autonomous Sustainable Urban Systems Tradeoffs at the Systems of Systems Level Governance - Community, Social, Economic, Equity, and Justice Issues  Building and the Built Environment, Land Use, &amp; Resilience       There is a need to better measure and model general human factors that affect the integration automation into sustainable urban systems. The dynamic interplay of autonomy--human agency, self-rule, self-decision making--within autonomous systems was an important point of tension that workshop attendees discussed. The related key research question is: how do we promote governance of autonomous technologies in an urban environment to ensure sustainability, equity, justice, and maximum positive social and economic impact, and how can technology aid such governance while preserving and respecting human autonomy? A critical need for sustainable urban systems is a resilient, equitable, and flexible governance process that evolves alongside the technology.     Intellectual Merit  This workshop fostered convergence by engaging participants from academia, government, and industry, across a range of disciplines in a focused dialogue that integrates these communities to identify the greatest systems-level opportunities for maximizing the sustainability benefits and minimizing the consequences of integration of urban automation. New ideas and research directions that will define the path forward were generated by this diverse group of participants.     Broader Impacts  The broader impacts of the proposed workshop are vast given the potential for automation to affect the trajectory of urban sustainability and the stakeholder need for information to support decisions. The workshop recruited a diverse group of talented junior faculty, postdocs, and emerging graduate students to the workshop, both to benefit from their perspectives and to connect them with potential multidisciplinary collaborators and mentors. The workshop provided a foundation for the academic community's involvement in supporting and furthering urban sustainability research, and for collaboration in research and education programs, projects, and related activities. It also helped participants to craft innovative research ideas, and contributed to the overall development of early career researchers.       Last Modified: 10/11/2020       Submitted by: Constantinos Samaras]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
