<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>3rd Summer School on Cognitive Robotics: Proposed Summer School</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11232.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11232</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Miller</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>damiller@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924914</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides partial support for a summer school that will provide an intensive and hands-on education experience to graduate students on the topic of cognitive robotics. The summer school will bring together students and experts in both robotics and artificial intelligence, providing the attendees with a strong introduction to both fields and knowledge of how they can be combined through Cognitive Robotics. Students attending the summer school will gain insight into planning, reasoning with risk and uncertainty, robust execution, perception, manipulation, and robot learning. The interdisciplinary nature of the summer school will expose graduate students to research and methodologies combining robotics and cognitive systems, educating and creating the next generation of researchers in this field. It is anticipated that the summer school will have a broad impact on the research community through facilitating new research collaborations in the field by bringing diverse researchers together to share ideas and knowledge. The travel and participation scholarships funded through this award will serve to ensure a broad participation that maximizes community impact. The content will be streamed live as well as archived online making it possible for a much larger number of students from academia and industry to benefit from the summer school.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The summer school will be held July 17-21, 2019 at the University of Southern California in Los Angeles, California. The summer school will be a combination of invited talks and tutorials that are designed to introduce researchers and students to issues in planning and executing robot behavior from experts in both robotics and artificial intelligence. Daily hands-on labs will provide students with experience with robotic hardware and software tools for developing robot behaviors. The summer school concludes with a grand challenge combining and testing what the students have learned during the week through a hands-on task with robot hardware.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1929270</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heather</FirstName>
<LastName>Culbertson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Heather Culbertson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hculbert@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7752323188</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000769776</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~11232</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The summer school was organized by Professor Heather Culbertson (USC), Sara Bernardini (Royal Holloway University of London), Brian C. Williams (MIT), and Tiago Vaquero (JPL), based upon the following premise:</p> <p>The goal of this unique summer school was to help catalyze a community of researchers that works closely together on a sustained basis, and that draws equally upon the disciplines of Robotics and Cognitive AI, particularly those focused on planning and execution within both disciplines. Building upon the success of the 1<sup>st</sup> and 2<sup>nd</sup> Summer School on Cognitive Robotics in 2017 and 2018, we provided students with a combination of tutorials and hands-on labs focusing on the major elements of cognitive robotics that are required to develop capable autonomous systems. The intended audience for this summer school included top graduate students, postdocs, and junior researchers, from both the cognitive AI and robotics disciplines.</p> <p>Tutorials centered around daily themes of robust execution, motion planning, activity planning, perception and manipulation, and planning under uncertainty and risk. This year, we had a new, transversal themes, which impacted all the others: learning. Five out of the sixteen speakers performed research at the crossover between learning, robotics, and AI. Students were given the chance to gain insight into imitation learning, learning to reach and grasp, hierarchical reinforcement learning, and robust deep learning. We complemented the tutorials with hands-on lab exercises featuring novel robotic architecture. At the end of the week, students participated in a Grand Challenge competition that incorporated aspects of all the labs and allowed students to demonstrate what they have learned.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/06/2020<br>      Modified by: Heather&nbsp;Culbertson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The summer school was organized by Professor Heather Culbertson (USC), Sara Bernardini (Royal Holloway University of London), Brian C. Williams (MIT), and Tiago Vaquero (JPL), based upon the following premise:  The goal of this unique summer school was to help catalyze a community of researchers that works closely together on a sustained basis, and that draws equally upon the disciplines of Robotics and Cognitive AI, particularly those focused on planning and execution within both disciplines. Building upon the success of the 1st and 2nd Summer School on Cognitive Robotics in 2017 and 2018, we provided students with a combination of tutorials and hands-on labs focusing on the major elements of cognitive robotics that are required to develop capable autonomous systems. The intended audience for this summer school included top graduate students, postdocs, and junior researchers, from both the cognitive AI and robotics disciplines.  Tutorials centered around daily themes of robust execution, motion planning, activity planning, perception and manipulation, and planning under uncertainty and risk. This year, we had a new, transversal themes, which impacted all the others: learning. Five out of the sixteen speakers performed research at the crossover between learning, robotics, and AI. Students were given the chance to gain insight into imitation learning, learning to reach and grasp, hierarchical reinforcement learning, and robust deep learning. We complemented the tutorials with hands-on lab exercises featuring novel robotic architecture. At the end of the week, students participated in a Grand Challenge competition that incorporated aspects of all the labs and allowed students to demonstrate what they have learned.          Last Modified: 01/06/2020       Submitted by: Heather Culbertson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
