<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>8th Midwest Workshop on Control and Game Theory; St. Louis, Missouri; 27-28 April 2019</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19640.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19640</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Irina Dolinskaya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>idolinsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927078</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Systematic modeling, analysis, and design of social, economical, and technological systems require confluence of ideas from diverse scientific disciplines, including control theory, optimization, economics and game theory. These systems often involve multiple decision-making agents interacting over a network and form a subset of so-called cyber-physical-human systems. Examples of such systems include smart grid, connected and autonomous vehicles, smart manufacturing, and mixed human-automata systems. Recent advances in technology have made these systems increasingly pervasive in a broad range of applications. Effective design of these systems requires interactions among experts from engineering, economics, and social sciences as well as industry. This forms the basis for organizing the 8th Midwest Workshop on Controls and Game Theory on April 27 - 28, 2019 in St. Louis, Missouri, where leading experts on controls, optimization, game theory, economics and computation from the Midwestern states are brought together to facilitate interdisciplinary and cross-disciplinary research interactions and collaborations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The purpose of the workshop is to facilitate and enhance research discussions and collaborations among experts in a broad range of disciplines, including biology, economics, and engineering. The invited speakers are leading experts in the areas of controls, game theory, applied probability, computation, dynamical systems, economics, and optimization. The four themes of this workshop are: (i) complex networks and large-scale control systems, (ii) game theory for economic and societal systems, (iii) optimization, learning, and computational methods, and (iv) emerging applications and technologies. These themes will ensure the workshop focuses on both the theory and application of cyber-physical-human systems. The workshop also includes a poster session in which students and postdoctoral researchers will present their current research. The feedback and mentoring of their research from leading experts in the field will tremendously benefit these young researchers. The invited speakers are selected to ensure a broad representation of research areas and substantial participation from underrepresented groups in engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/02/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1930038</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jr-Shin</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jr-Shin Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jsli@seas.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149357340</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000104918</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/02/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shen</FirstName>
<LastName>Zeng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shen Zeng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>s.zeng@wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149359357</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000759688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/02/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>Dynamics, Control and System D</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8024</Code>
<Text>Complex Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~19640</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Systems engineering and control theory have played a key role in the development of innovative approaches for modeling, analysis and design across social, economic and technological domains. These past successes hint at even greater opportunities and possibilities that could be revealed at the confluence of ideas from diverse and rich scientific disciplines, such as control theory, optimization, economics and game theory. Indeed, recent years have witnessed the emergence of many critical modern technologies that often involve multiple decision-making agents interacting over a network in a cooperative, adversarial, or mixed setting; such research forms a subset of what is sometimes referred to as cyber-physical-human systems. Recent advances in technology have made these systems increasingly pervasive in a broad range of applications, and a holistic understanding and an effective design of these systems require interactions among experts from engineering, economics, and social sciences as well as industry.<br /><br />The 8th Midwest Workshop on Control and Game Theory, which is a gathering of researchers from the Midwest region of the United States working on broad topics in control and game theory, sought to capitalize on these expertises by creating conduits through which ideas from control theory can more readily permeate and impact game theory and vise versa to make methods for solving problems that cannot be treated by either field alone. Held over April 27-28, 2019 on the campus of Washington University in St. Louis (St. Louis, MO), the workshop brought together participants in academia and industry from the control, game theory, and social sciences communities, who would otherwise not have specific opportunities to interact. A special emphasis was placed on enabling the participation of students and early career researchers in the exploration and formulation of new research questions and directions. In this regard, students and postdoctoral associates from around the Midwest region traveled to St. Louis to attend the workshop. There, they experienced lectures by leading researchers who are working at the intersection of control and game theory as well as economics and social sciences. These talks were organized around four themes, (i) Complex Networks and Large-scale Control Systems, (ii) Game Theory for Economic and Societal Systems, (iii) Optimization, Learning, and Computational Methods, and (iv) Emerging Applications and Technologies. Each theme contained four podium talks of 30 minutes duration. In addition to lectures, the Workshop featured an interactive poster session. This session provided a forum for student and postdoctoral participants to network and share ideas with faculty members. These sessions exposed students to a diverse range of topics in applications of control and game theory to economics and social sciences. In turn, students and junior researchers expanded their professional networks through contact with potential mentors and learned about potential future career opportunities. In total, over 100 faculty members, postdoctoral researchers, and students attended the workshop, and the Workshop fulfilled its goal of bringing together researchers and practitioners in control, game theory, and social sciences to accelerate the development of new research synergies across these disciplines. Participants indicated that the workshop was highly effective in conveying the potential that exists in promoting further growth of this interdisciplinary research area. In an effort to make the results of this workshop accessible to a wide audience, all podium talks were videotaped. These talks are available for free streaming via YouTube, and are easily accessible through the workshop website: https://mwcgt2019.wustl.edu/speakers/</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Jr-Shin&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Systems engineering and control theory have played a key role in the development of innovative approaches for modeling, analysis and design across social, economic and technological domains. These past successes hint at even greater opportunities and possibilities that could be revealed at the confluence of ideas from diverse and rich scientific disciplines, such as control theory, optimization, economics and game theory. Indeed, recent years have witnessed the emergence of many critical modern technologies that often involve multiple decision-making agents interacting over a network in a cooperative, adversarial, or mixed setting; such research forms a subset of what is sometimes referred to as cyber-physical-human systems. Recent advances in technology have made these systems increasingly pervasive in a broad range of applications, and a holistic understanding and an effective design of these systems require interactions among experts from engineering, economics, and social sciences as well as industry.  The 8th Midwest Workshop on Control and Game Theory, which is a gathering of researchers from the Midwest region of the United States working on broad topics in control and game theory, sought to capitalize on these expertises by creating conduits through which ideas from control theory can more readily permeate and impact game theory and vise versa to make methods for solving problems that cannot be treated by either field alone. Held over April 27-28, 2019 on the campus of Washington University in St. Louis (St. Louis, MO), the workshop brought together participants in academia and industry from the control, game theory, and social sciences communities, who would otherwise not have specific opportunities to interact. A special emphasis was placed on enabling the participation of students and early career researchers in the exploration and formulation of new research questions and directions. In this regard, students and postdoctoral associates from around the Midwest region traveled to St. Louis to attend the workshop. There, they experienced lectures by leading researchers who are working at the intersection of control and game theory as well as economics and social sciences. These talks were organized around four themes, (i) Complex Networks and Large-scale Control Systems, (ii) Game Theory for Economic and Societal Systems, (iii) Optimization, Learning, and Computational Methods, and (iv) Emerging Applications and Technologies. Each theme contained four podium talks of 30 minutes duration. In addition to lectures, the Workshop featured an interactive poster session. This session provided a forum for student and postdoctoral participants to network and share ideas with faculty members. These sessions exposed students to a diverse range of topics in applications of control and game theory to economics and social sciences. In turn, students and junior researchers expanded their professional networks through contact with potential mentors and learned about potential future career opportunities. In total, over 100 faculty members, postdoctoral researchers, and students attended the workshop, and the Workshop fulfilled its goal of bringing together researchers and practitioners in control, game theory, and social sciences to accelerate the development of new research synergies across these disciplines. Participants indicated that the workshop was highly effective in conveying the potential that exists in promoting further growth of this interdisciplinary research area. In an effort to make the results of this workshop accessible to a wide audience, all podium talks were videotaped. These talks are available for free streaming via YouTube, and are easily accessible through the workshop website: https://mwcgt2019.wustl.edu/speakers/       Last Modified: 10/29/2020       Submitted by: Jr-Shin Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
