<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - RA:  Novel Halogen-free Replacement for Halobutyl Rubber</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1987.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1987</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI:AIR Research Alliance project focuses on the translation and transfer of the Allomatrix technology, derived from the NSF Center for Tire Research (CenTiRe), an I/UCRC. The technology has the following market-valued features: the Allomatrix family of polymers uses raw materials from renewable resources, and is a potential replacement of halobutyl rubber, which is used to make the gas-barrier inner liner of car tires and pharmaceutical stoppers. It also has the potential to be used as a rubbery biomaterial that can be processed as plastic and can be recycled, with better combination of properties than silicone rubber. These features provide the following advantages: the performance of commercial halobutyl rubber without the presence of harmful halogens, and an improved cost-effective manufacturing process with a smaller carbon footprint. The Allomatrix technology is important because it uses raw materials from renewable resources, is expected to reduce the carbon footprint of current butyl and halobutyl manufacturing processes (600,000 tons/year), may lead to improved pharmaceutical stoppers and provide improved rubbery biomaterials for saving lives. If successful, this project has the potential to bring back high value-added manufacturing to the USA, creating jobs in the STEM disciplines.  &lt;br/&gt;  The innovative ecosystem that will be created includes partners such as Honeywell, Parker Hannifin, Bridgestone/Firestone, a small biotech company (Innovia), and LG Hausys.  Third party investors include the Rubber Division of the American Chemical Society by creating the International Center of Advanced Elastomers for Healthcare, and the Breast Cancer Innovation Foundation supporting the research if integrating breast reconstruction with cancer diagnosis and treatment. The potential economic impact is expected to be significant, creating new jobs in high value added manufacturing, new commercial products and students well-trained for the created jobs in the next 2-10 years   Students (high-school, undergraduate and graduate) will gain entrepreneurial and technology translation experience through the transfer of the Allomatix technology into commercial products. Students will be motivated and challenged to develop novel ideas, and to defend the feasibility of their ideas in front of industrial partners.  &lt;br/&gt;  This project addresses the following technology gap(s) as it translates from research discovery toward commercial application: to produce halogen-free rubber on a commercial scale that can compete with current halobutyl rubber; reduce the carbon footprint of the manufacturing process; produce thermoplastic biocompatible rubber with a much cheaper and simpler process. The proposed objectives in the PFI:AIR are based on the Allomatrix technology. This new family of materials is the basis for all objectives, thus the first step is to scale up the polymerization and to produce sufficient material for product development and testing. In objective II we aim to develop an optimized sulfur curing system for tire applications, and non-sulfur curing systems for biomedical and other applications. In objective III new application development will be implemented with various partners based on the favorable properties of Allomatrix family of polymers. In objective IV the potential of the reduction of the carbon footprint of the polymerization system is examined. This objective is based on the insight of the polymerization system that was acquired during the development and optimization stages of the CenTiRe project. Lastly, objective V focuses on the examination of the feasibility of the material to be used in biomedical applications, such as investigation of cytotoxicity, material stability under physiological conditions and other aspects.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1931818</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judit</FirstName>
<LastName>Puskas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judit E Puskas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>puskas.19@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3302633861</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000283585</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>019Z</Code>
<Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Experience</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PARTNRSHIPS FOR INNOVATION-PFI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~1987</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This PFI:AIR Research Alliance project (Award 1434014) focused on the translation and transfer of the Allomatrix technology, derived from the NSF Center for Tire Research (CenTiRe), an I/UCRC, at the University of Akron. The technology has the following market-valued features: the Allomatrix family of polymers uses raw materials from renewable resources, and is a potential replacement of halobutyl rubber, which is used to make the gas-barrier inner liner of car tires and pharmaceutical stoppers. It also has the potential to be used as a rubbery biomaterial that can be processed as plastic and can be recycled, with better combination of properties than silicone rubber. These features provide the following advantages: the performance of commercial halobutyl rubber (1 million tons per year world-wide consumption) without the presence of harmful halogens, and an improved cost-effective manufacturing process. The Allomatrix technology may lead to improved pharmaceutical stoppers and provide improved rubbery biomaterials for saving lives.</p> <p>Six companies participated in the project with matching funds: LG Hausys, Honeywell, Parker-Hannifin, Bridgestone/Firestone, Wyatt Technology, Innovia. The Rubber Division of the American Chemical Society and the Breast Cancer Innovation Foundation also supported the project financially. This allowed us to establish a world-class laboratory, fundamental for building the academic-based innovation ecosystem. We purchased a Size Exclusion Chromatography set-up to replace the old system. We also purchased a 3D printer, a UV curing unit, an electrospinning equipment and a Speedmixer (this from Parker-Hannifin matching funds). We also constructed a cryogenic reactor and a mill. The equipment was transferred to OSU where the PI moved into a brand-new laboratory. Funds were also used to buy and install a walk-in fume hood for the cryogenic reactor &ndash; this remained in Akron.</p> <p>The Allomatrix technology received patent protection in 2017 (Puskas, J.E.; Terpene/isoolefin copolymers having substantially heterogeneous compositional distribution and displaying thermoplastic elastomeric properties; U.S. Patent 9,790,301). PolyFiberMatrix LLC was granted an exclusive license for medical applications in 2018 and is currently developing a medical device in collaboration with Bloodstone Division LLC. Other companies are also interested and negotiations for licenses are ongoing.</p> <p>An I-Corps project was also developed for less lethal ammunition, and a new company was formed (Polyballistics LLC) with private funding that is developing various products. Market introduction is planned in 2020.</p> <p>The project contributed to the training of 4 Post-Doctoral Fellows, 5 Ph.D. students, 5 undergraduate students and two high-school students. Philpott Solutions hosted 1 Ph. D. student as an industrial intern for 6 months in 2018.</p> <p>These coworkers learned new polymerization techniques and characterization methods. They also learned how to write industrial technical reports which are very different from peer-reviewed papers. Close collaboration with industry prepares the students for industry positions by teaching them to appreciate the requirements of corporate culture and importance of deadlines. The coworkers also had the opportunity to learn from senior contributors: Dr. AdelHalasa, retired Goodyear Fellow, Gabor Kaszas, Goodyear, and Dr. Marcia Weidknecht, retired Polymer Science Faculty who regularly attended our weekly group meetings.</p> <p>The Mentors of the I-CORPs project (Dr. Gabor Kaszas, retired from Goodyear, and Susan Louscher, Foresight Innovation Partners LLC) continued providing great training and insight to our students. They remain closely associated with our group, helping to develop the innovation ecosystem.</p> <p>The project produced 3 inventions, 1 issued US patent, 8 refereed articles, 4 non-refereed papers, 2 conference proceedings, 5 invited presentations (one Best Graduate Student Presentation Award), and 18 student poster presentations (2 Best Poster Awards).</p> <p>In summary, a sustainable academic-based innovation ecosystem has been created and will be further developed with OSU&rsquo;s institutional support.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/22/2020<br>      Modified by: Judit&nbsp;E&nbsp;Puskas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This PFI:AIR Research Alliance project (Award 1434014) focused on the translation and transfer of the Allomatrix technology, derived from the NSF Center for Tire Research (CenTiRe), an I/UCRC, at the University of Akron. The technology has the following market-valued features: the Allomatrix family of polymers uses raw materials from renewable resources, and is a potential replacement of halobutyl rubber, which is used to make the gas-barrier inner liner of car tires and pharmaceutical stoppers. It also has the potential to be used as a rubbery biomaterial that can be processed as plastic and can be recycled, with better combination of properties than silicone rubber. These features provide the following advantages: the performance of commercial halobutyl rubber (1 million tons per year world-wide consumption) without the presence of harmful halogens, and an improved cost-effective manufacturing process. The Allomatrix technology may lead to improved pharmaceutical stoppers and provide improved rubbery biomaterials for saving lives.  Six companies participated in the project with matching funds: LG Hausys, Honeywell, Parker-Hannifin, Bridgestone/Firestone, Wyatt Technology, Innovia. The Rubber Division of the American Chemical Society and the Breast Cancer Innovation Foundation also supported the project financially. This allowed us to establish a world-class laboratory, fundamental for building the academic-based innovation ecosystem. We purchased a Size Exclusion Chromatography set-up to replace the old system. We also purchased a 3D printer, a UV curing unit, an electrospinning equipment and a Speedmixer (this from Parker-Hannifin matching funds). We also constructed a cryogenic reactor and a mill. The equipment was transferred to OSU where the PI moved into a brand-new laboratory. Funds were also used to buy and install a walk-in fume hood for the cryogenic reactor &ndash; this remained in Akron.  The Allomatrix technology received patent protection in 2017 (Puskas, J.E.; Terpene/isoolefin copolymers having substantially heterogeneous compositional distribution and displaying thermoplastic elastomeric properties; U.S. Patent 9,790,301). PolyFiberMatrix LLC was granted an exclusive license for medical applications in 2018 and is currently developing a medical device in collaboration with Bloodstone Division LLC. Other companies are also interested and negotiations for licenses are ongoing.  An I-Corps project was also developed for less lethal ammunition, and a new company was formed (Polyballistics LLC) with private funding that is developing various products. Market introduction is planned in 2020.  The project contributed to the training of 4 Post-Doctoral Fellows, 5 Ph.D. students, 5 undergraduate students and two high-school students. Philpott Solutions hosted 1 Ph. D. student as an industrial intern for 6 months in 2018.  These coworkers learned new polymerization techniques and characterization methods. They also learned how to write industrial technical reports which are very different from peer-reviewed papers. Close collaboration with industry prepares the students for industry positions by teaching them to appreciate the requirements of corporate culture and importance of deadlines. The coworkers also had the opportunity to learn from senior contributors: Dr. AdelHalasa, retired Goodyear Fellow, Gabor Kaszas, Goodyear, and Dr. Marcia Weidknecht, retired Polymer Science Faculty who regularly attended our weekly group meetings.  The Mentors of the I-CORPs project (Dr. Gabor Kaszas, retired from Goodyear, and Susan Louscher, Foresight Innovation Partners LLC) continued providing great training and insight to our students. They remain closely associated with our group, helping to develop the innovation ecosystem.  The project produced 3 inventions, 1 issued US patent, 8 refereed articles, 4 non-refereed papers, 2 conference proceedings, 5 invited presentations (one Best Graduate Student Presentation Award), and 18 student poster presentations (2 Best Poster Awards).  In summary, a sustainable academic-based innovation ecosystem has been created and will be further developed with OSU’s institutional support.       Last Modified: 02/22/2020       Submitted by: Judit E Puskas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
