<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Dynamic Distributed Fiber Optic Sensor System</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project on the new dynamic distributed fiber optic strain technology is that it could be applied within a field that requires or could benefit from a high density of data for strain or temperature detection. Infrastructure is a large part of a nation's assets and efficient management of these assets is vital to society. The lack of rich data on structural performance limits our understanding of infrastructure behavior.  The new technology can provide a single distributed monitoring system for large infrastructure projects in civil engineering, such as bridges, tunnels, foundations, dams, levees, etc.; or in the oil and gas industry such as for methane hydrate excavation, deep wells, surface or buried pipelines, and shale gas excavation monitoring. Through the use of monitoring systems centered on this technology, clients would be provided quality control data to observe and validate the construction of their assets and their long-term performance, potentially over the entire asset lifespan. The produced monitoring data can be presented and shared within a network data map that can be adopted as part of the 'smart city' approach for both hazard prevention or future city management.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project explores commercial opportunities for the new distributed fiber optic sensor system technology that reduces the reading time and provides the dynamic detection capability for strain or temperature sensing. The newly developed system provides very high density of data (every 2cm) over very long distance (10-50km), giving equivalent of thousands of conventional 'strain gauge', 'thermo-couple' or 'accelerometer' instruments through the use of a single low-cost fiber optic cable. Its dynamic performance opens a window of detection linear wave vibration along the fiber cable and detects the response of the infrastructural under external load or even seismic event.  The I-Corps team will interview potential clients, stakeholders, and key business adopters to better understand the monitoring needs and current areas for improvement within the marketplace. This exercise will allow the team to determine the potential commercial viability of the technology, as well as help identify potential areas for further research as well as other markets for deployment that are not currently using distributed fiber optic sensing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1931704</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenichi</FirstName>
<LastName>Soga</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenichi Soga</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>soga@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106428109</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000735833</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947201710</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Infrastructure is a large part of a nation's assets and efficient management of these assets is vital to society. The lack of rich data on structural performance limits our understanding of infrastructure behavior. An innovative distributed fiber optic strain system was developed at UC Berkeley. It provides a very high density of data (every 2cm) over a very long distance (10-50km), giving an equivalent of thousands of conventional 'strain gauge', or 'thermo-couple' instruments through the use of a single low-cost fiber optic cable. Its dynamic performance opens a window of detection linear wave vibration along the fiber cable and monitors the response of the instrumented infrastructural under external dynamic load or even seismic event. The new technology can provide a single distributed monitoring system for large infrastructure projects in civil engineering, such as bridges, tunnels, foundations, dams, levees, etc.; or in the energy industry such as deep wells for geothermal energy and surface or buried pipelines. Through the use of monitoring systems centered on this technology, clients would receive quality control data to observe and validate the construction of their assets and their long-term performance, potentially over the entire asset lifespan. The produced monitoring data can be presented and shared within a network data map that can be adopted as part of the 'smart city' approach for both hazard prevention or future city management.</p> <p>This I-Corps project explored opportunities for the newly developed low cost, real-time distributed fiber optic sensing technology that reduces the reading time and provides the dynamic detection capability for strain or temperature sensing. The primary goals were to examine the commercial opportunities for this technology and to promote the technology as part of engineering design and decision-making processes. The I-Corps team interviewed 104 potential clients, stakeholders, and key business adopters to better understand the monitoring needs and current areas for improvement within the marketplace. The exercise allowed the team to determine the potential commercial viability of the technology and to identify potential areas for further research as well as other markets for deployment that are not currently using distributed fiber optic sensing. The initial ideas of the market need were (i) lack of data is a major challenge for engineers and asset managers and (ii) more data provide proportionally more value. However, the interviews and I-Corps exercise revealed that more data is not always better, especially if it is not clear what to do with it. At present, infrastructure as a whole is designed to minimize risk ? there is no strong motivation to push the envelope. The market ecosystem was found to be complicated as the owners and funders of an infrastructure asset have to interact with many organizations, including design engineers, regulators, inspectors, construction contractors, instrumentation and monitoring contractor and asset manager/concessionaire. The project focused on the customer discovery by connecting customer segments to who owns the risk. It was also found that several agencies are interested in partnering with universities and the I-Corps team will continue the development of the technology in collaboration with public and private agencies. This includes more deployment and education to increase awareness.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/24/2020<br>      Modified by: Kenichi&nbsp;Soga</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1931704/1931704_10609102_1600969154392_Technolgy--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1931704/1931704_10609102_1600969154392_Technolgy--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Technology"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1931704/1931704_10609102_1600969154392_Technolgy--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Technology"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Distributed fiber optic sensing</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kenichi Soga</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kenichi&nbsp;Soga</div> <div class="imageTitle">Technology</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1931704/1931704_10609102_1600969011402_Soga_Bakar_0--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1931704/1931704_10609102_1600969011402_Soga_Bakar_0--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ICorps team"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1931704/1931704_10609102_1600969011402_Soga_Bakar_0--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ICorps team"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">BerkeleySens ICorps team</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kenichi Soga</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kenichi&nbsp;Soga</div> <div class="imageTitle">ICorps team</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1931704/1931704_10609102_1600969249313_Technolgy2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1931704/1931704_10609102_1600969249313_Technolgy2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ICorps Members"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1931704/1931704_10609102_1600969249313_Technolgy2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ICorps Members"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The details of the ICorps team members</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kenichi Soga</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kenichi&nbsp;Soga</div> <div class="imageTitle">ICorps Members</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Infrastructure is a large part of a nation's assets and efficient management of these assets is vital to society. The lack of rich data on structural performance limits our understanding of infrastructure behavior. An innovative distributed fiber optic strain system was developed at UC Berkeley. It provides a very high density of data (every 2cm) over a very long distance (10-50km), giving an equivalent of thousands of conventional 'strain gauge', or 'thermo-couple' instruments through the use of a single low-cost fiber optic cable. Its dynamic performance opens a window of detection linear wave vibration along the fiber cable and monitors the response of the instrumented infrastructural under external dynamic load or even seismic event. The new technology can provide a single distributed monitoring system for large infrastructure projects in civil engineering, such as bridges, tunnels, foundations, dams, levees, etc.; or in the energy industry such as deep wells for geothermal energy and surface or buried pipelines. Through the use of monitoring systems centered on this technology, clients would receive quality control data to observe and validate the construction of their assets and their long-term performance, potentially over the entire asset lifespan. The produced monitoring data can be presented and shared within a network data map that can be adopted as part of the 'smart city' approach for both hazard prevention or future city management.  This I-Corps project explored opportunities for the newly developed low cost, real-time distributed fiber optic sensing technology that reduces the reading time and provides the dynamic detection capability for strain or temperature sensing. The primary goals were to examine the commercial opportunities for this technology and to promote the technology as part of engineering design and decision-making processes. The I-Corps team interviewed 104 potential clients, stakeholders, and key business adopters to better understand the monitoring needs and current areas for improvement within the marketplace. The exercise allowed the team to determine the potential commercial viability of the technology and to identify potential areas for further research as well as other markets for deployment that are not currently using distributed fiber optic sensing. The initial ideas of the market need were (i) lack of data is a major challenge for engineers and asset managers and (ii) more data provide proportionally more value. However, the interviews and I-Corps exercise revealed that more data is not always better, especially if it is not clear what to do with it. At present, infrastructure as a whole is designed to minimize risk ? there is no strong motivation to push the envelope. The market ecosystem was found to be complicated as the owners and funders of an infrastructure asset have to interact with many organizations, including design engineers, regulators, inspectors, construction contractors, instrumentation and monitoring contractor and asset manager/concessionaire. The project focused on the customer discovery by connecting customer segments to who owns the risk. It was also found that several agencies are interested in partnering with universities and the I-Corps team will continue the development of the technology in collaboration with public and private agencies. This includes more deployment and education to increase awareness.       Last Modified: 09/24/2020       Submitted by: Kenichi Soga]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
