<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Student Travel Grant for 2019 Theoretical Computer Science (TCS) Women Meeting at Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tracy Kimbrel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tkimbrel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927924</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support student attendance at the Theoretical Computer Science (TCS) Women Event which will be co-located with the 51st Annual Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) Symposium on the Theory of Computing (STOC), June 23-26, 2019, as part of the Federated Computing Research Conferences (FCRC).  Scientists all over the world are increasingly acknowledging the need for diversity.  Many diversity-related workshops are being organized with the goal of building community, increasing camaraderie, and helping minorities to share their experience and receive mentoring.  While these workshops and meetings of minority communities are extremely important, it is equally important to co-locate these meetings with major technical conferences whenever possible. This allows the broader research community to hear the issues raised by minorities. It also allows the minority participants to better take advantage of the technical conferences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;STOC is one of the flagship annual research conference in the field of Theoretical Computer Science (TCS).  STOC features presentations covering all aspects of TCS and encourages papers that broaden the reach of computer science theory.  Moreover, the co-located theory festival organizes invited sessions with the best theoretical papers presented outside the TCS community.  This year, STOC is collocated with a dozen other computer science conferences under the umbrella of ACM FCRC 2019, including Conference on Learning Theory (COLT), Economics and Computation (EC), Symposium on Parallelism in Algorithms and Architectures (SPAA), and many others. This award will provide partial support to approximately 10 students to attend this leading conference as well as the TCS Women event. The event will consist of a lunch, a panel of senior female researchers, and a workshop open to all, featuring research presentations by prominent female researchers. An important goal will be to provide opportunities for network-building among women and minority researchers in TCS.  It will contribute towards attracting more under-represented groups to TCS research, and will provide a positive environment for their future professional development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1931307</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Virginia</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Virginia V Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>virgi@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6177155833</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000640555</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394307</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>Algorithmic Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7926</Code>
<Text>ALGORITHMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7927</Code>
<Text>COMPLEXITY &amp; CRYPTOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main goal of the TCS Women initiative is to help increase diversity in theoretical computer science (TCS). The approach is to organize an annual meeting, co-located with STOC, one of the two flagship research conferences in the field. This meeting aims to build a community for junior women and underrepresented minority researchers, increasing camaraderie, mentoring opportunities and visibility.<br />So far there have been three TCS Women meetings at STOC: in 2018, 2019 and (virtually) 2020. Events at these meetings have included: a lunch for women and minorities, a panel of senior women researchers, opportunities for the participants to present research posters at the STOC poster session, joint with all other participants, and a one-day research workshop, open to all STOC participants, but whose speakers consist of top female and minority researchers who will be on the job market, and an inspirational speaker who is a senior female or minority researcher. The events have been very well attended and have received overwhelmingly positive feedback.<br /><br />The NSF grant was used for providing travel scholarships to junior students from underrepresented backgrounds to attend the STOC 2019 conference and the TCS Women meeting. Attending STOC and other top theory conferences is an important stepping stone towards getting to know and joining the community. Unfortunately, the participation of underrepresented students in premier TCS conferences has been largely disappointing, and this has been a major contributing factor to the lack of diversity in TCS. The TCS Women event has helped increase the diversity at the last three STOC conferences significantly, most notably in 2019 when the NSF grant, together with industry sponsorship, helped fund 46 students who would otherwise not have been able to attend STOC. We hope that many of the students who attended the TCS Women events would stay in the TCS community, and that that in turn will help attract more students from underrepresented groups.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/22/2021<br>      Modified by: Virginia&nbsp;V&nbsp;Williams</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main goal of the TCS Women initiative is to help increase diversity in theoretical computer science (TCS). The approach is to organize an annual meeting, co-located with STOC, one of the two flagship research conferences in the field. This meeting aims to build a community for junior women and underrepresented minority researchers, increasing camaraderie, mentoring opportunities and visibility. So far there have been three TCS Women meetings at STOC: in 2018, 2019 and (virtually) 2020. Events at these meetings have included: a lunch for women and minorities, a panel of senior women researchers, opportunities for the participants to present research posters at the STOC poster session, joint with all other participants, and a one-day research workshop, open to all STOC participants, but whose speakers consist of top female and minority researchers who will be on the job market, and an inspirational speaker who is a senior female or minority researcher. The events have been very well attended and have received overwhelmingly positive feedback.  The NSF grant was used for providing travel scholarships to junior students from underrepresented backgrounds to attend the STOC 2019 conference and the TCS Women meeting. Attending STOC and other top theory conferences is an important stepping stone towards getting to know and joining the community. Unfortunately, the participation of underrepresented students in premier TCS conferences has been largely disappointing, and this has been a major contributing factor to the lack of diversity in TCS. The TCS Women event has helped increase the diversity at the last three STOC conferences significantly, most notably in 2019 when the NSF grant, together with industry sponsorship, helped fund 46 students who would otherwise not have been able to attend STOC. We hope that many of the students who attended the TCS Women events would stay in the TCS community, and that that in turn will help attract more students from underrepresented groups.       Last Modified: 02/22/2021       Submitted by: Virginia V Williams]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
