<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Bioreactor insert and biofilm support for improved biological and physical treatment of wastewater</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of the I-Corps project is in understanding the on-site industrial wastewater treatment market so that an effective solution can be designed to ensure that a municipal wastewater treatment plant can continue to function well and protect the environment and public health. Worldwide, UNICESCO estimates that 80% of wastewater is released untreated back into the environment resulting in harmful algal blooms, loss of freshwater ecosystems, and polluted drinking water sources. Even in high-income countries, roughly 30% of wastewater is released untreated. Not only are wastewater treatment solutions necessary for environmental and public health protection, they are fiscally sensible decisions, with investments in sanitation often yielding significant return to society. Municipal wastewater treatment facilities are often stressed by industrial discharge to sewers, and thus limit the pollutant loading by industries. In turn, industries are often stunted in growth by their wastewater production, which is especially a problem for smaller industries. The I-Corps work will initially focus on the pain points experienced by small industrial wastewater producers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project further develops a low-cost bioreactor to meet the wastewater treatment needs of industry. The underlying technology relies on flow recirculation of wastewater through meshes on which treating and filtering biofilms (microorganisms) form. This new approach to an attached growth bioreactor, which pushes wastewater through the biofilms, eliminates the mass transfer limitation of diffusion of metabolites into the biofilm, as occurs in conventional attached growth systems. Because the meshes on which the biofilms form allow for some solids transport across them, they do not clog easily and allow for low-pressure filtration. Therefore, this new approach offers improved biological and effective physical treatment of wastewater. Sufficient solids and organics removal have been observed at the lab-scale under challenging operating conditions, anaerobic, low-temperature treatment of dilute wastewater, which indicates promise for better performance in less challenging conditions of higher temperature and higher strength wastewater, typical of many industries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1932659</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Skerlos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven J Skerlos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>skerlos@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7346155253</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000305825</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 S. State St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Motivation</span>. A novel biological wastewater treatment technology was developed at the University of Michigan, which could provide small footprint, low-cost, and highly effective treatment. The treatment technology, termed a recirculating dynamic membrane bioreactor (R-DMBR), overcame cost hurdles and complexities of a commercialized technology, the membrane bioreactor. The initial R-DMBR prototypes were evaluated at the laboratory-scale for anaerobic treatment, which enables renewable energy recovery as organic pollutants are converted into methane gas. Notably, these prototypes operated around 70 degrees Fahrenheit instead of requiring heating to around 100 degrees Fahrenheit or higher as is typical of existing anaerobic technologies. Additionally, the dynamic membranes were significantly less vulnerable to fouling compared to conventional polymeric membranes used in membrane bioreactors. These promising performance results led the research team to pursue potential commercial applications of the novel R-DMBR technology.</p> <p>One such promising sector identified for R-DMBR application was brewery wastewater because of its high organic content, biological degradability, and significant market growth in the U.S. Craft beer production has more than doubled since 2010 in the U.S., and there are approximately six gallons of wastewater produced per gallon of beer made. Thus, there is a large production volume of high-strength brewery wastewater which may not be able to be handled by a local municipal treatment system. Even if a brewery's wastewater could be handled by a municipal treatment system, sewer discharge fees could incentivize pre-treatment onsite before discharging to the municipal sewer. The work conducted for this I-Corps program was to evaluate the opportunity to apply the novel R-DMBR technology in the U.S. craft brewery market, which appeared a promising option for early adoption.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Project Outcomes</span>. Over the course of the I-Corps program, the team interviewed over 150 stakeholders relevant to technology adoption in brewery and related sectors. The team learned that the largest challenges with brewery wastewater management occur for growing breweries located in municipalities with small and older wastewater treatment facilities. Many times, a brewery would be required to install a pre-treatment system onsite so that the small municipality would not exceed their pollutant discharge permit limits. Although this was a driving force for onsite treatment adoption in the mid 2010&rsquo;s, few craft breweries are currently growing quickly and most are well-served for their wastewater management. Thus, the team learned that the craft brewery wastewater treatment market is quite small even though the total market has grown considerably over the past decade. Through discussions with larger wastewater treatment technology providers, the team learned that the larger food and beverage wastewater treatment market is growing steadily in the U.S. and that there are drivers for innovation in this market. The team identified that this market is quite segmented and smaller wastewater technology companies have high customer acquisition costs and long sales cycles. Neither of these conditions is favorable for a startup company, so the team identified options to overcome these challenges. One option that has proven successful for other technology providers in the water sector is partnership of an emerging technology provider with a larger, well-established technology provider. Through these partnerships, the smaller company not only has access to sufficient capital for technology implementation but also gains the advantage of channel partners and trust from end users. Another option is through utility and consulting engineering partnerships where technology can be piloted at a relevant scale and be understood by engineering firms who bid on large projects where the emerging technology may be a suitable option. These two options are not exclusive, and both increase the chance of technology transition from the laboratory to commercial scale. The entrepreneurial skills learned in the I&#8209;Corps program have been incorporated into the principal investigator&rsquo;s research group and a startup company has been formed to pursue commercialization of the R-DMBR.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/04/2021<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;J&nbsp;Skerlos</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Motivation. A novel biological wastewater treatment technology was developed at the University of Michigan, which could provide small footprint, low-cost, and highly effective treatment. The treatment technology, termed a recirculating dynamic membrane bioreactor (R-DMBR), overcame cost hurdles and complexities of a commercialized technology, the membrane bioreactor. The initial R-DMBR prototypes were evaluated at the laboratory-scale for anaerobic treatment, which enables renewable energy recovery as organic pollutants are converted into methane gas. Notably, these prototypes operated around 70 degrees Fahrenheit instead of requiring heating to around 100 degrees Fahrenheit or higher as is typical of existing anaerobic technologies. Additionally, the dynamic membranes were significantly less vulnerable to fouling compared to conventional polymeric membranes used in membrane bioreactors. These promising performance results led the research team to pursue potential commercial applications of the novel R-DMBR technology.  One such promising sector identified for R-DMBR application was brewery wastewater because of its high organic content, biological degradability, and significant market growth in the U.S. Craft beer production has more than doubled since 2010 in the U.S., and there are approximately six gallons of wastewater produced per gallon of beer made. Thus, there is a large production volume of high-strength brewery wastewater which may not be able to be handled by a local municipal treatment system. Even if a brewery's wastewater could be handled by a municipal treatment system, sewer discharge fees could incentivize pre-treatment onsite before discharging to the municipal sewer. The work conducted for this I-Corps program was to evaluate the opportunity to apply the novel R-DMBR technology in the U.S. craft brewery market, which appeared a promising option for early adoption.  Project Outcomes. Over the course of the I-Corps program, the team interviewed over 150 stakeholders relevant to technology adoption in brewery and related sectors. The team learned that the largest challenges with brewery wastewater management occur for growing breweries located in municipalities with small and older wastewater treatment facilities. Many times, a brewery would be required to install a pre-treatment system onsite so that the small municipality would not exceed their pollutant discharge permit limits. Although this was a driving force for onsite treatment adoption in the mid 2010’s, few craft breweries are currently growing quickly and most are well-served for their wastewater management. Thus, the team learned that the craft brewery wastewater treatment market is quite small even though the total market has grown considerably over the past decade. Through discussions with larger wastewater treatment technology providers, the team learned that the larger food and beverage wastewater treatment market is growing steadily in the U.S. and that there are drivers for innovation in this market. The team identified that this market is quite segmented and smaller wastewater technology companies have high customer acquisition costs and long sales cycles. Neither of these conditions is favorable for a startup company, so the team identified options to overcome these challenges. One option that has proven successful for other technology providers in the water sector is partnership of an emerging technology provider with a larger, well-established technology provider. Through these partnerships, the smaller company not only has access to sufficient capital for technology implementation but also gains the advantage of channel partners and trust from end users. Another option is through utility and consulting engineering partnerships where technology can be piloted at a relevant scale and be understood by engineering firms who bid on large projects where the emerging technology may be a suitable option. These two options are not exclusive, and both increase the chance of technology transition from the laboratory to commercial scale. The entrepreneurial skills learned in the I&#8209;Corps program have been incorporated into the principal investigator’s research group and a startup company has been formed to pursue commercialization of the R-DMBR.          Last Modified: 02/04/2021       Submitted by: Steven J Skerlos]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
