<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for 2019 Symposium on Computer Science and Law</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The inaugural Association for Computing Machinery Symposium on Computer Science and Law (ACM CSLAW-19) will be held in October 2019, in New York City. By launching efforts in this nascent field of study, the symposium will have impact on a broad range of societal issues, ranging from online security and privacy to Internet platform regulation to digital intellectual property protection.  This award provides full or partial support for approximately 20 students to attend the symposium.  A subcommittee of the symposium program committee will select a diverse group of students for travel support, based on applications in which students explain their interest in Computer Science and Law and the ways in which they expect the symposium to further their educational and professional development, and advisors address the quality of the students' work and the reason that travel support is needed for attendance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The scope of the ACM CSLAW-19 symposium includes: Security, privacy, encryption, and surveillance; Cyber espionage, cyber war, and cyber diplomacy; Cyber crime, cyber law enforcement, and digital forensics; Freedom of expression online (or the lack thereof); Online market structure, platform monopolies, and antitrust law; Online government services; Digital intellectual property; Legal informatics; Automation of legal reasoning and legal services; Fairness, accountability, transparency, and ethics (FATE) in machine learning and data mining; Methodological compatibility and incompatibility between the discipline of computer science and the discipline of law; Educational imperatives and existing educational programs in Computer Science and Law.  The main expected outcome of the symposium is a comprehensive report on the findings of break-out-group discussions.  The report will explicate a rich agenda for research, practice, education, and fostering the interdisciplinary area of Computer Science and Law and make concrete suggestions about how the research community, ACM, funding agencies, universities, the technology industry, and other interested institutions can help advance this agenda.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1933535</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joan</FirstName>
<LastName>Feigenbaum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joan Feigenbaum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>joan.feigenbaum@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034326432</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000151987</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 208327]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208285</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[AK Watson Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>Algorithmic Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CPS-Cyber-Physical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025Z</Code>
<Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In October 2019, the inaugural ACM Symposium on Computer Science and Law was held at New York Law School in the Tribecca neighborhood of New York City. This NSF award provided full or partial support for approximately 20 of the students who attended the symposium.&nbsp; The symposium program can be found at&nbsp;https://computersciencelaw.org/.</p> <p>Unspent funds were reallocated to the November 2020 DIMACS Workshop on Co-Development of Computer Science and Law.&nbsp; The workshop program can be found at&nbsp;http://dimacs.rutgers.edu/events/details?eID=1740.</p> <p>Since computer science began to solidify as a discipline in the middle of the 20th century, computers have become essential tools in almost every form of human endeavor.&nbsp; Recently, a more profound change has begun: Sophisticated computation is becoming an essential component of many spheres of human activity, including advertising and marketing, law enforcement and intelligence, political campaigning and propaganda, finance, journalism, research and scholarship (in the arts and humanities as well as science and technology), and even friendship and romance. People who can understand and exploit computational methods and principles, rather than simply use computers as appliances, now have a decisive advantage over their less computationally astute competitors.&nbsp; One of the results of this change is the increasing emphasis in computer science departments on interdisciplinary areas, including Computer Science and Law.</p> <p>The emerging Computer Science and Law community is intellectualy and socially diverse and is populated by researchers, students, teachers, lawyers, engineers, politicians, regulators, entrepreneurs, and activists.&nbsp; It is concerned with a very broad set&nbsp;of sociotechnical issues, ranging from online security and privacy to Internet platform regulation to digital intellectual property protection.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/12/2021<br>      Modified by: Joan&nbsp;Feigenbaum</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In October 2019, the inaugural ACM Symposium on Computer Science and Law was held at New York Law School in the Tribecca neighborhood of New York City. This NSF award provided full or partial support for approximately 20 of the students who attended the symposium.  The symposium program can be found at https://computersciencelaw.org/.  Unspent funds were reallocated to the November 2020 DIMACS Workshop on Co-Development of Computer Science and Law.  The workshop program can be found at http://dimacs.rutgers.edu/events/details?eID=1740.  Since computer science began to solidify as a discipline in the middle of the 20th century, computers have become essential tools in almost every form of human endeavor.  Recently, a more profound change has begun: Sophisticated computation is becoming an essential component of many spheres of human activity, including advertising and marketing, law enforcement and intelligence, political campaigning and propaganda, finance, journalism, research and scholarship (in the arts and humanities as well as science and technology), and even friendship and romance. People who can understand and exploit computational methods and principles, rather than simply use computers as appliances, now have a decisive advantage over their less computationally astute competitors.  One of the results of this change is the increasing emphasis in computer science departments on interdisciplinary areas, including Computer Science and Law.  The emerging Computer Science and Law community is intellectualy and socially diverse and is populated by researchers, students, teachers, lawyers, engineers, politicians, regulators, entrepreneurs, and activists.  It is concerned with a very broad set of sociotechnical issues, ranging from online security and privacy to Internet platform regulation to digital intellectual property protection.         Last Modified: 06/12/2021       Submitted by: Joan Feigenbaum]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
