<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Novel Nano-Framework for Lithium</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is significant for lithium producers that can selectively extract and recover efficiently high-grade lithium from brine and salt water, resulting in a significant impact on the lithium market. The proposed research will enable understanding of the technology challenges, needs, and improvement in current lithium extraction technologies. The training process will help graduate students to improve their entrepreneurial skills, learn how to work with academia, industrial sectors, customers and the public. The developed technology is expected to find broader commercial applications in environmental, healthcare, and energy sectors. The customer of the proposed innovation is potentially any company that produces brine solution. Oil companies and lithium producers are the key targets for this innovation. The proposed innovation enables a novel technology that would selectively extract lithium from brine solution resulting in high lithium recovery and low-cost production and conversion of lithium to its end products, lithium carbonate and lithium hydroxide.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project develops a fibrous mat from a novel coordination polymer framework that possesses molecular sieving and selective chemical affinity to lithium, providing fast and efficient lithium extraction and recovery. The global demand for lithium is expected to witness substantial growth owing to its increased demand for energy storage, electronic bikes, electrification of tools, and other battery-intense applications. It is unlikely that traditional lithium extraction operations from hard rock and brine deposits will be able to respond to future lithium markets to meet current demands. Mining lithium from hard rock deposits requires high operating cost regardless of its low technology requirements and short processing time. The current brine operations are also more capital intensive, incur significant lead times to generate high grade lithium production. The proposed innovation is unique due to its high selectivity, rapid extraction ability, and the feasibility to apply into any shape and size brine ponds. The current stage of the project focuses on developing the fibrous mat with tailored porosity and high-density chemical affinity to demonstrate its utility and versatility for selective extraction of lithium ions from salt solutions and seawater.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1934248</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hemali</FirstName>
<LastName>Rathnayake</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hemali Rathnayake</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hprathna@uncg.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000542948</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina Greensboro</Name>
<CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
<ZipCode>274125013</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3363345878</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1111 Spring Garden Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2702 Moore Hum. & Research Admin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>616152567</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT GREENSBORO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Joint School of Nanoscience and Nanoengineering]]></Name>
<CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>274014897</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2907 E Gate City Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>NSF National I-Corp Program, Nano Mosaic - A Novel Nano-Framework for Lithium; Award #1934248; Team: Hemali Rathnayake (PI), Sheeba Dawood (EL), and Glenn Seymour (IM).</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Lessons Learned from Customer Discovery</span>: Nano Mosaic team participated in the NSF I-Corps program to identify potential customers through customer discoveries and experimentation. Our major goal was to effectively identify practical problems of our targeted customers and build a business model canvas. In order to test and validate our business thesis, we postulated our hypothesis, targeting four different customer segments, which include: <strong>(1)</strong> Business development officers/CEO/ Process development managers from lithium mining industries will be interested in the recovery of lithium from brine resources (Oilfield brines); <strong>(2)</strong> Business development officers/ Process engineers from water companies or chemical companies will be interested in recovery of minerals from produced water; <strong>(3)</strong> Site managers/Vice president/Environmental professionals from bromine extraction plants and oil service company will be interested in extraction of lithium from produced water; and <strong>(4)</strong> Process engineer/ Business development officers from mineral recovery industries will be interested in recovery of lithium from oil field brines. The total of 100 interviews, which included more than 20 customers from lithium industries and oil industries (Downstream, midstream, and upstream), was conducted. Initially, among various types of brines, we targeted oil industries as they produce $21 billion barrels of oil field brine per year. Oil field brines are also called produced water, which is basically a byproduct of oil recovery consisting of various useful minerals like magnesium, potassium, and lithium in it. The customer discovery interviews were conducted for above four identified customer segments.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conclusion:</span> We concluded that lithium extraction from produced water and other brine resources are geographically varies and the US market is not matured enough for product fit for extracting lithium from fracking-produced water. Although, Nano Mosaic technology was a "No Go" after the I-Corp customer discovery, team has learned that there is a room to pivot the technology with further lab-scale development and research. For example, bromine extraction companies are interested on lithium recovery from their bromine plants and our technology can be add-in-technology for bromine producers. Therefore, our future discoveries will focus on interviewing bromine producers, modify the business model, evaluate the cost structure vs revenue streams and the market size.&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span>: The global demand for lithium is expected to witness substantial growth owing to its increased demand for energy storage, electronic bikes, electrification of tools, and other battery-intense applications. For example, the lithium ion battery market itself is projected to reach US$ 92 billion by 2024. It is unlikely that traditional lithium extraction operations from hard rock and brine deposits will be able to respond to future lithium markets to meet current demands. Therefore, efficient, rapid, and cost-effective lithium extraction technologies are needed to ensure that supply matches the growing demand. The innovation based on natural polyphenol derived fibrous mat as liners, filters, and membranes is unique due to its high selectivity, pore dimension (&lt;2 nm), and surface area, and the feasibility to apply into any shape and size brine ponds. As this innovation uses readily available, abundant, natural reactants, and is rapid and scalable, it provides potential for low cost production of high-grade lithium.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts</span>: The Nano Mosaic technology will significantly impact on lithium market by providing fast and effective lithium extraction from brine and saltwater. During our participation in the I-Corps site program and National program, we were able to explore the impact of the proposed technology by focusing a wide variety of customer segments including lithium companies, battery industries, automobiles, oil companies, produced water companies, and medical stake holders. Through the customer discovery process, the team was able to identify the potential commercial impact of the technology for customer segments in oil companies, lithium producers, and produced water purification services as they are the largest producers of brines or providing services for purification and analysis of brines. Based on these discoveries, we have determined the value proposition to be low operation cost, high lithium recovery and less time consumption. The customer discovery enabled us to understand the technology challenges, needs, and improvement in current lithium technologies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/06/2020<br>      Modified by: Hemali&nbsp;Rathnayake</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1934248/1934248_10609121_1593107427997_pic30145_rmag_s20_rathnayake_dawood-004jpg_49638931463_o--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1934248/1934248_10609121_1593107427997_pic30145_rmag_s20_rathnayake_dawood-004jpg_49638931463_o--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sheeba Dawood holding Nano Mosaic fiber mat"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1934248/1934248_10609121_1593107427997_pic30145_rmag_s20_rathnayake_dawood-004jpg_49638931463_o--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sheeba Dawood holding Nano Mosaic fiber mat"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Nano Mosaic Filter Mat</div> <div class="imageCredit">UNCG</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hemali&nbsp;Rathnayake</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sheeba Dawood holding Nano Mosaic fiber mat</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1934248/1934248_10609121_1593107579830_pic30145_rmag_s20_rathnayake_dawood-275jpg_49639457241_o--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1934248/1934248_10609121_1593107579830_pic30145_rmag_s20_rathnayake_dawood-275jpg_49639457241_o--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nano Mosaic Frameworks imagine using Scanning Electron Microscope"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1934248/1934248_10609121_1593107579830_pic30145_rmag_s20_rathnayake_dawood-275jpg_49639457241_o--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nano Mosaic Frameworks imagine using Scanning Electron Microscope"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An Image of Nano Mosaic Frameworks</div> <div class="imageCredit">UNCG</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hemali&nbsp;Rathnayake</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nano Mosaic Frameworks imagine using Scanning Electron Microscope</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF National I-Corp Program, Nano Mosaic - A Novel Nano-Framework for Lithium; Award #1934248; Team: Hemali Rathnayake (PI), Sheeba Dawood (EL), and Glenn Seymour (IM).  Lessons Learned from Customer Discovery: Nano Mosaic team participated in the NSF I-Corps program to identify potential customers through customer discoveries and experimentation. Our major goal was to effectively identify practical problems of our targeted customers and build a business model canvas. In order to test and validate our business thesis, we postulated our hypothesis, targeting four different customer segments, which include: (1) Business development officers/CEO/ Process development managers from lithium mining industries will be interested in the recovery of lithium from brine resources (Oilfield brines); (2) Business development officers/ Process engineers from water companies or chemical companies will be interested in recovery of minerals from produced water; (3) Site managers/Vice president/Environmental professionals from bromine extraction plants and oil service company will be interested in extraction of lithium from produced water; and (4) Process engineer/ Business development officers from mineral recovery industries will be interested in recovery of lithium from oil field brines. The total of 100 interviews, which included more than 20 customers from lithium industries and oil industries (Downstream, midstream, and upstream), was conducted. Initially, among various types of brines, we targeted oil industries as they produce $21 billion barrels of oil field brine per year. Oil field brines are also called produced water, which is basically a byproduct of oil recovery consisting of various useful minerals like magnesium, potassium, and lithium in it. The customer discovery interviews were conducted for above four identified customer segments.  Conclusion: We concluded that lithium extraction from produced water and other brine resources are geographically varies and the US market is not matured enough for product fit for extracting lithium from fracking-produced water. Although, Nano Mosaic technology was a "No Go" after the I-Corp customer discovery, team has learned that there is a room to pivot the technology with further lab-scale development and research. For example, bromine extraction companies are interested on lithium recovery from their bromine plants and our technology can be add-in-technology for bromine producers. Therefore, our future discoveries will focus on interviewing bromine producers, modify the business model, evaluate the cost structure vs revenue streams and the market size.       Intellectual Merit: The global demand for lithium is expected to witness substantial growth owing to its increased demand for energy storage, electronic bikes, electrification of tools, and other battery-intense applications. For example, the lithium ion battery market itself is projected to reach US$ 92 billion by 2024. It is unlikely that traditional lithium extraction operations from hard rock and brine deposits will be able to respond to future lithium markets to meet current demands. Therefore, efficient, rapid, and cost-effective lithium extraction technologies are needed to ensure that supply matches the growing demand. The innovation based on natural polyphenol derived fibrous mat as liners, filters, and membranes is unique due to its high selectivity, pore dimension (&lt;2 nm), and surface area, and the feasibility to apply into any shape and size brine ponds. As this innovation uses readily available, abundant, natural reactants, and is rapid and scalable, it provides potential for low cost production of high-grade lithium.  Broader Impacts: The Nano Mosaic technology will significantly impact on lithium market by providing fast and effective lithium extraction from brine and saltwater. During our participation in the I-Corps site program and National program, we were able to explore the impact of the proposed technology by focusing a wide variety of customer segments including lithium companies, battery industries, automobiles, oil companies, produced water companies, and medical stake holders. Through the customer discovery process, the team was able to identify the potential commercial impact of the technology for customer segments in oil companies, lithium producers, and produced water purification services as they are the largest producers of brines or providing services for purification and analysis of brines. Based on these discoveries, we have determined the value proposition to be low operation cost, high lithium recovery and less time consumption. The customer discovery enabled us to understand the technology challenges, needs, and improvement in current lithium technologies.          Last Modified: 07/06/2020       Submitted by: Hemali Rathnayake]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
