<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Customer Discovery for Microwave Assisted Pasteurization</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is that this technology will strongly impact the commercial production, distribution and retailing of a number of food products which have frequently been impacted due to contamination by food-borne pathogens, causing various diseases and illnesses. In recent years, consumer foods in high demand such as eggs, oyster, avocado, tomatoes, melons, and berries have been subject to expensive and wasteful recall.  This technology will bring about a significant reduction in the numbers of recalls for various foods and also help in ensuring food safety and security of various food products and produces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project will further develop a microwave assisted pasteurization process that advances the use of microwaves to solve food safety problems. Due to their rich nutritive value and high-water activity, shell eggs, oysters and fresh produce are potential hosts and carriers of pathogenic microorganisms like Salmonella species. Heat pasteurization is the best solution for controlling these pathogens but affects the vital functional properties due to biochemical changes. Therefore, microwave heating was considered for pasteurization. Products like shell eggs are ideal candidates for this volumetric heating technology as the pasteurization process requires a higher temperature in the yolk and a lower temperature in the white. This microwave pasteurization process renders pathogens undetectable without affecting raw food characteristics significantly. Based on the optimal parameters obtained by simulations, non-linear slotted waveguide applicators for heating food products were designed and a prototype was built. The applicator consisted of a standard waveguide with an array of non-linear slots. The process parameters for different food products were optimized and found suitable for industrial application.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1935369</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Satyanarayan</FirstName>
<LastName>Dev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Satyanarayan Dev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>satyanarayan.dev@famu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8502964336</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000700706</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University</Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<ZipCode>323073200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8505993531</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 Lee Hall Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[400 Foote-Hilyer Admin Center]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>623751831</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Microsystems First Incorporated]]></Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323014547</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1030, East Lafayette Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Due to their rich nutritive value and high-water activity, shell eggs, oysters and fresh produce are potential hosts and carriers of pathogenic microorganisms like <em>Salmonella species</em>. Heat pasteurization is the best solution for controlling these pathogens but affects the vital functional properties due to protein denaturation and other biochemical changes. Therefore, microwave heating was considered for pasteurization.</p> <p>Products like shell eggs are ideal candidates for this volumetric heating technology as the pasteurization process requires a higher temperature in the yolk and a lower temperature in the white. This microwave pasteurization process directly addresses all elements of pathogen contamination without affecting raw food characteristics significantly. Based on the optimal parameters obtained by simulations, non-linear slotted waveguide applicators for heating food products were designed and a prototype was built. The applicator consisted of a standard waveguide with an array of non-linear slots. The issue of non-uniformity in microwave heating was overcome by optimizing the power density used for the process and/or by rotating the product during the heating process. The process parameters for different food products were optimized</p> <p>This technology will strongly impact the commercial production, distribution and retailing of a number of food products which have frequently been impacted due to contamination by food-borne pathogens, causing various diseases and illnesses. In recent years, consumer foods in high demand such as eggs, oyster, avocado, tomatoes, melons, and berries have been subject to expensive and wasteful recall, resulting in the need to destroy the foods, discover the source of contamination and disinfect the source of their production. This technology will also help in ensuring food safety and security of Raw Oysters and Chicken Eggs.</p> <p>Due to successful completion of this I-Corps Teams grant, it is expected that the outcomes will strengthen and sustain our new start-up business &ldquo;Microsystems&rdquo;. We had exclusively licensed the technology from Florida A&amp;M University and submit an SBIR proposal. A business model suitable for review by investors in egg and oyster ndustries was developed.</p> <p>The Funding through the NSF I-Corps Teams has enabled development of successful business model for commercializing this unique technology to enahmce food safety in the global shell fish and poutry egg indutries.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Satyanarayan&nbsp;Dev</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Due to their rich nutritive value and high-water activity, shell eggs, oysters and fresh produce are potential hosts and carriers of pathogenic microorganisms like Salmonella species. Heat pasteurization is the best solution for controlling these pathogens but affects the vital functional properties due to protein denaturation and other biochemical changes. Therefore, microwave heating was considered for pasteurization.  Products like shell eggs are ideal candidates for this volumetric heating technology as the pasteurization process requires a higher temperature in the yolk and a lower temperature in the white. This microwave pasteurization process directly addresses all elements of pathogen contamination without affecting raw food characteristics significantly. Based on the optimal parameters obtained by simulations, non-linear slotted waveguide applicators for heating food products were designed and a prototype was built. The applicator consisted of a standard waveguide with an array of non-linear slots. The issue of non-uniformity in microwave heating was overcome by optimizing the power density used for the process and/or by rotating the product during the heating process. The process parameters for different food products were optimized  This technology will strongly impact the commercial production, distribution and retailing of a number of food products which have frequently been impacted due to contamination by food-borne pathogens, causing various diseases and illnesses. In recent years, consumer foods in high demand such as eggs, oyster, avocado, tomatoes, melons, and berries have been subject to expensive and wasteful recall, resulting in the need to destroy the foods, discover the source of contamination and disinfect the source of their production. This technology will also help in ensuring food safety and security of Raw Oysters and Chicken Eggs.  Due to successful completion of this I-Corps Teams grant, it is expected that the outcomes will strengthen and sustain our new start-up business "Microsystems". We had exclusively licensed the technology from Florida A&amp;M University and submit an SBIR proposal. A business model suitable for review by investors in egg and oyster ndustries was developed.  The Funding through the NSF I-Corps Teams has enabled development of successful business model for commercializing this unique technology to enahmce food safety in the global shell fish and poutry egg indutries.       Last Modified: 02/28/2021       Submitted by: Satyanarayan Dev]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
