<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Support: 2020 Manufacturing Science and Engineering Conference and 48th North American Manufacturing Research Conference; Cincinnati, Ohio; June 22-26, 2020</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49920.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49920</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Wells</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>awells@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927225</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports 78 graduate and undergraduate students studying at US institutions to participate in the co-located conference event consisting of the 2020 International Manufacturing Science and Engineering Conference sponsored by the American Society of Mechanical Engineers and the 48th Annual North American Manufacturing Research Conference sponsored by the North American Manufacturing Research Institution of the Society of Manufacturing Engineers. These two leading conferences in the Manufacturing Engineering field act as global bridges between industries, government laboratories, and academic institutions. The award provides student participants with opportunities to exchange ideas with leading researchers and engineers from worldwide industrial and governmental facilities, as well as with students and faculty from both domestic and international engineering schools. In addition to nurturing a global manufacturing vision, participants will learn the latest research areas and results in manufacturing fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will provide support for conference registration and accommodation for student attendees. The call for student support applications will be disseminated through postings on main conference websites, promulgation through conference organizers, track chairs, and symposium organizers, and direct communication with students involved in poster session, student design competition and student author research presentation competition. The submitted applications go through a selection process by the conference committee. The eligibility criteria to receive the funding include (1) students must be from US institutions and (2) students must be actively participating in the conference through presenting a paper or poster, or participating in a competition, with preference given to students from underrepresented minorities. After the conference, the list of student awardees will be announced on the main conference website, in the Manufacturing Science and Engineering 2019 post-conference report in the Manufacturing Engineering Division's Newsletter, and in the Award and Recognition section on the North American Manufacturing Research Institution's website. This award will enable these students to improve their knowledge of manufacturing technologies, and help them to become engineers and researchers to lead the next generation of US manufacturing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1937049</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arif</FirstName>
<LastName>Malik</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arif S Malik</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>arif.malik@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728834550</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000283586</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800188161</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT DALLAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Dallas]]></Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 W. Campbell Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>088Y</Code>
<Text>AM-Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~49920</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
