<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: Applications to Interviews (A2I) - Preparing for the Faculty Job Market</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47355.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>47355</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dana L. Denick</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddenick@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928866</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Construction engineering and management faculty nationwide lack diversity, which reflects the construction industry. Research documents that students are more likely to pursue careers where they have visible role models. Beyond the lack of visible role models of the same race and/or gender, however, research also documents that females and other underrepresented minorities tend to have fewer and shorter meetings with their PhD advisors. Therefore, these students may not receive the same support as they prepare application materials for faculty positions. By extension, these same students may be under-prepared for the interview process. A preliminary review of recent construction engineering and management faculty searches at one university reveals that while women and underrepresented minorities might be short-listed for phone interviews, they do not receive invitations for campus interviews at the same rate as their majority male colleagues. The Applications to Interviews (A2I) workshop intends to address the interview preparation gap for women and underrepresented PhD students considering faculty careers in construction engineering and management. The workshop provides a unique and interactive forum for sharing and discussing motivations for pursuing faculty positions, as well as strategies to successfully prepare to apply and interview for such positions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The A2I workshop will be held at Arizona State University in conjunction with the Construction Research Congress (CRC) 2020 Conference. Participants include Ph.D. students as well as junior and senior faculty in construction engineering programs from a variety of institution types ranging from two-year colleges and research extensive universities to Historically Black Colleges and Universities and Tribal Colleges and Universities. A focus will be to recruit participants from historically underrepresented groups in construction engineering and management. Small group activities and panel discussions will be used to facilitate professional development related to applying and interviewing for faculty positions. Near-peer mentoring between junior faculty and PhD students will catalyze the interest in, and pursuit of, faculty positions as well as the formation of professional networks. Engaging a more diverse faculty is a critical step to attract underrepresented undergraduate and graduate students to construction engineering and management programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1938600</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristen</FirstName>
<LastName>Parrish</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristen Parrish</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Kristen.Parrish@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809655479</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620863</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>EDA-Eng Diversity Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~47355</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project, the PI sought to increase the interest in, and pursuit of, faculty positions in construction engineering and management by women and underrepresented minorities. To achieve this objective, the PI organized a workshop, <em>Applications to Interviews (A2I),</em> that leveraged small groups and panel discussions, alongside near-peer mentoring. The A2I workshop was hosted in conjunction with the 2020 Construction Research Congress, the premier international conference for Construction Engineering and Management. Forty (40) people attended the workshop: 28 graduate students, 7 junior faculty, and 5 senior faculty.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The most significant result of the A2I workshop is that the workshop improved construction engineering and management graduate students? confidence in their ability to prepare faculty application materials. Of the 27 respondents to the post-workshop survey, 20 report that their confidence improved (n=9) or improved quite a bit (n=20). Graduate students and junior faculty both reported that the senior faculty panel was a highlight of the workshop, and all 27 respondents to the survey reported that they would attend another A2I workshop were it offered in the future. Graduate student workshop attendees also suggested that they be given more time to work with junior faculty on their specific faculty application materials. Based on this feedback, the PI suggests that future workshop organizers consider pre-recording a session on developing the various elements of the application package (i.e., the cover letter; the CV; and the research, teaching, and diversity statements) and then requiring that workshop attendees submit these materials prior to the workshop for peer review.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Beyond the impact on the students and faculty that participated in the A2I workshop, the PI sought to support developing a more diverse faculty nationwide by empowering women and underrepresented minorities to apply for, and secure, faculty positions in construction engineering and management. In turn, this would contribute to a faculty that is more representative of the communities served by the construction engineering and management programs in higher education nationwide, as well as by the construction industry. This workshop was a first step in further developing a more diverse construction faculty, and subsequently, a more diverse population of students and practitioners in construction, as the workshop offered a diverse group of graduate students and junior faculty the opportunity to develop their own academic career paths. To support replication of this workshop, materials have been made available on dropbox (https://www.dropbox.com/sh/meypggbon08ooo7/AACe4d1laY0vT1QjjaNmhTcUa?dl=0).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/25/2021<br>      Modified by: Kristen&nbsp;Parrish</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1938600/1938600_10635680_1616713422387_IMG_7896--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1938600/1938600_10635680_1616713422387_IMG_7896--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Reviewing materials with junior faculty"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1938600/1938600_10635680_1616713422387_IMG_7896--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Reviewing materials with junior faculty"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Assistant Professor Rebekah Burke reviews application materials with A2I workshop participants.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kristen Parrish</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kristen&nbsp;Parrish</div> <div class="imageTitle">Reviewing materials with junior faculty</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1938600/1938600_10635680_1616713527717_IMG_7899--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1938600/1938600_10635680_1616713527717_IMG_7899--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mock phone interviews"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1938600/1938600_10635680_1616713527717_IMG_7899--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mock phone interviews"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Dr. Evan Bingham prepares a group of PhD students for the phone interview stage of the faculty  application process</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kristen Parrish</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kristen&nbsp;Parrish</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mock phone interviews</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project, the PI sought to increase the interest in, and pursuit of, faculty positions in construction engineering and management by women and underrepresented minorities. To achieve this objective, the PI organized a workshop, Applications to Interviews (A2I), that leveraged small groups and panel discussions, alongside near-peer mentoring. The A2I workshop was hosted in conjunction with the 2020 Construction Research Congress, the premier international conference for Construction Engineering and Management. Forty (40) people attended the workshop: 28 graduate students, 7 junior faculty, and 5 senior faculty.     The most significant result of the A2I workshop is that the workshop improved construction engineering and management graduate students? confidence in their ability to prepare faculty application materials. Of the 27 respondents to the post-workshop survey, 20 report that their confidence improved (n=9) or improved quite a bit (n=20). Graduate students and junior faculty both reported that the senior faculty panel was a highlight of the workshop, and all 27 respondents to the survey reported that they would attend another A2I workshop were it offered in the future. Graduate student workshop attendees also suggested that they be given more time to work with junior faculty on their specific faculty application materials. Based on this feedback, the PI suggests that future workshop organizers consider pre-recording a session on developing the various elements of the application package (i.e., the cover letter; the CV; and the research, teaching, and diversity statements) and then requiring that workshop attendees submit these materials prior to the workshop for peer review.      Beyond the impact on the students and faculty that participated in the A2I workshop, the PI sought to support developing a more diverse faculty nationwide by empowering women and underrepresented minorities to apply for, and secure, faculty positions in construction engineering and management. In turn, this would contribute to a faculty that is more representative of the communities served by the construction engineering and management programs in higher education nationwide, as well as by the construction industry. This workshop was a first step in further developing a more diverse construction faculty, and subsequently, a more diverse population of students and practitioners in construction, as the workshop offered a diverse group of graduate students and junior faculty the opportunity to develop their own academic career paths. To support replication of this workshop, materials have been made available on dropbox (https://www.dropbox.com/sh/meypggbon08ooo7/AACe4d1laY0vT1QjjaNmhTcUa?dl=0).          Last Modified: 03/25/2021       Submitted by: Kristen Parrish]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
