<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  A Novel Device Alternative to Temporary Ostomies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to improve the care and quality of life of colon cancer patients by reducing or eliminating the need for temporary ostomies, saving $25+ k per patient in direct surgical costs and eliminating $8.5 k per patient in annual maintenance costs; this could generate total savings of $60 k per patient treated. The proposed solution could address the need for temporary ostomy surgery; this procedure is performed 300,000+ times per year in the US.  This system would reduce the risks of bowel leakage after colon resections, a problem occurring in roughly 36% of patients and generating fatal consequences in 22%. More importantly, the technology has the potential to dramatically reduce or eliminate the morbidity and mortality from ostomies and improve a patient’s quality of life.   The research and development of a reliable, reversible, and cost-effective means to protect segments of bowel has broader implications and potential applications to treating a number of disease conditions, such as Crohn’s disease, ulcerative colitis, diverticulitis, ischemic bowel disease, bowel trauma, and even early colon cancer.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will develop a system to reduce diverting ostomies, which are often placed above the reconnection site to protect against leaks and their consequences. This project will develop an intraluminal fecal diversion technology using a novel anchoring mechanism that is safe, reliable, and easily reversible.  The goal of this project is to optimize the design of both the device and clinical treatment algorithms for design, safety, and use; and validate the new design and protocols in subsequent animal studies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1938482</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenton</FirstName>
<LastName>Fong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenton D Fong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kenton.fong@savagemed.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507996298</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000719625</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Savage Medical Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Belmont</CityName>
<ZipCode>940022235</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507996298</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2622 Belmont Canyon Rd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080183596</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAVAGE MEDICAL INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Savage Medical Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>940021023</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Savage Medical&rsquo;s SBIR Phase I award supported the development of a novel medical device to protect the colon after surgery, potentially eliminating the need for temporary ostomies. The award supported end user needs understanding and design input, prototype testing, and manufacturing process development of a device that meets the requirements of the &nbsp;identified end user, namely patients with colorectal cancer and colon surgeons. The award allowed for the manufacturing of a testable devices that were then used in animal studies to prove feasibility of the technology and informed further revisions of the device design. The function, usability, and preliminary safety of the technology was established during this award. Support was also provided for testing and creating of custom tooling required for larger scale manufacturing of the medical device. With the help of this award, the technology was developed to the point where it is now ready to begin the necessary regulatory testing required for human use through an FDA Investigational Device Exemption trial.The successful development of the supported medical device will have a dramatic impact on surgical outcomes and quality of life of patients who undergo rectal cancer resection surgery by eliminating the high morbidity, mortality, and psychological burden of a diverting ostomy. This translates into a health care cost savings of around $60,000 per patient treated. Development of the supported technology also has the ability to be a platform technology that can be used to treat many other diseases that benefit from temporary fecal diversion such as diverticulitis, inflammatory bowel disease (Crohn&rsquo;s and Ulcerative Colitis), Ischemic Bowel Disease, and perianal/perineal wounds with a total market impact of $6.4 Billion.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/18/2021<br>      Modified by: Kenton&nbsp;D&nbsp;Fong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Savage Medical’s SBIR Phase I award supported the development of a novel medical device to protect the colon after surgery, potentially eliminating the need for temporary ostomies. The award supported end user needs understanding and design input, prototype testing, and manufacturing process development of a device that meets the requirements of the  identified end user, namely patients with colorectal cancer and colon surgeons. The award allowed for the manufacturing of a testable devices that were then used in animal studies to prove feasibility of the technology and informed further revisions of the device design. The function, usability, and preliminary safety of the technology was established during this award. Support was also provided for testing and creating of custom tooling required for larger scale manufacturing of the medical device. With the help of this award, the technology was developed to the point where it is now ready to begin the necessary regulatory testing required for human use through an FDA Investigational Device Exemption trial.The successful development of the supported medical device will have a dramatic impact on surgical outcomes and quality of life of patients who undergo rectal cancer resection surgery by eliminating the high morbidity, mortality, and psychological burden of a diverting ostomy. This translates into a health care cost savings of around $60,000 per patient treated. Development of the supported technology also has the ability to be a platform technology that can be used to treat many other diseases that benefit from temporary fecal diversion such as diverticulitis, inflammatory bowel disease (Crohn’s and Ulcerative Colitis), Ischemic Bowel Disease, and perianal/perineal wounds with a total market impact of $6.4 Billion.           Last Modified: 03/18/2021       Submitted by: Kenton D Fong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
