<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Fifth International Colloquium on Nonlinear Dynamics and Control of Deep Drilling Systems; College Park, Maryland; 1-3 June 2020</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47559.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>47559</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Landers</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rlanders@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922652</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant will provide 40 attendees, several of whom are from under-represented groups, the opportunity to participate in the Fifth International Colloquium on Nonlinear Dynamics and Control of Deep Drilling Systems, in College Park, Maryland, 1-3 June 2020, where they will attend technical presentations and participate in a panel session on the future of deep drilling. The lecture sets will focus on the following emerging topics in deep drilling systems: modeling of drill strings through analysis, experiments, and computations, nonlinear dynamics of drill strings, and the control of drill strings. The participants will address challenges arising in the context of stick-slip dynamics, nonlinear modeling of directional drilling, state-dependent delay effects, and control schemes based on partial differential systems. Discussions will be undertaken on the problems faced in the field and developments that can be pursued to address them, as well as current and future directions associated with horizontal drilling and deep water drilling. The colloquium will serve as an opportunity to expose graduate students, post-doctoral researchers, and junior faculty to complex problems involving nonlinear dynamics and nonlinear control, as well as approaches and methodologies used in the deep drilling systems industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This colloquium could provide ways in which modeling, nonlinear dynamics, and nonlinear control can be used to tackle challenges faced in practice, beyond the considered application of deep drilling systems. Examples of other areas include those that involve flexible rotors and other distributed parameter systems, and manufacturing. In addition to 30 technical experts, 10 students, post-doctoral researchers, and junior faculty members, in particular, minorities and underrepresented groups, will be invited to participate in this colloquium to introduce them to the field as well as encourage their participation in future efforts. This colloquium is expected to be an exceptional learning experience for them. Furthermore, this colloquium can serve as a template for future colloquia and workshops involving academia and industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1939324</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Balakumar</FirstName>
<LastName>Balachandran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Balakumar Balachandran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>balab@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014055309</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000246233</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207423035</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Department of Mechanical Eng.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD"</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>Dynamics, Control and System D</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8024</Code>
<Text>Complex Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~47559</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
