<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Student Travel Grant for 2019 International Symposium on Networks-on-Chip (NOCS2019)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Brunvand</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ebrunvan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922767</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This travel grant provides support for up to 15 US-based students to attend the 13th ACM/IEEE 2019 International Symposium on Networks-on-Chip (NOCS2019), to be held in New York City, October 17-18, 2019. For over 10 years, NOCS has been a forum for innovative research in networks-on-chip (NoC) architectures. The event is dedicated to interdisciplinary research on on-chip, package-scale, chip-to-chip, and data center rack-scale communication technology, architecture, design methods, applications and systems, the NOCS 2019 will bring together scientists and engineers, as well as the best and brightest of the PhD candidates, working on NoC innovations and applications from inter-related research communities, including discrete optimization and algorithms, computer architecture, networking, circuits and systems, packaging, embedded systems, and design automation. The goal of NOCS 2019 and this travel grant is to advance the science of network design by bringing together researchers from across the computer engineering community and to foster cross disciplinary approaches that address shared research challenges. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This travel grant will enable career development and learning opportunities for US-based and/or US citizen graduate students. Attending the NOCS conference could significantly contribute to the career path of students interested in system-level and network design challenges. Students have the opportunity to discuss leading edge research with world-class researchers in science of network design, as well as help them establish connections and mentoring relationships that will serve them well during their research careers. This project aims at increasing the participation of students from underrepresented groups and those from smaller institutions of education and provide them with equal opportunities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1939961</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Bogdan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul B Bogdan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pbogdan@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137407762</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000639281</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3720 South Flower Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Network-on-Chip (NoC) is an enabling methodology to integrate many embedded cores or processing elements on a single die. NoC has emerged as the de-facto mechanism to provide a scalable and energy efficient interconnection infrastructure for multicore chips. It is an interdisciplinary research area spanning across the fields of computer architecture, embedded systems, networking, digital communications, complex networks,machine learning, artificial intelligence, optimization, control systems, etc. Multi-core processing platforms have emerged to meet the performance needs of many important applications such as graphics, financial and scientific modeling, biomonitoring, national security scanning, intelligent transportation, networking, computational biology, multimedia and wireless infrastructure. These diverse applications will benefit from the efficient on-chip communication network. During the last decade and particularly in the last ten years, this area has produced a prodigious amount of knowledge that requires a forum like the NOCS for discussion, dissemination and collection of ideas.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The International Symposium on Networks-on-Chip (NOCS) is the premier event dedicated to interdisciplinary research on on-chip, chipscale, and multichip package scale communication technology, architecture, design methods, applications and systems. NOCS brings together scientists and engineers working on NoC innovations and applications from inter-related research communities, including computer architecture, networking, circuits and systems, packaging, embedded systems, and design automation. NOCS has established itself as the premier conference in this area. With these funds we provided travel grants to students, who were not able to attend NOCS and take advantage of the available learning opportunities in this evolving research area.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The grant allowed students interested in architecture, networks, circuit design, software, and applications, to find useful information on the topics of their choice. It also provided an excellent opportunity for many students nation-wide to get familiar with and engage in a new research area of national importance.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2020<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;B&nbsp;Bogdan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Network-on-Chip (NoC) is an enabling methodology to integrate many embedded cores or processing elements on a single die. NoC has emerged as the de-facto mechanism to provide a scalable and energy efficient interconnection infrastructure for multicore chips. It is an interdisciplinary research area spanning across the fields of computer architecture, embedded systems, networking, digital communications, complex networks,machine learning, artificial intelligence, optimization, control systems, etc. Multi-core processing platforms have emerged to meet the performance needs of many important applications such as graphics, financial and scientific modeling, biomonitoring, national security scanning, intelligent transportation, networking, computational biology, multimedia and wireless infrastructure. These diverse applications will benefit from the efficient on-chip communication network. During the last decade and particularly in the last ten years, this area has produced a prodigious amount of knowledge that requires a forum like the NOCS for discussion, dissemination and collection of ideas.     The International Symposium on Networks-on-Chip (NOCS) is the premier event dedicated to interdisciplinary research on on-chip, chipscale, and multichip package scale communication technology, architecture, design methods, applications and systems. NOCS brings together scientists and engineers working on NoC innovations and applications from inter-related research communities, including computer architecture, networking, circuits and systems, packaging, embedded systems, and design automation. NOCS has established itself as the premier conference in this area. With these funds we provided travel grants to students, who were not able to attend NOCS and take advantage of the available learning opportunities in this evolving research area.     The grant allowed students interested in architecture, networks, circuit design, software, and applications, to find useful information on the topics of their choice. It also provided an excellent opportunity for many students nation-wide to get familiar with and engage in a new research area of national importance.       Last Modified: 12/01/2020       Submitted by: Paul B Bogdan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
