<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Human Variance and Assessment for Learning Implications for Diverse Learners of STEM, A National Conference</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99920.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>118303</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gavin Fulmer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gfulmer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925182</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The conference purpose is to stimulate a national conversation concerning the relationships between assessment, teaching and learning that include scholarly research and development of tests; members of city and state boards of education; officials from states and major school systems; policymakers; and representatives of teachers' associations and parents' associations. This conference aims to attract these important professionals has important co-sponsors like the Urban Institute. This national conference flows from the work of the Gordon Commission on the Future of Assessment for Education that addressed the advancement of achievement in STEM disciplines (PRE-K - 12) for students who are underrepresented among high achieving students. This issue of advancement of underrepresented high achieving students has received little concentrated effort and a conference would help in providing greater understanding of this special concern, which includes a student in poverty in complexed family structures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will attract thought leaders, policy makers, supervisors of practice and scholars of measurement science to be informed of emerging thought and developments and to discuss selected models for the implementation of new ways of generating and utilizing data from education tests. The conference will stimulate national conversation and ultimately a market that demands educational assessments that inform and improve teaching and learning transactions. The conference will be organized around four conceptual and theoretical papers that focus on the knowledge base upon which six concurrent workshops will be based. The four papers are: (1) Human Diversity and Assessment; (2) The Limits of Test Bias and Its Corrections; (3) Towards an Assessment Science Capable of Informing and Improving Learning; and  (4) Assessment in the Service of Learning. The workshops will focus on models of pedagogical practice that show promise for informing and improving teaching and learning processes and their outcomes. These issues will be discussed by 11-15 expert presenters who understand student learning and the types of information gleaned from different types of assessments. The attention to URMs and their needs and contexts are prioritized in discussions surrounding measurement science and the integration of assessment. Several important issues that address understanding of student learning, and the relationship between the varieties of information concerning students that can be accessed through assessments are: (1)The importance of the broader and more productive use of educational testing to improve the learning of STEM subject matter and values;(2) Curriculum embedded assessment and the reduction in disparities in achievement by STEM learners from diverse social divisions;(3)Innovative procedures and programs for the use of data concerning learners and teaching and learning transactions in the teaching and learning of STEM with learners who are underrepresented among high achieving STEM learners.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Discovery Research K-12 program (DRK-12) seeks to significantly enhance the learning and teaching of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) by preK-12 students and teachers, through research and development of innovative resources, models and tools. Projects in the DRK-12 program build on fundamental research in STEM education and prior research and development efforts that provide theoretical and empirical justification for proposed projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1939192</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edmund</FirstName>
<LastName>Gordon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edmund W Gordon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eg379@tc.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126783413</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000250316</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Teachers College, Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276625</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126783000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>525 West 120th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Box 151]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071050983</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEACHERS COLLEGE, COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071050983</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Teachers College, Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276696</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[525 West 120th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0419</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~99920</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~18383</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This packet consists primarily with a public conference intended to make available to a scholarly and professional service community information concerning the relationship of diverse human characteristics to STEM education and its assessment. Papers in the conference were directed at making the case for pedagogical attention to the ways in which learners differ and the necessity for assessing these learners in ways that better inform pedagogical intervention.<br /><br />Moving from a widely accepted notion that learners come to learning situations with different needs and characteristics, the conference opened with the unfortunate fact that the strongest traditions in assessment have produced limited amounts of information concerning learners that could be used to better inform the management of teaching and learning transactions.<br /><br />The second portion of the conference consisted of models for about a half-dozen educational programs that are in the process of being developed which try to address these problems. In most instances, these experimental models seek to embed in the instructional process assessment probes that are either instructive - that, is, they actually teach something to the learners - or descriptive of the manner in which the learner is seeking to learn. The idea behind these models as a group is that the assessment process and measurement science can contribute to the cultivation of abilities as well to their measurement.<br /><br />The third segment of the conference featured a panel of practitioners who work in a variety of educational settings, including community colleges, museums, student support organizations, universities, and public high schools. The panelists considered modes of assessment for STEM learning across diverse educational environments with consideration given to multiple sources of evidence practitioners bring into the service of learning.<br /><br />The principal findings of this study are that human diversity in STEM pedagogy should be concerned with driving attention to the importance of the functional characteristics of learners. Traditionally, education has tended to classify learners by demographic characteristics. This work calls our attention to the fact that the ways in which learners function are the grist for the mill of teaching and learning transactions. The second finding of this study is that although educational assessments were intentionally designed to determine learner status, advances in the field are progressively enabling measurement information to be used to inform and actually impact outcomes for the learner.<br /><br />The initial findings of this study were generated with and communicated to participants at the Human Variance and Assessment for Learning conference held at Teachers College, Columbia University on November 1st, 2019. This Final Report includes these findings as well as conference proceedings authored by the Primary Investigator which seek to make publicly accessible the conceptual framework and rubber-meets-road examples of it in a variety of classroom settings. The results will also be shared with a broad audience of academics, researchers, and practitioners, and especially those affiliating with social justice organizations, some of which provided logistical support for the conference and delegated representatives to open and conclude grant-related events.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/02/2021<br>      Modified by: Edmund&nbsp;W&nbsp;Gordon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1939192/1939192_10622463_1614708409557_HumanVarianceConferenceAgenda-Final--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1939192/1939192_10622463_1614708409557_HumanVarianceConferenceAgenda-Final--rgov-800width.jpg" title="HV&amp;AfL Conference Agenda"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1939192/1939192_10622463_1614708409557_HumanVarianceConferenceAgenda-Final--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="HV&amp;AfL Conference Agenda"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Agenda for the November 1, 2019 "Human Variance and Assessment For Learning: Implications for Diverse Learners of STEM" Conference held at Teachers College, Columbia University</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonthon Coulson</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Edmund&nbsp;W&nbsp;Gordon</div> <div class="imageTitle">HV&AfL Conference Agenda</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This packet consists primarily with a public conference intended to make available to a scholarly and professional service community information concerning the relationship of diverse human characteristics to STEM education and its assessment. Papers in the conference were directed at making the case for pedagogical attention to the ways in which learners differ and the necessity for assessing these learners in ways that better inform pedagogical intervention.  Moving from a widely accepted notion that learners come to learning situations with different needs and characteristics, the conference opened with the unfortunate fact that the strongest traditions in assessment have produced limited amounts of information concerning learners that could be used to better inform the management of teaching and learning transactions.  The second portion of the conference consisted of models for about a half-dozen educational programs that are in the process of being developed which try to address these problems. In most instances, these experimental models seek to embed in the instructional process assessment probes that are either instructive - that, is, they actually teach something to the learners - or descriptive of the manner in which the learner is seeking to learn. The idea behind these models as a group is that the assessment process and measurement science can contribute to the cultivation of abilities as well to their measurement.  The third segment of the conference featured a panel of practitioners who work in a variety of educational settings, including community colleges, museums, student support organizations, universities, and public high schools. The panelists considered modes of assessment for STEM learning across diverse educational environments with consideration given to multiple sources of evidence practitioners bring into the service of learning.  The principal findings of this study are that human diversity in STEM pedagogy should be concerned with driving attention to the importance of the functional characteristics of learners. Traditionally, education has tended to classify learners by demographic characteristics. This work calls our attention to the fact that the ways in which learners function are the grist for the mill of teaching and learning transactions. The second finding of this study is that although educational assessments were intentionally designed to determine learner status, advances in the field are progressively enabling measurement information to be used to inform and actually impact outcomes for the learner.  The initial findings of this study were generated with and communicated to participants at the Human Variance and Assessment for Learning conference held at Teachers College, Columbia University on November 1st, 2019. This Final Report includes these findings as well as conference proceedings authored by the Primary Investigator which seek to make publicly accessible the conceptual framework and rubber-meets-road examples of it in a variety of classroom settings. The results will also be shared with a broad audience of academics, researchers, and practitioners, and especially those affiliating with social justice organizations, some of which provided logistical support for the conference and delegated representatives to open and conclude grant-related events.       Last Modified: 03/02/2021       Submitted by: Edmund W Gordon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
