<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Evaluating Impact of Student Debt on Early Career Choices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>193065.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>193065</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brian Humes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhumes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927284</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The U.S. scientific community and industry groups have observed that the United States is not producing&lt;br/&gt;sufficient numbers of skilled native workers to meet demand, especially in the physical sciences,&lt;br/&gt;computer science, and engineering fields that drive innovation. Merit-based aid, for example,&lt;br/&gt;scholarships and fellowships, reduces both the immediate cost to students of investing in higher&lt;br/&gt;education, and students' longer-term risk of high cumulative student debt loads after graduation. This&lt;br/&gt;project will evaluate both efficacy and consequences of merit awards for increasing&lt;br/&gt;retention of women and racial/ethnic minority students in STEM degree programs, and in the scientific&lt;br/&gt;workforce after graduation. The project examines the extent of any observed effects of merit aid&lt;br/&gt;on underrepresented students' early career choices are specifically due to reducing students' risk of higher&lt;br/&gt;cumulative debt. This research aims to inform policies and institutional strategies to retain U.S. students&lt;br/&gt;and graduates in science and engineering careers. In addition, because graduates in scientific and&lt;br/&gt;technical fields also have greater expected lifetime earnings, encouraging broader participation in these&lt;br/&gt;fields by historically underrepresented racial/ethnic minorities, first-generation college students, and other&lt;br/&gt;economically-disadvantaged individuals may help to address persistent and growing socioeconomic&lt;br/&gt;inequality.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will employ linear and nonlinear econometric estimation for causal inference, leveraging two&lt;br/&gt;existing data sources. First, using newly-developed institutional administrative data from a large&lt;br/&gt;public Minority-Serving Institution with student-level observations matched to publicly available&lt;br/&gt;statistical data, the project will assess whether income-contingent merit aid in particular, the U.S.&lt;br/&gt;Department of Education SMART grants, or prior community college or associate's degree transfer&lt;br/&gt;credit affected STEM degree completion among observably STEM-interested undergraduate students.&lt;br/&gt;Then, using longitudinal survey data under restricted-use license from the NSF National Center for&lt;br/&gt;Science and Engineering Statistics, the project will estimate the influence of different higher education&lt;br/&gt;funding mechanisms on students' cumulative debt load at graduation, and further whether higher&lt;br/&gt;cumulative student debt deters recent graduates in STEM fields from pursuing science and engineering&lt;br/&gt;occupations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1940736</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
<LastName>Blume-Kohout</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Margaret E Blume-Kohout</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mblumeko@gettysburg.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5053820826</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000543280</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gettysburg College</Name>
<CityName>Gettysburg</CityName>
<ZipCode>173251483</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7173376505</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>North Washington Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071445134</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GETTYSBURG COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071445134</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gettysburg College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>173251483</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SciSIP-Sci of Sci Innov Policy</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8800</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE RESOURCES STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~193065</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
