<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: Applications of Machine Learning to Experimental Mechanics and Materials; Arlington, Virginia; 24-25 September 2019</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49981.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49981</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nakhiah Goulbourne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ngoulbou@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927715</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant supports a workshop to explore the use of machine learning with experimental mechanics and materials. The rapid development of new materials with complex processing and structure, along with the emergence of new and potent computer-assisted experimental methods for materials and mechanical characterization have led to challenges in effectively and efficiently analyzing very large data sets in order to determine the important parameters that control the overall mechanical behavior. While established and detailed methodologies, grounded on materials physics and mechanics, serve as the foundation to evaluate and design new classes of materials with desirable mechanical properties, Data Science driven approaches for rapid assessment of important problem parameters could accelerate materials development and facilitate transitions through rapid processes for identifying structure-mechanical properties relationships from large experimental and modeling data sets. Such capabilities can impact new and emerging manufacturing methods, e.g. additive manufacturing, help us to understand complex processes in biological material systems, and finally accelerate the design of mechanically robust material systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop aims at connecting mechanicians with researchers in the Data Sciences field for a dialogue that could open new avenues in the field of mechanics of materials, with special emphasis on the application of machine learning to experimental mechanics. It will bring together researchers who engage in new, multimodal, experimental methods in mechanics, with early adopters of machine learning tools in the fields of materials and mechanics, and leaders from the machine learning community. The workshop aims at developing a long term perspective for the introduction of Data Science methods to the field of mechanics of materials. Therefore, a specific aim is to assess the potential and the limitations of machine learning techniques in providing guidance and enhanced capabilities to quantify the contribution of the, often numerous and coupled, parameters governing the mechanics of complex materials and systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1940102</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ioannis</FirstName>
<LastName>Chasiotis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ioannis Chasiotis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chasioti@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172441474</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488327</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S. Wright St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>013E</Code>
<Text>MULTI-SCALE MODELING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>022E</Code>
<Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~49981</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In the last decade, Experimental Mechanics has made great strides in adding new techniques and methods to its inventory, which have provided full-field 2D and 3D data that are amenable to rigorous calculations and analysis. New instrumentation such as x-ray computed microtomography has contributed to an abundance of experimental data of material microstructure and deformation. When these data are coupled with computational tools, such as Digital Volume Correlation, a wealth of information can be extracted to derive local microstructure-property relationships.</p> <p>This one-and-a-half day NSF-sponsored workshop on <em>Applications of Machine Learning to Experimental Mechanics and Materials</em> (Westin Crystal City Hotel, Arlington, VA, November 6-7, 2019) aimed at connecting mechanicians with researchers in the broad field of Data Sciences to foster a dialog that could open new avenues in the field of mechanics and materials, with special emphasis in the application of Machine Learning (ML) to experimental mechanics. Specifically, the workshop identified <strong>(i)</strong> the potential impact of, and opportunities for, data sciences in mechanics, with an emphasis on integrating experimental and computational mechanics, and <strong>(ii)</strong> an immediate action plan to facilitate acceleration of the potential benefits of ML to mechanics of materials research.</p> <p>Members of the Academia and US National Laboratories convened with colleagues who were early adopters of ML as well as with leaders from the Data Sciences community. The workshop participants represented a diverse group of scientists and engineers from universities and research centers across the US, who were at different stages of their careers, as well as representatives from federal government funding agencies. The presenters were encouraged to discuss unpublished work and pose open-ended questions to stimulate the discussion both during their presentations and at the three break-out panel meetings at the end of the workshop.</p> <p>The workshop was structured around three topics:</p> <ol> </ol> <p><strong>1. Experiments with Complex Materials</strong>, that showcased the wealth of experimental information that is gathered today, and the potential and limitations of Big Data in Experimental Mechanics.<br /><strong>2. Data Sciences, Mechanics and Materials, </strong>that showcased examples of the application of Data Sciences to the broader field of mechanics and materials including computational materials science.<br /><strong>3. Data Sciences and Computational Mechanics</strong>, that highlighted success stories of the use of ML and Artificial Intelligence (AI) in fields of research that are related to Experimental Mechanics.</p> <ol> </ol> <p>Special emphasis was placed on open discussions and brainstorming among participants with very diverse technical backgrounds and different levels of expertise in ML. At the end of the workshop three panels convened and discussed the following topics:</p> <ol> </ol><ol> </ol> <p>1. Success examples, challenges and opportunities in the application of ML to experimental mechanics and materials.<br />2. Advancing ML through its application to mechanics of materials.<br />3. Open ended discussion: Opportunities in mechanics of materials enabled by ML.</p> <ol> </ol> <p>The recommendations provided by the panels were addressed to the NSF and, in general, to US Federal Agencies supporting research in experimental mechanics and, more broadly, mechanics and materials. Three key actionable items emerged from the consensus of the panels:</p> <ol> </ol> <p><strong></strong><strong>1. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Support the Development of ML Human Resources:</span></strong> Need to develop the skill set of young engineers, scientists and faculty through educational, training and Grand Challenge programs sponsored by the NSF and, in general, US Federal Agencies that fund research.<br /><strong></strong><strong>2. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Support the Development of ML Infrastructure:</span></strong> Need for accessible ML and AI infrastructure in the form of user-friendly codes and examples, as well as data repositories with benchmark data for training and learning purposes.<br /><strong></strong><strong>3. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Support Cross-disciplinary Collaborations:</span></strong> Support collaborative activities between experimental mechanicians and ML/Data Science experts to establish successful paradigms of the transition and application of ML tools to experimental mechanics.</p> <ol> </ol><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/02/2020<br>      Modified by: Ioannis&nbsp;Chasiotis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the last decade, Experimental Mechanics has made great strides in adding new techniques and methods to its inventory, which have provided full-field 2D and 3D data that are amenable to rigorous calculations and analysis. New instrumentation such as x-ray computed microtomography has contributed to an abundance of experimental data of material microstructure and deformation. When these data are coupled with computational tools, such as Digital Volume Correlation, a wealth of information can be extracted to derive local microstructure-property relationships.  This one-and-a-half day NSF-sponsored workshop on Applications of Machine Learning to Experimental Mechanics and Materials (Westin Crystal City Hotel, Arlington, VA, November 6-7, 2019) aimed at connecting mechanicians with researchers in the broad field of Data Sciences to foster a dialog that could open new avenues in the field of mechanics and materials, with special emphasis in the application of Machine Learning (ML) to experimental mechanics. Specifically, the workshop identified (i) the potential impact of, and opportunities for, data sciences in mechanics, with an emphasis on integrating experimental and computational mechanics, and (ii) an immediate action plan to facilitate acceleration of the potential benefits of ML to mechanics of materials research.  Members of the Academia and US National Laboratories convened with colleagues who were early adopters of ML as well as with leaders from the Data Sciences community. The workshop participants represented a diverse group of scientists and engineers from universities and research centers across the US, who were at different stages of their careers, as well as representatives from federal government funding agencies. The presenters were encouraged to discuss unpublished work and pose open-ended questions to stimulate the discussion both during their presentations and at the three break-out panel meetings at the end of the workshop.  The workshop was structured around three topics:    1. Experiments with Complex Materials, that showcased the wealth of experimental information that is gathered today, and the potential and limitations of Big Data in Experimental Mechanics. 2. Data Sciences, Mechanics and Materials, that showcased examples of the application of Data Sciences to the broader field of mechanics and materials including computational materials science. 3. Data Sciences and Computational Mechanics, that highlighted success stories of the use of ML and Artificial Intelligence (AI) in fields of research that are related to Experimental Mechanics.    Special emphasis was placed on open discussions and brainstorming among participants with very diverse technical backgrounds and different levels of expertise in ML. At the end of the workshop three panels convened and discussed the following topics:     1. Success examples, challenges and opportunities in the application of ML to experimental mechanics and materials. 2. Advancing ML through its application to mechanics of materials. 3. Open ended discussion: Opportunities in mechanics of materials enabled by ML.    The recommendations provided by the panels were addressed to the NSF and, in general, to US Federal Agencies supporting research in experimental mechanics and, more broadly, mechanics and materials. Three key actionable items emerged from the consensus of the panels:    1. Support the Development of ML Human Resources: Need to develop the skill set of young engineers, scientists and faculty through educational, training and Grand Challenge programs sponsored by the NSF and, in general, US Federal Agencies that fund research. 2. Support the Development of ML Infrastructure: Need for accessible ML and AI infrastructure in the form of user-friendly codes and examples, as well as data repositories with benchmark data for training and learning purposes. 3. Support Cross-disciplinary Collaborations: Support collaborative activities between experimental mechanicians and ML/Data Science experts to establish successful paradigms of the transition and application of ML tools to experimental mechanics.         Last Modified: 10/02/2020       Submitted by: Ioannis Chasiotis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
