<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CoPe Conference: Interoperability and data needs of models for understanding vulnerability of coastal systems to stresses and shocks associated with sea level rise: Miami, 2020</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99137.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99137</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ICER</Abbreviation>
<LongName>ICER</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Manda S. Adams</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amadams@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924708</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Projected environmental changes, including sea level rise and increased frequency and intensity of storm events, are leading to rapid departures from past trends. However, the ability to model, predict, and understand the impacts of these changes is extremely limited. This is especially of great concern for coastal cities with high population density, valuable properties and tax base, and extremely vulnerable and underserved communities. This is a complex problem requiring an integrated approach that accounts for potential physical, ecological and socioeconomic impacts of projected environmental change. Therefore, goal of this conference to bring together an interdisciplinary group of experts to develop an Integrated Environmental Modeling system. A single model cannot simulate every potential impact, so numerous models have been developed to address subsets of these effects. Conference participants will focus on developing an integrated approach by addressing the interoperability of the various models across social, ecological, and physical factors. The conference will include a diverse group of participants, with a specific emphasis on recruiting students and stakeholders from vulnerable, underserved communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Results based on model simulations play a pivotal role in understanding vulnerabilities of both natural and built environments in coastal regions. Land- based models that simulate flooding due to sea level rise, storm surge, waves, inland rainfall, and, in some cases, groundwater levels are maturing. Models for predicting economic losses due to property damage and service interruptions are also being developed. Discussions are also underway for how to model human behavior in coastal environments in the presence of increasing frequency of flooding that is expected from enhanced stresses and shocks due to projected environmental changes. This Coastlines and People conference will review the current state of each category of models, their requirements in terms of spatial and temporal resolution of information necessary for integrated assessment and, more importantly, develop an appropriate coastal observation system to test and improve the interoperability of these models. Conference participants will provide guidance on interoperability that can serve as a "standard of practice" among the modeling community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1940264</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Sukop</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael C Sukop</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sukopm@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053483117</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000211903</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tiffany</FirstName>
<LastName>Troxler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tiffany Troxler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>troxlert@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053481453</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000064512</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sparkle</FirstName>
<LastName>Malone</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sparkle L Malone</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smalone@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053481988</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000699842</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jayantha</FirstName>
<LastName>Obeysekera</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jayantha Obeysekera</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jobeysek@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5617229994</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000782265</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida International University</Name>
<CityName>Miami</CityName>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3053482494</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11200 SW 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MARC 430]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071298814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA INTERNATIONAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida International University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>097Y</Code>
<Text>CoPe-Coastlines and People</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~99137</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Coastlines and People Conference was designed to discuss observations and models associated with biophysical, social-behavioral, and economic systems in vulnerable coastal regions. Specifically, the workshop focused on understanding the interactions of biophysical, social-behavioral, and economic systems in coastal regions, explicitly defining new data gaps that can be addressed by nongovernmental, local, regional, and federal networks for the formulation of a comprehensive Coastal Observatory, and the development of interoperability requirements of data and models.</p> <p>The workshop was held on September 8th, 2020. Due to <span><span>COVID</span></span>-19 pandemic concerns, the entire workshop was held virtually. It brought together more than 100 national experts and practitioners with the goal of defining gaps in science and the interoperability of observational systems and models. Selected panelists discussed observations and models associated with biophysical, social-behavioral and economic systems in vulnerable coastal regions.</p> <p>Workshop Partners:</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Federal and State Partners:</span> (a) NASA; (b)Everglades National Park; (c) United States Geological Survey; (d) South Florida Water Management District; (e) City of Miami Beach; (f) Palm Beach, <span><span>Broward</span></span> and Miami Dade Counties;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Non-Governmental</span>: (a) Catalyst Miami; (b) CLEO Institute; (c) Miami Foundation</p> <p>The all-day workshop consisted in four different sessions, with sixteen speakers from across the nation discussing the importance of each coastal system to predict and mitigate climatic hazards. From understanding human behavior to exploring the economy of the ocean, each speaker provided insightful data on improving coastal hazard resiliency, the work being done and ways to create a safer environment to communities. During the plenary session, panelists and attendees discussed understanding the limitations between the interactions between social, economic and biophysical models. The necessity to bring the public into the process of data collection and help them understand its importance was emphasized.</p> <p>The workshop offered a rare opportunity to bring together modeling and data experts from multiple, but diverse disciplines.&nbsp; It was an opportunity to review the current state of each category of models, their requirements in terms of spatial and temporal resolution of information necessary for integrated assessment and more importantly, the interoperability of these models being developed by researchers in a variety of disciplines.&nbsp;</p> <p>The workshop deliberations revealed that there have been several advancements in the development of biophysical models which simulate effects of ?shocks? such as land falling hurricanes, and ?stresses? such as slowly rising sea levels.&nbsp; Simulation models in other two fields (social-behavioral, and economic) are available but they are still in the early stages of development for applications in coastal regions. Integration of physical impacts, peoples? behavior, response of the economy due coastal hazards require increased focus and emphasis which can eventually lead to the development of ?standards of practice.?</p> <p>The workshop included a specific emphasis on graduate students from <span><span>underserved</span></span> communities among collaborating institutions and the involvement of Non-governmental Organizations (<span><span>NGOs</span></span>).&nbsp; The collaborating institutions benefited to acquire on-the-ground realities of <span><span>underserved</span></span> communities in places such as Miami Dade County, helping develop the types of data that need to be collected for the development of behavioral models.</p> <p>Further information on the workshop including recordings of presentation may be obtained from its website</p> <p><a href="https://environment.fiu.edu/coastlines-and-oceans/sea-level-solutions-center/solutions/workshop-on-coastal-observation-and-modeling-systems/index.html"><span><span>https</span></span>://environment.<span><span>fiu</span></span>.<span><span>edu</span></span>/coastlines-and-oceans/sea-level-solutions-center/solutions/workshop-on-coastal-observation-and-modeling-systems/index.<span><span>html</span></span></a></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Jayantha&nbsp;Obeysekera</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1940264/1940264_10638440_1609356630457_Virtual_workshop_image--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1940264/1940264_10638440_1609356630457_Virtual_workshop_image--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Virtual workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1940264/1940264_10638440_1609356630457_Virtual_workshop_image--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Virtual workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Initial snapshot of the virtual workshop which replaced the in-person event due to COVID-19 pandemic concerns</div> <div class="imageCredit">Workshop organizers</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jayantha&nbsp;Obeysekera</div> <div class="imageTitle">Virtual workshop</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Coastlines and People Conference was designed to discuss observations and models associated with biophysical, social-behavioral, and economic systems in vulnerable coastal regions. Specifically, the workshop focused on understanding the interactions of biophysical, social-behavioral, and economic systems in coastal regions, explicitly defining new data gaps that can be addressed by nongovernmental, local, regional, and federal networks for the formulation of a comprehensive Coastal Observatory, and the development of interoperability requirements of data and models.  The workshop was held on September 8th, 2020. Due to COVID-19 pandemic concerns, the entire workshop was held virtually. It brought together more than 100 national experts and practitioners with the goal of defining gaps in science and the interoperability of observational systems and models. Selected panelists discussed observations and models associated with biophysical, social-behavioral and economic systems in vulnerable coastal regions.  Workshop Partners:  Federal and State Partners: (a) NASA; (b)Everglades National Park; (c) United States Geological Survey; (d) South Florida Water Management District; (e) City of Miami Beach; (f) Palm Beach, Broward and Miami Dade Counties;  Non-Governmental: (a) Catalyst Miami; (b) CLEO Institute; (c) Miami Foundation  The all-day workshop consisted in four different sessions, with sixteen speakers from across the nation discussing the importance of each coastal system to predict and mitigate climatic hazards. From understanding human behavior to exploring the economy of the ocean, each speaker provided insightful data on improving coastal hazard resiliency, the work being done and ways to create a safer environment to communities. During the plenary session, panelists and attendees discussed understanding the limitations between the interactions between social, economic and biophysical models. The necessity to bring the public into the process of data collection and help them understand its importance was emphasized.  The workshop offered a rare opportunity to bring together modeling and data experts from multiple, but diverse disciplines.  It was an opportunity to review the current state of each category of models, their requirements in terms of spatial and temporal resolution of information necessary for integrated assessment and more importantly, the interoperability of these models being developed by researchers in a variety of disciplines.   The workshop deliberations revealed that there have been several advancements in the development of biophysical models which simulate effects of ?shocks? such as land falling hurricanes, and ?stresses? such as slowly rising sea levels.  Simulation models in other two fields (social-behavioral, and economic) are available but they are still in the early stages of development for applications in coastal regions. Integration of physical impacts, peoples? behavior, response of the economy due coastal hazards require increased focus and emphasis which can eventually lead to the development of ?standards of practice.?  The workshop included a specific emphasis on graduate students from underserved communities among collaborating institutions and the involvement of Non-governmental Organizations (NGOs).  The collaborating institutions benefited to acquire on-the-ground realities of underserved communities in places such as Miami Dade County, helping develop the types of data that need to be collected for the development of behavioral models.  Further information on the workshop including recordings of presentation may be obtained from its website  https://environment.fiu.edu/coastlines-and-oceans/sea-level-solutions-center/solutions/workshop-on-coastal-observation-and-modeling-systems/index.html             Last Modified: 12/30/2020       Submitted by: Jayantha Obeysekera]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
