<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Taekion Defense-hardened Blockchain File System using aBFT Consensus</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224646.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224646</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady-Estevez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project include the ability to enhance the security and trust of critical infrastructure networks for applications including defense, electric grids, health care, and emerging autonomous systems (i.e., self-driving vehicles and robotics).  As billions of internet connected things are added to our existing infrastructure, providing a trusted data layer will rise in importance to maintain reliability and security of our critical infrastructure, as many of these systems are mission and life-critical.  Our proposed innovation will allow highly distributed and autonomous systems the ability to make decisions based on highly trusted data sources.  Our innovation will enhance the practical applications of distributed computing fault tolerance and consensus (agreement) mechanisms by applying them to real-world, critically needed defense networks initially and to other critical infrastructure areas later.  The commercial opportunity is to provide a missing piece of the puzzle to support a trusted data layer in the next generation, or Internet evolution.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to prototype a novel, next-generation Distributed Ledger Technology (DLT) consensus algorithm to be plugged into open source DLTs to enhance the data and transaction integrity aspects under asynchronous (disconnected, flaky, or malicious) networking scenarios.  The challenge is to provide the ability to maintain agreement and decision finality (or integrity) among consensus nodes operating in asynchronous (network partition, crash fault, byzantine fault) networking environments.  In simpler terms, this means the ability to keep and store a file or update within a DLT node, even though the fault keeps the DLT update from taking place over an extended period of time.  This capability is highly important when running DLTs in critical infrastructure networks.  The research objectives are to combine local, hash-chained write-ahead journaling methods with state-of-the-art asynchronous byzantine fault tolerant (aBFT) consensus to prototype high data integrity (ability to retain all transactions, provide liveness guarantees, maintain local node state integrity, and maintain data ordering and timestamps) under asynchronous network conditions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1940349</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Cohen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Cohen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dave@taekion.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3038083329</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000802118</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>GRID7 LLC</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803013831</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3038083329</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7136 PETURSDALE CT</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605505531</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GRID7 LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Grid7 LLC DBA Taekion]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803022600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1434 Spruce street, Suite 100]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~224646</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Phase I work titled "<strong><em>Defense-hardened Blockchain File System using aBFT Consensus</em></strong>" represents novel and game-changing innovation in distributed consensus and fault tolerance protocols to enable secure, resilient, and trusted computer networks. Our invention is based on distributed consensus methods which combine our Taekion File System (TFS) innovation with flexible and optimal Asynchronous Byzantine Fault Tolerant (aBFT) consensus mechanisms to achieve high data integrity and maximum network resiliency (retains all transactions and guarantees liveness) within disconnected, flaky, and constrained networks which we have market validated with customers needing critical data protection. Asynchronous (disconnected) networks are subject to various sources of uncertainties that influence their behavior, including randomly changing topologies, link failures, data arrival times, network nodes turning on and off randomly, as well as bad actors (Byzantine Faults). The proposed innovation retains all transactions and is the first innovation to maintain local state integrity under these types of conditions. During disconnected times, or under crash and Byzantine faults, the system will store relevant data on the local host and ensure the integrity of this data before it is inserted into the blockchain using TFS and pluggable Asynchronous Byzantine Fault Tolerance (aBFT).&nbsp;</p> <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0"> <tbody> <tr> <td valign="top"> <p><strong>Phase I Milestone</strong></p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p><strong>Description</strong></p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p><strong>Validation</strong></p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td valign="top"> <p>M1</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>Provable code on combined TFS and aBFT Consensus. Validate ability to not drop transactions and handle disconnects/reconnects without losing messages.</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>Code is validated and runs on a 5-node cluster with tunable connectivity dropouts between each node from between 1-30 seconds. The resulting implementation is much more resilient and extensible for asynchronous design patterns.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td valign="top"> <p>M2</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>Validate Scalability Metrics (throughput, bandwidth, scalability)</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>We validated good initial performance under highly asynchronous network conditions, where every node had random sustained network failures occurring during testing. Consensus was always achieved when minimum nodes for agreement were available. We obtained full recovery from all stalled states, and node catchup under all conditions given time and connectivity.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td valign="top"> <p>M3</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>Validate Use of the Taekion journal consensus</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>Code was validated for TFS running with aBFT consensus.&nbsp;&nbsp;The addition of TFS to our aBFT enabled DLT validated that we could maintain local state integrity before committing to the blockchain/DLT which resulted in deciding to patent TFS.&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Merit:</strong>&nbsp;The innovation solves the complex problem of maintaining data integrity for mission critical data within critical infrastructure networks.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our innovation simplifies the extremely complex science of consensus and fault tolerance in distributed systems by combining flexible deployment of state-of-the-art Asynchronous Byzantine Fault Tolerant (aBFT) consensus algorithms with our novel Taekion File System (TFS) innovation creating highly useful solution to protect data integrity before it can be compromised under varying network operating conditions including asynchronous network conditions (byzantine and crash fault scenarios, ability to retain all transactions, provide liveness guarantees, maintain local node state integrity, and maintain data ordering and timestamps).&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Impacts:</strong>&nbsp;The broader impacts and commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project include the ability to enhance the security and trust of critical infrastructure networks for applications including defense, electric grids, health care, and emerging autonomous systems (i.e., self-driving vehicles and robotics), as many of these systems are mission and life-critical. Our proposed innovation will allow highly distributed and autonomous systems the ability to make decisions based on highly trusted data sources. More importantly, the innovation addresses an immediate customer need to stop data breaches and prevent unauthorized activity on networks under flaky and uncertain conditions.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our innovation will enhance the practical applications of distributed computing fault tolerance and consensus mechanisms by applying them to real-world critical infrastructure networks. Mission critical systems data is constantly under attack by adversaries at the rate of a billion times per year. According to IBM, the average cost of a data breach for corporate customers is $8.6 million in the USA and the costs persist more than 3 years after the breach.&nbsp;&nbsp;For mission critical systems, compromised data is a serious problem including huge economic losses, potential for mission failures, and in some situations, life critical consequences.&nbsp;&nbsp;Protecting that data/information is one of the biggest market opportunities of this decade and the Phase II NSF product addresses the concerns of information assurance directly. Our commercialization plan leverages an experienced team that has built, scaled, and commercialized software platforms.&nbsp;&nbsp;In Phase I, we provided technical proof-of-concept and provided customer market validation for the product. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/08/2021<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;A&nbsp;Cohen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Phase I work titled "Defense-hardened Blockchain File System using aBFT Consensus" represents novel and game-changing innovation in distributed consensus and fault tolerance protocols to enable secure, resilient, and trusted computer networks. Our invention is based on distributed consensus methods which combine our Taekion File System (TFS) innovation with flexible and optimal Asynchronous Byzantine Fault Tolerant (aBFT) consensus mechanisms to achieve high data integrity and maximum network resiliency (retains all transactions and guarantees liveness) within disconnected, flaky, and constrained networks which we have market validated with customers needing critical data protection. Asynchronous (disconnected) networks are subject to various sources of uncertainties that influence their behavior, including randomly changing topologies, link failures, data arrival times, network nodes turning on and off randomly, as well as bad actors (Byzantine Faults). The proposed innovation retains all transactions and is the first innovation to maintain local state integrity under these types of conditions. During disconnected times, or under crash and Byzantine faults, the system will store relevant data on the local host and ensure the integrity of this data before it is inserted into the blockchain using TFS and pluggable Asynchronous Byzantine Fault Tolerance (aBFT).       Phase I Milestone    Description    Validation      M1    Provable code on combined TFS and aBFT Consensus. Validate ability to not drop transactions and handle disconnects/reconnects without losing messages.    Code is validated and runs on a 5-node cluster with tunable connectivity dropouts between each node from between 1-30 seconds. The resulting implementation is much more resilient and extensible for asynchronous design patterns.        M2    Validate Scalability Metrics (throughput, bandwidth, scalability)    We validated good initial performance under highly asynchronous network conditions, where every node had random sustained network failures occurring during testing. Consensus was always achieved when minimum nodes for agreement were available. We obtained full recovery from all stalled states, and node catchup under all conditions given time and connectivity.        M3    Validate Use of the Taekion journal consensus    Code was validated for TFS running with aBFT consensus.  The addition of TFS to our aBFT enabled DLT validated that we could maintain local state integrity before committing to the blockchain/DLT which resulted in deciding to patent TFS.          Merit: The innovation solves the complex problem of maintaining data integrity for mission critical data within critical infrastructure networks.  Our innovation simplifies the extremely complex science of consensus and fault tolerance in distributed systems by combining flexible deployment of state-of-the-art Asynchronous Byzantine Fault Tolerant (aBFT) consensus algorithms with our novel Taekion File System (TFS) innovation creating highly useful solution to protect data integrity before it can be compromised under varying network operating conditions including asynchronous network conditions (byzantine and crash fault scenarios, ability to retain all transactions, provide liveness guarantees, maintain local node state integrity, and maintain data ordering and timestamps).   Impacts: The broader impacts and commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project include the ability to enhance the security and trust of critical infrastructure networks for applications including defense, electric grids, health care, and emerging autonomous systems (i.e., self-driving vehicles and robotics), as many of these systems are mission and life-critical. Our proposed innovation will allow highly distributed and autonomous systems the ability to make decisions based on highly trusted data sources. More importantly, the innovation addresses an immediate customer need to stop data breaches and prevent unauthorized activity on networks under flaky and uncertain conditions.  Our innovation will enhance the practical applications of distributed computing fault tolerance and consensus mechanisms by applying them to real-world critical infrastructure networks. Mission critical systems data is constantly under attack by adversaries at the rate of a billion times per year. According to IBM, the average cost of a data breach for corporate customers is $8.6 million in the USA and the costs persist more than 3 years after the breach.  For mission critical systems, compromised data is a serious problem including huge economic losses, potential for mission failures, and in some situations, life critical consequences.  Protecting that data/information is one of the biggest market opportunities of this decade and the Phase II NSF product addresses the concerns of information assurance directly. Our commercialization plan leverages an experienced team that has built, scaled, and commercialized software platforms.  In Phase I, we provided technical proof-of-concept and provided customer market validation for the product.         Last Modified: 02/08/2021       Submitted by: David A Cohen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
