<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Tailored Interphases for High-Strength and Functional Composites - Advances in Experiments, Simulations and AI-Based Designs</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Schlueter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jschluet@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927766</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project will support the Symposium CT04: "Tailored Interphases for High Strength and Functional Composites ? Advances in Experiments, Simulations and AI-Based Designs", at the 2020 Spring Meeting of the Materials Research Society (MRS) during April 13-17, 2020, at the Phoenix Convention Center. The symposium will bring together many of the world?s leading experts in composites research, which has applications in defense, aerospace, and commercial transportation technologies. The project also supports the mission of MRS as the world's foremost international scientific gathering for materials research to showcase leading interdisciplinary research in both fundamental and applied areas. The symposium organizers are part of a team of 200 scientists from academia and industry in many countries around the world that coordinate the MRS meeting and technical programming. The symposium will bring together leading scientists, junior scientists, and attendees from an interdisciplinary research community to foster idea exchange and new collaborations in the topical area of composite materials and data driven design of complex materials. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this project is to pay travel costs for invited speakers, students and early-career researchers participating in the symposium. Funds will be specifically directed to invited and contributed speakers with disabilities, underrepresented minorities, and women. The project will also support young, diverse US-based researchers such as assistant professors and researchers in equivalent positions in other work sectors, post-doctoral scholars, and students. Recruitment efforts for minority presenters and broad participation from various related disciplines will be made. The symposium aims at better connecting scientists and engineers with expertise in different research fields related to structural and functional composites, such as physics, materials science, chemistry, engineering, bioengineering, and data science to advance cutting-edge research tools and design materials for transportation, aerial vehicles and aerospace technology. Specifically, research areas to be covered in the symposium include self-assembly and directed assembly of polymers, biopolymers, and colloids at ceramic and mineral interfaces, including graphitic, CNT, and BNNT based composites, nanoscale confinement of polymers near interfaces, as well as interfacial chemistry and reactions of materials to generate high strength. In-situ nanoscale mechanics and atomic-scale interfacial mechanisms, atomistic, coarse-grain, multiscale, and AI models of interphases and composites, interphase properties in biomimetic and bio-inspired composites, as well as advances in experiment, simulation, and artificial intelligence related to processing and property prediction will be discussed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1941104</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hendrik</FirstName>
<LastName>Heinz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hendrik Heinz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hendrik.heinz@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037357517</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000281542</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>J. Ardie Butch</FirstName>
<LastName>Dillen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>J. Ardie Butch Dillen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dillen@mrs.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7247792732</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000602561</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Materials Research Society</Name>
<CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
<ZipCode>150867573</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>506 KEYSTONE DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>107328510</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MATERIALS RESEARCH SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Materials Research Society]]></Name>
<CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>150867573</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 Keystone Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goal is to support the symposium "CT04: Tailored Interphases for High Strength and Functional Composites&mdash;Advances in Experiments, Simulations and AIBased Design" at the MRS Spring meeting 2020. Due to the COVID19 pandemic, the symposium has been postponed to take place at the MRS Fall meeting 2020.</p> <p>The updated symposium program is very similar, including a panel discussion. The speakers were very supportive to postpone the talks and posters to Fall, and we anticipate no major issues other than going virtual for the Fall symposium.</p> <p>The MRS symposium was held delayed in Fall 2020 at the then "MRS Spring and Fall meeting 2020", and attracted a significant live audience as well as asynchronous audience for remote viewing.</p> <p>The audience consisted of invited speakers, junior faculty members, attendees from industry, postdocs, graduate students, and undergraduate students.<br />The funds targeted reimbursement of graduate students, postdocs, and junior/diverse faculty members for their registration fees.</p> <p>The symposium fostered interesting discussions among the speakers during the session, as well as during our panel discussion about opportunities in the symposium topical area (bioinspired composites).</p> <p>The attendees could take advantage of netwokring opportunities.</p> <p>The results are disseminated in individual abstracts and publications.</p> <p>The program can be viewed at www.mrs.org</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2021<br>      Modified by: J. Ardie Butch&nbsp;Dillen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goal is to support the symposium "CT04: Tailored Interphases for High Strength and Functional Composites&mdash;Advances in Experiments, Simulations and AIBased Design" at the MRS Spring meeting 2020. Due to the COVID19 pandemic, the symposium has been postponed to take place at the MRS Fall meeting 2020.  The updated symposium program is very similar, including a panel discussion. The speakers were very supportive to postpone the talks and posters to Fall, and we anticipate no major issues other than going virtual for the Fall symposium.  The MRS symposium was held delayed in Fall 2020 at the then "MRS Spring and Fall meeting 2020", and attracted a significant live audience as well as asynchronous audience for remote viewing.  The audience consisted of invited speakers, junior faculty members, attendees from industry, postdocs, graduate students, and undergraduate students. The funds targeted reimbursement of graduate students, postdocs, and junior/diverse faculty members for their registration fees.  The symposium fostered interesting discussions among the speakers during the session, as well as during our panel discussion about opportunities in the symposium topical area (bioinspired composites).  The attendees could take advantage of netwokring opportunities.  The results are disseminated in individual abstracts and publications.  The program can be viewed at www.mrs.org       Last Modified: 06/29/2021       Submitted by: J. Ardie Butch Dillen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
