<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Aleutian - Alaska Workshop at Lamont for GeoPrisms Synthesis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14064.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14064</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Deborah K. Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dksmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927978</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will support a two-day workshop at the Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory campus of Columbia University on August 5-6, 2019 in order to synthesize research results from the Aleutian-Alaska Subduction Zone. Participants are drawn from ~ 20 individual projects funded by the NSF-GeoPRISMS Program (Geodynamic Processes at RIfting and Subducting Margins), with a focus on understanding the fundamental processes underlying great earthquakes and other types of fault slip, hazardous volcanic eruptions and the building of the continental crust.  Approximately 50 participants will gather at Lamont for the purposes of sharing and synthesizing results across disciplines and across the subduction zone, from the incoming plate through the megathrust to the volcanic arc.  Over 35% of the participants will be early-career scientists or graduate students who will be engaged in formal and informal discussions to develop a lasting network. The primary workshop output will be publications, including synthesis papers, that will integrate GeoPRISMS science. The other primary output will be the scientific connections made between individual projects that would not otherwise happen, essential to realizing the value of the focus site approach within GeoPRISMS.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Alaska-Aleutian Margin is one of the focus sites for the GeoPRISMS Subduction Cycles and Deformation Initiative. It was chosen as an ideal location to study arc volcanism, development of continental crust, and earthquake processes over the seismic cycle. GeoPRISMS-NSF projects funded since FY12 span topics ranging from deformation in the megathrust to plutonic building blocks of continents to volatile cycling from slab to surface.  Approaches include laboratory deformation experiments and geochemical analyses, and novel field deployments using portable mass spectrometers, seafloor strain sensors, and the Alaska Amphibious Array. This synthesis workshop is necessary to share initial findings, make cross-project connections, and integrate results from the Alaska-Aleutian focus site. Workshop participants will engage deeply in multi-disciplinary discussions (including geophysics, geochemistry, experimental and theoretical approaches). All presentations and discussions will be plenary to entrain everyone in the issues, results and controversies of each science topic and approach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1941699</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
<LastName>Plank</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terry A Plank</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tplank@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8453658410</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000237697</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Palisades</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>109641707</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[61 Route 9W]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8076</Code>
<Text>GeoPRISMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8076</Code>
<Text>GeoPRISMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~14064</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary goal of this project was to hold a two day conference at the Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University in order to synthesize research results from the NSF-GeoPRISMS program on the Aleutian-Alaska Subduction Zone. On August 5-6, 2019, forty-five (45) participants gathered, representing all GeoPrisms-AK project PI's (~35) and groups. Over half of the participants were early career faculty, postdocs or graduate students. There were 35 speakers and 15 posters, and all sessions were plenary and included plenty discussion. The conference was organized around several themes: 1) Subduction Inputs and the Megathrust, 2) Volatiles and Magma Storage, 3) Crustal Structure and Continental Growth, 4) Volcano Dynamics.</p> <p>Based on a post-conference survey, students and postdocs cited positive outcomes as new proposal ideas and new job opportunities. The majority of the 22 respondents (&gt;75%) said they learned about new topics from a different discipline and that they would like to be part of an on-going working group for Alaska subduction science. Other post-workshop activities included PI Plank presenting a meeting summary and leading a discussion about science synthesis at the GeoPRISMS mini-workshop in San Francisco in December 2019. Another outcome of the project is a a GeoPrisms-Alaska Bibliography initiated by Plank to reside and grow on the GeoPRISMS website. This contains an annotated and thematically-organized list of publications carried out by GeoPRIMS Alaska PI's, papers in prep, preparation and planned, and recently funded, submitted or planned proposals. The goal is to highlight and collate the 31 papers published, 7 in press/submitted, and 18 in preparation that demonstrate both the science products of GeoPRISMs, and also the on-going work and continuing projects, in order to keep the community informed and engaged.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Terry&nbsp;A&nbsp;Plank</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of this project was to hold a two day conference at the Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University in order to synthesize research results from the NSF-GeoPRISMS program on the Aleutian-Alaska Subduction Zone. On August 5-6, 2019, forty-five (45) participants gathered, representing all GeoPrisms-AK project PI's (~35) and groups. Over half of the participants were early career faculty, postdocs or graduate students. There were 35 speakers and 15 posters, and all sessions were plenary and included plenty discussion. The conference was organized around several themes: 1) Subduction Inputs and the Megathrust, 2) Volatiles and Magma Storage, 3) Crustal Structure and Continental Growth, 4) Volcano Dynamics.  Based on a post-conference survey, students and postdocs cited positive outcomes as new proposal ideas and new job opportunities. The majority of the 22 respondents (&gt;75%) said they learned about new topics from a different discipline and that they would like to be part of an on-going working group for Alaska subduction science. Other post-workshop activities included PI Plank presenting a meeting summary and leading a discussion about science synthesis at the GeoPRISMS mini-workshop in San Francisco in December 2019. Another outcome of the project is a a GeoPrisms-Alaska Bibliography initiated by Plank to reside and grow on the GeoPRISMS website. This contains an annotated and thematically-organized list of publications carried out by GeoPRIMS Alaska PI's, papers in prep, preparation and planned, and recently funded, submitted or planned proposals. The goal is to highlight and collate the 31 papers published, 7 in press/submitted, and 18 in preparation that demonstrate both the science products of GeoPRISMs, and also the on-going work and continuing projects, in order to keep the community informed and engaged.       Last Modified: 07/30/2020       Submitted by: Terry A Plank]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
