<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>AF: Small: Motion Planning Techniques for Protein Motion</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>192067.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>208067</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mitra Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928649</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Protein motions play an essential role in many biochemical processes.  For example, as proteins fold to their native, functional state, they sometimes undergo critical conformational changes that affect their functionality, e.g., diseases such as Mad Cow disease or Alzheimer's disease are associated with protein misfolding and aggregation.  Proteins also undergo conformational change when interacting with other molecules as they transition between bound and unbound states.  Knowledge of the mechanics of these motion processes may help provide insight into how and why proteins misfold, how binding regulation is communicated through the protein structure, and how to design more effective drugs.  For example, a better understanding of protein misfolding and aggregation has the potential to provide insight into neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer's disease, Parkinson's disease, prion diseases, and related diseases that have a major impact on society.  An important, and more immediate, goal of the project is to share detailed results generated by the new methods with the community in a publicly available database of protein motions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop new modeling, simulation and analysis tools that specialize and apply a novel computational method for studying molecular motions that has been developed and validated against experimental data in preliminary work.  This method represents a trade-off between methods such as molecular dynamics and Monte Carlo simulations that provide detailed individual folding trajectories and techniques such as statistical mechanical methods that provide global landscape statistics.  The approach, derived from robotic motion planning methods, builds a graph that encodes many (typically thousands) of motion pathways.  The proposed work involves both algorithmic research to further develop and optimize the techniques and research necessary to apply them to study issues of current interest in protein science.  While the algorithmic research will be performed by computer scientists, the application and testing of the techniques will benefit from collaborations with labs currently studying these problems.  The main research goals include: (i) The development of new and/or improved metrics and analysis techniques for conformations, pathways, and roadmaps that can be applied to modeling more complex motion applications.  These methods will be validated and applied to protein transitions, decoy database improvement, and ligand binding. (ii) New methods for modeling and simulating constrained motion and incorporating greater bond flexibility in areas of legitimate need (neither supported by current framework).  These methods will be applied to modeling protein transitions, and ligand binding. (iii) Strategies for employing high-performance computing to increase the size and complexity of the systems that can be studied.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1941530</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Amato</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nancy M Amato</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>namato@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173333373</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000430397</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 South First Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>Algorithmic Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7931</Code>
<Text>Computational Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7931</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~192067</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Protein motions play an essential role in many biochemical processes.&nbsp; For example, as proteins fold to their native, functional state, they sometimes undergo critical changes in their three-dimensional structure that affect their functionality, e.g., diseases such as Mad Cow or Alzheimer's are associated with protein misfolding and aggregation.&nbsp; Proteins also undergo structural change when interacting with other molecules, such as drug molecules.&nbsp; Since these structural changes are difficult to observe experimentally computational techniques are important to understanding these motions and processes and are crucial tools in computational drug design.<br /><br />Intellectual Merit: In this project, novel computational methods for studying molecular motions were developed that are complementary to existing methods such as molecular dynamics and Monte Carlo simulations.&nbsp; The approach, inspired by motion planning algorithms originally developed for robotics, uses a sampling-based approach to construct representative motion trajectories for the protein or drug molecule which can then be analyzed to study properties of interest.&nbsp; The main outcomes included development of new and/or improved metrics and analysis techniques for protein conformations and folding pathways, new methods for modeling and simulating protein/drug binding or docking, new techniques for studying binding site accessibility to drug molecules, advances to the foundations of motion planning, and strategies for employing high-performance computing to increase the size and complexity of the systems studied.<br /><br />Broader Impacts: The algorithmic advances and new computational approaches developed in this project have the potential to provide new insight into the structural and functional behavior of proteins and protein/drug interactions.&nbsp; Additionally, this project provided training and multi-disciplinary research opportunities for students and researchers, ranging from high school students, undergraduates, and graduate students to postdocs and research scientists, and provided opportunities to broaden participation in computing research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Nancy&nbsp;M&nbsp;Amato</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Protein motions play an essential role in many biochemical processes.  For example, as proteins fold to their native, functional state, they sometimes undergo critical changes in their three-dimensional structure that affect their functionality, e.g., diseases such as Mad Cow or Alzheimer's are associated with protein misfolding and aggregation.  Proteins also undergo structural change when interacting with other molecules, such as drug molecules.  Since these structural changes are difficult to observe experimentally computational techniques are important to understanding these motions and processes and are crucial tools in computational drug design.  Intellectual Merit: In this project, novel computational methods for studying molecular motions were developed that are complementary to existing methods such as molecular dynamics and Monte Carlo simulations.  The approach, inspired by motion planning algorithms originally developed for robotics, uses a sampling-based approach to construct representative motion trajectories for the protein or drug molecule which can then be analyzed to study properties of interest.  The main outcomes included development of new and/or improved metrics and analysis techniques for protein conformations and folding pathways, new methods for modeling and simulating protein/drug binding or docking, new techniques for studying binding site accessibility to drug molecules, advances to the foundations of motion planning, and strategies for employing high-performance computing to increase the size and complexity of the systems studied.  Broader Impacts: The algorithmic advances and new computational approaches developed in this project have the potential to provide new insight into the structural and functional behavior of proteins and protein/drug interactions.  Additionally, this project provided training and multi-disciplinary research opportunities for students and researchers, ranging from high school students, undergraduates, and graduate students to postdocs and research scientists, and provided opportunities to broaden participation in computing research.       Last Modified: 11/29/2020       Submitted by: Nancy M Amato]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
