<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Student Travel Grant for the 2019 ACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems (ACM SenSys 2019)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Sprintson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asprints@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922170</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 17th Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems (ACM SenSys 2019) is a premier symposium with a highly selective single-track technical program dedicated to systems issues of networked sensing and actuation, broadly defined.  Systems of smart sensors and actuators have a wide array of application areas such as cyber-physical systems, vehicular networks, and smart grid. This award supports graduate and undergraduate students who will substantially benefit from attending this conference but have limited foreign travel funds. Priority will be given to students from under-represented groups (women, minorities, and those with disabilities), authors without other funding, and first-time attendees.  The students will be exposed to the state-of-the-art developments in the field and will have the opportunity to interact with peers from institutions worldwide, participate in a mentoring event, meet with leading researchers, and participate in discussions that are likely to shape their future and that of the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1945574</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lu</FirstName>
<LastName>Su</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lu Su</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lusu@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7166451588</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000671163</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038633251</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142602000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[338 Davis Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~18400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project aims to support students at U.S. institutions to attend the 17th ACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems (ACM SenSys 2019) to be held November 10-13, 2019 in New York City, USA. This preeminent technical conference is the primary venue for presenting new research results in the area of sensing systems, and is widely attended by leading scientists, researchers and practitioners from all around the world. With the opportunities of paper presentation, attending panel and keynote sessions, and interacting with others performing cutting-edge research in the field, the conference attendance is extremely valuable for the graduate students&rsquo; education and long-term career development.</p> <p class="Default">This NSF SenSys 2019 student travel grant was used to cover the travel expenses of 19 students from 18 universities. Among the 19 recipients, there are 6 female students, 2 Hispanic students, 1 black student, and 15 first-time attendees.</p> <p class="Default">The award amount made to each awardee covers the majority of the travel and registration expenses. About the transportation expense, only US-based carriers were counted. The award amount made to each awardee is around $1,000. The total amount made to all the awardees is $18,400. All the NSF fund was used to support the student travel.</p> <p class="Default">During the conference, the awardees expressed their deep appreciation for the travel support and acknowledged the great value and importance of attending the conference. They not only learned the state-of-the-art research in the field, participated panel discussions, but also had the opportunities of interacting with peers, meeting new colleagues, and for the students about to graduate, obtaining advices on academic job search.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/21/2021<br>      Modified by: Lu&nbsp;Su</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project aims to support students at U.S. institutions to attend the 17th ACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems (ACM SenSys 2019) to be held November 10-13, 2019 in New York City, USA. This preeminent technical conference is the primary venue for presenting new research results in the area of sensing systems, and is widely attended by leading scientists, researchers and practitioners from all around the world. With the opportunities of paper presentation, attending panel and keynote sessions, and interacting with others performing cutting-edge research in the field, the conference attendance is extremely valuable for the graduate students’ education and long-term career development. This NSF SenSys 2019 student travel grant was used to cover the travel expenses of 19 students from 18 universities. Among the 19 recipients, there are 6 female students, 2 Hispanic students, 1 black student, and 15 first-time attendees. The award amount made to each awardee covers the majority of the travel and registration expenses. About the transportation expense, only US-based carriers were counted. The award amount made to each awardee is around $1,000. The total amount made to all the awardees is $18,400. All the NSF fund was used to support the student travel. During the conference, the awardees expressed their deep appreciation for the travel support and acknowledged the great value and importance of attending the conference. They not only learned the state-of-the-art research in the field, participated panel discussions, but also had the opportunities of interacting with peers, meeting new colleagues, and for the students about to graduate, obtaining advices on academic job search.       Last Modified: 02/21/2021       Submitted by: Lu Su]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
