<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Pin(2)-Symmetry in Monopole Floer Homology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>123825.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>123825</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>snaik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The main focus of this National Science Foundation funded project is the interaction between two areas of research known as gauge theory and low-dimensional topology. The former is the language in which many physical theories are formulated, while the latter studies the shapes of three- and four-dimensional spaces. It is common to apply knowledge of geometry to predict the behavior of physical systems. For example, it is straightforward to predict the sound of a drum from its shape. The opposite approach is sometimes also feasible; in particular, the study of differential equations originating from gauge theories can lead to very deep insights about the topology of spaces. In recent ground-breaking work, Ciprian Manolescu disproved the almost hundred-year-old Triangulation conjecture, which roughly asserted that in higher dimensions, every space can be cut into very simple pieces. The main goal of this project is to use the PI's recently developed computational techniques to understand in greater detail several properties of the object studied by Manolescu, called the three-dimensional homology cobordism group.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project has two main goals. First, to explore the properties of Pin(2)-monopole Floer homology, a package of invariants of three-manifolds defined in analogy to Manolescu's construction within the Morse-theoretic framework of Kronheimer and Mrowka. The Pin(2)-symmetry is reflected in an extremely rich A-infinity structure on these invariants, and we will focus on understanding the higher operations and their implications for natural topological operations such as connected sums. Second, to apply these tools to study problems in low-dimensional topology, focusing particularly on the homology cobordism group in dimension three. Very little is known about this group, especially regarding the existence of torsion, and Pin(2)-monopole Floer homology may provide an avenue to solve many of these problems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1948820</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Francesco</FirstName>
<LastName>Lin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Francesco Lin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fl2550@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8579197465</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000761545</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>New  York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2990 Broadway Rm509 MC4406]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~123825</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">This project focused on certain aspects of three-dimensional topology, i.e. the study of shapes that near each point look like the usual Euclidean space (up to bending). A very successful tool in the field is provided by the monopole Floer homology groups introduced by Kronheimer and Mrowka; these are algebraic invariants obtained by studying certain differential equations arising from theoretical physics called Seiberg-Witten equations. This project in particular dealt with two specific directions: the applications of Pin(2)-symmetry and the interactions with geometrization.</p> <p class="p1">Regarding the first, the Seiberg-Witten equations admit in certain situations more symmetries than one might naively expect; by exploiting an extra symmetry, called <em>Pin(2)-symmetry,</em> one can obtain much more subtle information about shapes. For example, in 2013 Manolescu used Pin(2)-symmetry to solve the almost 100-year old Triangulation conjecture. This project developed several foundational aspects of the theory, and provided computational tools which will be useful for future applications to three-dimensional topology (and its interactions with the fourth dimension).</p> <p class="p1">About the second, Thurston&rsquo;s geometrization is an extremely powerful tool to study shapes in three-dimensions; roughly speaking, it allows to use tools from geometry (such as lengths, volumes, etc. ) to distinguish the topology of spaces. Even though both geometrization and Floer homology are by now well-understood tools in the subject, their interaction (if any) in very mysterious. This project explored several direction to clarify such interactions, with a specific focus on the case of hyperbolic geometry (i.e. constant negative curvature), which is by far the richest geometry in dimension three. For example, this project found the first example of hyperbolic three-manifold for which the Seiberg-Witten equations do not admit non-trivial solutions. Along the way, this project provided new connections with spectral geometry, i.e. how such shapes sound as drums.</p> <p class="p1">Finally, this project has provided support to help disseminate the mathematical ideas around monopole Floer homology to a wide audience in the US and all over the world; this is especially important for the subject because most experts are concentrated at very few institutions. In particular, it has supported five invited lecture series by the PI, and 28 invited talks/colloquia. The visits have also lead to very inspiring interactions that directly influenced many of the products of this project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/23/2021<br>      Modified by: Francesco&nbsp;Lin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This project focused on certain aspects of three-dimensional topology, i.e. the study of shapes that near each point look like the usual Euclidean space (up to bending). A very successful tool in the field is provided by the monopole Floer homology groups introduced by Kronheimer and Mrowka; these are algebraic invariants obtained by studying certain differential equations arising from theoretical physics called Seiberg-Witten equations. This project in particular dealt with two specific directions: the applications of Pin(2)-symmetry and the interactions with geometrization. Regarding the first, the Seiberg-Witten equations admit in certain situations more symmetries than one might naively expect; by exploiting an extra symmetry, called Pin(2)-symmetry, one can obtain much more subtle information about shapes. For example, in 2013 Manolescu used Pin(2)-symmetry to solve the almost 100-year old Triangulation conjecture. This project developed several foundational aspects of the theory, and provided computational tools which will be useful for future applications to three-dimensional topology (and its interactions with the fourth dimension). About the second, Thurston’s geometrization is an extremely powerful tool to study shapes in three-dimensions; roughly speaking, it allows to use tools from geometry (such as lengths, volumes, etc. ) to distinguish the topology of spaces. Even though both geometrization and Floer homology are by now well-understood tools in the subject, their interaction (if any) in very mysterious. This project explored several direction to clarify such interactions, with a specific focus on the case of hyperbolic geometry (i.e. constant negative curvature), which is by far the richest geometry in dimension three. For example, this project found the first example of hyperbolic three-manifold for which the Seiberg-Witten equations do not admit non-trivial solutions. Along the way, this project provided new connections with spectral geometry, i.e. how such shapes sound as drums. Finally, this project has provided support to help disseminate the mathematical ideas around monopole Floer homology to a wide audience in the US and all over the world; this is especially important for the subject because most experts are concentrated at very few institutions. In particular, it has supported five invited lecture series by the PI, and 28 invited talks/colloquia. The visits have also lead to very inspiring interactions that directly influenced many of the products of this project.          Last Modified: 08/23/2021       Submitted by: Francesco Lin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
