<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Smartphone-based peanut maturity grading and analytic system</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project will be the improvement of crop yield and quality by providing accurate and consistent color-based peanut classification. Many crops are based on color classification to determine the harvest day and quality. Also, optimizing harvest dates is a key to maximizing peanut quality and production. A loss of the total yield can be caused by underestimating or overestimating the harvest dates. In addition, overestimation can cause a low selling price and suboptimal peanut quality due to immaturity, while underestimation may cause over-mature crops to be left in the soil due to the weak stems. Currently, the color classification procedures in peanuts are human-vision based. Comparing to them, this technology will provide a standardized, accurate and consistent peanut grading results. Also, the accumulated data will provide updated insights to financial institutes, food industries, growers on peanut pricing, yield and quality. This I-Corps program will provide opportunities for the team to explore commercialization of the technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is the first peanut maturity prediction and analytic system designed to streamline and simplify the current procedure. Existing method for maturity prediction is based on human vision, which can lead to variability in results due to the subjective nature of the test, and 30+ minutes to finish one set of 200+ peanut samples. In this proposal, a standardized peanut maturity prediction and analytic system based on color classification has been developed. The system includes a light-controlled photo booth, a peanut sorting board and a smartphone to grade and analyze up to 400 peanuts each time. Automation will allow the grading process to be completed in under 3 minutes and generate a report for the user. This will help save 500-800 hours of labor cost per peanut grader in each peanut season. Furthermore, a peanut information system will be developed to collect peanut information through the grading procedure. This information can be used for providing pricing and growth prediction information in the peanut market. Several prototypes have been developed to prove the concept. Tests have been performed with peanut samples to prove the concept of the proposed technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1949790</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tsz Ho</FirstName>
<LastName>Tse</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tsz Ho Tse</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ziontse@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7065425939</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000636934</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Tucker Hall Room 409]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004315578</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 East Campus Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">The overall goal of this project</span></em> is to complete market research and develop a commercialization strategy for our product, a peanut maturity prediction and analytic machine system for predict maturity prediction. This project also provides a graduate student with the opportunity to practice entrepreneurial skills.</p> <p><strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Our major activities are as follows:</span></em></strong><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span></strong></p> <ul> <li><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">I-Corps Curriculum:</span></em> We completed the 8-week VentureWell course&mdash;required by our grant&mdash;which included two on-site workshops in Philadelphia, PA in the winter of 2019.</li> <li><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Customer Discovery:</span></em> We used a comprehensive customer discovery process and developed a detailed business plan.</li> <li><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Customer Interviews:</span></em> We conducted over 100 interviews, more than 90 of which were in person, with potential customers, distribution channels, and partners.</li> <li><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Final Presentation:</span></em> We presented our past activities and plans for the future of our project at the Philadelphia cohort</li> </ul> <p><strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Our key outcomes are as follows:</span></em></strong><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span></strong></p> <ul> <li>To address current pain points in peanut maturity deterimination:</li> <li>Current peanut maturity prediction is based on human vision. This is a time-consuming procedure and the results are inconsistent from this method.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>It needs a long-time training to master this skill, so most of growers are highly depended on the well-trained county officers for predicting the peanut maturity. This is very inconvenient for them to get the optimal harvest day.&nbsp; </li> <li>In the current peanut industry, the peanut trade procedure is totally based on the pre-signed contract. The buyers have no control of the yield and quality of peanut they will get from growers since they do not have a complete peanut information database to help them do predication based on the historic data.&nbsp;&nbsp; </li> <li></li> <li>To identify the customer segments:</li> <li>The main end users will be peanut growers, who regularly predict peanut maturity day</li> <li>Distribution channels and partnerships have been identified to be key agrigulatural device companies and county agriculture services.</li> <li>The peanut food providers will be key customers of the generated data. The data service helps them track the crops situation year by year, which can help them easily adjust their market strategies based on the maturity situation of crops and better evaluate the allocation of their resources.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Impact</strong></p> <p>This project allowed us to conduct market research and identify customer segments, channels, and partners through scientific validation of our hypotheses. Going forward, we can pursue commercialization with more market knowledge, collaborative relationships with customers, and a structured business plan.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;<span style="white-space: pre;"> </span></strong>Our product will have a positive impact the peanut industry. Our automated system allows the collected peanut data and analysis report be easily gathered and uploaded to our peanut information system for future use in prediction models and further research.&nbsp;The prototype system has also be piloted tested with real peanut samples in a number of peanut grower sites in Georgia with positive user feedback from the growers and crop consultants showing comparable results &nbsp;with peanut experts in manual maturity grading.</p> <p>&nbsp;<span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Once we have successfully developed and demonstrated our product, we will consult the University of Georgia&rsquo;s Innovation Gateway for assistance with finding opportunities for technology transfer and licensing.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;<span style="white-space: pre;"> </span></strong>Beyond science and technology transfer, this project has the potential to improve peanut harvesting and yield. Peanuts are a major agricultural crop in the United States. Peanut harvest dates are important since outside the optimal maturity could cause an 8% to 40% loss of the total yield. Incorrectly assessing the peanut maturity at harvest could cause large economic loss not just to the peanut growers but to the food industry as a whole. Our technology can reduce the loss associated to inaccuracy prediction of the peanut maturity and harvesting date.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Tsz Ho&nbsp;Tse</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall goal of this project is to complete market research and develop a commercialization strategy for our product, a peanut maturity prediction and analytic machine system for predict maturity prediction. This project also provides a graduate student with the opportunity to practice entrepreneurial skills.  Our major activities are as follows:   I-Corps Curriculum: We completed the 8-week VentureWell course&mdash;required by our grant&mdash;which included two on-site workshops in Philadelphia, PA in the winter of 2019. Customer Discovery: We used a comprehensive customer discovery process and developed a detailed business plan. Customer Interviews: We conducted over 100 interviews, more than 90 of which were in person, with potential customers, distribution channels, and partners. Final Presentation: We presented our past activities and plans for the future of our project at the Philadelphia cohort   Our key outcomes are as follows:   To address current pain points in peanut maturity deterimination: Current peanut maturity prediction is based on human vision. This is a time-consuming procedure and the results are inconsistent from this method.   It needs a long-time training to master this skill, so most of growers are highly depended on the well-trained county officers for predicting the peanut maturity. This is very inconvenient for them to get the optimal harvest day.   In the current peanut industry, the peanut trade procedure is totally based on the pre-signed contract. The buyers have no control of the yield and quality of peanut they will get from growers since they do not have a complete peanut information database to help them do predication based on the historic data.     To identify the customer segments: The main end users will be peanut growers, who regularly predict peanut maturity day Distribution channels and partnerships have been identified to be key agrigulatural device companies and county agriculture services. The peanut food providers will be key customers of the generated data. The data service helps them track the crops situation year by year, which can help them easily adjust their market strategies based on the maturity situation of crops and better evaluate the allocation of their resources.   Impact  This project allowed us to conduct market research and identify customer segments, channels, and partners through scientific validation of our hypotheses. Going forward, we can pursue commercialization with more market knowledge, collaborative relationships with customers, and a structured business plan.    Our product will have a positive impact the peanut industry. Our automated system allows the collected peanut data and analysis report be easily gathered and uploaded to our peanut information system for future use in prediction models and further research. The prototype system has also be piloted tested with real peanut samples in a number of peanut grower sites in Georgia with positive user feedback from the growers and crop consultants showing comparable results  with peanut experts in manual maturity grading.    Once we have successfully developed and demonstrated our product, we will consult the University of Georgia’s Innovation Gateway for assistance with finding opportunities for technology transfer and licensing.    Beyond science and technology transfer, this project has the potential to improve peanut harvesting and yield. Peanuts are a major agricultural crop in the United States. Peanut harvest dates are important since outside the optimal maturity could cause an 8% to 40% loss of the total yield. Incorrectly assessing the peanut maturity at harvest could cause large economic loss not just to the peanut growers but to the food industry as a whole. Our technology can reduce the loss associated to inaccuracy prediction of the peanut maturity and harvesting date.                Last Modified: 07/28/2021       Submitted by: Tsz Ho Tse]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
