<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IRES Track I: Behavioral Ecology, Demography and Conservation of Primates in the Humid Chaco of Argentina</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will train U.S. students to conduct research that contributes to understanding the evolution of mammal and primate societies and how ecological and social factors influence their structure and functioning. The students will conduct research projects to examine if the interactions with predators and competitors (e.g. coatis, howler monkeys) influence owl monkey monogamous groups and solitary floaters differently. Developed within the fields of behavioral ecology, demography and conservation of primates, the projects will be conducted within the Owl Monkey Project in the Humid Chaco of  Argentina. This IRES site will leverage a successful 23-year-old international research program to offer opportunities to 18 undergraduate students recruited nationally from Primarily Undergraduate Institutions. The students will receive training, networking opportunities and mentorship before, during and after the 8-week summer research experience. Societal benefits will include, among other things, a series of freely available educational materials for use in biological anthropology and primatology courses (in both English and Spanish). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will contribute to a research program that is making theoretical and empirical contributions to the study of the evolution of mating and social systems in mammals and primates. The student activities will be developed within the Owl Monkey Project, which has been studying monogamous owl monkeys (Aotus azarae) without interruption since 1996. Owl monkeys are one of the few monogamous primates in the world, the only primate genus with nocturnal habits in the Americas, and one of two primates with the most extreme forms of paternal care among mammals. To further understand the mechanisms and evolution of monogamy, pair-bonding, and paternal care, the students will conduct studies contributing to an evaluation of the influence that the competition between owl monkey solitary floaters and resident adults has on the demography, life-history and genetic correlates of the owl monkey population. In the spring prior to summer field work, students will participate in an online course to introduce them to key concepts in primate behavior and ecology, and to guide them designing high-quality feasible research projects. Students will spend 8 weeks in the field collecting, curating and analyzing data under the guidance and mentoring of the PIs and 4 foreign collaborators. Back in the US, participants will receive additional training and mentoring in data analysis and scientific writing via virtual meetings. At the end of the fall semester, participants will present their projects at a professional meeting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/25/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/25/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1952072</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eduardo</FirstName>
<LastName>Fernandez-Duque</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eduardo Fernandez-Duque</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eduardo.fernandez-duque@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034328403</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000062350</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claudia</FirstName>
<LastName>Valeggia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claudia R Valeggia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>claudia.valeggia@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034323685</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000533505</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 208327]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208277</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10 Sachem Street, Rm 314]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7727</Code>
<Text>IRES Track I: IRES Sites (IS)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5911</Code>
<Text>ARGENTINA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5977</Code>
<Text>AMERICAS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~300000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
