<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Second International Conference on Computational Methods and Applications in Engineering</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>13999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>13999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in the Second International Conference on Computational Methods and Applications in Engineering held at Mississippi State University on May 7-9, 2020.  With the rapid development of high-performance computing and its applications, robust mathematical models and their efficient computational algorithms and simulations have emerged as an essential analysis tool in science and engineering. In this regard, various professional scientific/engineering societies host cross-disciplinary conferences and meetings in related areas. However, a truly multidisciplinary conference with a focused theme, which provides a forum for mathematical scientists and engineers to share their research, is needed in the field of computational mathematics, sciences, and engineering. Moreover, this effort should reach researchers from many different countries. For this purpose, an interdisciplinary conference was successfully organized in 2018 by Mississippi State University and Universitatea Politehnica Timisoara, Romania. The main objective of this project is to continue to carry the same theme and tradition of the first conference and to host “The Second International Conference on Computational Methods and Applications in Engineering” on the campus of Mississippi State University. A mission of the conference is to further expand the established collaboration between the organizing institutions and to provide a joint forum where computational scientists and engineers from all over the world exchange research ideas in related fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference offers five plenary lectures to be given by experts. The conference will also feature around 50 mini-symposium talks and 80 contributed papers. The mini-symposium topics include: 1) Recent Developments in Non-conforming Finite Element Methods, 2) Recent Advances in Time-Integration of Partial Differential Equations (PDEs), 3) Instability, Transition and Turbulence in Fluids: from Fundamentals to Applications, 4) Constitutive Modeling of Engineering Materials and Computational Simulations, 5) Lower Length Scale Methods in Machine Learning, 6) Recent Advances in Numerical PDEs: Fast Algorithms and Applications, 7) Numerical Methods and Models for High-Performance Computational Fluid Dynamics, and 8) Numerical Methods for Optimization Problems with PDE Constraints. Proceedings of the conference will be published as refereed manuscripts in a special issue of the Journal of Computational and Applied Mathematics. The conference will provide graduate students and early career researchers with an opportunity to present their work, meet other researchers and educators, and learn of recent developments in the field of computational methods and engineering applications.  More details are available on the conference web site https://www.iccmae2020.math.msstate.edu/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1952848</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohsen</FirstName>
<LastName>Razzaghi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mohsen Razzaghi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6013253414</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000342728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hyeona</FirstName>
<LastName>Lim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hyeona Lim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hlim@math.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623257142</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000320796</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amanda</FirstName>
<LastName>Diegel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amanda E Diegel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>adiegel@math.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623257153</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000792290</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vu Thai</FirstName>
<LastName>Luan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vu Thai Luan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>luan@math.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623257162</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000810064</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mississippi State University</Name>
<CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6623257404</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>PO Box 6156</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MS03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075461814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MISSISSIPPI STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075461814</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mississippi State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Mississippi State</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 6156]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MS03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~13999</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
