<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Deep Dive Into Deep Tech Incubation Workshop; Arlington, VA; Spring 2020</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>75000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Deep technologies (deep tech) are typically defined as those that are based on substantial scientific discoveries and engineering advances with high potential to profoundly impact existing and emerging industries as well as people’s lives. Because challenges facing deep tech startups are different from those for other startup companies, they frequently take longer time and require more financial resources to reach market-ready maturity. To strengthen our economic and technological competitiveness, it is critical to explore methods and develop best practices to accelerate deep tech commercialization. The Deep Dive Into Deep Tech Incubation workshop will bring together key players in the deep tech ecosystem, including incubators, universities, government, investors, and industrial partners. The Workshop aims to address fundamental issues of deep tech commercialization, providing an opportunity for participants to share knowledge and form partnerships with the ultimate goal of accelerating time to market of deep tech. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Deep Dive Into Deep Tech Incubation Workshop will convene thought leaders and key stakeholders from the deep tech incubation ecosystem around the country to (1) better understand relationships among incubators, universities, government, investors, and industrial partners; (2) explore how to most effectively engage with incubators and other venture development organizations that provide deep tech incubation; (3) study how to advance the deep tech incubation ecosystem and grow more and stronger early-stage deep-tech companies in the U.S.; and (4) share best practices among stakeholders. The Workshop will generate knowledge and insights in deep tech incubation and foster collaborations among participants, accelerating time to market for deep tech. Given its broad scope and success in deep tech research and incubation, the State University of New York (SUNY) is uniquely qualified to lead the planning, execution and post-program follow-up of the Workshop.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/08/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1953023</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Grace</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Grace Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>grace.wang@suny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5184454100</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000743880</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/08/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Querques</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicholas Querques</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nicholas.querques@rfsuny.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5184347183</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000845970</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY System Administration</Name>
<CityName>Albany</CityName>
<ZipCode>122072826</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5184347174</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[35 State Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>129340902</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY System Administration]]></Name>
<CityName>Albany</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>122072798</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[353 Broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Deep Dive Into Deep Tech Incubation project evolved from an in-person workshop to a five-part virtual series due to the pandemic. This series brought together the nation's top thought leaders with over 1,200 participants to discuss how they are making an impact on the deep tech incubation ecosystem and accelerating commercialization for deep tech startups.</p> <p>To support ongoing deep tech efforts across the country, data sheets were assembled that highlight key discussion points from the webinar sessions, as well as related program links and funding opportunities.</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://rfsuny.us5.list-manage.com/track/click?u=e627bd3285f289a50e4f3cc4f&amp;id=1d35f41288&amp;e=38a1a62807" target="_blank">Part I: How COVID-19 Is Affecting The Deep Tech      Startup Ecosystem</a></li> <li><a href="https://rfsuny.us5.list-manage.com/track/click?u=e627bd3285f289a50e4f3cc4f&amp;id=3fe4dddb37&amp;e=38a1a62807" target="_blank">Part II: Deep Tech Incubation Fundamentals and Best      Practices</a></li> <li><a href="https://rfsuny.us5.list-manage.com/track/click?u=e627bd3285f289a50e4f3cc4f&amp;id=31c6c6117b&amp;e=38a1a62807" target="_blank">Part III: Deep Tech Incubation and Academia Nexus</a></li> <li><a href="https://rfsuny.us5.list-manage.com/track/click?u=e627bd3285f289a50e4f3cc4f&amp;id=aba94d78df&amp;e=38a1a62807" target="_blank">Part IV: Deep Tech Venture Capital and Corporate      Partnerships</a></li> <li><a href="https://rfsuny.us5.list-manage.com/track/click?u=e627bd3285f289a50e4f3cc4f&amp;id=4978ffd411&amp;e=38a1a62807" target="_blank">Part V: Diversity and Inclusion In Deep Tech</a></li> </ul> <p>The series was actively promoted and reached interested constituencies across all 50 states in the United States as well as internationally. The series will remain an easily accessible, living asset available via the event website, https://www.rfsuny.org/deeptech, which serves as a one-stop shop for the on-demand webinars, datasheets, and links to resources.</p> <p>The Deep Dive Into Deep Tech Incubation webinar series was sponsored and hosted by the National Science Foundation and The State University of New York (SUNY), and facilitated by SUNY Research Foundation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/24/2021<br>      Modified by: Nicholas&nbsp;Querques</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1953023/1953023_10650587_1624539604573_NSFDeepDiveIntoDeepTechIncubationImage1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1953023/1953023_10650587_1624539604573_NSFDeepDiveIntoDeepTechIncubationImage1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NSF Deep Dive Into Deep Tech Incubation Image 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1953023/1953023_10650587_1624539604573_NSFDeepDiveIntoDeepTechIncubationImage1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NSF Deep Dive Into Deep Tech Incubation Image 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NSF Deep Dive Into Deep Tech Incubation Speakers</div> <div class="imageCredit">SUNY Research Foundation</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Nicholas&nbsp;Querques</div> <div class="imageTitle">NSF Deep Dive Into Deep Tech Incubation Image 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Deep Dive Into Deep Tech Incubation project evolved from an in-person workshop to a five-part virtual series due to the pandemic. This series brought together the nation's top thought leaders with over 1,200 participants to discuss how they are making an impact on the deep tech incubation ecosystem and accelerating commercialization for deep tech startups.  To support ongoing deep tech efforts across the country, data sheets were assembled that highlight key discussion points from the webinar sessions, as well as related program links and funding opportunities.  Part I: How COVID-19 Is Affecting The Deep Tech      Startup Ecosystem Part II: Deep Tech Incubation Fundamentals and Best      Practices Part III: Deep Tech Incubation and Academia Nexus Part IV: Deep Tech Venture Capital and Corporate      Partnerships Part V: Diversity and Inclusion In Deep Tech   The series was actively promoted and reached interested constituencies across all 50 states in the United States as well as internationally. The series will remain an easily accessible, living asset available via the event website, https://www.rfsuny.org/deeptech, which serves as a one-stop shop for the on-demand webinars, datasheets, and links to resources.  The Deep Dive Into Deep Tech Incubation webinar series was sponsored and hosted by the National Science Foundation and The State University of New York (SUNY), and facilitated by SUNY Research Foundation.       Last Modified: 06/24/2021       Submitted by: Nicholas Querques]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
