<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Stochastic Computing Host Intrusion Detection System (HIDS) for IoT devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224355.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224355</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>patherto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928772</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will result from providing a new additional layer of security protection for Internet of Things (IoT) devices by using a novel hardware-based intrusion detection system. Security remains a challenge with most IoT devices, mainly due to the resource-constrained nature of these devices – limited power, computing power and memory.  The proposed approach will provide an additional IoT security layer by enabling the detection of anomalous behavior in such devices, encouraging adoption in many new applications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project employs Stochastic Computing (SC) in a hardware-based Host Intrusion Detection System (HIDS) security solution for IoT devices. Current approaches to IoT security are unable to provide HIDS capability due to the resource constrained nature of such devices. As a result, anomalous behavior may go undetected. The proposed approach exploits two salient properties of SC: (i) low power and silicon area requirements, and (ii) the inherently probabilistic nature, enabling a HIDS for IoT devices by using a combination of SC hardware and a Neural Network to monitor incoming packets for malicious activity. This project will develop, train and test an SC-based HIDS for industrial drones.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1956291</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kazi</FirstName>
<LastName>Ahmed</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kazi Ahmed</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amy.hasan@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3474588312</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000792380</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SECUTOPIA CORPORATION</Name>
<CityName>PARAMUS</CityName>
<ZipCode>076525542</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2016935413</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>325 SILVER ROD CT</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>116837680</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SECUTOPIA CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Secutopia Corportation]]></Name>
<CityName>Paramus</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>076525542</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[325 Silver Rod Court]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~224355</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As the numbers and types of security breaches are on the rise, defense-in-depth security strategy becomes ever more imperative. As such, putting every possible security control in layers is not any more an option. With the enhancement of 5G-network and embracement of IoT, new security threats are continuously popping up. Especially, the integration of weak IoT devices into the main network makes it even more unsecure. To boost the security of weak IoT, we have introduced small form factor, low energy consumed, hardware based HIDS (Host Intrusion Detection System). Our HIDS can be adopted by weak IoT device without expanding its resource capability. Exploiting the advantage of Stochastic Computing (SC), a deep Neural Network Machine Learning algorithm is running in hardware, making our HIDS a strong security measure (layer). However, our HIDS does not come without facing unbounded challenges. First set of challenges come from the training of HIDS. Following the constraint in SC, keeping all variables within [-1, +1] margin while doing the IDS training is the very first attempt. During this stage, we have invented new ways of calculating Matrix Product, activation function and softmax function. Subsequently, a major change is brought in forward and backward propagation of Neural Network Algorithm (NNA). FPGA implementation of HIDS for incoming packet detection faces even more challenges as the initial design encounter serious issues. However, these challenges beget new SC hardware modules theoretically more accurate for NNA. At the same time, issues with limited number of Random Number Generator (RNG) required to do Binary Radix Computing (BC) to SC conversion are resolved. Time synchronization is yet another issue stemming from the mixture of combinational and sequential logic. A smart combination of digital counter and delay gates create perfect time synchronization. Towards the end we face difficulty in &nbsp;integrating feature collection block with the HIDS. Employing divide and conquer approach, we create the feature collection in software domain and integrate it with HIDS with the help of Advanced eXtensible Interface 4 (AXI4) interface.</p> <p>Upon completing our HIDS we tested its performance and compared it with that of the software based one. Following table shows the comparative performance outcomes from Python and SC HIDS:</p> <p>Platform&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Training data set&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Testing data set</p> <p>Python&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 98-99%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;80-85%</p> <p>SC HIDS&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 98%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;80-85%</p> <p>As shown, the performance of the SC hardware based HIDS is essentially the same as the one with software based (i.e, theoretical), which serves to prove that our SC based HIDS works as it should. We also created a real attack environment with the help of Raspberry Pi SBC (Single Board Computer). An effective proof of concept demo was built in preparation of presenting it to potential investors and partners. However, during the Phase I R&amp;D, we came across new findings that we would like to carry out during the SBIR/STTR Phase II. This activity of phase II will not only improve the current HIDS in terms of performance and overall platform; it helps make the HIDS a real commercial product.&nbsp; In this connection, we have the following R&amp;D objectives for next phase: a) hardware based feature extraction block (currently software based); b) HIDS training system expansion for new IoT environment; c) web based IDE for the customer for the ease of operation. As we are planning to apply for the SBIR/STTR Phase II, an acceptance from the NSF will be a perfect opportunity to complete these objectives and bring our product to the IoT security market.</p> <p>On the other hand, IoT market is continuously growing however, according to customer discovery and internet research security is considered one of the&nbsp; biggest barriers in adopting IoT. The main reason of this security concern is due to the limited resource of IoT devices that makes it difficult to apply all layers of security protections. The adoption of the proposed approach will provide additive security layer to the IoT devices that will boost the confidence in IoT device security in cameras, drones, sensors and others. Consequently it may induce new industries which have previously been reluctant to apply IoT solutions to their businesses. Due to the small resource occupation of the proposed device security, even non-IoT industries may apply the proposed approach to their security applications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><br /></strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2021<br>      Modified by: Kazi&nbsp;Ahmed</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As the numbers and types of security breaches are on the rise, defense-in-depth security strategy becomes ever more imperative. As such, putting every possible security control in layers is not any more an option. With the enhancement of 5G-network and embracement of IoT, new security threats are continuously popping up. Especially, the integration of weak IoT devices into the main network makes it even more unsecure. To boost the security of weak IoT, we have introduced small form factor, low energy consumed, hardware based HIDS (Host Intrusion Detection System). Our HIDS can be adopted by weak IoT device without expanding its resource capability. Exploiting the advantage of Stochastic Computing (SC), a deep Neural Network Machine Learning algorithm is running in hardware, making our HIDS a strong security measure (layer). However, our HIDS does not come without facing unbounded challenges. First set of challenges come from the training of HIDS. Following the constraint in SC, keeping all variables within [-1, +1] margin while doing the IDS training is the very first attempt. During this stage, we have invented new ways of calculating Matrix Product, activation function and softmax function. Subsequently, a major change is brought in forward and backward propagation of Neural Network Algorithm (NNA). FPGA implementation of HIDS for incoming packet detection faces even more challenges as the initial design encounter serious issues. However, these challenges beget new SC hardware modules theoretically more accurate for NNA. At the same time, issues with limited number of Random Number Generator (RNG) required to do Binary Radix Computing (BC) to SC conversion are resolved. Time synchronization is yet another issue stemming from the mixture of combinational and sequential logic. A smart combination of digital counter and delay gates create perfect time synchronization. Towards the end we face difficulty in  integrating feature collection block with the HIDS. Employing divide and conquer approach, we create the feature collection in software domain and integrate it with HIDS with the help of Advanced eXtensible Interface 4 (AXI4) interface.  Upon completing our HIDS we tested its performance and compared it with that of the software based one. Following table shows the comparative performance outcomes from Python and SC HIDS:  Platform          Training data set       Testing data set  Python                98-99%                   80-85%  SC HIDS              98%                       80-85%  As shown, the performance of the SC hardware based HIDS is essentially the same as the one with software based (i.e, theoretical), which serves to prove that our SC based HIDS works as it should. We also created a real attack environment with the help of Raspberry Pi SBC (Single Board Computer). An effective proof of concept demo was built in preparation of presenting it to potential investors and partners. However, during the Phase I R&amp;D, we came across new findings that we would like to carry out during the SBIR/STTR Phase II. This activity of phase II will not only improve the current HIDS in terms of performance and overall platform; it helps make the HIDS a real commercial product.  In this connection, we have the following R&amp;D objectives for next phase: a) hardware based feature extraction block (currently software based); b) HIDS training system expansion for new IoT environment; c) web based IDE for the customer for the ease of operation. As we are planning to apply for the SBIR/STTR Phase II, an acceptance from the NSF will be a perfect opportunity to complete these objectives and bring our product to the IoT security market.  On the other hand, IoT market is continuously growing however, according to customer discovery and internet research security is considered one of the  biggest barriers in adopting IoT. The main reason of this security concern is due to the limited resource of IoT devices that makes it difficult to apply all layers of security protections. The adoption of the proposed approach will provide additive security layer to the IoT devices that will boost the confidence in IoT device security in cameras, drones, sensors and others. Consequently it may induce new industries which have previously been reluctant to apply IoT solutions to their businesses. Due to the small resource occupation of the proposed device security, even non-IoT industries may apply the proposed approach to their security applications.                Last Modified: 08/05/2021       Submitted by: Kazi Ahmed]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
