<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IUCRC Phase II Rice University: Center for Atomically Thin Multifunctional Coatings (ATOMIC)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>90000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Crystal Leach</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>crleach@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922667</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Phase II proposal seeks to continue and expand the Center for Atomically Thin Multifunctional Coatings (ATOMIC), devoted to the design and development of advanced coatings based on two-dimensional (2D) materials. ATOMIC Phase II will synergistically integrate students, faculty, and staff from Pennsylvania State University, Rice University, and Boise State University to advance coating science across multiple technology readiness levels. Research performed at Rice will focus on multifunctional hexagonal boron nitride(hBN) coatings, photocatalytic coatings, printed nano-antennas, and advanced microscopy characterization of 2D materials. Because of the aligned partnership among academia, government, and industry, ATOMIC phase II will seeks to impact the education and training of students, particularly those who are underrepresented minorities. To encourage young people to pursue science-technology research degrees, the center will jointly conduct outreach activities and leverage ongoing NSF Engineering Research Centers (REU), Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) and Research Experiences for Teachers (RET) programs at Rice. ATOMIC will leverage the Rice Alliance for Technology and Entrepreneurship to foster academic-industry relationships and enhance the transfer of knowledge from the Universities to the marketplace. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Two-dimensional (2D) materials exhibit a variety of unique properties, different from bulk phases, that will enhance the performance of existing coating technologies. Phase I of ATOMIC laid the foundation for demonstrating these ultrathin materials with improved performance in corrosion resistance, extreme environmental tolerance, energy harvesting/storage, biocompatibility, and enhanced molecular sensitivity. ATOMIC Phase II plans to build on the foundation of scientific innovation in 2D materials at Penn State and Rice University and expand it into scalable 2D materials printing enabled by the addition of Boise State University. Penn State and Rice have successfully employed fundamental research programs in novel 2D materials, such as graphene, hBN, MoS2, and WS2; and Boise State has joined with experience in nanomaterial ink development and controlled precision printing such as inkjet, plasma jet, aerosol jet, and micro-dispensing. The joint research efforts chosen and designed by ATOMIC will concentrate on addressing key societal and industrial problems in areas of U.S. national interest that can be mitigated through advanced multifunctional coatings, such as infrastructure protection, internet of things (IoT) sensing, electronics, energy harvesting/storage, autonomous systems, and biological threat reduction.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2113882</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pulickel</FirstName>
<LastName>Ajayan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pulickel M Ajayan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ajayan@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7133485904</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000155962</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jun</FirstName>
<LastName>Lou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jun Lou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jlou@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7133483573</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000268759</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WILLIAM MARSH RICE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[William Marsh Rice University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6100 Main Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~90000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
