<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Retaining Students in STEM on a Commuter Campus with Efficient High Impact Practices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1439824.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1439824</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Susan Carson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>scarson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928094</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will contribute to the national need for well-educated scientists, mathematicians, engineers, and technicians by supporting the recruitment, retention and graduation of high-achieving, low-income students with demonstrated financial need at University of Michigan-Dearborn. The project aims to adapt high impact practices and support services, that have been proven to benefit students on residential campuses, to a 100% commuter population composed of a diverse group of students in metro-Detroit. Over its duration, this project will fund scholarships to 56 unique first year, full time students pursuing bachelor’s degrees in the Biological Sciences, Biochemistry, Computer and Information Science, Engineering, Electrical Engineering, Industrial and Systems Engineering, Mechanical Engineering, Computer Engineering, Mathematics, Environmental Science, Bioengineering, and Chemistry (ACS Certified). Selected first year students will receive four-year scholarships along with academic and social support, research opportunities, and professional development. These interventions are specifically designed to accommodate the schedules of commuter students, who typically live at home and have commitments that prevent them from participating in high impact practices. The scholars will be placed in 2-3 common classes during their first year to build a cohort community, receiving direct and intentional peer support in their math and chemistry classes. Dedicated mentoring by faculty and professional advising by a trained project coordinator will be provided, while support services that are delivered either remotely or at convenient times, will be available to the scholars throughout their four years on campus. A new, paid undergraduate research experience called “Research Rotations” intended to broaden exposure to research in various science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) fields and to foster a sense of belonging will allow students the opportunity to work closely with faculty on a part-time basis, investigating multiple research projects. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overall goal of this project is to increase degree completion in STEM disciplines for low-income, high-achieving undergraduates with demonstrated financial need. The specific objectives include: maintaining a first to second year retention rate of 85%, attaining a 50% four-year graduation rate, and adapting existing, proven interventions for commuter students who have limited time due to outside responsibilities. Cohort building, peer mentoring, active learning, and research experiences have all proven to be effective strategies for increasing retention and graduation rates on traditional, residential campuses. For commuter students, especially those with low income, many of these interventions are inaccessible because of constraints on their time due to financial, work, or family obligations. This project aims to adapt these support structures, introducing more flexible time commitments or remote access, and will study the effectiveness of these adaptations on persistence, student learning, and retention and graduation rates in STEM. An external evaluator will measure the success of the project, determining which interventions and what frequency of participation is correlated with meeting the objectives. The project has the potential to advance understanding of effective and efficient retention strategies for students on commuter campuses, including community colleges. This project is funded by NSF’s Scholarships in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics program, which seeks to increase the number of low-income academically talented students with demonstrated financial need who earn degrees in STEM fields. It also aims to improve the educational experiences of future STEM workers, and to generate knowledge about best practices for academic success, retention, transfer, graduation, and academic/career pathways of low-income students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2130058</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marilee</FirstName>
<LastName>Benore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marilee Benore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marilee@umd.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3135935490</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574356</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Lawson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Lawson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dblawson@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3135934921</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000592025</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joan</FirstName>
<LastName>Remski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joan Remski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>remski@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3135935414</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000823980</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Dearborn</Name>
<CityName>Dearborn</CityName>
<ZipCode>481282406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4901 EVERGREEN RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>782738207</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan-Dearborn]]></Name>
<CityName>Dearborn</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481282406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4901 Evergreen Rd,]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>1300XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>045176</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~1439824</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
