<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: A Metamodeling Machine Learning Framework for Multiscale Behavior of Nano-Architectured Crystalline-Amorphous Composites</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2022</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>333267.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>333267</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Siddiq Qidwai</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sqidwai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922211</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nanostructured composites may achieve the preferred combination of strength, ductility, toughness, and irradiation tolerance through microstructure tailoring and chemistry; thus, they are highly desired structural materials in harsh environments. In accelerating the design of nanostructured composites, the need is for models that can capture microstructure-dominated deformation mechanisms from the atomic scale to the structural scale. This award supports the development of a meta-modeling framework that enables the incorporation of atomic-level knowledge of microstructure-dominated deformation behaviors to predict structural response. This framework will be applied to design amorphous ceramic reinforced nickel alloys used in advanced nuclear reactors and high-temperature environments. The interdisciplinary nature of the research will provide graduate students a diverse training in computational and experimental mechanics, collaborative teamwork experience, as well as research experience at Los Alamos National Laboratory. Research opportunities and mentorship programs will be created at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln and the University of Alabama for undergraduate students, especially for women and underrepresented minorities. Additionally, outreach activities at university museums will attract local K-12 students towards STEM careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The accelerated design of nanostructured composites with desired properties needs sophisticated models that can capture microstructure-dominated deformation mechanics at multiple scales. In this project, a metamodeling machine learning based framework that enables the incorporation of microstructure-dominated deformation mechanics into a predictive macroscale model will be developed though an integrated characterization, experimental, and computational approach. Nanocrystalline nickel with high crystallization temperature amorphous ceramic SiOC at the grain boundaries will be the model material. Microstructures, deformation mechanisms, and mechanical properties of the Ni-SiOC nanocomposites will be characterized using advanced microscopes and in situ micromechanical testing. The atomic details of amorphous boundaries-mediated deformation in the nanostructures will be revealed through the combination of density functional theory calculations and large-scale molecular dynamics simulations. A dual-phase micromechanics model will be developed by coarse-graining the key deformation mechanisms identified at the atomic level. Surrogate models of the activation functionals for various mechanisms in the micromechanics model will be derived by training machine learning models from atomistic simulation data. At the macroscopic scale, a physics-informed neural network model in which the hybridized machine learning models will be used as surrogates to bridge scales will complete the metamodeling framework.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/04/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/04/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2132336</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jian</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jian Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jianwang@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4024721514</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000692246</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2200 Vine St]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555456995</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068662618</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska-Lincoln]]></Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>685880001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[900 N 16th St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1630</Code>
<Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>013E</Code>
<Text>MULTI-SCALE MODELING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>022E</Code>
<Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>027E</Code>
<Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~333267</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
